<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1CO" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">1 CORINTHIANS</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc3">1Co</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book is one of the letters that the Apostle Paul wrote to the Christians at Corinth. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 Corinthians</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1CO 1"/>
  <para style="s1">1 Corinthians 1:1-3</para>
  <para style="s1">As your apostle, I greet you Corinthian believers, and I desire that God bless you.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 1:1"/>I, Paul, <char style="add">am writing this letter</char>. Sosthenes, our fellow believer, is with <char style="add">me as I write it</char>. <char style="add">God</char> appointed me to be an apostle of Christ Jesus because that is what God desired. <verse eid="1CO 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 1:2"/><char style="add">I am sending this letter</char> to all you who are God’s believers in Corinth <char style="add">city</char>. You have been set apart <char style="add">by God</char> {<char style="add">God</char> has set you apart} for himself because ◄of your close relationship with/you belong to► Christ Jesus. God has appointed you to be his people and to live in a morally pure way, just like he has appointed all the people everywhere who belong to him to live in a morally pure way. You and they have trusted in the Lord Jesus Christ [MTY]. He is their sovereign Lord as well as the sovereign Lord of all of us <char style="add">(inc)</char> who have trusted in him.<verse eid="1CO 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 1:3"/>We <char style="add">(exc)</char> desire that God, who is our <char style="add">heavenly</char> Father, and Jesus Christ, who is our sovereign Lord, will continue to act kindly toward you and cause you to experience <char style="add">inner</char> peace.<verse eid="1CO 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I thank God for you and for all the spiritual abilities that he has given you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 1:4-9">1 Corinthians 1:4-9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 1:4"/>I very often [HYP] thank God for you because he has acted toward you kindly, acting in ways that you do not deserve. He has done this because of your ◄having a close relationship with/being united to► Christ Jesus. <verse eid="1CO 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 1:5"/>That is, <char style="add">God</char> has [HYP] helped you spiritually very much because of your ◄having a close relationship with/being united to► Christ. Specifically, God has very much [HYP] enabled you to speak messages <char style="add">that his Spirit revealed to you</char>, and he has very much enabled you to know many things [HYP] that his Spirit revealed to you. <verse eid="1CO 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 1:6"/>In that way, <char style="add">he</char> confirmed to you that what we <char style="add">(exc)</char> proclaimed about Christ is true. <verse eid="1CO 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 1:7"/>As a result, while you wait for our Lord Jesus Christ to return, within your group you truly have [LIT] every ability that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit gives <char style="add">to believers</char>. <verse eid="1CO 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 1:8"/>God will also cause you to steadfastly <char style="add">trust Christ to the very end of your lives</char> [EUP]. The result will be that God will not consider you guilty <char style="add">of any sin</char> when our Lord Jesus Christ returns to earth [MTY]. <verse eid="1CO 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 1:9"/>You can depend on God to do that. He is the one who chose you to become intimately associated with his Son, Jesus Christ, who is our Lord.<verse eid="1CO 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Stop dividing into groups in your congregations on the basis of which Christian leader you favor.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 1:10-17">1 Corinthians 1:10-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 1:10"/>My fellow believers, by the authority of [MTY] our Lord Jesus Christ, I urgently appeal to all of you to agree with one another. What I mean is, stop dividing into groups. Instead, be united [MET] concerning what you understand <char style="add">about spiritual matters</char>,, and be united in what you decide. <verse eid="1CO 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 1:11"/>My fellow believers, <char style="add">I urge this</char> because some members of Chloe’s household have told me that you are quarreling among yourselves. <verse eid="1CO 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 1:12"/>That is, some of you say, “Paul is the one to whom we <char style="add">are loyal</char>,” and others say, “Peter is the one to whom we <char style="add">are loyal</char>,” and still others say, “Christ is the one to whom we <char style="add">are loyal</char>.” <verse eid="1CO 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 1:13"/><char style="add">It is ridiculous that</char> [RHQ] <char style="add">you are quarreling and</char> dividing up <char style="add">into groups instead of being loyal to</char> Christ alone. Christ certainly has not divided himself into parts and distributed those parts out <char style="add">to groups of people who oppose each other</char>! [MET, RHQ] I, Paul, certainly did not die on the cross for you! [RHQ] When you were baptized {When someone baptized you}, you certainly did not promise that you were submitting to me! [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 1:14"/>I thank <char style="add">God</char> that Crispus and Gaius were the only ones from among you whom I baptized. <verse eid="1CO 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 1:15"/>As a result, no one <char style="add">there in Corinth except those two</char> can say, “Paul baptized me so that I would become ◄his disciple/submissive to him►.” <verse eid="1CO 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 1:16"/><char style="add">Now I remember that</char> I also baptized the household of Stephanas, but I do not remember baptizing anyone else <char style="add">there</char>. <verse eid="1CO 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 1:17"/>Christ sent me not <char style="add">primarily</char> to baptize people but to preach the good message about him. When I do that, he does not want me to use words that human philosophers <char style="add">consider</char> wise [IRO]. I do not want the message about <char style="add">what</char> he <char style="add">accomplished when he was nailed to</char> the cross [MTY] to lose its power.<verse eid="1CO 1:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The message about Christ dying on the cross is the means of saving us who believe it.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 1:18-19">1 Corinthians 1:18-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 1:18"/>Those who are perishing spiritually <char style="add">because they do not believe that message consider</char> that the message <char style="add">about what Christ accomplished when he was nailed to the</char> cross [MTY] <char style="add">is</char> foolish. But to us who are being saved {whom <char style="add">God</char> is saving} <char style="add">spiritually because we believe that message</char>, it <char style="add">demonstrates that</char> God acts powerfully <char style="add">in order to save us</char>. <verse eid="1CO 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 1:19"/><char style="add">It is like what God said that</char> a prophet wrote long ago,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="1CO 1:19">
    <char style="add">By the things that I will do</char>, I will show that the ideas of those who <char style="add">think</char> [IRO] they are wise are completely useless. I will ignore the ideas that they think are [IRO] so smart.<verse eid="1CO 1:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Some people think that the message about Christ is foolish, but to us whom God has chosen, it shows God’s power.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 1:20-25">1 Corinthians 1:20-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 1:20"/>So, do you know <char style="add">what God thinks</char> about what [RHQ] people who [IRO] consider themselves to be wise and scholars and philosophers say? <char style="add">He does not pay attention to what they say, because</char> [RHQ] he has shown clearly that what unbelievers <char style="add">think is</char> [IRO] wise is <char style="add">not wise at all</char>, but is really foolish. <verse eid="1CO 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 1:21"/>God, acting very wisely, made it impossible for unbelievers to know God by doing what they thought was [IRO] wise. Instead, he was happy to save those who trust <char style="add">in Christ</char> as the result of their hearing <char style="add">the message that</char> was proclaimed to them, a message that others consider to be foolish. <verse eid="1CO 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 1:22"/>The Jews want <char style="add">people to prove, by performing</char> miracles, <char style="add">that their message is true</char>. The non-Jews want to hear only messages consisting of talk that they consider to be very wise. <verse eid="1CO 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 1:23"/>As for us, we proclaim <char style="add">the message about what</char> Christ <char style="add">accomplished for us when</char> he was nailed {<char style="add">when they</char> nailed him} to the cross. That message offends Jews <char style="add">because they do not think that the Messiah will die, and</char> non-Jews think it is [IRO] a foolish message. <verse eid="1CO 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 1:24"/>But to us whom God has chosen to belong to himself, both Jews and non-Jews, that message shows that God acted powerfully and wisely <char style="add">by sending</char> Christ <char style="add">to die</char> for us. <verse eid="1CO 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 1:25"/><char style="add">Unbelievers may think</char> [IRO] <char style="add">that</char> God was <char style="add">acting</char> foolishly <char style="add">by doing that</char>, but <char style="add">the truth is that</char> he was acting more wisely than unbelievers who <char style="add">just think that</char> [IRO] they are wise. And unbelievers may think that God was <char style="add">acting</char> weakly <char style="add">by sending his son to die</char>, but he was acting more powerfully than unbelievers who <char style="add">just think</char> [IRO] <char style="add">that they</char> act powerfully.<verse eid="1CO 1:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God chose mostly despised, not important, people to belong to Christ; so you should boast only about him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 1:26-31">1 Corinthians 1:26-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 1:26"/>My fellow believers, remember what <char style="add">kind of people you</char> were when God chose you. <char style="add">Not many of you</char> whom he chose are people whom <char style="add">unbelievers considered to be</char> wise. Very few of you were considered to be important. Very few of you came from families with a high social standing. <verse eid="1CO 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 1:27"/>Instead, it was <char style="add">usually</char> those whom <char style="add">unbelievers considered to be</char> foolish whom God chose. He did that in order to shame/discredit those whom <char style="add">unbelievers consider</char> [IRO] wise. It was <char style="add">usually</char> those <char style="add">whom unbelievers</char> considered [IRO] unimportant whom God chose, in order to shame/discredit those whom unbelievers consider important. <verse eid="1CO 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 1:28"/>It was usually those who are despised and considered {whom <char style="add">unbelievers</char> despise and consider} worthless whom God chose, in order to make completely ineffective <char style="add">what unbelievers consider to be important</char>. <verse eid="1CO 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 1:29"/><char style="add">He did that</char> in order that no one could boast to God about being wise or important. <verse eid="1CO 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 1:30"/>It is because of what God <char style="add">has done</char> that you ◄have a close relationship with/belong to► Christ Jesus. God <char style="add">put into effect</char> his wise <char style="add">plan to save us</char> by what Christ did for us. As a result of what Christ did, God erases the record of our sins, sets us apart for himself, and frees us from our being guilty <char style="add">for our sins</char>. <verse eid="1CO 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 1:31"/>So, it is <char style="bd">the Lord</char> whom we should boast about, <char style="add">not about one spiritual leader being better than another</char>. We should do as ◄<char style="add">a prophet/Jeremiah</char>► wrote <char style="add">in the Scriptures that we should do</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 1:31">Those who boast should boast <char style="add">only</char> about what the Lord <char style="add">has done</char>.<verse eid="1CO 1:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1CO 2"/>
  <para style="s1">God showed that my message was true by the powerful things that he did, not because I spoke in a way that would make people think highly of me.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 2:1-5">1 Corinthians 2:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 2:1"/>My fellow believers, when I came to you, I proclaimed to you the message that God had revealed to me. But I did not proclaim it using eloquent words that would make people think highly of me, nor did I argue in a way that unbelievers would think was very wise. <verse eid="1CO 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 2:2"/>I did that because I decided that I would speak only about Jesus Christ. Specifically, I told you <char style="add">what he accomplished for us when</char> he was killed by being nailed {<char style="add">when they</char> killed him by nailing him} to a cross. <verse eid="1CO 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 2:3"/>Furthermore, when I was with you, I felt that I was not adequate <char style="add">to do what Christ wanted me to do</char>. I was afraid <char style="add">that I would not be able to do it</char>, and because of that I was trembling very much. <verse eid="1CO 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 2:4"/>When I taught you and preached to you, I did not speak words that <char style="add">unbelievers would consider</char> [IRO] wise in order to convince them that my message was true. Instead, <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit showed that it was true by <char style="add">enabling me to</char> powerfully <char style="add">perform miracles</char>. <verse eid="1CO 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 2:5"/><char style="add">I taught and preached that way</char> in order that you might believe <char style="add">my message</char>, not because you heard words that people <char style="add">considered to be</char> [IRO] wise, but <char style="add">because you recognized</char> God’s power.<verse eid="1CO 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Unbelievers do not consider that my message is wise, because I speak what God’s Spirit reveals to me.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 2:6-16">1 Corinthians 2:6-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 2:6"/>I do teach a message that people who are <char style="add">spiritually</char> mature <char style="add">consider to</char> be wise. But I do not teach a message that unbelievers <char style="add">consider to be</char> wise. I also do not teach a message that unbelieving rulers in the world consider to be wise. <char style="add">What they think about it does not matter</char>, because <char style="add">some day</char> ◄they will lose their power/not be ruling any more►. <verse eid="1CO 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 2:7"/>Instead, I teach about what God planned wisely <char style="add">long ago</char>. It is something that people did not know about previously because <char style="add">God</char> did not reveal it previously. But God determined before he created the world that he would greatly benefit us by his wise plan. <verse eid="1CO 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 2:8"/>None of those who rule this world knew that wise plan. If they had known it, they would not have nailed our wonderful Lord to the cross. <verse eid="1CO 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 2:9"/>But <char style="add">we believers need to remember these words that a prophet</char> wrote <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 2:9">Things that no one has ever seen,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 2:9">things that no one ever heard,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 2:9">things that no one ever thought could happen,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 2:9">those are the things that God has prepared for those who love him.<verse eid="1CO 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 2:10"/>God has caused his Spirit to reveal those things to us <char style="add">(inc)</char> believers. His Spirit can do that because he knows thoroughly the meaning of all things. He even knows the things about God that are very difficult to understand. <verse eid="1CO 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 2:11"/>Only a person himself (OR, a person’s spirit) knows what he is thinking. Similarly, only God’s Spirit knows what God is thinking. <verse eid="1CO 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 2:12"/>It was not the ideas that unbelievers teach that we accepted. Instead, it was the Spirit who came from God that we received, in order that we might know the things that God has freely done for us. <verse eid="1CO 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 2:13"/>Those are the things that I tell you about. As I do that, I do not tell you things that someone <char style="add">whom others thought</char> was [IRO] wise taught me. Instead, I tell you truths that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit taught <char style="add">me</char>, and I explain those spiritual truths to people whose thinking is guided by God’s Spirit (OR, I teach spiritual <char style="add">truths to</char> spiritual <char style="add">people</char>). <verse eid="1CO 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 2:14"/>Those who are unbelievers reject the truths that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit teaches us <char style="add">(inc)</char>, because they <char style="add">consider those truths to be</char> foolish. They cannot understand them, because it is God’s Spirit who enables us to evaluate those truths correctly, <char style="add">and those people do not have God’s Spirit</char>. <verse eid="1CO 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 2:15"/>We who have God’s Spirit can judge correctly the <char style="add">value of</char> all truths <char style="add">that the Spirit reveals</char>, but <char style="add">unbelievers</char> cannot evaluate us correctly. <verse eid="1CO 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 2:16"/>As <char style="add">one of our prophets wrote:</char></para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 2:16">No human [RHQ] has known what the Lord is thinking.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 2:16">No human [RHQ] is able to instruct him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 2:16">But we believers are able to think about things [MTY] in the way that Christ thinks about them.<verse eid="1CO 2:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1CO 3"/>
  <para style="s1">I was unable to teach you difficult concepts, because you were controlled by your self-directed nature, as evidenced by your quarreling about which leader you should be loyal to.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 3:1-4">1 Corinthians 3:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 3:1"/>My fellow believers, <char style="add">when I was with you previously</char>, I was not able to teach you as <char style="add">I would teach people who are controlled by the Holy</char> Spirit {<char style="add">whom the Holy</char> Spirit <char style="add">controls</char>}. Instead, <char style="add">I had to teach you as I would teach</char> people whom their self-directed nature controls. <char style="add">I taught very simple concepts to you who had recently believed</char> in Christ, <char style="add">as a parent would speak very simple words</char> to a baby. <verse eid="1CO 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 3:2"/>I did not <char style="add">teach</char> you <char style="add">things that were difficult for you to understand, just like a woman does not</char> give <char style="add">her baby</char> solid food <char style="add">that the baby cannot chew and digest</char>. <char style="add">And just like a woman</char> ◄<char style="add">gives her baby milk/breast-feeds her baby</char>►, <char style="add">I taught you simple spiritual concepts</char>, because at that time you were not able to understand difficult things. And you are still not able to understand difficult concepts, <verse eid="1CO 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 3:3"/>because you are still controlled by your self-directed nature. Some of you are jealous and quarreling. ◄That shows that your self-directed nature is controlling you!/Does not that prove your self-directed nature is controlling you?► [RHQ] It shows that <char style="add">you are acting like</char> unbelievers act. <verse eid="1CO 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 3:4"/>By some of you saying, “I am <char style="add">loyal to</char> Paul,” and others saying, “I am <char style="add">loyal to</char> Apollos,” ◄you show that <char style="add">you are acting like</char> unbelievers./does not it show that <char style="add">you are acting like</char> unbelievers?► [RHQ]<verse eid="1CO 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I preached the gospel to you first, and Apollos followed, but we are both serving God equally.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 3:5-9a">1 Corinthians 3:5-9a</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 3:5"/>
    <char style="add">So what you really ought to think about</char> Apollos and me [RHQ] is that we(dl) are merely men who serve God. As a result of our <char style="add">telling you the message about Christ</char>, you trusted in him. Both of us <char style="add">(dl)</char> are merely doing the work that the Lord appointed us to do. <verse eid="1CO 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 3:6"/>I was <char style="add">the first one who preached God’s message to you. I was like</char> [MET] someone who plants seeds. <char style="add">Later</char>, Apollos <char style="add">taught you more of God’s message. That was like</char> [MET] someone who waters plants <char style="add">after they start to grow</char>. But it is God who <char style="add">enables people to grow spiritually, just like he is the one who</char> causes <char style="add">plants</char> to grow. <verse eid="1CO 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 3:7"/>So <char style="add">the person who first preaches God’s message to people is not important, and the person who later teaches people more of God’s message is not important, just like</char> [MET] it is not the person who plants <char style="add">the seeds</char> or the person who waters <char style="add">the plants</char> who is important. Instead, it is God, who causes plants to grow <char style="add">and who causes people to grow spiritually, who is important</char>. <verse eid="1CO 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 3:8"/>The person <char style="add">who first preaches God’s message to people and the one who later teaches them more of God’s message</char> [MET] both ◄are <char style="add">trying to reach the</char> same <char style="add">goal</char>/have the same <char style="add">purpose</char>►. And <char style="add">God</char> will reward each of them according to how they served him. <verse eid="1CO 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 3:9"/>Remember that Apollos and I are both working together for God. <char style="add">You do not belong to us</char>. Just like a field <char style="add">belongs to its owner, not to those who work in it</char>, you belong to God, <char style="add">not to us who work for him</char>.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="1CO 3:9">Each one who teaches believers must examine what he is teaching them because God will reward him only if his teaching is valuable and long-lasting.</para>
  <para style="sr" vid="1CO 3:9">
    <ref loc="1CO 3:9b-15">1 Corinthians 3:9b-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p" vid="1CO 3:9">Also, a house belongs to its owner. <char style="add">It does not belong to the man who built it. Similarly, God is the one to whom you belong</char>. <verse eid="1CO 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 3:10"/><char style="add">Just like</char> a skilled person puts a foundation in the ground <char style="add">before he builds a house</char>, as a result of God kindly helping me [MET], <char style="add">I was the first one who declared the message about Christ to you. And, just like</char> others build a house on its foundation, there were <char style="add">others who later taught you more about Christ</char>. But <char style="add">just like each person who builds a house</char> must be careful about what materials he uses to build it [MET], each person <char style="add">who teaches God’s truth must be careful about what he teaches</char>. <verse eid="1CO 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 3:11"/>Just like people can put in <char style="add">only</char> one foundation <char style="add">for a house</char> [MET], <char style="add">there is only one message that we can give to people. That message is about</char> Jesus Christ. <verse eid="1CO 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 3:12"/>Furthermore, people can build a house on its foundation <char style="add">with materials that are valuable and do not burn easily, such as</char> gold, silver, and expensive jewels. Or they could build a house with <char style="add">materials that are not valuable and that burn easily, such as</char> wood, hay, and straw. <verse eid="1CO 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 3:13"/>Later it will become clear/evident what kind of material they used to build the house. <char style="add">Similarly, when people teach others God’s truth</char>, it will later become clear <char style="add">what kind of things they taught</char>. <char style="add">God</char> will make that clear/evident at the time <char style="add">when he judges us</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="1CO 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 3:14"/>When a fire <char style="add">starts burning a house</char>, it becomes clear whether the builders used <char style="add">materials in their</char> work <char style="add">that will burn, or materials that will not burn</char>. Similarly [MET], when God judges us, it will be clear whether we taught others things that were long-lasting and valuable or not. If <char style="add">the materials that are used to</char> build a house <char style="add">are materials that</char> do not burn, the builder will receive a reward [MET]. <char style="add">Similarly, if we have taught others things that are valuable and long-lasting, God will give us a reward</char>. <verse eid="1CO 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 3:15"/>If <char style="add">the things that we have taught</char> are not valuable and long-lasting [MET], <char style="add">we will not get a reward</char>. We will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save us} <char style="add">from hell</char>, but <char style="add">that is all that we will get. We will be like a man who</char> escapes from a fire <char style="add">without saving any of his possessions</char>.<verse eid="1CO 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God will destroy anyone who destroys the unity of a congregation.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 3:16-17">1 Corinthians 3:16-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 3:16"/>You need to remember that God <char style="add">is present among</char> you <char style="add">(pl) as he was present in the</char> Temple <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>. [RHQ] God’s Spirit lives within you. <verse eid="1CO 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 3:17"/>So, <char style="add">just like</char> God will destroy anyone who tries to destroy his Temple, <char style="add">he will destroy anyone who destroys the unity of a congregation. He will do that</char> because <char style="add">he has set</char> you, <char style="add">his people, apart for himself, just like he set</char> his Temple <char style="add">apart for himself</char>.<verse eid="1CO 3:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Stop being proud of one Christian leader or another, because we are all just working for your benefit.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 3:18-23">1 Corinthians 3:18-23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 3:18"/>Some among you think that you are wise because unbelievers thought you were wise previously. Stop deceiving yourselves. <char style="add">If you really want to be wise, by accepting what God considers to be wise</char> you should <char style="add">be willing to let unbelievers consider that you are</char> foolish [IRO]. <verse eid="1CO 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 3:19"/>You should do that because things that unbelievers <char style="add">consider to be</char> [IRO] wise, God considers to be foolish. <char style="add">We can learn from</char> the Scriptures <char style="add">what God says about</char> that:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 3:19">Those who think that they are [IRO] wise, he messes up their plans by the mistakes they make!<verse eid="1CO 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 3:20"/>And <char style="add">we can learn from</char> these words of Scripture,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 3:20">The Lord considers as useless the thoughts of <char style="add">humans who think that they are</char> [IRO] wise.<verse eid="1CO 3:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 3:21"/>So, stop boasting about <char style="add">how good one Christian leader is or how good another Christian leader is</char>. All <char style="add">of us(exc) exist as leaders only to help</char> you! <verse eid="1CO 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 3:22"/>Specifically, do not boast about me, or about Apollos, or about Peter! Everything in the world exists to <char style="add">benefit</char> you <char style="add">believers</char>. Whether you live or whether you die, the things that are happening now or the things that will happen in the future, they are all to benefit you. <verse eid="1CO 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 3:23"/><char style="add">You should boast about</char> Christ, <char style="add">not about your leaders, because</char> you belong to Christ, and Christ belongs to God.<verse eid="1CO 3:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1CO 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Stop evaluating your leaders’ value; do not be proud of one and despise another.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 4:1-7">1 Corinthians 4:1-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 4:1"/>So, people ought to consider us <char style="add">apostles</char> (OR, Apollos and me) to be <char style="add">merely</char> servants of Christ. God has given to us <char style="add">(exc) the work of</char> telling others the message that God has now revealed to us. <verse eid="1CO 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 4:2"/>With respect to doing that, those who are given work are required {give others some work to do require them} to do that work faithfully. <verse eid="1CO 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 4:3"/>I am not concerned whether you or <char style="add">the judges in</char> some court decide whether I have done my work faithfully or not. I do not even judge myself <char style="add">about that</char>. <verse eid="1CO 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 4:4"/>I do not think that I have done anything wrong, but that does not prove that I have done nothing wrong. The Lord is the one who judges me. <verse eid="1CO 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 4:5"/>So, stop evaluating any of us <char style="add">(exc)</char> before the time <char style="add">when God judges everyone</char> [MTY]! Do not judge us before the Lord comes. He is the one who will reveal the sinful things that people have done secretly. He will even reveal what people have thought. At that time God will praise each person as <char style="add">each one of them deserves</char>.<verse eid="1CO 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 4:6"/>My fellow believers, I have <char style="add">told you</char> all these things as illustrations of myself and Apollos. I have done this for your sake, in order that you may learn <char style="add">to live according to</char> the saying, “Do not act contrary to what is {what they have} written <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>.” If you follow that rule, you will not be proud of one <char style="add">spiritual leader</char> and despise another. <verse eid="1CO 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 4:7"/>◄No one has made any of you superior to others!/Why do any of you think that you are superior to others?► [RHQ] <char style="add">All the abilities</char> that you have, you received <char style="add">from God</char>. [RHQ] So if you received them all <char style="add">from God</char>, ◄you should not boast <char style="add">thinking</char>, “I got these abilities <char style="add">from myself</char>, <char style="add">not from God</char>!”/why do you boast <char style="add">thinking</char>, “I got these abilities <char style="add">from myself</char>, <char style="add">not from God</char>?”► [RHQ]<verse eid="1CO 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is disgusting that you are so proud of your spiritual gifts and that you despise us apostles.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 4:8-13">1 Corinthians 4:8-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 4:8"/>
    <char style="add">It is disgusting that you act as though</char> [IRO] you have already received everything that you need <char style="add">spiritually</char>. You act as though [IRO] you were <char style="add">spiritually</char> rich (OR, you had received all <char style="add">the spiritual gifts you need</char>). You act as though [IRO] you had already begun to rule as kings with Christ. Well, I wish that you really were ruling <char style="add">with him</char>, in order that we <char style="add">apostles</char> might also rule with you! <verse eid="1CO 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 4:9"/>But it seems as though God has put us <char style="add">apostles</char> on display, <char style="add">like prisoners</char> at the end <char style="add">of the victor’s parade</char>. We <char style="add">(exc)</char> are like men who have been condemned to die, who have been put in the arena where everyone can see <char style="add">the wild animals</char> killing them. And not only people, but even angels all over the world <char style="add">are watching us, as people</char> watch those who are performing a play <char style="add">in a theater</char>. <verse eid="1CO 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 4:10"/>Many people consider us to be [IRO] fools because <char style="add">we preach about</char> Christ, but you proudly <char style="add">think [IRO] that</char> you are wise because ◄of your close relationship with/you belong to► Christ. Many people <char style="add">consider us</char> [IRO] to be unimpressive, but you <char style="add">proudly think that you</char> impress others. People respect you, but they do not respect us. <verse eid="1CO 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 4:11"/>Up to this present time we have often been hungry. We have often been thirsty. We have ragged clothes. Often we have been beaten {others have beaten us}. We <char style="add">have traveled so much that we</char> have no regular homes to live in. <verse eid="1CO 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 4:12"/>We work very hard <char style="add">to earn a living</char>. When we are cursed <char style="add">by people</char> {When <char style="add">people</char> curse us}, we <char style="add">ask God to</char> bless them. When we are persecuted {When <char style="add">people</char> cause us to suffer}, we endure it. <verse eid="1CO 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 4:13"/>When we are slandered <char style="add">by people</char> {When <char style="add">people</char> slander us}, we reply kindly to them. Up to now, <char style="add">unbelievers consider us to be worthless</char> [MET], <char style="add">as though we were</char> just garbage.<verse eid="1CO 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Imitate the way in which I serve Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 4:14-17">1 Corinthians 4:14-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 4:14"/>I am writing this to you, not to make you feel ashamed, but instead to warn you as <char style="add">though you were</char> my own dear children. <verse eid="1CO 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 4:15"/>I say that because as <char style="add">an apostle of</char> Christ Jesus I <char style="add">was the first one who</char> proclaimed the good message to you. As a result, I was the one who enabled you to have eternal life. So even if there were thousands of Christians who instruct you [MET], I am the only one who became <char style="add">like</char> a father to you. <verse eid="1CO 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 4:16"/>So I urge you to <char style="add">live for Christ</char> the way I do. <verse eid="1CO 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 4:17"/>In order to <char style="add">help you do that</char>, I have sent/will be sending Timothy to you. I love him <char style="add">as though he were</char> my son. He serves the Lord faithfully. He will remind you of the way I conduct my life <char style="add">as one who</char> ◄has a close relationship with/belongs to► the Lord. The way I conduct my life is the same as how I teach <char style="add">others to live</char> in all the congregations <char style="add">to whom I have spoken</char>.<verse eid="1CO 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I hope you will change your thinking, so I do not have to punish you when I come there.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 4:18-21">1 Corinthians 4:18-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 4:18"/>Some of you have become proud, thinking that I will not come there <char style="add">to rebuke your congregation about what they are doing</char>. <verse eid="1CO 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 4:19"/>But if the Lord wants me to come, I will come to you soon. Then I will not <char style="add">pay any attention to</char> what those proud people say. Instead, I will find out <char style="add">whether they have God’s</char> power. <verse eid="1CO 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 4:20"/>Remember that God <char style="add">judges whether or not we are letting him</char> rule <char style="add">our lives</char>, not by <char style="add">listening to how we</char> talk, but <char style="add">by seeing whether his</char> power <char style="add">is present</char> ◄<char style="add">among us/in our lives</char>►. <verse eid="1CO 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 4:21"/>So which do you prefer? Do you want me to come to you and punish you <char style="add">because you have not changed your ways</char>, or shall I come to you and act lovingly and gently toward you <char style="add">because you have done what I told you to do</char>?<verse eid="1CO 4:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1CO 5"/>
  <para style="s1">You should expel the man in your congregation who has acted so immorally.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 5:1-5">1 Corinthians 5:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 5:1"/>
    <char style="add">Now I want to discuss another matter</char>. It has been {People have} reported to me, and I believe that it is true, that some people among you have been acting in a sexually immoral way, in a way that is so bad that not even ◄pagans/people who do not know about God► act that way. People tell me that a man is living with his stepmother (OR, his father’s other wife). <verse eid="1CO 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 5:2"/>You should be sad about what that man is doing! He should have been expelled {<char style="add">You</char> should have expelled him} from your congregation! <char style="add">But you</char> have not <char style="add">done that</char>, so ◄how can you be proud, <char style="add">thinking that you are spiritually mature?</char>/it is disgusting that you are proud, <char style="add">thinking that you are spiritually mature</char>!► [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 5:3"/>As for me, I have already decided <char style="add">how you should</char> punish that man. And even though I am away from you, my spirit is with you, and you should do as I would do if I were there with you. <verse eid="1CO 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 5:4"/><char style="add">What I have decided is that</char> when you have gathered together with the authority [MTY] of our Lord Jesus, and my spirit is with you, and the power of our Lord Jesus <char style="add">is with you</char>, <verse eid="1CO 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 5:5"/>you should hand that man over to Satan. Then Satan can injure/punish his body, in order that <char style="add">he will turn away from his sinful behavior</char> and his spirit will be saved on the day when the Lord <char style="add">returns</char> [MTY].<verse eid="1CO 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Make sure that no one in your congregation is acting immorally or maliciously or wickedly.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 5:6-8">1 Corinthians 5:6-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 5:6"/>It is not good that, <char style="add">while you are letting that immoral man continue to be in your congregation</char>, you are boasting <char style="add">about being spiritually mature</char>. ◄You know that a small amount of yeast affects all the bread dough [MET] <char style="add">into which it is put</char> {<char style="add">a woman puts it</char>}./Do you not know that a small amount of yeast affects all the bread dough [MET] <char style="add">into which it is put</char>?► [RHQ] <char style="add">Similarly, one person who continues to sin will have a bad effect on all the congregation</char>. <verse eid="1CO 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 5:7"/>So, <char style="add">just like we Jews</char> expel the old yeast <char style="add">from our houses during the Passover celebration</char> in order that we may have a fresh batch of dough without yeast in it [MET], <char style="add">you must expel such evil people from your congregation</char>. Do <char style="add">that so that you can truly be holy people</char>, as <char style="add">I know that</char> you really are. Remember that Christ was sacrificed {sacrificed himself} <char style="add">so that God could spare us from being punished for our sins, just like the Jews sacrificed lambs during</char> the <char style="add">first</char> Passover celebration <char style="add">so that God would spare their firstborn sons from being killed</char>. <verse eid="1CO 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 5:8"/>So let us celebrate <char style="add">the fact that God has freed us from being punished us for our sins</char> [MET], <char style="add">just like the Jews</char> in <char style="add">later years</char> celebrated Passover <char style="add">to celebrate God freeing them from being slaves in Egypt. They made sure that there was</char> no old yeast in the dough. <char style="add">They ate bread that</char> had no yeast in it. <char style="add">Similarly</char>, <char style="add">we should make sure that there are no people in our congregations</char> [MET] <char style="add">who act</char> maliciously <char style="add">toward others</char> or <char style="add">act</char> wickedly. Instead, <char style="add">make sure</char> [MET] <char style="add">that all those in our congregations are ones who act</char> sincerely and <char style="add">speak</char> truthfully.<verse eid="1CO 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Expel wicked people from your congregation.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 5:9-13">1 Corinthians 5:9-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 5:9"/>In the previous letter that I wrote to you, I said that you should not associate with sexually immoral people. <verse eid="1CO 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 5:10"/>I did not mean that you should not associate with unbelievers who are immoral, or who desire things that belong to others, or who ◄forcefully seize things that belong to others/are swindlers►, or who worship idols. You would have to leave this world <char style="add">to avoid all people</char> like that. <verse eid="1CO 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 5:11"/>But now <char style="add">I am stating clearly that</char> when I wrote, I <char style="add">meant that</char> you should not associate with those who say that they are fellow believers, if they are sexually immoral or if they desire and forcefully seize things that belong to others, or worship idols, or slander others, or become drunk. You should not associate with people like that, and you should not even eat with them! <verse eid="1CO 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 5:12"/>It is certainly not [RHQ] my business to judge people who are not believers and who do not belong to <char style="add">Christian congregations</char>. But it certainly is [RHQ] your business to judge those who are in <char style="add">your congregation</char>! <verse eid="1CO 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 5:13"/>God is the one who will judge those who are not believers. <char style="add">Do as the Scriptures command</char>: “Expel the wicked person from your midst!”<verse eid="1CO 5:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="1CO 6"/>
  <para style="s1">It is disgusting that you prosecute fellow believers and let judges who are not believers decide your cases.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 6:1-6">1 Corinthians 6:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 6:1"/>
    <char style="add">Now another matter</char>: When any of you <char style="add">believers</char> accuses another believer about some matter, he takes that matter to judges who are not believers, <char style="add">for them to decide the case</char>, instead of asking God’s people <char style="add">to decide it</char>. ◄That is disgusting!/Why do you do that?► [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 6:2"/><char style="add">I want</char> you to know that <char style="add">we who are</char> God’s people will <char style="add">some day</char> judge those who are unbelievers. [RHQ] So, since you will be judging unbelievers, you certainly are capable of judging between <char style="add">believers who disagree on</char> small matters! [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 6:3"/>◄You should keep in mind that we will even judge angels!/Do you not know that we will even judge angels?► [RHQ] So we certainly should be able to judge about <char style="add">matters that relate to how we</char> conduct our lives here on earth! <verse eid="1CO 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 6:4"/>Therefore, when you <char style="add">believers</char> have a dispute, you should certainly not choose as judges <char style="add">to decide your case</char> people whom the congregation cannot respect <char style="add">because those judges are not believers</char>! [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 6:5"/>I am saying this to make you ashamed. Surely there is someone among you who is wise enough to judge disputes between believers! [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 6:6"/>But instead, some believers <char style="add">among you</char> accuse other believers in a legal court. And what is worse, you let the cases be judged by unbelievers {unbelievers judge the cases}!<verse eid="1CO 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God has freed you from your former sinful behavior, so remember that he will exclude from his kingdom those who engage in all kinds of sinful behavior.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 6:7-11">1 Corinthians 6:7-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 6:7"/>The fact that you have any lawsuits among you <char style="add">shows that</char> you have completely failed <char style="add">as Christians</char> (OR, <char style="add">allowed Satan to</char> defeat you). You should <char style="add">allow other believers</char> to wrong you <char style="add">without taking them to court!</char>! [RHQ] You should not accuse them when <char style="add">they</char> cheat you! [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 6:8"/>But <char style="add">what is happening is that</char> some of you are cheating others and doing wrong to them. <char style="add">That is bad</char>. But you are doing that to fellow believers, <char style="add">and that is worse</char>!<verse eid="1CO 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 6:9"/>◄You should keep in mind that wicked people will not become <char style="add">members of</char> the group over whom God will rule./Do you not know that wicked people will not become <char style="add">members of</char> the group over whom God will rule?► [RHQ] Do not be deceived {Do not deceive yourselves} <char style="add">by thinking wrongly about these matters</char>. People who are sexually immoral, or who worship idols, or who ◄commit adultery/have sex with someone to whom they are not married►, or who happily allow others to commit homosexual acts with them, or who take the initiative in committing homosexual acts, <verse eid="1CO 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 6:10"/>or who are thieves, or who desire and forcefully seize things that belong to others, or who are drunkards, or who slander others, or who are swindlers, will not enter the place where God rules. <verse eid="1CO 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 6:11"/>Some of you previously did things like that. But <char style="add">God</char> has freed/cleansed you [MET] <char style="add">from your sinful behavior</char>. <char style="add">He</char> has set you apart for himself. <char style="add">He</char> has erased the record of your sins <char style="add">because you trusted</char> [MTY] in the Lord Jesus Christ and because of what the Spirit of our God <char style="add">has done for you</char>.<verse eid="1CO 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because the Lord wants us to use our bodies in ways that please him, we must avoid all sexually immoral acts.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 6:12-20">1 Corinthians 6:12-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 6:12"/>
    <char style="add">Some of you may say</char>, “God allows us to do anything <char style="add">that he does not forbid</char>.” But <char style="add">I would reply</char>, “<char style="add">That is true</char>, but not everything that God permits us to do helps us.” <char style="add">Yes, as some of you say</char>, God permits us to do anything <char style="add">that he does not forbid</char>. But as for me, I will not let anything make me <char style="add">its slave; that is, I will not do anything that will gain control over me in such a way that I will not be able to stop doing it</char>. <verse eid="1CO 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 6:13"/><char style="add">Some of you may also say</char>, “Food is just for <char style="add">us to put in</char> the stomach, and the stomach is just for <char style="add">us to put</char> food <char style="add">in</char>. And since God will do away with food and stomachs <char style="add">when he gives us our new bodies, what we do with our bodies sexually does not affect us any more than eating food does.” But what you have concluded is wrong, because</char> the Lord does not <char style="add">want us to use</char> our bodies to do sexually immoral things. Instead, the Lord <char style="add">wants us to use our bodies in ways that please him</char>. Also, the Lord <char style="add">wants us to do what is good</char> for our bodies. <verse eid="1CO 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 6:14"/>God, by his power, caused the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> to live again after he died, and he will cause us to live again after we die, <char style="add">which shows that he is very concerned about our bodies</char>.<verse eid="1CO 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 6:15"/>You should keep in mind that your bodies belong to Christ. [RHQ] So, should I <char style="add">or any other believer</char> [RHQ] take our body, which belongs to Christ, and join it <char style="add">sexually</char> to a prostitute? No, certainly not! <verse eid="1CO 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 6:16"/>When a man has sexual relations [EUP] with a prostitute, <char style="add">it is as though</char> their two bodies become one body. ◄You should never forget that!/Do you not know that?► [RHQ] What <char style="add">Moses</char> wrote <char style="add">about people who join together sexually is</char>, “The two of them will become <char style="add">as though they are</char> one body.” <verse eid="1CO 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 6:17"/>But anyone who is united {who joins himself} to the Lord becomes one with him spiritually.<verse eid="1CO 6:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 6:18"/>Always ◄run away from/avoid► committing sexually immoral acts. Other sins that people commit do not affect their bodies, but those who commit sexually immoral acts sin against their own bodies. <verse eid="1CO 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 6:19"/>◄Keep in mind that your bodies are <char style="add">like</char> [MET] temples of the Holy Spirit./Do you not know that your bodies are <char style="add">like</char> [MET] temples of the Holy Spirit?► [RHQ] The Spirit, whom God gave you, lives within you. You do not belong to yourselves. You belong to God, <verse eid="1CO 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 6:20"/><char style="add">because when his Son died for you it was as though</char> [MET] <char style="add">God</char> paid a price for you. So honor God by <char style="add">how you use</char> your bodies!<verse eid="1CO 6:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="1CO 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Married people should not deprive their spouses of sexual relations, except under special conditions.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:1-7">1 Corinthians 7:1-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 7:1"/>Now <char style="add">I will reply to</char> the things that you wrote to me about.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1CO 7:1">It is good for people not to get married. <verse eid="1CO 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 7:2"/>But because many people are committing sexual immorality, <char style="add">which God detests</char>, every man should have his own wife <char style="add">with whom he can have sexual relations</char>, and every woman should have her own husband <char style="add">with whom she can have sexual relations</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 7:3"/>Every man must continue having sexual relations [EUP] with his wife, and every woman must continue having sexual relations with her husband. <verse eid="1CO 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 7:4"/>A man’s wife does not have the right over her own body <char style="add">to be the only one to decide about having sexual relations with her husband</char>. Instead, her husband also has a right <char style="add">to decide about that</char>. Similarly, a woman’s husband does not have the right over his own body <char style="add">to be the only one to decide about having sexual relations with his wife</char>. Instead, his wife also has a right <char style="add">to decide about that</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 7:5"/>You may refuse <char style="add">to have sexual relations with</char> each other [EUP] only if you both first agree to do that for a short time, in order that you may both have more time to pray. Then after that, begin having sexual relations again [EUP] in order that Satan will not be able to persuade you <char style="add">to have sex with someone else</char> because you are unable to control your sexual desires.<verse eid="1CO 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 7:6"/>I am telling you these things to say that <char style="add">God</char> allows <char style="add">you to get married, but he</char> does not say that you must <char style="add">get married</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 7:7"/>I myself wish that all people would stay <char style="add">unmarried/single</char>, as I am. But God has enabled each person to live in ways that seem right for them. He has enabled some people to <char style="add">live without getting married</char>, and he has enabled other people to <char style="add">get married</char>.<verse eid="1CO 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is all right to get married, but it is wrong to get divorced. However, you should not force an unbelieving spouse to keep living with you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:8-16">1 Corinthians 7:8-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 7:8"/>Now I want to say this to you unmarried people and to you whose spouses have died: It would be good for you to remain <char style="add">unmarried</char> as I am. <verse eid="1CO 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 7:9"/>But if you cannot control your <char style="add">sexual desires</char> [EUP], you should get married. It is better to be married <char style="add">so that you can satisfy your sexual desires with your spouse</char> than to constantly have a strong desire [EUP] <char style="add">for sexual relations</char>.<verse eid="1CO 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 7:10"/>And now I will give a command for <char style="add">believers who are</char> married. This is not a command from me alone; it also comes from the Lord Jesus. You married women must not ◄separate from/divorce► your husbands! <verse eid="1CO 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 7:11"/>But if any of you do that, you must remain unmarried, or else you should be reconciled with your husband <char style="add">and live with him again</char>. Similarly, men must not ◄separate from/divorce► their wives.<verse eid="1CO 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 7:12"/>Now I say this to the rest of you, <char style="add">to those who became believers after they were married. This is what</char> I <char style="add">am saying</char>, not what the Lord <char style="add">has commanded</char>. If someone has a wife who is not a believer, if she is willing to keep living with him, he must not divorce her. <verse eid="1CO 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 7:13"/>Similarly, if a woman has a husband who is not a believer, if he is willing to keep living with her, she must not divorce him. <verse eid="1CO 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 7:14"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because God has set apart every woman’s unbelieving husband <char style="add">for himself</char> because of his wife <char style="add">being a believer</char>, and God has set apart every man’s unbelieving wife <char style="add">for himself</char> because of her husband <char style="add">being a believer</char>. If that were not true, <char style="add">God would consider</char> their children unacceptable. But, the fact is that <char style="add">God does consider</char> them acceptable to him.<verse eid="1CO 7:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 7:15"/>However, if a woman’s husband who is not a believer or a man’s wife who is not a believer wants to leave, let <char style="add">him or her</char> do so. The husband or wife who is a believer should not force the other one to stay. God has chosen us in order that we may live peacefully. <verse eid="1CO 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 7:16"/><char style="add">You women believers should allow your unbelieving spouses to leave you if they want to</char>, because there is no way that you can be sure that God will save your husband if you stay together [RHQ] (OR, perhaps God will save your husband if you stay together.) Similarly, you men <char style="add">who are believers</char>, there is no way that you can be sure that God will save your wives if you stay together [RHQ] (OR, perhaps God will save your wives if you stay together.)<verse eid="1CO 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">In general, each person should remain in the status that he had before he became a believer.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:17-24">1 Corinthians 7:17-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 7:17"/>However, each person should continue in the status that the Lord gave him, the status that he had when the Lord called him <char style="add">to belong to him</char>. That is the rule that I tell people in all the congregations <char style="add">where I speak</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 7:18"/>If a man had already been circumcised [RHQ] when he became a Christian, he should not <char style="add">try to pretend that he is not</char> circumcised. If a man had not been circumcised [RHQ] before he became a Christian, he should not become circumcised. <verse eid="1CO 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 7:19"/><char style="add">You should not try to change your status that way</char>, because it means nothing <char style="add">to God</char> whether someone is circumcised or not. What is important is that we obey what God has commanded. <verse eid="1CO 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 7:20"/><char style="add">Generally</char>, each person should remain in the status that he had when he became a Christian. <verse eid="1CO 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 7:21"/>If one of you was a slave when you <char style="add">(sg)</char> became a Christian [RHQ], do not be concerned about it. However, if you get an opportunity to be free, do <char style="add">what you need to do to become free</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 7:22"/><char style="add">Do not worry about your previously being a slave</char>, because those who were slaves before they became Christians, the Lord has freed them <char style="add">from Satan’s control</char>. Similarly, those who were not slaves before they became Christians, <char style="add">it is as though</char> [MET] they are Christ’s slaves <char style="add">because they must do what he tells them to do</char> [MET]. <verse eid="1CO 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 7:23"/><char style="add">Christ</char> paid a price to buy you <char style="add">when he died for you</char>. So do not <char style="add">act as if you are evil people’s</char> slaves <char style="add">by doing the evil things that they tell you to do</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 7:24"/>My fellow believers, <char style="add">I repeat that in general</char> each believer, being in fellowship with God, should continue in the status that he had before he became a Christian.<verse eid="1CO 7:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is not sinful to get married, but married people will have a lot of problems.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:25-28">1 Corinthians 7:25-28</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 7:25"/>Now <char style="add">I will answer your question</char> about women who have never married. There is nothing that the Lord has commanded me <char style="add">to write about them</char>, but I am writing this to tell you what I think <char style="add">is best</char>, because the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> has mercifully enabled me to <char style="add">say</char> what is reliable. <verse eid="1CO 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 7:26"/>There are a lot of distressing events <char style="add">happening</char> now (OR, that will soon happen), so I think that it is better for people to remain in the marital status that they now have. <verse eid="1CO 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 7:27"/>If any of you <char style="add">men</char> are married [RHQ], do not try to divorce your wife. If any of you are unmarried [RHQ], do not seek a wife. <verse eid="1CO 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 7:28"/>But if <char style="add">any of</char> you <char style="add">men</char> get married, you have not committed a sin <char style="add">by doing that</char>. Likewise, if an unmarried woman gets married, she has not committed a sin <char style="add">by doing that</char>. However, those who get married will have many troubles, <char style="add">so I am urging you to remain unmarried in order that</char> you may not experience <char style="add">such troubles</char>.<verse eid="1CO 7:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We believers should not devote our time to the affairs of this life.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:29-31">1 Corinthians 7:29-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 7:29"/>My fellow believers, this is what I mean: There is not much time left <char style="add">before Christ returns</char>. So, from now on those men who are married should <char style="add">devote themselves to serving the Lord as much</char> as they would if they were not married. <verse eid="1CO 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 7:30"/>Those who are sad should <char style="add">devote themselves to serving the Lord as much</char> as they would if they were not sad. Those who are rejoicing <char style="add">should devote themselves to serving the Lord as much</char> as they would if they were not joyful. <verse eid="1CO 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 7:31"/>Those who are buying things should <char style="add">devote themselves to serving the Lord as much</char> as they would if they did not possess those things. Because this world as it exists now will soon be gone, those who are actively involved in the affairs of this life <char style="add">should not devote all their time</char> to be involved in those things.<verse eid="1CO 7:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is better to remain unmarried because married people are more concerned about pleasing their spouses than about how to please the Lord.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:32-35">1 Corinthians 7:32-35</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 7:32"/>
    <char style="add">Another reason why</char> I <char style="add">encourage you to remain unmarried is that</char> I desire that none of you be anxious <char style="add">about the everyday affairs of this life</char>. Unmarried men are <char style="add">able to be primarily</char> concerned about serving the Lord Jesus and trying to please him. <verse eid="1CO 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 7:33"/>But married men are <char style="add">often</char> greatly concerned about the affairs of this life. Specifically, they are concerned about pleasing their wives. <verse eid="1CO 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 7:34"/>So their thinking is divided. Unmarried women are <char style="add">able to be</char> concerned about serving the Lord. They want to set apart their minds and their bodies for serving the Lord. But married women are <char style="add">often</char> concerned about the affairs of this life. Specifically, they are concerned about how to please their husbands. <verse eid="1CO 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 7:35"/>I am telling you this for your own good. I am not saying it in order to restrict you. Instead, I am saying it in order that you may do what is proper and be able to serve the Lord without being distracted {things distracting you}.<verse eid="1CO 7:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is better for a man to decide that his daughter should remain unmarried than that she should get married, but either decision is all right.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:36-38">1 Corinthians 7:36-38</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 7:36"/>
    <char style="add">Some of you men have asked about your unmarried daughters</char>. <char style="add">I suggest that</char> if any man thinks that he may be treating his daughter unfairly <char style="add">by keeping her from marrying</char>, and if it is already past <char style="add">the right</char> time for her to get married, and if he thinks that she ought to be married, he should do what he wants to do. He should let her get married. He will not be sinning <char style="add">by doing that</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 7:37"/>But if a man feels absolutely sure <char style="add">that it is better that his daughter not get married</char>, and if nothing is forcing <char style="add">her to get married</char>, and if he is free to do what he decides to do on the matter, if he decides that his daughter should not get married, he is doing what is right in <char style="add">keeping her from marrying</char>. <verse eid="1CO 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 7:38"/>So any man who decides that his daughter should get married is doing what is good, but if he decides that she should not get married, he is doing something even better. (OR, <char style="vp">36</char> <char style="add">Some of you men have asked about the women to whom you are engaged to marry</char>. If any man thinks that he may be treating that woman unfairly <char style="add">by not marrying her</char>, and if it is already past <char style="add">the right</char> time for her to get married, and if he wants to marry her very much, he should do what he wants to do. He should marry her. He will not be sinning <char style="add">by doing that</char>. <char style="vp">37</char> But if a man feels absolutely sure <char style="add">that it is better</char> for him not to get married, and if nothing is forcing <char style="add">them to get married</char>, if he is free to make his own decision on the matter, if he decides not to get married, he is doing what is right. <char style="vp">38</char> So any man who decides that he should get married to the woman he is engaged to is doing what is good, but if he decides that he should not get married, he is doing something even better.)<verse eid="1CO 7:38"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Women whose husbands have died are free to get remarried, but only to believers. However, they will probably be happier if they do not marry again.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 7:39-40">1 Corinthians 7:39-40</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 7:39"/>Women must remain married to their husbands while their husbands are still alive. But if a woman’s husband dies, she is free to marry any <char style="add">unmarried</char> man whom she wants to marry, but he must belong to the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 7:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 7:40"/>However, I think that she will be happier if she does not marry again. And I believe that the Spirit of God is <char style="add">directing</char> me <char style="add">as I say that</char>.<verse eid="1CO 7:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="1CO 8"/>
  <para style="s1">We should not be proud about knowing the truth about idols.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 8:1-3">1 Corinthians 8:1-3</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 8:1"/>Now <char style="add">I will answer what you asked</char> about <char style="add">us believers</char> eating meat that has been sacrificed to idols. <char style="add">We know what some of you say, that God has enabled</char> all of us <char style="add">to</char> know <char style="add">the truth about things such as idols. But often we become</char> proud because we say that we know <char style="add">all those things</char>. But instead of being proud about what we know, we should show that we love <char style="add">our fellow believers by helping them to</char> become spiritually mature. <verse eid="1CO 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 8:2"/>Those who think that they thoroughly know something do not yet know it as they should. <verse eid="1CO 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 8:3"/>But as for those who love God, they know that they belong to him.<verse eid="1CO 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">There are many idols that people think are gods, but there is only one true God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 8:4-6">1 Corinthians 8:4-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 8:4"/>So <char style="add">I will tell you</char> about eating meat that people have sacrificed to idols. We know that it is true, <char style="add">as you say</char>, that idols are not really alive. We also know that there is only one real God. <verse eid="1CO 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 8:5"/>It is true that there are gods whom people think live in the heavens or whom they think live on earth. Truly, there are many beings that <char style="add">people</char> call gods, and whom <char style="add">they</char> call lords. <verse eid="1CO 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 8:6"/>But for us <char style="add">believers</char> there is only one real God. He is <char style="add">our heavenly</char> Father who created everything. He is the one whom we <char style="add">worship and serve</char>. Also, for us believers Jesus Christ is the one and only Lord. He is the one whom <char style="add">God caused</char> to create everything. It is because of what he <char style="add">has done for us on the cross</char> that we have <char style="add">spiritual</char> life.<verse eid="1CO 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not eat meat offered to idols if that would encourage other believers to eat that food contrary to their conscience.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 8:7-13">1 Corinthians 8:7-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 8:7"/>Nevertheless, some people do not understand <char style="add">that idols are not really alive</char>. In the past, some among you who are believers now were accustomed to believing that idols <char style="add">were really alive</char>. As a result, when they eat such meat <char style="add">now</char>, they still think that it was sacrificed to an idol <char style="add">that is alive</char>. They are not sure <char style="add">that God allows believers to eat meat that has been offered to idols</char>. So, <char style="add">when they eat such meat</char>, they think that they have sinned. <verse eid="1CO 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 8:8"/>But God will not think more highly about us <char style="add">if we eat certain</char> foods, or if we do not eat <char style="add">certain foods</char>. That is, we are not more acceptable to God if we do not eat certain foods, nor are we more acceptable to him if we eat those foods. <verse eid="1CO 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 8:9"/>However, be sure that you do not do anything that God allows you to do, if by doing that you would encourage any of <char style="add">your fellow believers to do something that</char> they are not sure <char style="add">God allows them to do</char>. As a result, you would be causing them to sin. <verse eid="1CO 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 8:10"/>For example, you know <char style="add">that idols are not really alive</char>. Suppose that in a temple <char style="add">where they worship</char> idols you eat <char style="add">food that has been sacrificed to idols</char>. Suppose that someone who is not sure whether God allows us to eat that food sees you eating it. <char style="add">You</char> would be encouraging him to eat it, too. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 8:11"/>As a result, you who know that <char style="add">idols are not really alive</char>, might cause that fellow believer, one for whom Christ died, ◄to be ruined <char style="add">spiritually</char>/to stop believing <char style="add">in Christ</char>►. <verse eid="1CO 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 8:12"/>By sinning against your fellow believer by causing him to do something that he thinks God does not allow us to do, <char style="add">it is as though</char> you are sinning against Christ himself! <verse eid="1CO 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 8:13"/>So if <char style="add">I, Paul, think that by</char> eating a certain food I might cause a fellow believer to be ruined spiritually, I will never eat such food again. I do not want to cause any fellow believer ◄to be ruined spiritually/to stop believing in Christ►. <char style="add">And you should</char> ◄<char style="add">do as I do/imitate my example</char>►.<verse eid="1CO 8:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="1CO 9"/>
  <para style="s1">As your apostle I am free to do anything that God allows me to do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 9:1-2">1 Corinthians 9:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 9:1"/>I am certainly free <char style="add">to do all the things that God allows me to do.</char> [RHQ] I am an apostle. [RHQ] <char style="add">You</char> certainly <char style="add">know that</char> I have seen Jesus our Lord. [RHQ] It is a result of my work that you <char style="add">have believed in</char> the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char>. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 9:2"/>And even though other people may think that I am not an apostle, you certainly should know that I am an apostle. <char style="add">Remember that</char> your having become Christians [MET] <char style="add">as a result of my telling you about</char> the Lord ◄confirms/shows that it is true► that I am an apostle.<verse eid="1CO 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Barnabas and I have the same right to receive financial support that the other apostles have.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 9:3-7">1 Corinthians 9:3-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 9:3"/>In order to defend myself, this <char style="add">is what I say</char> to those who criticize me <char style="add">by claiming that I do not act like an apostle</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 9:4"/>As for Barnabas and me, we certainly have the right <char style="add">as apostles</char> to receive <char style="add">from you and other congregations</char> food and drink <char style="add">for our work</char>. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 9:5"/><char style="add">We have the</char> same right <char style="add">that</char> the other apostles and the Lord Jesus’ <char style="add">younger</char> brothers and <char style="add">especially</char> Peter have. They all take along a wife who is a believer <char style="add">when they travel various places in order to tell people about Christ. And they have a right that the people whom they work among will support their wives, too</char>. So Barnabas and I certainly have those same rights. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 9:6"/>It would be ridiculous to think that Barnabas and I are the only apostles who must work to earn money to pay our expenses <char style="add">while we are doing God’s work! [RHQ]</char> <verse eid="1CO 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 9:7"/>Soldiers certainly do not pay their own wages. [RHQ] Those who plant a vineyard would certainly eat some of the grapes <char style="add">when they become ripe</char>. [RHQ] Those who care for sheep would certainly drink the milk from those sheep. [RHQ] <char style="add">Similarly, those who tell others about Christ certainly have a right to receive</char> ◄<char style="add">financial help/food</char>► <char style="add">from the people to whom they preach</char>.<verse eid="1CO 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s servants have always had the right to receive financial help from others, but we have not insisted on that right because we want to preach the gospel without charge.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 9:8-18">1 Corinthians 9:8-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 9:8"/>I am saying that, not only because people think that it is right. [RHQ] <char style="add">No</char>, I am [RHQ] saying it because it is what <char style="add">God said</char> in the laws <char style="add">that he gave to Moses</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 9:9"/>Moses wrote in one of those laws, “While an ox is threshing <char style="add">grain</char>, you must not tie its mouth shut <char style="add">so that it cannot eat the grain</char>.” ◄God was not only concerned about oxen <char style="add">when he gave that law</char>./Was God <char style="add">only</char> concerned about oxen <char style="add">when he gave that law</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 9:10"/><char style="add">No</char>, he was [RHQ] concerned about us, also! Yes, <char style="add">God caused Moses to</char> write those words <char style="add">because he is concerned</char> about us! Those who plow the ground confidently expect <char style="add">to eat some of</char> the crop <char style="add">that grows</char>. Those who thresh grain confidently expect <char style="add">to eat some of the grain that they thresh. Similarly, we who proclaim the message about Christ have the right to confidently expect to receive financial help for our work</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 9:11"/>And because we have proclaimed God’s message to you, we certainly have the right to receive from you the things that we need for our bodies [MET]! [MET, RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 9:12"/>Since other people <char style="add">who preached to you</char> had that right, certainly Barnabas and I have the same right. [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1CO 9:12">However, neither of us insisted <char style="add">that you give us the things that</char> we have a right <char style="add">to receive from you</char>. Instead, we were willing to endure anything in order that we not hinder <char style="add">anyone from believing</char> the message about Christ. <verse eid="1CO 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 9:13"/>You should keep in mind that <char style="add">the priests and servants</char> in the Temple eat <char style="add">some of the food that people bring to</char> the Temple. [RHQ] Specifically, the priests who work at the altar eat some of <char style="add">the food that the people bring to sacrifice on</char> the altar. <verse eid="1CO 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 9:14"/>So the Lord has commanded that those who proclaim the good message <char style="add">about him</char> should receive from <char style="add">those who hear that</char> message what they need to live on.<verse eid="1CO 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 9:15"/>However, I have not requested that you <char style="add">give me</char> those things that I have a right <char style="add">to receive from you</char>. Furthermore, I am writing this to you, not in order to request you to begin <char style="add">giving me financial help now</char>. I would rather die than to <char style="add">receive help from you</char>. I do not want anyone to prevent me from boasting <char style="add">about my proclaiming God’s message to you without receiving financial help from you</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 9:16"/>When I proclaim the message about Christ, I cannot boast <char style="add">about doing it</char>, because <char style="add">Christ</char> has commanded me <char style="add">to do it</char>. I would be very miserable (OR, <char style="add">I am afraid that</char> God would punish me) if I did not proclaim that message. <verse eid="1CO 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 9:17"/>If I had decided by myself to proclaim it, <char style="add">God</char> would reward me. But I did not decide by myself to do that. I am simply doing the work that <char style="add">God</char> entrusted to me. <verse eid="1CO 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 9:18"/>So perhaps you wonder what my reward is. [RHQ] <char style="add">I will tell you</char>. When I proclaim the good message <char style="add">about Christ</char>, I do not ask people for financial help. It <char style="add">makes me very happy not to ask for help, and being happy is the</char> reward I get. I do not want to use the rights that I have <char style="add">when I proclaim</char> the gospel.<verse eid="1CO 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I have adopted the code of conduct of whatever group I have been among, in order to bring more people to Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 9:19-27">1 Corinthians 9:19-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 9:19"/>I am not obligated to do what anyone else thinks that I should do. Nevertheless, when I have been with any group of people, I have made myself <char style="add">do what they believed that I should do, just like a slave does what his master wants him to do</char>. I have done that in order that I might convince more people <char style="add">to trust in Christ</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 9:20"/>Specifically, when I was with fellow Jews, I did the things that Jews <char style="add">think that people should do</char>. I did that in order that I might convince some of them <char style="add">to trust in Christ</char>. Although I am now not obligated to obey the Jewish laws and rituals, when I was with those who believe that they are obligated to obey those laws, I did the things that they <char style="add">think that people should do</char>. I did that in order to convince some of them <char style="add">to trust in Christ</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 9:21"/>When I was with ◄non-Jews/those who do not know those laws►, I did the things that non-Jews <char style="add">think that people should do</char>, in order that I might convince some of them <char style="add">to trust in Christ</char>. I do not mean that I disobey God’s laws. No, I obey the things that Christ commanded us to do. <verse eid="1CO 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 9:22"/>When I was with those who doubt <char style="add">whether God will permit them to do certain things that others</char> ◄<char style="add">disapprove of/think it is not right to do</char>►, I <char style="add">avoided doing those things</char>, in order that I might convince some of them <char style="add">to trust in Christ</char>. In summary, I have done all the things <char style="add">that the people I have been with think that others should do</char>, in order that by every possible means I might convince some of them <char style="add">to trust in Christ</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 9:23"/>I do all these things in order that <char style="add">more people will believe</char> the message about Christ, and in order that I, along with other believers, may receive the good things <char style="add">that God promises to give us</char>.<verse eid="1CO 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 9:24"/>When people run in a race, they all run, but only one of them wins the race and as a result gets a prize. You certainly know that [RHQ]. So, <char style="add">just like</char> runners <char style="add">exert themselves fully to win a race</char> [MET], <char style="add">you should exert yourselves fully to do the things that God wants you to do</char>, in order that you may receive the reward <char style="add">that God wants to give you</char>. <verse eid="1CO 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 9:25"/>All athletes exercise their bodies strenuously in many ways. They do that in order to receive a wreath <char style="add">as a reward to wear on their heads</char>. Those wreaths fade, but we will receive a reward that will last forever [LIT]. <verse eid="1CO 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 9:26"/>For that reason, I <char style="add">try hard to please God</char> [MET], <char style="add">like a</char> runner who runs toward the goal [LIT]. I <char style="add">try hard to accomplish what God wants me to accomplish, like</char> a boxer tries hard to hit his opponent, not to miss hitting him. <verse eid="1CO 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 9:27"/>I beat my body <char style="add">to make it do what I want it to do</char> [MET], <char style="add">as</char> slaves <char style="add">obey their masters</char>, in order that, after I have proclaimed <char style="add">God’s message</char> to others, he will not <char style="add">say that I do</char> not deserve to receive a reward.<verse eid="1CO 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="1CO 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Our Jewish ancestors all experienced God’s power, but almost all of them died in the desert because they sinned against him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 10:1-5">1 Corinthians 10:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 10:1"/>My fellow believers, I want to remind you about our(exc) <char style="add">Jewish</char> ancestors. They were all under the cloud <char style="add">by which God miraculously led them and protected them when they left Egypt with Moses</char>. All those ancestors crossed the <char style="add">Red</char> Sea <char style="add">after God miraculously made the water separate so that they could walk through it</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 10:2"/>God caused all of them to begin to live under the authority of [MTY] Moses <char style="add">when they walked</char> under that cloud and <char style="add">walked through the Red</char> Sea. <verse eid="1CO 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 10:3"/>All <char style="add">those ancestors of ours ate the same food that God</char> miraculously <char style="add">provided</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 10:4"/>They all drank water that <char style="add">God</char> miraculously <char style="add">provided</char>. That is, they all drank water that God miraculously made come out of the rock. That rock was <char style="add">a symbol of</char> [MET] Christ, who went with them. <char style="add">So we conclude that God helped all of those people in many ways</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 10:5"/>However, <char style="add">we also conclude that</char> God was angry [LIT] with most of those people <char style="add">because they sinned against him. He caused almost all of them to die, and as</char> a result their bodies were scattered in the desert.<verse eid="1CO 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">What happened to our Jewish ancestors was a warning of what will happen to us if we give in to temptation.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 10:6-13">1 Corinthians 10:6-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 10:6"/>Those things <char style="add">that happened long ago</char> became examples to teach us <char style="add">the following things</char>: We should not desire to <char style="add">do</char> evil things as those people desired to do. <verse eid="1CO 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 10:7"/>We should not worship idols as many of those people did. <char style="add">Remember that Moses</char> wrote, “The people sat down. They ate and drank <char style="add">to honor the golden calf that they had just made</char>. Then they got up to dance <char style="add">immorally</char>.” <verse eid="1CO 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 10:8"/>We should not have sexual relations with someone to whom we are not married, as many of them did. As a result, God <char style="add">punished them by</char> causing 23,000 people to die in <char style="add">only</char> one day. <verse eid="1CO 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 10:9"/>We should not try to see how much we can sin without the Lord punishing us. Some of them did that, and as a result they died because <char style="add">poisonous</char> snakes <char style="add">bit them</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 10:10"/>We should not complain <char style="add">about what God does</char>. Some of them did that, and as a result an angel destroyed them. <char style="add">So God will certainly punish us if we sin like they did</char>.<verse eid="1CO 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 10:11"/>All those things <char style="add">that happened to our ancestors long ago</char> are examples for us. <char style="add">Moses</char> wrote those things to warn us <char style="add">who are living at this time which is near the end</char>. We are the people for whom God has done <char style="add">the things that he decided to do in</char> the previous periods of time. <verse eid="1CO 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 10:12"/>So <char style="add">I say this to</char> all those who confidently <char style="add">think that they will always</char> steadfastly continue to <char style="add">believe what God said and will never disobey what he commanded</char>: Be careful that you <char style="add">(sg)</char> do not sin <char style="add">when you are tempted</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 10:13"/><char style="add">Remember that</char> your desires to sin are the same desires that other people have. But when you are tempted to sin, you can trust God <char style="add">to help you</char>. He will not permit you to be tempted {anything to tempt you} more than you are able to resist. Instead, when you are tempted {things tempt you}, he will also provide a way <char style="add">for you</char> to endure it <char style="add">without sinning</char>.<verse eid="1CO 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God will punish us if we participate in demon worship by eating food sacrificed to demons when we eat the Lord’s Supper.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 10:14-22">1 Corinthians 10:14-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 10:14"/>So, <char style="add">I say to</char> you people whom I love, <char style="add">avoid</char> worshipping idols <char style="add">just like you would</char> run away from <char style="add">anything that is dangerous</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 10:15"/>It is to people who <char style="add">think that they</char> are wise that I write. So, you, as wise people, judge whether what I am writing <char style="add">is true</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 10:16"/><char style="add">During the Lord’s Supper, after we ask God to</char> bless ◄the <char style="add">wine</char>/the <char style="add">juice</char>► <char style="add">in the</char> cup, we give thanks for it <char style="add">and drink it</char>. By doing that, we certainly are [RHQ] sharing in what Christ <char style="add">did for us when</char> his blood <char style="add">flowed from his body when he died. During the Lord’s Supper, when we break</char> the bread <char style="add">and eat it</char>, we are certainly sharing in [MTY] what Christ <char style="add">did for us when</char> his body <char style="add">suffered for us on the cross</char>. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 10:17"/>Because it is one loaf of bread that we <char style="add">break and eat during the Lord’s Supper, it symbolizes that</char> we who are many are one group, because we all eat from the one loaf.<verse eid="1CO 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 10:18"/>Consider <char style="add">what happens when</char> the Israeli people <char style="add">eat the food that the priests</char> sacrifice on the altar <char style="add">outside the Temple</char>. They participate in <char style="add">what the priests do at</char> [MTY] the altar. [RHQ] <char style="add">Similarly, if you eat food that non-believers have offered to an idol in a temple, you are participating in their worship of the idol there</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 10:19"/>By saying that, <char style="add">I</char> do not mean that offering food to an idol makes it anything <char style="add">more than just ordinary food [RHQ].</char> I do not mean that an idol is anything <char style="add">more than just an idol</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 10:20"/>No! Instead, I mean that what people sacrifice <char style="add">to idols</char>, they are sacrificing to demons, not to God. So, <char style="add">if you eat food that has been sacrificed to idols, you are participating in worshipping the demons that the idols represent</char>. And I do not want you to participate in worshipping demons! <verse eid="1CO 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 10:21"/>When you drink the <char style="add">grape juice/wine in</char> [MTY] the cup <char style="add">at the Lord’s Supper</char>, you cannot participate in the <char style="add">blessings that</char> the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> brought to us and at the same time drink the <char style="add">wine in the</char> [MTY] cup that people offer to demons! When you eat at the Lord’s table, you cannot participate in the blessings the Lord provided [MTY] when he died for us and at the same time participate in the things that represent demons <char style="add">by eating food that has been sacrificed to idols</char> <verse eid="1CO 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 10:22"/><char style="add">If you participate in honoring demons in that way</char>, you will certainly make the Lord very angry [RHQ]! ◄Remember that you are certainly not stronger than he is./Do you think that you are stronger than he is?► [RHQ] <char style="add">Certainly not, so you will not escape his punishing you if you honor demons in that way!</char><verse eid="1CO 10:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is all right to eat food offered to idols, but we should not do so if it would offend those who think that it is wrong.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 10:23-11:1">1 Corinthians 10:23—11:1</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 10:23"/>
    <char style="add">Some people say</char>, “<char style="add">God</char> permits <char style="add">believers to do</char> anything.” But <char style="add">I say that</char> not everything that people do benefits <char style="add">those who do it! Yes, some people say</char>, “God permits <char style="add">believers to do</char> all things.” But not everything that people do helps them to become <char style="add">spiritually</char> mature. <verse eid="1CO 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 10:24"/>No one should try to benefit <char style="add">only</char> himself. Instead, each person should try to benefit other people <char style="add">spiritually</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 10:25"/><char style="add">This is what you should do</char>: Eat any <char style="add">food</char> that is sold {that people sell} in the market. Do not ask questions <char style="add">to find out if that food has been offered</char> {<char style="add">someone offered that food</char>} <char style="add">to idols, just</char> because you think it would be wrong <char style="add">to eat such food</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 10:26"/><char style="add">Remember that the Psalmist wrote</char>, “Everything on the earth belongs to <char style="add">the</char> Lord <char style="add">God because he created it!</char>” <char style="add">So, food that has been offered to idols belongs to the Lord, not to the idols, and you may eat it</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 10:27"/>If a non-believer invites you to a meal, go if you want to, and eat any food that is set {that <char style="add">he</char> sets} before you. Do not ask <char style="add">whether it was offered to idols, just</char> because you think that it would be wrong <char style="add">to eat such food</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 10:28"/>But if someone says to you, “This is food that was sacrificed <char style="add">to an idol</char>,” do not eat it, for the sake of the person who told that to you, and also because someone there may think that it is wrong <char style="add">to eat such food</char>. <verse eid="1CO 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 10:29"/>I do not mean that you <char style="add">should be concerned about whether it is all right to eat such food</char>. What I mean is that you should be concerned about others who may think that it is wrong to eat such food. Since I know that I ◄am free/have the right► <char style="add">to eat such food without God punishing me</char>, no one should [RHQ] say that what I am doing is wrong just because he himself thinks that it is wrong. <verse eid="1CO 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 10:30"/>If I thank <char style="add">God</char> for the food when I eat <char style="add">food that has been offered to an idol</char>, no one should criticize me for eating food for which I have thanked God [RHQ]!<verse eid="1CO 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 10:31"/>So <char style="add">I say to you in conclusion</char>, when you eat <char style="add">food</char>, or drink <char style="add">something</char>, or do anything else, do everything in order that <char style="add">people will</char> praise God. <verse eid="1CO 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 10:32"/>Do not do anything that would hinder Jews or Greeks <char style="add">from becoming believers</char>, and do not do things that would encourage members of God’s congregations to sin. <verse eid="1CO 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 10:33"/><char style="add">Do as I do</char>. I try to please everyone in every way. I do this by not seeking to benefit myself. Instead, I try to benefit many others, in order that they may be saved {that <char style="add">God</char> may save them} <char style="add">from the guilt of their sins</char>.<verse eid="1CO 10:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="1CO 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 11:1"/>
    <char style="add">Follow my example</char>, just like I <char style="add">try to</char> follow Christ’s example.<verse eid="1CO 11:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Women should wear a hair covering while praying or prophesying in a service, but men should not do so.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 11:2-16">1 Corinthians 11:2-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 11:2"/>I praise you because you remember all the things <char style="add">that I taught you</char> and because you follow the instructions that I gave you. You have done just like I told you to do. <verse eid="1CO 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 11:3"/><char style="add">Now</char>, I want you to know that the one who has authority over [MTY] every man is Christ, and the ones who have authority over women are men (OR, their husbands), and the one who has authority over Christ is God. <verse eid="1CO 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 11:4"/><char style="add">So</char> if any man <char style="add">wears a covering over</char> his head when he prays or speaks a message God gave him, he disgraces himself [SYN]. <verse eid="1CO 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 11:5"/>Also, if any woman does not wear a covering over her head when she prays or speaks a message that God gave her, she disgraces herself (OR, she dishonors her husband). That would be acting like [SIM] <char style="add">women who are ashamed because</char> their heads have been shaved. <verse eid="1CO 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 11:6"/>So, if women do not wear coverings over their heads <char style="add">when they pray or speak messages that God gave them</char>, they should let someone shave their heads <char style="add">so that they will be ashamed</char>. But since women are ashamed if someone cuts their hair <char style="add">short</char> or shaves off their hair, they should wear coverings over their heads <char style="add">when they pray or speak messages that God gave them</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 11:7"/>Men should not wear coverings over their heads <char style="add">when they pray or speak messages that God gave them</char>, because they represent what God is like [MET] and they show how great God is. But women show how great men (OR, their husbands) are. <verse eid="1CO 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 11:8"/><char style="add">Remember that God intends that men have authority over women. We know that</char> because <char style="add">God</char> did not make <char style="add">the first</char> man, <char style="add">Adam</char>, from the <char style="add">first</char> woman, <char style="add">Eve</char>. Instead, he made that woman <char style="add">from a bone that he took</char> from the man. <verse eid="1CO 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 11:9"/>Also, <char style="add">God</char> did not create <char style="add">the first</char> man <char style="add">to help</char> the woman. Instead, <char style="add">he</char> created the woman <char style="add">to help</char> the man. <verse eid="1CO 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 11:10"/>For that reason, women should wear something <char style="add">to cover</char> their heads <char style="add">as a symbol of their being under their husbands’</char> [MTY] authority. They should also <char style="add">cover their heads</char> so that the angels <char style="add">will see that and rejoice</char>.<verse eid="1CO 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11-12" style="v" sid="1CO 11:11-12"/>However, remember that <char style="add">even though God created the first</char> woman from <char style="add">the first</char> man, all other men <char style="add">have been born</char> from women. So men cannot be independent of women, nor can women be independent of men. But all things, <char style="add">including men and women</char>, come from God. <verse eid="1CO 11:11-12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 11:13"/>Consider this for yourselves: Is it proper for [RHQ] women to pray to God while they do not have coverings over their heads? <verse eid="1CO 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 11:14"/>◄Everyone senses that it is disgraceful for men to have long hair./Doesn’t everyone sense that it is disgraceful for men to have long hair?► [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 11:15"/>But it is very delightful if women have long hair, because <char style="add">God</char> gave them long hair to be like a <char style="add">beautiful</char> covering <char style="add">for their heads</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 11:16"/>But whoever wants to argue <char style="add">with me about my saying that women should have a covering over their heads when they pray or speak a message from God should consider the fact that</char> we <char style="add">apostles</char> do not <char style="add">permit</char> any other custom, and the <char style="add">other</char> congregations of God do not have any other custom.<verse eid="1CO 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When you gather to eat the Lord’s Supper, you act selfishly. I cannot praise you for that.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 11:17-22">1 Corinthians 11:17-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 11:17"/>Now I want to tell you <char style="add">about some other things</char>. I do not praise you about them, because whenever you believers meet together, good <char style="add">things do not happen</char>. Instead, bad things <char style="add">happen</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 11:18"/>First of all, people have told me that when you gather together as a group <char style="add">to worship God</char>, you divide into groups <char style="add">that are hostile to each other</char>. To some extent I believe that is true. <verse eid="1CO 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 11:19"/>It seems that you must divide into <char style="add">groups that despise each other</char> in order that it might be clear/evident which people among you <char style="add">God</char> approves of! <verse eid="1CO 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 11:20"/>When you gather together, you [IRO] eat the meal <char style="add">that you say is to remember the death of</char> the Lord <char style="add">Jesus for us</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 11:21"/>But <char style="add">what happens when</char> you eat is that each person eats his own meal before <char style="add">he thinks about sharing his food with anyone else</char>. As a result, <char style="add">when the meal is over</char>, some people are <char style="add">still</char> hungry and others are drunk! <char style="add">So it is not a meal that honors the Lord</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 11:22"/>◄<char style="add">You act as though</char> you do not have your own houses in which you can eat and drink <char style="add">whatever you want to</char>!/Do you not have your own houses in which you can eat and drink <char style="add">whatever you want to</char>?► [RHQ] Do you not realize [RHQ] <char style="add">that by acting selfishly in this way</char>, it is God’s people whom you are despising, and it is the poor people <char style="add">in your group</char> whom you are treating as though they were not important? What shall I say to you about that [RHQ]? Do <char style="add">you expect</char> me to praise you <char style="add">about what you do</char> [RHQ]? I certainly will not praise you!<verse eid="1CO 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Lord gave us instructions about the significance of the Lord’s Supper.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 11:23-26">1 Corinthians 11:23-26</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 11:23"/>The Lord taught me these things that I also taught you: During the night that Jesus was betrayed {<char style="add">Judas</char> enabled <char style="add">the enemies of</char> the Lord Jesus to seize him}, he took some bread. <verse eid="1CO 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 11:24"/>After he thanked God for it, he broke it into pieces. <char style="add">Then he gave it to his disciples</char> and said, “This bread <char style="add">represents</char> [MET] (OR, is) my body, that <char style="add">I am about to sacrifice</char> for you. Eat bread in this <char style="add">way again and again</char> to remember my <char style="add">offering myself as a sacrifice for you</char>.” <verse eid="1CO 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 11:25"/>Similarly, after they ate their meal, he took a cup [MTY] <char style="add">of wine</char>. He <char style="add">thanked God for it. Then he gave it to his disciples</char>, saying, “<char style="add">The wine in</char> [MTY] this cup <char style="add">represents</char> [MET] (OR, is) my blood <char style="add">that will flow from my body</char> ◄<char style="add">to put into effect/to establish</char>► the new agreement <char style="add">that God is making with people</char>. Whenever you drink wine in this way, do it to remember that <char style="add">my blood flowed for you</char>.” <verse eid="1CO 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 11:26"/><char style="add">Remember that</char> until the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> returns <char style="add">to the earth</char>, whenever you eat the <char style="add">bread that represents his body</char> and drink the wine [MTY] <char style="add">that represents his blood</char>, you are telling other people that he died <char style="add">for you</char>.<verse eid="1CO 11:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God punishes those who eat the Lord’s Supper in a way that does not express the unity of his people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 11:27-34">1 Corinthians 11:27-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 11:27"/>So, those who eat that bread and drink that wine [MTY] in a way that is not proper <char style="add">for those who belong to the Lord</char> are guilty of <char style="add">acting in a way that is contrary to what</char> our <char style="add">Lord intended when he offered</char> his body <char style="add">as a sacrifice</char> and his blood <char style="add">flowed when he died</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 11:28"/>Before any believer eats that bread and drinks that wine [MTY], he should think carefully about <char style="add">what he is doing</char>, <verse eid="1CO 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 11:29"/>because if anyone eats <char style="add">the bread that represents Christ’s body</char> and drinks <char style="add">the wine that represents his blood</char> without recognizing that all God’s <char style="add">people should be united, God will</char> punish him <char style="add">for doing that</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 11:30"/>Many people in your group are weak and sick, and several have died [EUP] because of <char style="add">the way they acted when they ate that bread and drank that wine</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 11:31"/>If we would think carefully about what we <char style="add">are doing</char>, <char style="add">God</char> would not judge <char style="add">and punish</char> us <char style="add">like that</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 11:32"/>But when the Lord judges <char style="add">and punishes</char> us <char style="add">for acting wrongly</char>, he disciplines us <char style="add">to correct us</char>, in order that he will not <char style="add">need to</char> punish us when he punishes <char style="add">the people who do not trust in Christ</char> [MTY].<verse eid="1CO 11:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 11:33"/>So, my fellow believers, when you gather together to eat <char style="add">food to remember the Lord’s dying for you</char>, wait until everyone <char style="add">has arrived so that you can find out who does not have enough food</char>. <verse eid="1CO 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 11:34"/>Those who are so hungry <char style="add">that they cannot wait to eat until everyone else has arrived</char> should eat in their own homes <char style="add">first</char>, in order that when you gather together God will not judge <char style="add">and punish them for</char> ◄<char style="add">being inconsiderate of/not being concerned about</char>► <char style="add">others</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1CO 11:34">And when I come <char style="add">to Corinth</char> I will give you instructions about other matters <char style="add">concerning the Lord’s Supper</char>.<verse eid="1CO 11:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="1CO 12"/>
  <para style="s1">It is only God’s Spirit who enables people to say that Jesus is Lord.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 12:1-3">1 Corinthians 12:1-3</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 12:1"/>Now, my fellow believers, <char style="add">I will answer your questions</char> about the things God’s Spirit <char style="add">enables believers to do</char>. I want you to know clearly [LIT] <char style="add">about these things</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 12:2"/>You know that before you became Christians, various things led you to <char style="add">worship</char> idols, which are unable to tell you <char style="add">any of God’s message</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 12:3"/>So <char style="add">the first thing</char> that I will tell you now is that it is not the Spirit of God who would cause anyone to say, “Jesus deserved to die,” and that the Holy Spirit is the only one who can enable anyone to say, “Jesus is <char style="add">truly</char> the Lord.”<verse eid="1CO 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Spirit gives believers special abilities as he desires.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 12:4-11">1 Corinthians 12:4-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 12:4"/>There are various things <char style="add">that God’s</char> Spirit enables <char style="add">various believers to do</char>, but it is that same Spirit <char style="add">who enables us to do them</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 12:5"/>There are many different ways to serve <char style="add">the Lord</char>, but it is the same Lord <char style="add">whom we all are serving</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 12:6"/><char style="add">We believers</char> have the power to do various <char style="add">tasks</char>, but it is the same God who gives all of us the power <char style="add">to do</char> these things.<verse eid="1CO 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 12:7"/>
    <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit gives his power to each believer in order to benefit all the other <char style="add">believers</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 12:8"/>To some, the Spirit gives the ability to speak very wise messages. To others, the same Spirit gives the ability to know <char style="add">things that he reveals to them</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 12:9"/>To others, the same Spirit gives the ability to believe <char style="add">that God will work miracles</char>. To others, the Spirit gives the ability to heal <char style="add">sick people</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 12:10"/>To others, he gives the power <char style="add">to perform</char> miracles. To others, he gives the ability to speak messages that come directly from God. To others, he gives the ability to tell <char style="add">if a message is really from God or not</char>. To others he gives the ability to speak messages in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that they have not learned</char>. To others, he gives the ability to tell the meaning of those messages [MTY]. <verse eid="1CO 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 12:11"/>It is the same Spirit who gives all these abilities. He gives whatever abilities he wants to give, to whatever person he wants to give them.<verse eid="1CO 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A congregation needs all the abilities that God’s Spirit gives to its members, but you should especially desire the ones that help others the most.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 12:12-31">1 Corinthians 12:12-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 12:12"/>Although a person’s body has many parts, all the parts form just one body [DOU]. It is like that <char style="add">with those who belong to</char> Christ. <verse eid="1CO 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 12:13"/>When we were baptized {When people baptized us}, the one <char style="add">Holy</char> Spirit caused us to become one group <char style="add">of believers</char>. It does not matter whether we are Jews or non-Jews. It does not matter whether we are slaves or not slaves. <char style="add">When we believed in Christ</char>, the one Spirit came to live [MET] within all of us.<verse eid="1CO 12:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 12:14"/>
    <char style="add">Our</char> bodies do not have only one part. They have many parts <char style="add">with various functions</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 12:15"/>If our foot could <char style="add">talk and</char> say <char style="add">to us</char>, “Because I am not <char style="add">your</char> hand, I am not a part of <char style="add">your</char> body,” it would still be a part of <char style="add">our</char> body. <verse eid="1CO 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 12:16"/>If our ear could <char style="add">talk and</char> say, “Because I am not <char style="add">your</char> eye, I am not a part of your body,” it would still be a part of our body. <verse eid="1CO 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 12:17"/>If our body were only an eye, ◄we would not be able to hear./how could we hear?► [RHQ] If our body were only an ear, ◄we would not be able to smell <char style="add">anything</char>!/how could we smell <char style="add">anything</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 12:18"/>But the truth is that God has put all the parts of our bodies together exactly as he wanted to put them. <verse eid="1CO 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 12:19"/>If <char style="add">our body</char> had only one part, it would not be a body. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 12:20"/>But the truth is that there are many parts <char style="add">in our body</char>, but it is still only one body. <verse eid="1CO 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 12:21"/>That is why if our eye <char style="add">could talk</char>, it should never say to our hand, “I do not need you!” And if our head <char style="add">could talk</char>, it should not say to our feet, “I do not need you!” <verse eid="1CO 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 12:22"/>Instead, the parts of our body that seem to be weaker are the ones that are absolutely necessary. <verse eid="1CO 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 12:23"/>And the parts that we do not think highly of are the parts that we clothe carefully. And we protect carefully those parts that we do not show to people. <verse eid="1CO 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 12:24"/>The parts that are <char style="add">all right to</char> show people, we do not need to protect. Instead, God, who has put all the parts of our bodies together, causes us to care for in a special way the parts that we think are less important. <verse eid="1CO 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 12:25"/>He does that in order that all the parts of our body will work together harmoniously [LIT], and so that all the parts will care for all the other parts equally. <verse eid="1CO 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 12:26"/>If one part of our body hurts, <char style="add">it is as though</char> all the parts of our body are hurting. If we pay special attention to one part of our body, <char style="add">it is as though</char> all the parts of our body feel pleasure [MET].<verse eid="1CO 12:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 12:27"/>
    <char style="add">Everything I have just said about how the parts of our bodies relate to each other applies to how</char> all of you who belong to Christ <char style="add">should relate to each other</char>. Each of you belongs to him, <char style="add">but you have not all been given the same abilities and work</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 12:28"/>God has placed apostles in our congregations. Apostles are first <char style="add">in rank</char>. Next <char style="add">in rank</char> are those who speak messages which come directly from God. Next <char style="add">in rank</char> are those who teach <char style="add">spiritual truth</char>. Then there are those who have the power to work miracles, those who have the ability to heal <char style="add">sick people</char>, those who have the ability to help <char style="add">others</char>, those who have the ability to govern <char style="add">the affairs of the congregation</char>, and those who have the ability to speak <char style="add">messages</char> in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that they have not learned</char>. <verse eid="1CO 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 12:29"/>Certainly not all <char style="add">believers</char> are apostles. [RHQ] They all do not have the ability to speak messages that come directly from God. [RHQ] They do not all have the ability to teach <char style="add">spiritual truth</char>. [RHQ] They do not all have the power to work miracles. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 12:30"/>They do not all have the ability to heal people. [RHQ] They do not all have the ability to speak <char style="add">messages</char> in languages [MTY] <char style="add">they have not learned</char>. [RHQ] They do not all have the ability to tell others the meaning of those messages. [RHQ] <char style="add">Certainly not!</char> <verse eid="1CO 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 12:31"/>But you should eagerly desire to have <char style="add">the abilities that will help other believers</char> the most (OR, <char style="add">the abilities that God considers</char> to be the most important). But now I will tell you the best way <char style="add">to use the abilities that God’s Spirit has given you</char>.<verse eid="1CO 12:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="1CO 13"/>
  <para style="s1">We should use the abilities that God’s Spirit has given us in ways that show that we love others.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 13:1-13">1 Corinthians 13:1-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 13:1"/>Supposing we could speak <char style="add">all</char> the various languages [MTY] that people <char style="add">in the world speak</char> and even speak <char style="add">the language</char> that angels <char style="add">speak</char>. If we did not love <char style="add">others, speaking those languages</char> would be <char style="add">as useless as beating</char> a brass gong or clanging cymbals <char style="add">together</char>. <verse eid="1CO 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 13:2"/>Supposing we had the ability to speak messages that come directly from God, and we could understand the plans that he has not yet revealed <char style="add">to others</char>, and we could know everything <char style="add">about everything</char>, and we believed in God so strongly that we could <char style="add">do impossible things like</char> causing mountains to move. If we did not love <char style="add">others, God would consider all that</char> to be worthless. <verse eid="1CO 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 13:3"/>And supposing we would give everything that we own to poor people, and would let others kill us in order that we could boast about <char style="add">sacrificing our</char> own bodies. If we did not love <char style="add">others</char>, we would not get any reward <char style="add">from God</char>.<verse eid="1CO 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 13:4"/>Those who [PRS] truly love <char style="add">others</char> act patiently and kindly toward them. Those who [PRS] truly love <char style="add">others</char> are not jealous of them, they do not boast <char style="add">about what they themselves have done</char>, and are not proud. <verse eid="1CO 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 13:5"/>Those who [PRS] truly love <char style="add">others</char> do not act in disgraceful/disrespectful ways towards them. They do not ◄act selfishly/think only of themselves and what they want►. They do not quickly become angry. They do not keep remembering the bad things <char style="add">that others have done to them</char>. <verse eid="1CO 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 13:6"/>Those who [PRS] truly love <char style="add">others</char> do not rejoice when <char style="add">people do</char> evil things, but they do rejoice when <char style="add">people act</char> righteously. <verse eid="1CO 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 13:7"/>Those who truly love <char style="add">others</char> patiently put up with<char style="add">the faults of others</char>. They do not quickly assume <char style="add">that others have done something bad</char>. They confidently expect <char style="add">that others will act righteously</char>. They patiently endure <char style="add">all their own troubles</char>.<verse eid="1CO 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 13:8"/>We should never [PRS] let anything stop us from continuing to love <char style="add">others</char>. As for the ability to speak messages that come directly from God, some day that will come to an end. As for the ability to speak languages [MTY] <char style="add">that we have not learned</char>, that will <char style="add">also</char> come to an end some day. And as for the ability to know things that God reveals to us, that will come to an end some day <char style="add">because it will not be necessary any more</char>. <verse eid="1CO 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 13:9"/>God does not reveal everything to us, and we cannot know everything that he knows. <verse eid="1CO 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 13:10"/>But when everything is perfect <char style="add">after Christ returns</char>, things which are not perfect <char style="add">now</char>, <char style="add">such as the abilities which God’s Spirit gives us</char>, will ◄disappear/come to an end►. <verse eid="1CO 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 13:11"/>When we were children, we talked like children talk, we thought like children think, we reasoned like children reason. But when we grew up, we got rid of our childish ways [MET]. <char style="add">Similarly</char>, <char style="add">you need to get rid of your childish thinking about the abilities that the Spirit has given you</char>. <verse eid="1CO 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 13:12"/>In this life we do not understand everything fully. It is like [MET] looking at something indirectly by seeing it in a mirror. But <char style="add">when we get to heaven</char> [MTY], we will <char style="add">understand everything clearly. It will be like</char> talking to someone face-to-face. Now we know only part <char style="add">of everything that God wants us to know</char>. Then we will know everything completely, just like <char style="add">God</char> knows us completely. <verse eid="1CO 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 13:13"/>So now there are three things <char style="add">that we must</char> continue <char style="add">to do</char>: To trust <char style="add">in God</char>, to confidently expect <char style="add">to receive what he will give us</char>, and to love <char style="add">others</char>. But the greatest of those three things is loving <char style="add">others</char>.<verse eid="1CO 13:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="1CO 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Speaking messages that come directly from God will help believers much more than speaking messages in unknown languages.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 14:1-25">1 Corinthians 14:1-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 14:1"/>You must want to love others more <char style="add">than you want anything else</char>. But you should <char style="add">also</char> eagerly desire the abilities that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">gives to believers</char>. And you should desire most of all to have the ability to speak messages that come directly from God [MTY]. <verse eid="1CO 14:1"/><verse number="2-3" style="v" sid="1CO 14:2-3"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because those who speak messages that come directly from God <char style="add">are speaking in languages that they and the other believers in the congregation know, and so</char> they are able to strengthen them <char style="add">spiritually</char> and to encourage and comfort them. But those who speak in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that they have not learned</char> are not speaking to people. Instead, they are <char style="add">only</char> speaking to God. No one understands them. By <char style="add">the power/guidance of God’s</char> Spirit (OR, From within <char style="add">their own</char> spirit) they speak things that others do not know. <verse eid="1CO 14:2-3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 14:4"/>Those who speak in languages <char style="add">that they have not learned</char> are receiving a blessing for themselves, but those who speak messages that come directly from God are giving a blessing to <char style="add">all the believers in</char> the congregation <char style="add">because they are speaking in a language that the congregation knows</char>.<verse eid="1CO 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 14:5"/>I would like you all to have the ability to speak in languages [MTY] <char style="add">you have not learned</char>. But I would like even more for you to have the ability to speak messages that come directly from God. People can speak messages in a language that they have not learned, but if there is no one there who can explain the meaning, that situation is not as helpful to the congregation as speaking messages that come directly from God <char style="add">in the language that the congregation knows</char>.<verse eid="1CO 14:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 14:6"/>My fellow believers, suppose I came and spoke to you in a language that none of you knows <char style="add">and I did not explain the meaning of what I told you</char>. Even if I told you something that God had revealed to me, or told you some message that had come directly from him, or taught you something that you needed to know, ◄that certainly would not help you!/how would that help you?► [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 14:7"/><char style="add">It is like</char> lifeless <char style="add">musical instruments</char>, like flutes and harps for example. When they are played, if the notes are not played {if <char style="add">those playing those instruments</char> do not play the notes} clearly, no one will know what tune is being played {what tune they are playing}. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 14:8"/>If someone playing the trumpet <char style="add">wants to signal that the soldiers should prepare to fight a battle</char>, <char style="add">the soldiers</char> certainly will not get ready if <char style="add">the call to battle</char> is not played {he does not play <char style="add">the call to battle</char>} clearly. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 14:9"/>It is the same with you! If you do not speak words that other people can understand, ◄no one will know what you are saying./how will anyone know what you are saying?► [RHQ] <char style="add">It will be as though</char> you are just speaking to the air! <verse eid="1CO 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 14:10"/>There are many different languages in the world, and all of them convey meaning [LIT] <char style="add">to the people who know those languages</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 14:11"/>But if we do not understand the language that others are speaking, <char style="add">it will be as though</char> they are foreigners to us, and we will be foreigners to them. <verse eid="1CO 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 14:12"/>So <char style="add">I say this to</char> you: Because you are eager to have the abilities that God’s Spirit gives, earnestly desire those abilities that will do the most to help <char style="add">all the believers in</char> the congregation.<verse eid="1CO 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 14:13"/>So, those who have the ability to speak in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that they have not learned</char> should pray that <char style="add">God will give them the ability to</char> explain the meaning of what they say. <verse eid="1CO 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 14:14"/>If they pray in a language [MTY] <char style="add">that they have not learned</char>, their spirits are praying, but they are not using their minds. <verse eid="1CO 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 14:15"/>So I will tell you [RHQ] what we should do. <char style="add">At times</char> we may pray, <char style="add">using</char> only our spirits, <char style="add">in languages we have not learned. And at other times</char> we should pray using our minds, <char style="add">thinking about the words that we are praying. Similarly</char>, at times we may sing using only our spirits, using languages that we have not learned, and at other times we should sing using our minds, <char style="add">thinking about the words that we are singing</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 14:16"/>Suppose that any one of you praises God (OR, thanks God for what he has done), using only your <char style="add">(sg)</char> spirit <char style="add">and not using your mind</char>. Maybe some people <char style="add">will be present who</char> do not know about <char style="add">the abilities that God’s Spirit gives to believers</char>. Because they do not know what you are saying, after you thank God, they will not [RHQ] know when to say “Amen!/I agree!” <verse eid="1CO 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 14:17"/>You may be thanking God very well, but you are not helping them. <verse eid="1CO 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 14:18"/>I thank God that I speak in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that I have not learned</char> more than any of you do. <verse eid="1CO 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 14:19"/>But during a worship service, <char style="add">in order that others will understand what I am saying</char>, I would prefer to speak five words using my mind, in order that I may teach others, rather than to speak 10,000 words in a language [MTY] <char style="add">that is not understood by the congregation</char>.<verse eid="1CO 14:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 14:20"/>My fellow believers, stop being like little children in the way that you think <char style="add">about these abilities that God’s Spirit gives</char>. Instead, think about them in a mature way. If you really want to be like little children, do as few wicked things as babies do! <verse eid="1CO 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 14:21"/><char style="add">When the Jews long ago refused to obey God, he warned them about what would happen when he allowed their enemies to punish them</char>. In the Scriptures it is written {<char style="add">the prophet Isaiah</char> wrote} what the Lord <char style="add">God</char> said <char style="add">about that</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 14:21">
    <char style="add">They didn’t listen to prophets speaking their own language, so I will send</char> people from foreign <char style="add">lands to attack</char> my people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 14:21">Those foreigners will speak languages that my people do not know [DOU].</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 14:21">
    <char style="add">In that way</char>, I will warn my people,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1CO 14:21">but they will still not pay attention to what I say.<verse eid="1CO 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 14:22"/>If we speak in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that we have not learned</char>, unbelievers <char style="add">who are there will realize that the Spirit of God is truly among us</char>. That will warn them <char style="add">that they need to fear God</char>. But believers do not <char style="add">need such a warning</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 14:23"/>Suppose during the worship service everyone started to speak in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that they have not learned</char>. If unbelievers or people who do not know <char style="add">about the abilities that God’s Spirit gives to believers</char> come in <char style="add">and hear that</char>, they will surely think that you are crazy. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 14:24"/>But if an unbeliever or someone who does not know <char style="add">about those abilities</char> comes in while all of you believers are <char style="add">one by one</char> speaking messages that come directly from God, everything that you <char style="add">say</char> will show that person that he is a sinner and that <char style="add">God</char> will punish him <char style="add">if he does not turn from his sinful behavior</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 14:25"/>He will realize that <char style="add">God knows the evil things that he has done that</char>, things that other people do not know. Then he will kneel down and worship God and say, “God is truly among you!”<verse eid="1CO 14:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Believers should all be prepared to participate in an orderly way during worship services.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 14:26-40">1 Corinthians 14:26-40</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 14:26"/>So, my fellow believers, I will tell you [RHQ] what I think that you should be doing. When you come together <char style="add">to worship God</char>, some of you may have a hymn to sing. Others may have something to teach <char style="add">the congregation</char>. Others may have <char style="add">something to say that God has</char> revealed to them. Others may give messages in languages <char style="add">that they have not learned</char>. Others will explain the meaning of those messages. Make sure that all of these things that you do will make the congregation become more mature spiritually. <verse eid="1CO 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 14:27"/><char style="add">It is all right</char> if two people, or at the most three people, speak in languages [MTY] <char style="add">that they have not learned</char>. But they must speak one at a time, and someone must explain the meaning of what the others have said. <verse eid="1CO 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 14:28"/>If <char style="add">those who want to speak in a language that they have not learned realize that</char> there is no one <char style="add">there</char> who will be able to explain the meaning <char style="add">of what they will say</char>, they should not speak in that language during the meeting. Instead, they should speak to God by themselves, <char style="add">somewhere else</char>.<verse eid="1CO 14:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 14:29"/>
    <char style="add">During a meeting</char>, two or three people should speak messages that come directly from God, and others who are there should think carefully about what those people have said. <verse eid="1CO 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 14:30"/>If someone receives a new message directly from God while someone else is speaking, the one who is speaking should stop speaking <char style="add">and let the other person tell what God has revealed to him</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 14:31"/>You can all, one by one, speak messages that have come directly from God, in order that you can teach others and all be encouraged {encourage everyone}. <verse eid="1CO 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 14:32"/>Those who speak messages that come directly from God are in control of their own spirits, <char style="add">so they can wait for their turn to speak</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 14:33"/>Remember that God does not desire that things be done in a disorderly way <char style="add">during your worship services</char>. Instead, he desires that everything be done in an orderly way.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1CO 14:33">Just like it happens in all the other congregations of believers, <verse eid="1CO 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 14:34"/>the women should not be permitted {do not permit the women} <char style="add">to interrupt the meeting by</char> asking <char style="add">questions</char>. They must keep quiet. They must be subject <char style="add">to their husbands</char>. What Moses wrote [PRS] <char style="add">about how God created the first two people</char> suggests <char style="add">that the women should do that</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 14:35"/>If they want to know <char style="add">more</char> about something <char style="add">that a speaker said</char>, they should ask their husbands when they get home, for it is disgraceful for women to <char style="add">interrupt a service by</char> asking <char style="add">such questions</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 14:36"/><char style="add">If you do not agree with these things that I have been telling you</char>, remember that [RHQ] the message from God did not first come from you <char style="add">people in Corinth</char>. Also, you are not [RHQ] the only ones who have heard it! <char style="add">Many others have heard it and accepted it, so you should not act as though you are the only believers who have heard the message from God</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 14:37"/>Those of you who think that you have the ability to speak messages that come directly from God, or think that you have some other ability <char style="add">that God’s</char> Spirit gives, should realize that the things that I have written about in this letter are things that the Lord has commanded. <verse eid="1CO 14:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 14:38"/>But if they are not willing to accept <char style="add">my authority</char>, <char style="add">God</char> will not accept them (OR, they will not be accepted <char style="add">by the congregation</char>).<verse eid="1CO 14:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 14:39"/>So, my fellow believers, be eager to speak messages that come directly from God, and do not prevent anyone from speaking in a language <char style="add">that he has not learned</char>. <verse eid="1CO 14:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 14:40"/>But make sure <char style="add">that</char> <char style="bd">everything</char> that you do <char style="add">during the worship services</char> is done in a proper and orderly way.<verse eid="1CO 14:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="1CO 15"/>
  <para style="s1">I was not worthy to become an apostle, but the Lord Jesus committed to me the message about his death and resurrection.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 15:1-11">1 Corinthians 15:1-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 15:1"/>Now, my fellow believers, I want to remind you about the message about Christ that I preached to you. It is the message that you received and that you have continued to trust firmly. <verse eid="1CO 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 15:2"/>If you keep on firmly <char style="add">believing</char> this message that I preached to you, you will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save you}. If you do not continue to believe it, your believing <char style="add">in Christ</char> was ◄all for nothing/useless►!<verse eid="1CO 15:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 15:3"/>The most important part of the message that I received <char style="add">from the Lord Jesus</char>, and that I told you, was this: Christ died to <char style="add">take away the guilt</char> of our sins, as the Scriptures <char style="add">said that he would do</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 15:4"/>His <char style="add">dead body</char> was buried {They buried his <char style="add">body</char>}. On the third day <char style="add">after that</char>, <char style="add">God</char> caused him to become alive again, as the Scriptures <char style="add">said would happen</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 15:5"/>After that, <char style="add">Christ</char> was seen by {appeared to} Peter. Then he appeared to <char style="add">eleven of</char> the <char style="add">original</char> twelve <char style="add">apostles</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 15:6"/>Later he was seen by {appeared to} more than 500 of our fellow believers. Most of those are still living, but some of them have died [EUP]. <verse eid="1CO 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 15:7"/>Then he was seen by {appeared <char style="add">to</char>} <char style="add">his younger brother</char> James, <char style="add">who became the leader of the congregation in Jerusalem</char>. Then he appeared to all of the apostles. <verse eid="1CO 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 15:8"/>Finally, he was seen by {appeared to} me, but I became an apostle in a way that was very unusual [MET]. <verse eid="1CO 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 15:9"/>The fact is, I <char style="add">consider that I</char> am the least important of the apostles. I do not deserve to be an apostle, because I ◄persecuted God’s groups of believers/caused God’s groups of believers to suffer► <char style="add">everywhere I went</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 15:10"/>But it is because God acted kindly toward me in ways that I did not deserve that I became what I am now. And his acting kindly toward me produced a great result [LIT], which is that I worked harder <char style="add">for Christ</char> than all the other apostles. But it was not that I <char style="add">was working with my own ability</char>. Instead, God was helping me in a way I did not deserve. <verse eid="1CO 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 15:11"/>So it does not matter whether it was I <char style="add">who was preaching or whether it was the other apostles who were preaching</char>. We all preached <char style="add">the same message</char>, and that message is what you believed.<verse eid="1CO 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ has truly come back to life, and he will some day raise all believers.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 15:12-34">1 Corinthians 15:12-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 15:12"/>So now <char style="add">let me ask you this</char>: Since <char style="add">we</char> have all preached to you that Christ was raised again {that <char style="add">God</char> caused Christ to become alive} after he died, ◄no one among you should be saying that <char style="add">God</char> will not cause <char style="add">believers</char> to become alive again after they die!/why do some of you say that <char style="add">God</char> will not cause <char style="add">believers</char> to become alive again after they die?► [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 15:13"/>If <char style="add">it is true that God</char> will not cause anyone to become alive again, that situation would mean that Christ was not raised from the dead {<char style="add">he</char> did not cause Christ to become alive again}! <verse eid="1CO 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 15:14"/>And if Christ was not raised from the dead {if <char style="add">God</char> did not cause Christ to become alive again}, then what we preached to you was useless, and your believing <char style="add">in Christ</char> is useless. <verse eid="1CO 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 15:15"/><char style="add">If it is true that</char> no one will be raised from the dead {<char style="add">that God</char> will not cause anyone to become alive again after he dies}, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> have been guilty of lying to you about God, because we told you that God caused Christ to become alive again. <verse eid="1CO 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 15:16"/>But if it were really true that no one who has died will be raised {that <char style="add">God will</char> not cause anyone who has died to become alive} again, then Christ was not raised {<char style="add">he</char> did not cause Christ to become alive} again either! <verse eid="1CO 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 15:17"/>If it were true that Christ was not raised {that <char style="add">God</char> did not cause Christ to become alive} again after he died, you have believed in Christ for nothing, <char style="add">because</char> God will still <char style="add">punish</char> you for [MTY] your sins. <verse eid="1CO 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 15:18"/>And those people who died [EUP] <char style="add">while they were trusting</char> in Christ will go to hell. <verse eid="1CO 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 15:19"/>In this life <char style="add">many of us have suffered much for Christ</char> because we confidently expect <char style="add">that he will reward us in heaven</char>. If we have confidently expected this in vain, people should pity us more than they pity anyone else!<verse eid="1CO 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 15:20"/>But <char style="add">the truth is that</char> Christ has been raised from the dead {that <char style="add">God</char> has caused Christ to live again after he had died}, and ◄that guarantees/because of that, it is certain► [MET] that he will also cause those <char style="add">believers</char> who have died [EUP] to become alive again. <verse eid="1CO 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 15:21"/>What one man, <char style="add">Adam, did affects us all</char>. We all die. Similarly, what one man—<char style="add">Christ</char>—did <char style="add">affects us(inc) all</char>: God will cause <char style="add">all believers</char> to become alive again. <verse eid="1CO 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 15:22"/>Because of what Adam did, all <char style="add">of us who are descended</char> from him die. Similarly, because of what <char style="add">Christ did</char>, all of us who have a close relationship with him will be brought back to life {<char style="add">God</char> will make alive all of us who have a close relationship with Christ}. <verse eid="1CO 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 15:23"/>But we must all take our turn. <char style="add">God raised</char> Christ first [MET]. And when Christ returns, <char style="add">God will cause</char> those who belong to Christ to become alive again. <verse eid="1CO 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 15:24"/>Then, after Christ has destroyed all [DOU] the evil powers that oppose God, <char style="add">the world</char> will end. Then Christ will give to God, his Father, his kingdom to completely rule over it. <verse eid="1CO 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CO 15:25"/>You must realize that Christ must rule <char style="add">here on earth</char> until he has completely defeated [MTY] all his enemies. <verse eid="1CO 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CO 15:26"/>The last thing that <char style="add">he</char> will get rid of is death. <char style="add">But he certainly will get rid of death, which is like</char> an enemy <char style="add">to us</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CO 15:27"/><char style="add">In the Scriptures the Psalmist wrote that</char> God will cause everything to be under Christ’s <char style="add">authority</char> [MTY]. But it is clear that the word ‘everything’ here does not include God, because God is the one who will cause everything to be under Christ’s <char style="add">authority</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="1CO 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CO 15:28"/>After everything is put under <char style="add">the authority of</char> God’s Son, then Christ will put himself completely under <char style="add">the authority of</char> God, the one who gave him that authority. Then God will be completely in control of everything [IDM], everywhere.<verse eid="1CO 15:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CO 15:29"/>
    <char style="add">Now think about this: Some among you</char> are being baptized (OR, are baptizing people) on behalf of those who died <char style="add">before someone baptized them</char> (OR, who died <char style="add">before they became believers</char>). If, <char style="add">as some people say, believers</char> will not be raised <char style="add">from the dead</char> {<char style="add">God</char> will not cause <char style="add">believers</char> to become alive again}, ◄what is the value in those people doing that?/there is no value in those people doing that!► [RHQ] If <char style="add">God</char> will not cause any <char style="add">believers</char> to become alive again, it is senseless to be baptized {baptize anyone} on behalf of someone who has died. [RHQ] <verse eid="1CO 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CO 15:30"/>Furthermore, <char style="add">if God will not cause us believers to become alive again</char>, it is [RHQ] very foolish for me and the other apostles to be constantly <char style="add">putting ourselves</char> in danger <char style="add">because we tell people the gospel</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CO 15:31"/>My fellow believers, every day I <char style="add">am in danger of</char> being killed {people killing me}! That is as true as it is that I am pleased with you because of your close relationship with Christ Jesus our Lord. <verse eid="1CO 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CO 15:32"/><char style="add">If God will not cause us believers to become alive again after we die</char>, ◄I will receive no benefit at all <char style="add">from having opposed those who attacked me so strongly</char> in Ephesus <char style="add">city</char>./what will I gain <char style="add">from having opposed those who attacked me so strongly</char> in Ephesus <char style="add">city</char>?► [RHQ] They were <char style="add">fighting me like</char> wild beasts! If we <char style="add">believers</char> will not be raised <char style="add">from the dead</char> {If <char style="add">God</char> will not cause us <char style="add">believers</char> to live again}, we might as well say <char style="add">as people often say</char>: “Tomorrow we are going to die, so we might as well enjoy now everything that we can. We might as well feast and get drunk!” <verse eid="1CO 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CO 15:33"/>Do not let <char style="add">yourselves be deceived by those who say that God will not cause believers to live again</char> {Do not let <char style="add">people who say that God will not cause believers to live again</char> deceive you}. If you associate with evil people <char style="add">who say such things</char>, they will ◄influence you to do evil things/destroy your good moral way of living►. <verse eid="1CO 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CO 15:34"/>Start thinking correctly again <char style="add">about these matters</char>, as you should, and <char style="add">stop your sinful behavior which has resulted from</char> your wrong thinking. <char style="add">I say that</char> because <char style="add">it seems that</char> some among you do not know God, and as a result they <char style="add">are thinking wrongly</char>. I say that to make you ashamed.<verse eid="1CO 15:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">In heaven we will have glorious indestructible bodies.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 15:35-58">1 Corinthians 15:35-58</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CO 15:35"/>But some of you are asking, “How will dead people be raised {How will <char style="add">God</char> cause dead people to become alive} again? What kind of bodies will they have?” <verse eid="1CO 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CO 15:36"/><char style="add">Anyone who asks such questions is</char> foolish. You <char style="add">know that</char> a seed that is planted in the ground must completely change its form [MET] before it sprouts. <verse eid="1CO 15:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CO 15:37"/>A seed, such as a wheat seed, is very different from the plant that sprouts from it. <verse eid="1CO 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CO 15:38"/>God gives everything that lives the form that he desires. He gives each seed its own form. <verse eid="1CO 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CO 15:39"/><char style="add">Similarly</char>, people, animals, birds, and fish all have flesh, but each one has a different kind of flesh. <verse eid="1CO 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CO 15:40"/>Also, there are angelic beings in heaven (OR, stars and planets in the sky), and there are people with bodies on the earth. The angelic beings (OR, stars and planets) are beautiful in one way, and people on earth are beautiful in a different way. <verse eid="1CO 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CO 15:41"/>The sun is bright in one way, and the moon is bright in a different way, and the stars are bright in a different way. And even the various stars are different from each other in how bright they are.<verse eid="1CO 15:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CO 15:42"/>And it is the same way <char style="add">with our bodies. The bodies that we will have when God causes us</char> to live again after we die <char style="add">will not be the same as the bodies that we have now</char> [MET]. <char style="add">The bodies that we have now</char> will die and decay. <char style="add">The new bodies that we will have</char> will never die. <verse eid="1CO 15:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CO 15:43"/>We despise <char style="add">the bodies that we have now</char>, before we die. But our <char style="add">new bodies</char> will be glorious. The <char style="add">bodies that we have before we die</char> are weak. But our new bodies will be strong. <verse eid="1CO 15:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CO 15:44"/>The bodies that we have before we die are natural bodies. But <char style="add">our new bodies</char> will be ones that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit ◄<char style="add">controls/gives us</char>►. Just like there are natural bodies, there are bodies that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">completely</char> controls (OR, makes alive).<verse eid="1CO 15:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1CO 15:45"/>
    <char style="add">In the Scriptures</char> it is written {we read} that <char style="add">when</char> the first man, Adam, <char style="add">was created</char>, he became a living human being. <char style="add">Christ later also became a human being</char>. But <char style="add">he is different from Adam, because he</char> became a person who gives us <char style="add">spiritual</char> life. <verse eid="1CO 15:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1CO 15:46"/>But our bodies that God’s Spirit ◄will completely control/will give us► are not the first bodies that we have. We have our natural bodies first. <verse eid="1CO 15:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1CO 15:47"/>The first man, <char style="add">Adam</char>, was created {<char style="add">God</char> created the first man, Adam} from the dust of the earth. But <char style="add">Christ</char>, the one who came later, came from heaven. <verse eid="1CO 15:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1CO 15:48"/>Everyone on earth <char style="add">has a body</char> like the first man on the earth had. And in heaven, <char style="add">everyone will have a body like Christ</char>, the man who came from heaven, has. <verse eid="1CO 15:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1CO 15:49"/>And just like <char style="add">God</char> gave us bodies like the first man on earth had, so we <char style="add">believers will have bodies</char> like <char style="add">Christ</char> has, who is now in heaven.<verse eid="1CO 15:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="1CO 15:50"/>My fellow believers, I want you to know that we <char style="add">(inc)</char> [SYN] cannot go <char style="add">to heaven, where</char> God rules <char style="add">over everything</char>, with our physical bodies, because our bodies <char style="add">cannot last forever</char>. They will die and decay. <verse eid="1CO 15:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1CO 15:51"/>But I will tell you something that <char style="add">God</char> has not revealed <char style="add">before</char>: <char style="add">Some of</char> us <char style="add">believers</char> will not die [EUP]. However, all of us will be changed {<char style="add">God</char> will change all of us}. <verse eid="1CO 15:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="1CO 15:52"/><char style="add">It will happen</char> suddenly, as <char style="add">fast as someone can</char> blink his eye [MET], when <char style="add">we hear the sound of God’s</char> trumpet for the last time. When we hear that trumpet, all <char style="add">the believers</char> who have died will come back to life and will have bodies that are changed {that <char style="add">God</char> has changed}, bodies that will never decay. <verse eid="1CO 15:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1CO 15:53"/>And the <char style="add">bodies of us who are alive at that time</char> will <char style="add">also</char> be changed {And <char style="add">God</char> will <char style="add">also</char> change the <char style="add">bodies of us who are alive at that time</char>}. These bodies of ours that die and decay must be transformed into <char style="add">new bodies that</char> will never die; <char style="add">it will be like someone</char> [MET] getting rid of <char style="add">his old clothes</char> and putting on <char style="add">new ones</char>. <verse eid="1CO 15:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="1CO 15:54"/>When that happens, what is written {what ◄<char style="add">a prophet/Isaiah</char>► wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char> will come true/happen:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="1CO 15:54">
    <char style="add">God</char> will completely get rid of [MET] death. Our dying will no longer have any power to defeat us; <verse eid="1CO 15:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="1CO 15:55"/>Death [APO] will not win a victory over us. Death will not be able to hurt us.<verse eid="1CO 15:55"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" sid="1CO 15:56"/>It is because we sin [MET] <char style="add">that we die, and it is because we</char> have God’s laws that we <char style="add">know that we</char> have sinned. <verse eid="1CO 15:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="1CO 15:57"/>But because of what our Lord Jesus Christ <char style="add">has done</char>, he enables us to be free <char style="add">from having to obey God’s laws to be saved and to be free of being afraid to die</char>. We should thank God for that!<verse eid="1CO 15:57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="1CO 15:58"/>So, my fellow believers whom I love, continue to hold strongly to <char style="add">the things that you believe</char>. Do not let anything cause you to doubt them. Always be doing enthusiastically the work that the Lord <char style="add">gives you</char>. And remember that the work that you do for the Lord is never ◄in vain/useless►, <char style="add">as it would be if God will not cause us to live again after we die</char>.<verse eid="1CO 15:58"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="1CO 16"/>
  <para style="s1">You should set aside funds each week for the offering to be sent to believers in Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 16:1-4">1 Corinthians 16:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CO 16:1"/>Now <char style="add">I will reply to another question that you asked. You asked</char> about the <char style="add">money you are</char> collecting <char style="add">to send</char> to God’s people <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>. Do what I told the congregations in Galatia to do. <verse eid="1CO 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CO 16:2"/>Every Sunday each of you should set aside <char style="add">at home</char> some funds [EUP] <char style="add">for this purpose</char>, in proportion to how much <char style="add">God</char> has prospered you. Then you should save it up, so that when I arrive there, you will not need to collect <char style="add">any more money. Choose some men whom you approve of, to take</char> this money to Jerusalem. <verse eid="1CO 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CO 16:3"/>Then, when I arrive, I will write letters stating that you have authorized these men to take the funds there. <verse eid="1CO 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CO 16:4"/>And if <char style="add">you</char> (OR, <char style="add">I</char>) think that it is appropriate, I will go with them.<verse eid="1CO 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I plan to spend some time with you. Treat Timothy respectfully when he arrives. Apollos plans to visit you later.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 16:5-12">1 Corinthians 16:5-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CO 16:5"/>Now I plan to travel through Macedonia <char style="add">province</char>. I <char style="add">plan to</char> come to visit you, but I want to go through Macedonia first. <verse eid="1CO 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CO 16:6"/>Perhaps I will stay with you for a short while, or I may stay with you for the whole winter, in order that you yourselves can provide some of the things <char style="add">that I will need</char> [EUP] for my next trip. <verse eid="1CO 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CO 16:7"/>I do not want to see you just for a short time and then continue my trip. I am hoping to stay with you for a while, if the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> allows me to do that. <verse eid="1CO 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CO 16:8"/>But I will stay <char style="add">here</char> in Ephesus <char style="add">city</char> until <char style="add">after</char> the Pentecost <char style="add">festival</char>. <verse eid="1CO 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CO 16:9"/><char style="add">I want to do that</char> because <char style="add">God</char> has given me a great opportunity [MET] <char style="add">to proclaim his good message here</char>. <char style="add">As a result of my work here, God is producing</char> great results. I also want to stay here because there are many people here who oppose <char style="add">my work, and I need to refute them</char>.<verse eid="1CO 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CO 16:10"/>When Timothy arrives <char style="add">there in Corinth</char>, treat him respectfully [LIT], because he is working for the Lord just as I am. <verse eid="1CO 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CO 16:11"/>Do not let anyone despise him. And when he leaves there, give him some of the things that he needs <char style="add">for his trip</char> [EUP] <char style="add">here</char>, and also <char style="add">ask God to</char> bless him. I am waiting for him to come, along with the other fellow believers <char style="add">who have been traveling with him</char>.<verse eid="1CO 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CO 16:12"/>
    <char style="add">You also asked</char> about our fellow believer, Apollos. I urged him strongly that he should go back to you with the three fellow believers <char style="add">who came here from Corinth</char>. He was not at all willing to go <char style="add">now</char>, but he will go later, when he has an opportunity.<verse eid="1CO 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I give you my final instructions, greetings from others, and my final blessings.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="1CO 16:13-24">1 Corinthians 16:13-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CO 16:13"/>Be on guard <char style="add">against anything that would hinder you spiritually</char>. You have believed <char style="add">the true message</char>; continue believing it firmly. Be courageous. Keep strong <char style="add">in your relationship with God</char>. <verse eid="1CO 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CO 16:14"/>Act in a loving <char style="add">way</char> in everything that <char style="add">you do</char>.<verse eid="1CO 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CO 16:15"/>You know that Stephanas and his family were the first ones <char style="add">there</char> in Achaia <char style="add">province to believe in Christ</char> [IDM]. They have devoted themselves to helping God’s people. <verse eid="1CO 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CO 16:16"/>My fellow believers, I urge you to submit yourselves to them and to people like them who do <char style="add">God’s</char> work and who work hard. <verse eid="1CO 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CO 16:17"/>I was glad when Stephanas, Fortunatus, and Achaicus arrived here <char style="add">from Corinth</char>, because <char style="add">they did things for</char> me that you were not able to do <char style="add">because you were not with me</char>. <verse eid="1CO 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CO 16:18"/>They comforted and encouraged me [SYN], and <char style="add">I expect that this news from me</char> will do the same for you. You should honor <char style="add">them, and you should also honor</char> others like them.<verse eid="1CO 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CO 16:19"/>The congregations <char style="add">here</char> in Asia <char style="add">province</char> ◄send their greetings to/say that they are thinking fondly of► you. Aquila and <char style="add">his wife</char> Priscilla and the congregation that meets in their house ◄send their warm greetings to/say that they are thinking fondly of► you because both they and you belong to the Lord. <verse eid="1CO 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CO 16:20"/>All your fellow believers <char style="add">here</char> ◄send their greetings to/say that they are thinking of► you. Greet each other affectionately, as fellow believers <char style="add">should</char>.<verse eid="1CO 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CO 16:21"/>Now I, Paul, having taken the pen from the hand of my secretary, write with my own hand to say that I am thinking fondly of you/to give you my greetings. I do this to show you that this letter really comes from me.<verse eid="1CO 16:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CO 16:22"/>◄I pray that God will/May God► curse/cause bad things to happen to ◄anyone who does not love the Lord Jesus. I pray that our Lord will come soon/May our Lord come soon►!<verse eid="1CO 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CO 16:23"/>I pray that our Lord Jesus will/May our Lord Jesus ◄continue to act toward you all kindly/in ways that you do not deserve.►<verse eid="1CO 16:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CO 16:24"/>I love all of you who have a close relationship with Christ Jesus.<verse eid="1CO 16:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1CO 16"/>
</usx>
