<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1KI" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">1 KINGS</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 Kings</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Kings</para>
  <para style="toc3">1Ki</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of King Solomon’s reign and of Israel being divided into two kingdoms, Israel and Judah, after his death. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 Kings</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1KI 1"/>
  <para style="s1">When King David was an old man</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 1:1"/>When King David was very old [IDM, DOU], even though his servants put many blankets on top of him, he was unable to become warm. <verse eid="1KI 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 1:2"/>So they said to him, “Your Majesty, allow us to search for a young virgin who can stay with you and take care of you. She can sleep close to you and enable you to become warm.”<verse eid="1KI 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 1:3"/>
    <char style="add">The king gave them permission, </char> so they searched throughout Israel for a beautiful young woman. They found a woman named Abishag, from Shunem <char style="add">town</char>, and brought her to the king. <verse eid="1KI 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 1:4"/>She was <char style="add">truly</char> very beautiful. She took care of [DOU] the king, but the king did not have sexual relations with her.<verse eid="1KI 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Adonijah tried to become the king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5-6" style="v" sid="1KI 1:5-6"/>
    <char style="add">After Absalom died</char>, David’s oldest surviving son was Adonijah, whose mother was Haggith. He was a very handsome/good-looking man. But David had never rebuked him about anything he did. <char style="add">After Absalom died, Adonijah thought that he would become king</char>. So he started to boast, saying “I will become king <char style="add">now</char>.” Then he provided for himself some chariots, and men to drive them, and horses <char style="add">to pull them</char>, and 50 men to run <char style="add">as his bodyguards</char> in front of those chariots <char style="add">wherever he went</char>.<verse eid="1KI 1:5-6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 1:7"/>One day he conferred with Joab, <char style="add">David’s army commander</char>, and Abiathar the priest, and they promised/agreed to help/support Adonijah. <verse eid="1KI 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 1:8"/>But Zadok, who was also a priest, Benaiah <char style="add">who had supervised David’s bodyguards</char>, Nathan the prophet, Shimei and Rei, and David’s most capable soldiers refused to help/support Adonijah.<verse eid="1KI 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 1:9"/>One day Adonijah went to Snake Rock near En-Rogel <char style="add">Spring, which is near Jerusalem</char>, to sacrifice some sheep and oxen and fattened cattle. He invited most of his brothers, King David’s other sons, to come. He also invited all of the king’s officials from Judah to come to the celebration. <verse eid="1KI 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 1:10"/>But he did not invite Nathan or Benaiah or the king’s most capable soldiers or his <char style="add">younger/half</char>-brother Solomon.<verse eid="1KI 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 1:11"/>Nathan <char style="add">found out what they were doing, so he went to</char> Solomon’s mother Bathsheba <char style="add">and</char> asked her, “Have you not heard that Haggith’s son Adonijah is declared himself to be the king? And King David does not know about it! <verse eid="1KI 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 1:12"/>So if you want to save yourself and your son Solomon from being killed, allow me to tell you what you should do. <verse eid="1KI 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 1:13"/>Go immediately to King David. Say to him, ‘Your Majesty, you solemnly promised me [RHQ] that my son Solomon would become the king after you <char style="add">die</char>, and that he would sit on your throne <char style="add">and rule</char>. So why is it that Adonijah <char style="add">has said that he</char> is now the king?’ <verse eid="1KI 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 1:14"/>Then, while you are still talking to the king, I will come in and tell him that what you are saying to him <char style="add">about Adonijah</char> is true.”<verse eid="1KI 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 1:15"/>So Bathsheba went to see the king in his bedroom. He was very old, and Abishag was taking care of him. <verse eid="1KI 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 1:16"/>Bathsheba bowed very low in front of the king, and the king asked her, “What do you want?”<verse eid="1KI 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 1:17"/>She replied, “Your Majesty, you solemnly promised me, knowing that Yahweh our God <char style="add">was listening</char> [IDM], that my son Solomon would become king after you <char style="add">die</char>, and that he would sit on your throne <char style="add">and rule</char>. <verse eid="1KI 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 1:18"/>But now, believe it or not, Adonijah has become king, and you do not know anything about it. <verse eid="1KI 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 1:19"/>He has sacrificed a lot of oxen and fattened cattle and sheep, and he has invited all of your other sons to the celebration. He has also invited Abiathar the priest and Joab the commander of your army, but he did not invite your son Solomon. <verse eid="1KI 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 1:20"/>Your Majesty, all the people [SYN] of Israel are expecting you to tell them who is the one who will become king after you are no longer the king. <verse eid="1KI 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 1:21"/>If you do not do that, what will happen is that after you die [EUP] people will consider that my son Solomon and I are rebelling, <char style="add">and they will execute us because we did not help Adonijah to become king</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 1:22"/>While she was still talking to the king, Nathan came <char style="add">to the palace</char>. <verse eid="1KI 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 1:23"/>The king’s servants/advisors told David, “Nathan the prophet has come.” So <char style="add">Bathsheba left, and</char> Nathan went into where the king was and knelt down, with his face on the ground.<verse eid="1KI 1:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 1:24"/>Then Nathan said, “Your Majesty, have you declared that Adonijah will become king after you are no longer the king? <verse eid="1KI 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 1:25"/><char style="add">I say that </char> because today he has gone down <char style="add">to En-Rogel Spring</char> and has sacrificed a lot of oxen, fattened cattle, and sheep. And he has invited all of your other sons, Joab the army commander, and Abiathar the priest. They are all eating and drinking with him and saying ‘We hope/desire that King Adonijah will live a long time!’ <verse eid="1KI 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 1:26"/>But he did not invite me or Zadok the priest or Benaiah or Solomon. <verse eid="1KI 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 1:27"/>Did you, as the king, say that they should do this without telling your other officials who you want to become king [MTY] after you are no longer the king?”<verse eid="1KI 1:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David arranged for Solomon to be declared king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 1:28"/>Then <char style="add">after Nathan left the room,</char> King David said <char style="add">to one of his servants</char>, “Tell Bathsheba to come in here again.” So <char style="add">he went and told her, and</char> she came in and stood in front of the king.<verse eid="1KI 1:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29-30" style="v" sid="1KI 1:29-30"/>Then the king said, “Yahweh has rescued me from all my troubles. I promised you, with Yahweh the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char> listening, that your son Solomon would be king after I am no longer the king. Today, as surely as Yahweh lives, <char style="add">I solemnly declare that</char> I will do what I promised.” <verse eid="1KI 1:29-30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 1:31"/>Bathsheba knelt down with her face on the ground and said, “Your Majesty, I hope/desire that you will live for many more years [HYP]!”<verse eid="1KI 1:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 1:32"/>Then King David said, “Summon Zadok the priest, Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah.” <char style="add">So someone went and summoned them.</char> When they came in, <verse eid="1KI 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 1:33"/>he said to them, “Put my son Solomon on my mule. Take him with my officials down to Gihon <char style="add">Spring</char>. <verse eid="1KI 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 1:34"/>There, you two, Zadok and Nathan, should anoint him, <char style="add">with olive oil to appoint him to be</char> the king of Israel. Then you must blow trumpets, and <char style="add">all the people there must</char> shout, ‘We hope/desire that King Solomon will live for many years!’ <verse eid="1KI 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 1:35"/>Then follow him back here, and he will come and sit on my throne. He will then become king instead of me. I have appointed him to be the ruler of <char style="add">all the people of</char> Israel and of Judah.”<verse eid="1KI 1:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 1:36"/>Benaiah replied, “We will do that! We hope/wish that Yahweh, who is your God <char style="add">and our God</char>, will cause it to happen! <verse eid="1KI 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 1:37"/>King David, Yahweh has helped you; we hope/wish that he will also help Solomon and enable him to become a greater king than you have been.”<verse eid="1KI 1:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 1:38"/>So Zadok, Nathan, Benaiah, and the two groups of men who were the king’s bodyguards went and put Solomon on King David’s mule and escorted him down to Gihon <char style="add">Spring</char>. <verse eid="1KI 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 1:39"/>There Zadok took the container of <char style="add">olive</char> oil from the Sacred Tent and ◄anointed/poured some oil on► Solomon. Then the trumpets were blown, and all the people shouted, “We hope/wish that King Solomon will live for many years!” <verse eid="1KI 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 1:40"/>Then all the people followed him back up <char style="add">to the city</char>, shouting joyfully and playing flutes. They shouted very loudly, with the result that the ground shook.<verse eid="1KI 1:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Adonijah’s reaction</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1KI 1:41"/>When Adonijah and all ◄his guests/the people whom he had invited► were finishing eating at their celebration, they heard the noise. When Joab heard the sound of the trumpets, he asked, “What is causing all that noise in the city?”<verse eid="1KI 1:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="1KI 1:42"/>While he was still speaking, Jonathan, the son of Abiathar the priest, arrived. Adonijah said, “Come in! You are a man whom we can trust, so you must be bringing us good news!”<verse eid="1KI 1:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 1:43"/>Jonathan replied, “No, <char style="add">I do not have good news</char>! His Majesty, King David, has caused Solomon to be the king! <verse eid="1KI 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1KI 1:44"/>He sent Zadok, Nathan, Benaiah, and his own group of bodyguards to go with Solomon. They put Solomon on King David’s mule. <verse eid="1KI 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1KI 1:45"/>They <char style="add">went down to</char> Gihon <char style="add">Spring</char>, and there Zadok and Nathan anointed him to become the king. Now they have returned from there to the city, shouting joyfully. That is why there is that great/loud noise that you are hearing. <verse eid="1KI 1:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1KI 1:46"/>So Solomon is now our king [MTY]. <verse eid="1KI 1:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1KI 1:47"/>Furthermore, the palace officials came to His Majesty, King David, to tell him that they approved of what he had done. They said, ‘We wish/hope that our God will enable Solomon [MTY] to become more famous than you have been and enable him to be a better king than you have been.’ When they said that, the king, lying on his bed, bowed his head to worship <char style="add">Yahweh</char>. <verse eid="1KI 1:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1KI 1:48"/>Then he said, ‘I praise Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, because he has allowed one of my sons to become the king today, and has permitted me to see it happen.’”<verse eid="1KI 1:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="1KI 1:49"/>Then all of Adonijah’s guests ◄trembled/were afraid►, so they all immediately got up and left and scattered. <verse eid="1KI 1:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="1KI 1:50"/>Adonijah was afraid of what Solomon <char style="add">would do</char>, so he went <char style="add">to the Sacred Tent</char> and grabbed the projections at the corners of the altar, <char style="add">because he knew that no one would kill him there</char>. <verse eid="1KI 1:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1KI 1:51"/>But someone told Solomon, “Hey/Listen, Adonijah is afraid of you, so he <char style="add">has gone to the Sacred Tent and </char> is holding on to the corners of the altar. He is saying, ‘<char style="add">Before I leave,</char> I want King Solomon to solemnly promise that he will not command that I be executed.’”<verse eid="1KI 1:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="1KI 1:52"/>Solomon replied, “If he proves that he is loyal to me, I will not harm him at all [IDM]. But if he does anything that is wrong, he will be executed.” <verse eid="1KI 1:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1KI 1:53"/>So King Solomon sent <char style="add">some men to Adonijah</char>, and they brought him back from the altar. He came to Solomon and bowed down in front of him. Then Solomon said to him, “Go home.”<verse eid="1KI 1:53"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1KI 2"/>
  <para style="s1">David’s final instructions before he died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 2:1"/>When David <char style="add">knew that he</char> was about to die, he gave these final instructions to his son Solomon:<verse eid="1KI 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 2:2"/>“I am about to die [EUP], like everyone else on earth does. Be courageous and conduct yourself as an adult should. <verse eid="1KI 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 2:3"/>Do what Yahweh our God tells you to do. Conduct yourself as he wants you to do. Obey all of his laws and commands and precepts and instructions that are written in the laws that Moses <char style="add">gave us</char>. Do this in order that you will prosper in all that you do and wherever you go. <verse eid="1KI 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 2:4"/>If you continually do that, Yahweh will do what he promised me: He said, ‘If your descendants do what I tell them to do, and faithfully obey my commands with all their inner beings, they will always be [LIT] the ones who will rule [MTY] Israel.’<verse eid="1KI 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 2:5"/>“There is something else <char style="add">that I want you to do</char>. You know what Joab did to me. He killed my two army commanders, Abner and Amasa. He murdered them violently [MTY] during a time of peace, pretending that it was a time of war. Those two men ◄were innocent/had not done what was wrong►. But Joab <char style="add">killed them and </char>caused their blood to stain his belt and his sandals. <verse eid="1KI 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 2:6"/>Because you are wise, do to him what you think is best <char style="add">for you to do</char>, but do not allow him to become old [MTY] and then die [IDM] peacefully.<verse eid="1KI 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 2:7"/>“But be kind to the sons of Barzillai, the man from <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, and be sure that they always have enough food to eat [MTY]. Do that because Barzillai helped me when I was running away from your older brother Absalom.<verse eid="1KI 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 2:8"/>Also, <char style="add">you remember</char> Gera’s son Shimei from Bahurim <char style="add">town</char> in the area where the descendants of Benjamin live. <char style="add">You know what he did to me</char>. He cursed me terribly on the day I <char style="add">left Jerusalem and</char> went to Mahanaim <char style="add">town</char>. But when he later came down to see me at the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, I solemnly promised, while Yahweh listened [MTY], that I would not cause him to be executed. <verse eid="1KI 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 2:9"/>But now you must [LIT] surely punish him. You are a wise man, so you will know what you should do to him. He is an old man [MTY], but be sure that he <char style="add">loses/sheds</char> a lot of blood when you kill him [MTY].”<verse eid="1KI 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 2:10"/>Then David died [EUP] and was buried in <char style="add">that part of Jerusalem which was called</char> ‘The City of David’. <verse eid="1KI 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 2:11"/>David had been the king of Israel for 40 years: He ruled for seven years in Hebron and for 33 years in Jerusalem. <verse eid="1KI 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 2:12"/>Solomon became the ruler/king [MTY] to take the place of his father David and took control of all of the kingdom.<verse eid="1KI 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon had Adonijah killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 2:13"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> Adonijah came to Solomon’s mother Bathsheba. She said to him, “Have you come because you want things to go well?” He replied, “Yes.”<verse eid="1KI 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 2:14"/>But then he said, “I have something to ask you to do.” She said, “Tell me <char style="add">what you want me to do</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 2:15"/>He said, “You know that all the Israeli people expected me to be their king <char style="add">because I am David’s oldest surviving son</char>. But that did not happen. Instead, my <char style="add">younger</char> brother became king, because that is what Yahweh wanted. <verse eid="1KI 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 2:16"/>Now I have one thing that I ask you to do. Please do not refuse to do it.” She replied, “Tell me <char style="add">what you want me to do</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 2:17"/>He said, “Please ask King Solomon to give to me Abishag, the woman from Shunem <char style="add">town</char>, to be my wife. <char style="add">I am sure that</char> he will not refuse.”<verse eid="1KI 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 2:18"/>Bathsheba replied, “Okay, I will speak to the king for you.”<verse eid="1KI 2:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 2:19"/>So Bathsheba went to King Solomon, to tell him what Adonijah wanted. The king got up <char style="add">from his throne</char> and went to greet her and bowed down to her. Then he sat on his throne again and asked someone to bring a chair for her. So she sat down at the king’s right side.<verse eid="1KI 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 2:20"/>Then she said, “I have one small thing which I want you to do; please do not say that you will not do it.” The king replied, “Mother, what do you want? I will not refuse you.”<verse eid="1KI 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 2:21"/>She said, “Allow Abishag to be given to your <char style="add">older</char> brother Adonijah to be his wife.”<verse eid="1KI 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 2:22"/>The king replied <char style="add">angrily</char>, “What? Are you requesting me to give Abishag to Adonijah? <char style="add">Does he want me</char> to allow him to rule the kingdom, too? Because he is my older brother, <char style="add">does he think that he should be the king</char>? Does he think that Abiathar should be the priest <char style="add">instead of Zadok</char>, and that Joab <char style="add">should be the army commander instead of Benaiah</char> because they supported him <char style="add">when he tried to become the king</char>?”<verse eid="1KI 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 2:23"/>Then Solomon solemnly promised, requesting Yahweh to listen, “I wish God would strike me and kill me if I do not cause Adonijah to be executed for requesting this! <verse eid="1KI 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 2:24"/>Yahweh has appointed me to be the king and placed me here to rule [MTY] as my father David did. He has promised that my descendants [MTY] will be the kings of Israel. So just as surely as Yahweh lives, I solemnly promise that Adonijah will be executed today!” <verse eid="1KI 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 2:25"/>So King Solomon gave orders to Benaiah to <char style="add">go and</char> kill Adonijah, and Benaiah did that.<verse eid="1KI 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 2:26"/>Then Solomon said to Abiathar the priest, “Go to Anathoth <char style="add">town</char>, to your land there. You deserve to be killed, but I will not execute you now, because you were the one who <char style="add">supervised the men who</char> carried Yahweh’s Sacred Chest for David my father, and you endured all the troubles that my father endured.” <verse eid="1KI 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 2:27"/>So Solomon dismissed Abiathar from being the priest of Yahweh. By doing that he caused to happen what Yahweh had said <char style="add">many years previously</char> at Shiloh, <char style="add">that some day he would get rid</char> of the descendants [MTY] of Eli.<verse eid="1KI 2:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 2:28"/>Joab had not supported Absalom <char style="add">when he tried to become the king</char>, but he had supported Adonijah. So when Joab heard what had happened, he ran to the Sacred Tent, and he grasped the projections on the corners of the altar, <char style="add">because he knew that no one would kill him there</char>. <verse eid="1KI 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 2:29"/>When someone told Solomon that Joab had run to the Sacred Tent and was standing alongside the altar, Solomon told Benaiah, “Go and execute Joab.”<verse eid="1KI 2:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 2:30"/>So Benaiah went to the Sacred Tent and said to Joab, “The king commands you to come out!” But Joab replied, “No, I will die here.” So Benaiah went back to the king and reported <char style="add">what he had said to Joab, and</char> what Joab had replied.<verse eid="1KI 2:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 2:31"/>The king replied to him, “Do what he has requested. Kill him and bury his body. If you do that, my descendants [MTY] and I will no longer be punished for what Joab did when he killed [MTY] two men who ◄were innocent/had not done anything that is wrong►. <verse eid="1KI 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 2:32"/>But Yahweh will punish [MTY] Joab for attacking and killing Abner, the commander of the army of Israel, and Amasa, the commander of the army of Judah, two men who were more righteous and better [DOU] men than he is. My father David did not even know that Joab <char style="add">was planning to murder them</char>. <verse eid="1KI 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 2:33"/>Joab and his descendants will be punished [IDM] forever for his murdering Abner and Amasa. But things will forever go well for David’s descendants [MTY] who rule [MTY] as King David did.”<verse eid="1KI 2:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 2:34"/>So Benaiah went <char style="add">into the Sacred Tent</char> and killed Joab. Joab was buried on his property in the desert <char style="add">part of Judah</char>. <verse eid="1KI 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 2:35"/>Then the king appointed Benaiah to be the commander of the army instead of Joab, and he appointed Zadok to be the priest instead of Abiathar.<verse eid="1KI 2:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 2:36"/>Then the king sent <char style="add">a messenger</char> to summon Shimei, and the king said to him, “Build a house for yourself here in Jerusalem. Remain there and do not leave the city to go anywhere. <verse eid="1KI 2:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 2:37"/>Be sure that the day that you leave Jerusalem and go across the Kidron Brook, you will be executed, and it will be ◄your own fault/what you deserve►.”<verse eid="1KI 2:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 2:38"/>Shimei replied, “Your Majesty, what you say is good. I will do what you have said.” So Shimei remained in Jerusalem for several years.<verse eid="1KI 2:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 2:39"/>But three years later, two of Shimei’s slaves ran away. They went to stay with Maacah’s son Achish, the king of Gath <char style="add">city</char>. When someone told Shimei that they were in Gath, <verse eid="1KI 2:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 2:40"/>he put a saddle on his donkey and <char style="add">got on it and</char> went to Gath. He found his slaves staying with King Achish and brought them back home.<verse eid="1KI 2:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1KI 2:41"/>But someone told King Solomon that Shimei had gone from Jerusalem to Gath and had returned. <verse eid="1KI 2:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1KI 2:42"/>So the king sent <char style="add">a soldier</char> to summon Shimei and said to him, “I told you to solemnly promise, knowing that Yahweh [MTY] was listening, that you must not leave Jerusalem. I told you [RHQ], ‘Be sure that if you ever leave Jerusalem, you will be executed.’ And you replied [RHQ] to me, ‘What you have said is good; I will do what you have said.’ <verse eid="1KI 2:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 2:43"/>So why did you not do what you solemnly promised to Yahweh? Why did you disobey what I commanded you?”<verse eid="1KI 2:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="1KI 2:44"/>The king also said to Shimei, “You know all the evil things that you did to my father David. So Yahweh will now punish you for the evil things that you did. <verse eid="1KI 2:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1KI 2:45"/>But Yahweh will bless me, and he will enable David’s descendants [MTY] to rule forever.”<verse eid="1KI 2:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="1KI 2:46"/>Then the king gave an order to Benaiah, and he went and killed Shimei.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 2:46">So Solomon was completely in control of the kingdom.<verse eid="1KI 2:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1KI 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Solomon requested wisdom</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 3:1"/>Solomon went to see the king of Egypt. Solomon <char style="add">made an agreement with him to</char> marry his daughter. They also made an alliance/agreement <char style="add">that their armies would not attack each other</char>. Then Solomon brought the king’s daughter to live in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. <char style="add">She lived there</char> until Solomon’s workers had finished building his house and the temple of Yahweh and the wall around Jerusalem. <verse eid="1KI 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 3:2"/><char style="add">At that time</char> the temple of Yahweh had not yet been built, so the Israeli people were still offering sacrifices at many other places of worship. <verse eid="1KI 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 3:3"/>Solomon loved Yahweh, and he obeyed all the instructions that his father David had given him. But he also offered sacrifices and burned incense at various altars.<verse eid="1KI 3:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 3:4"/>One day the king went to Gibeon <char style="add">city</char> to offer a sacrifice there, because that was where the most famous/important altar was. In previous years he had offered hundreds of sacrifices on that altar. <verse eid="1KI 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 3:5"/>That night, Yahweh appeared to him in a dream. He asked Solomon, “What would you like me to give to you?”<verse eid="1KI 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 3:6"/>Solomon replied, “You always greatly and faithfully loved my father David, who served you <char style="add">well</char>. You did that because he ◄was faithful to/faithfully obeyed► you and acted righteously and honestly toward you. And you have showed how greatly and faithfully you loved him by giving to him me, his son, and now I am ruling [MTY] as he did <char style="add">before he died</char>.<verse eid="1KI 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 3:7"/>“Now, Yahweh my God, you have appointed me to be the king like my father was. But I am <char style="add">very young, like</char> a little child [MET]. I do not know how to lead/rule my people at all [IDM]. <verse eid="1KI 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 3:8"/>I am here among the people whom you have chosen. They are a very large group of people; there are very, very many of them, with the result that no one can count them [DOU]. <verse eid="1KI 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 3:9"/>So please enable me to think clearly, in order that I may rule your people <char style="add">well</char>. Enable me to know what is good and what is evil. <char style="add">If you do not do that,</char> I will never [RHQ] be able to rule this great group of people who belong to you.”<verse eid="1KI 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 3:10"/>Yahweh was very pleased that Solomon had requested that. <verse eid="1KI 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 3:11"/>God said to him, “You did not request that you live for many years or that you become very rich or that you be able to kill all your enemies. Instead, you have requested that I enable you to be wise, in order that you will be able to know <char style="add">and to do</char> what is right <char style="add">while you govern these people</char>. <verse eid="1KI 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 3:12"/>So, I will certainly do what you requested. I will enable you to be very wise [DOU]. The result will be that no one who has lived before you or who will live after you will be as <char style="add">wise as</char> you are. <verse eid="1KI 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 3:13"/>I will also give you things that you did not request: I will enable you to become very rich and honored, as long as you live. You will be richer and more honored than any other king. <verse eid="1KI 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 3:14"/>If you conduct your life [IDM] as I want you to, and if you obey all my laws and commandments, as your father David did, I will enable you to live for many years.”<verse eid="1KI 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 3:15"/>Then Solomon awoke, and he realized that <char style="add">God had spoken to him in</char> a dream. Then he went to Jerusalem and stood in front of <char style="add">the Sacred Tent where</char> the Sacred Chest <char style="add">was</char>, and he offered many sacrifices that were completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> and offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. Then he made a feast for all his officials.<verse eid="1KI 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon made a very wise decision concerning two women</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 3:16"/>One day two prostitutes came and stood in front of King Solomon. <verse eid="1KI 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 3:17"/>One of them said, “Your Majesty, this woman and I live in the same house. I gave birth to a baby while she was there in the house. <verse eid="1KI 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 3:18"/>Three days after my baby was born, this woman also gave birth to a baby. Only the two of us were in the house; there was no one else there.<verse eid="1KI 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 3:19"/>“But one night this woman’s baby died because she <char style="add">accidentally</char> rolled on top of her baby <char style="add">while sleeping and smothered it</char>. <verse eid="1KI 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 3:20"/>So she got up at midnight and took my baby boy who was lying beside me while I was sleeping. She carried him to her bed and brought her dead baby and put it in my bed. <verse eid="1KI 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 3:21"/>When I awoke the next morning and was ready to nurse my baby, I saw that it was dead. But when I looked at it closely in the morning light, I saw that it was not my baby!”<verse eid="1KI 3:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 3:22"/>But the other woman said, “That is not true! The baby that is alive is mine, and the baby that is dead is yours!” Then the first woman said, “No, the dead baby is yours, and the one that is alive is mine!” And they continued to argue in front of the king.<verse eid="1KI 3:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 3:23"/>Then the king said, “Both of you are saying, ‘My baby is the one that is alive and the one that is dead is yours.’ ” <verse eid="1KI 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 3:24"/>So he said to one of his servants, “Bring me a sword.” So the servant brought a sword to the king. <verse eid="1KI 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 3:25"/>Then the king said to the servant, “Cut the baby that is alive into two parts. Give one part to each of the women.”<verse eid="1KI 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 3:26"/>But the woman whose baby was alive loved her baby very much, so she said to the king, “No, Your Majesty! Do not allow him to kill the baby! Give her the child that is alive!” But the other woman said to the king, “No, cut it in half. Then it will not be her baby or my baby.”<verse eid="1KI 3:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 3:27"/>Then the king said to the servant, “Do not kill the baby. Give the baby to the woman who said ‘Do not cut the baby in half,’ because she is truly the baby’s mother.”<verse eid="1KI 3:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 3:28"/>All the Israeli people heard about what the king had decided, and they revered him. They realized that God had truly enabled him to be very wise, to judge people’s matters fairly.<verse eid="1KI 3:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1KI 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s governors and officials</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 4:1"/>Solomon was the king who ruled all of Israel, <verse eid="1KI 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 4:2"/>and these were his most important officials:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1KI 4:2"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 4:2">Zadok’s son Azariah was the priest.<verse eid="1KI 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 4:3"/>Shisha’s sons Elihoreph and Ahijah were the <char style="add">official</char> secretaries.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 4:3">Ahilud’s son Jehoshaphat was the one who announced to the people the king’s decisions.<verse eid="1KI 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 4:4"/>Benaiah was the commander of the army.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 4:4">Zadok and Abiathar were also priests.<verse eid="1KI 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 4:5"/>Nathan’s son Azariah was the administrator of the governors.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 4:5">Another of Nathan’s sons, Zabud, was a priest and the king’s chief advisor.<verse eid="1KI 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 4:6"/>Ahishar supervised the servants who worked in the palace.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 4:6">Abda’s son Adoniram supervised the men who were forced to do work <char style="add">for the government</char>.<verse eid="1KI 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 4:7"/>Solomon appointed twelve men, one to govern <char style="add">each of the regions </char> in Israel. They also were required to provide food for the king and all the others who lived and worked in the palace. Each man was required to provide from his own region the food for one month each year. <verse eid="1KI 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 4:8"/>Their names were:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1KI 4:8"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 4:8">Ben-Hur, for the hilly area of the tribe of Ephraim.<verse eid="1KI 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 4:9"/>Ben-Deker, for Makaz, Shaalbim, Beth-Shemesh, and Elon-Bethhanan <char style="add">cities</char>;<verse eid="1KI 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 4:10"/>Ben-Hesed, for Arubboth and Socoh <char style="add">towns</char> and the area near Hepher <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="1KI 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 4:11"/>Ben-Abinadab, who was married to Solomon’s daughter Taphath, for all the Dor district;<verse eid="1KI 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 4:12"/>Ahilud’s son Baana, for Taanach and Megiddo <char style="add">towns</char>, and all the region near Zarethan <char style="add">city</char>, and from Beth-Shan <char style="add">city</char> south of Jezreel as far as Abel-Meholah <char style="add">town</char> and Jokmeam <char style="add">city</char>;<verse eid="1KI 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 4:13"/>Ben-Geber, for Ramoth <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, and for the villages in Gilead that belonged to Jair, who was a descendant of Manasseh, and the Argob area in <char style="add">the</char> Bashan <char style="add">region</char>. There were 60 large towns in that region altogether, each town with a wall around it and bronze bars across the gates.<verse eid="1KI 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 4:14"/>Iddo’s son Ahinadab, for Mahanaim <char style="add">city east of the Jordan River</char>;<verse eid="1KI 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 4:15"/>Ahimaaz, who had married Solomon’s daughter Basemath, for <char style="add">the territory of the tribe of</char> Naphtali;<verse eid="1KI 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 4:16"/>Hushai’s son Baana, for <char style="add">the territory of the tribe of</char> Asher and for Aloth <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="1KI 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 4:17"/>Paruah’s son Jehoshaphat, for <char style="add">the territory of the tribe of</char> Issachar;<verse eid="1KI 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 4:18"/>Ela’s son Shimei, for <char style="add">the territory of the tribe of</char> Benjamin;<verse eid="1KI 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 4:19"/>Uri’s son Geber, for the Gilead region, the land that Sihon the king of the Amor people-group <char style="add">formerly ruled</char>, and the Bashan <char style="add">area</char>, which was the area that Og <char style="add">formerly ruled</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 4:19">
    <char style="add">In addition to all those</char>, Solomon appointed one governor for the <char style="add">territory of the</char> tribe of Judah.<verse eid="1KI 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s kingdom</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 4:20"/>There were as many people in Judah and Israel as there are grains of sand [HYP] on the seashore. They <char style="add">had plenty to</char> eat and drink and they were happy. <verse eid="1KI 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 4:21"/>Solomon’s kingdom extended from the Euphrates <char style="add">River in the northeast</char> to the Philistia area <char style="add">in the west</char> and to the border of Egypt <char style="add">in the south</char>. The <char style="add">conquered</char> people in those areas paid taxes and were under Solomon’s control for the rest of his life.<verse eid="1KI 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 4:22"/>
    <char style="add">To feed the people in his palace and his guests</char> Solomon needed people to bring to him every day 150 bushels of fine flour and 300 bushels of wheat, <verse eid="1KI 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 4:23"/>ten cattle that were kept in stalls/barns, 20 cattle that were kept in pastures, 100 sheep, and ◄deer and gazelles and roebucks/three kinds of deer►, and poultry. <verse eid="1KI 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 4:24"/>Solomon ruled over all the area west of the Euphrates <char style="add">River</char>, from Tiphsah <char style="add">city in the northeast</char> to Gaza <char style="add">city in the southwest</char>. He ruled over all the kings in that area. And there was peace between his <char style="add">government</char> and the <char style="add">governments of</char> nearby countries. <verse eid="1KI 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 4:25"/>All during the years that Solomon ruled, the people of Judah and Israel lived safely. Each family had its own grapevines and fig trees.<verse eid="1KI 4:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 4:26"/>Solomon had 4,000 stalls for the horses <char style="add">that pulled</char> his chariots and 12,000 men who rode on horses (OR, in the chariots).<verse eid="1KI 4:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 4:27"/>His twelve governors supplied the food that King Solomon needed for himself and for all those who ate in the palace. Each governor supplied food for one month each year. They provided everything [LIT] that Solomon required. <verse eid="1KI 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 4:28"/>They also brought <char style="add">stalks of</char> barley and wheat for the fast horses <char style="add">that pulled the chariots</char> and for the <char style="add">other work</char> horses. They brought it to the places where the horses were kept.<verse eid="1KI 4:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s wisdom</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 4:29"/>God enabled Solomon to be extremely wise and to have great insight/understanding. He understood about more things than the number of grains of sand on the seashore [HYP]. <verse eid="1KI 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 4:30"/>He was wiser than all the wise men in Arabia and Mesopotamia and all the wise men in Egypt. <verse eid="1KI 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 4:31"/>Ethan from Ezrah and Heman and Calcol and Darda and the sons of Mahol were <char style="add">considered to be</char> very wise, but Solomon was wiser than all of them. People in all the nearby countries heard about Solomon. <verse eid="1KI 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 4:32"/>He composed/wrote 3,000 ◄proverbs/wise sayings► and more than 1,000 songs. <verse eid="1KI 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 4:33"/>He talked about various kinds of plants, from the <char style="add">huge</char> cedar trees in Lebanon to the <char style="add">tiny</char> hyssop plants that grow in cracks in walls. He also talked about wild animals and birds and reptiles and fish. <verse eid="1KI 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 4:34"/>People came from all over the world to hear the wise things that Solomon said. Many kings sent men to listen to him <char style="add">and then return and tell them what Solomon said</char>.<verse eid="1KI 4:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1KI 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Preparations for building the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 5:1"/>Hiram, the king of Tyre <char style="add">city</char>, had always been a close friend of King David. When he heard that Solomon had been appointed to become the king after his father was no longer king, he sent some messengers to Solomon <char style="add">to congratulate him</char>. <verse eid="1KI 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 5:2"/>Solomon <char style="add">gave those messengers</char> this message to take back to Hiram:<verse eid="1KI 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 5:3"/>“You know that my father David <char style="add">led his soldiers to</char> fight many wars against his enemies in the nearby countries. So he could not <char style="add">arrange to</char> build a temple in which we [MTY] could worship Yahweh our God, until after Yahweh enabled <char style="add">the Israeli army</char> to defeat [IDM] all his enemies. <verse eid="1KI 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 5:4"/>But now Yahweh our God has enabled us to have peace with all the surrounding countries. <char style="add">◄There is no danger that/We do not need to worry that►</char> we will be attacked. <verse eid="1KI 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 5:5"/>Yahweh promised my father David, ‘Your son, whom I will enable to be king after you are no longer king, will build a temple for me [MTY].’ Because of that, I have decided to build a temple in which we can worship [MTY] Yahweh our God.<verse eid="1KI 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 5:6"/>“So <char style="add">I am requesting that</char> you command your workers to cut cedar trees for me. My men will work with them, and I will pay your workers whatever you decide. <char style="add">But</char> my men <char style="add">cannot do the work alone,</char> because they do not know how to cut down trees like your workers from Sidon <char style="add">city</char> do.”<verse eid="1KI 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 5:7"/>When Hiram heard the message from Solomon, he was very happy and said, “I praise Yahweh today for giving David a very wise son to rule that great nation!”<verse eid="1KI 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 5:8"/>He sent this message back to Solomon: “I have heard the message that you sent to me, and I am ready to do what you ask. I will provide cedar and cypress logs. <verse eid="1KI 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 5:9"/>My workers will bring the logs down from <char style="add">the</char> Lebanon <char style="add">mountains</char> to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> sea. Then they will <char style="add">tie them together to</char> make rafts to float them <char style="add">in the water</char> along the coast to the place that you indicate. Then my workers will untie the logs, and your workers will take them from there. What I want you to do is to supply food for the people who work in my palace.”<verse eid="1KI 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 5:10"/>So Hiram <char style="add">arranged for his workers to</char> supply all the cedar and cypress logs that Solomon wanted. <verse eid="1KI 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 5:11"/>Each year Solomon gave Hiram 100,000 bushels of wheat and 110,000 gallons of pure <char style="add">olive</char> oil to feed the people who worked in his palace. <verse eid="1KI 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 5:12"/>Yahweh enabled Solomon to be wise, just like he had promised. Solomon and Hiram made a treaty/agreement that there would be peace between their <char style="add">two governments/countries</char>.<verse eid="1KI 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 5:13"/>King Solomon forced 30,000 men from all over Israel to become his workers. <verse eid="1KI 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 5:14"/>Adoniram was their boss. Solomon divided the men into three groups. Each month 10,000 of them went to Lebanon and worked for a month there, and then they came back home for two months. <verse eid="1KI 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 5:15"/>Solomon also forced 80,000 men to cut stones in the hilly area and 70,000 men to haul the stones <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char>. <verse eid="1KI 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 5:16"/>And he also assigned 3,600 men to supervise their work. <verse eid="1KI 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 5:17"/>The king also commanded his workers to cut huge blocks of stones from the quarries and to smooth the sides of the stones. Those huge stones were for the foundation of the temple. <verse eid="1KI 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 5:18"/>Solomon’s workers and Hiram’s workers and men from Gebal/Byblos <char style="add">city</char> shaped the stones and prepared the timber to build the temple.<verse eid="1KI 5:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="1KI 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s men built the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 6:1"/>480 years after the Israeli people left Egypt, during the fourth year that Solomon ruled Israel, early in May, Solomon’s workers began to build the temple.<verse eid="1KI 6:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 6:2"/>Inside, <char style="add">the main part of</char> the temple was 90 feet long, 30 feet wide, and 45 feet high. <verse eid="1KI 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 6:3"/>The entrance room was 15 feet long and 30 feet wide, just as wide as the main part of the temple. <verse eid="1KI 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 6:4"/>There were windows in <char style="add">the walls of</char> the temple. The windows were narrower on the outside than on the inside. <verse eid="1KI 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 6:5"/>Against the two sides and against the back of the temple walls, they built a structure/building that had rooms in it. <char style="add">This structure had three levels/stories and each was 7-1/2 feet high</char>. <verse eid="1KI 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 6:6"/><char style="add">Each room in</char> the lowest level/story was 7-1/2 feet wide. <char style="add">Each room in</char> the middle level/story was nine feet wide. <char style="add">The rooms in</char> the top level/story were 10-1/2 feet wide. The wall of the temple at the top level/story was thinner than the wall at the middle level/story, and the wall of the middle level/story was thinner than the wall at the bottom level/story. The result was that the rooms could be supported by the wall underneath them, and did not require wooden beams to support them.<verse eid="1KI 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 6:7"/>The huge stones for <char style="add">the foundation of</char> the temple were cut and shaped at the quarry <char style="add">to become very smooth</char>. The result was that while the workers were building the temple there was no noise, because they did not use hammers or chisels or any other iron tools there.<verse eid="1KI 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 6:8"/>The entrance to the bottom level/story <char style="add">of that attached structure</char> was on the south side of the temple. There were stairs from the bottom level/story to the middle and top level/story. <verse eid="1KI 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 6:9"/>So Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> finished building the <char style="add">framework of the</char> temple. They made the ceiling from cedar beams and boards. <verse eid="1KI 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 6:10"/>They built the structure that had three levels/stories, that was against the walls of the temple. Each level/story was 7-1/2 feet high, and was joined to the temple with cedar beams.<verse eid="1KI 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 6:11"/>Then Yahweh said this to Solomon: <verse eid="1KI 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 6:12"/>“<char style="add">I want to tell you</char> about this temple that you are building. If you continually obey all my statutes and laws and commands, I will do for you what I promised to your father David. <verse eid="1KI 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 6:13"/>I will live among the Israeli people, <char style="add">in this temple,</char> and I will never abandon them.”<verse eid="1KI 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 6:14"/>Solomon’s <char style="add">workers </char> finished building the temple. <verse eid="1KI 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 6:15"/>On the inside, they lined/covered the walls with cedar boards. They lined/covered them from the floor to the ceiling. They made the floor from cypress boards. <verse eid="1KI 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 6:16"/>Inside the back part of the temple they built an inner room, called the Very Holy Place. It was 30 feet long. All the walls of this room were lined with cedar boards. <verse eid="1KI 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 6:17"/>In front of the Very Holy Place there was a room that was 60 feet long. <verse eid="1KI 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 6:18"/>The cedar <char style="add">boards on the walls</char> inside the temple were decorated with carvings of gourds and flowers. <char style="add">The walls were</char> completely covered with cedar boards, with the result that the stones <char style="add">of the walls behind them</char> could not be seen.<verse eid="1KI 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 6:19"/>At the back of the temple they made the Very Holy Place, where the Sacred Chest would be put. <verse eid="1KI 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 6:20"/>That room was 30 feet long, 30 feet wide, and 30 feet high. They covered the walls with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> pure gold. <char style="add">For burning incense</char> they also made an altar of cedar <char style="add">boards</char>. <verse eid="1KI 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 6:21"/>Solomon told them to cover the other walls inside the temple with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> pure gold and to fasten gold chains across the entrance to the Very Holy Place. <verse eid="1KI 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 6:22"/>They covered all the walls of the temple and the altar that was outside the Very Holy Place with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> gold.<verse eid="1KI 6:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 6:23"/>Inside the Very Holy Place, they made from olive tree wood <char style="add">large statues of</char> two creatures with wings. Each one was 15 feet tall. <verse eid="1KI 6:23"/><verse number="24-26" style="v" sid="1KI 6:24-26"/>They each were the same size and had the same shape. They each had two wings <char style="add">which were spread out</char>. Each wing was 7-1/2 feet long, with the result that the distance between the outer ends of the two wings was 15 feet. <verse eid="1KI 6:24-26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 6:27"/>They put those statues next to each other in the Very Holy Place so that the wing of the one touched the one wing of the other in the center of the room, and the outer wings touched the walls. <verse eid="1KI 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 6:28"/>They covered the statues with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> gold.<verse eid="1KI 6:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 6:29"/>
    <char style="add">Solomon told them to</char> decorate the walls of the main room and the Very Holy Place by carving representations of winged creatures and palm trees and flowers. <verse eid="1KI 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 6:30"/>They also covered the floor of both rooms with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> gold.<verse eid="1KI 6:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 6:31"/>They made a set of doors from olive tree wood, and placed them at the entrance to the Very Holy Place. The doorposts joined at the top to form a pointed arch. <verse eid="1KI 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 6:32"/>The doors were decorated by carving on them representations of winged creatures, palm trees, and flowers. All of these things were covered with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> gold. <verse eid="1KI 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 6:33"/>They made a rectangular door frame from olive tree wood, and put it <char style="add">between the entrance room and</char> the main room. <verse eid="1KI 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 6:34"/>They made two folding doors from cypress wood <char style="add">and fastened them to the door frame</char>. <verse eid="1KI 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 6:35"/>The doors were also decorated with wood carvings of winged creatures, palm trees, and flowers, and they were also covered evenly with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> gold.<verse eid="1KI 6:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 6:36"/>They built a courtyard in front of the temple. The walls around the courtyard were made of cedar and stone; to make the walls, between each layer of cedar beams they put down two layers of stone.<verse eid="1KI 6:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 6:37"/>They laid the foundation of the temple of Yahweh in early May, in the fourth year <char style="add">that Solomon ruled</char>. <verse eid="1KI 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 6:38"/>In the eleventh year <char style="add">that he ruled</char>, in the middle of October, they finished building the temple and all of its parts, doing exactly what Solomon told them to do. It required seven years to build it.<verse eid="1KI 6:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="1KI 7"/>
  <para style="s1">They built a palace for Solomon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 7:1"/>They also built a palace for Solomon, but it required 13 years to build it. <verse eid="1KI 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 7:2"/>One of the buildings they constructed was <char style="add">a</char> large <char style="add">ceremonial hall</char>. It was called the Hall of the Forest of Lebanon. It was 150 feet long, 75 feet wide, and 45 feet high. It was supported/held up by four rows of pillars of <char style="add">wood from</char> cedar <char style="add">trees</char>. There were 15 pillars in each row. There were cedar beams across each row. <verse eid="1KI 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 7:3"/><char style="add">To support the roof</char> there were cedar beams that connected the rows of pillars. <verse eid="1KI 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 7:4"/>On each of the two side walls there were three rows of windows. <verse eid="1KI 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 7:5"/>All the windows and doorways had rectangular frames. The windows along the long wall on one side faced the windows on the other side.<verse eid="1KI 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 7:6"/>They also built another building called the Hall of Pillars. It was 75 feet long and 45 feet wide. It had a covered porch <char style="add">whose roof was</char> supported by pillars.<verse eid="1KI 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 7:7"/>Then they made a building called the Hall of the Throne. It was also called the Hall of Judgment. That was where Solomon decided/judged concerning people’s disputes. The walls were covered with cedar boards, from the floor to the rafters.<verse eid="1KI 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 7:8"/>In the courtyard behind the Hall of Judgment they built a house for Solomon to live in that was made like the other buildings. They also built the same kind of house for his wife, who was the daughter of the king of Egypt.<verse eid="1KI 7:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 7:9"/>All of those buildings and the walls around the palace courtyard were made from costly blocks of stone, from the foundations up to the eaves. The stones were cut <char style="add">at the quarry</char>, according to the sizes that were needed, and the sides of the stones were shaped by cutting/smoothing them with saws. <verse eid="1KI 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 7:10"/>The foundations were also made from huge blocks of stone <char style="add">that were prepared at the quarry</char>. Some of them were twelve feet long and some were fifteen feet long. <verse eid="1KI 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 7:11"/>On top of the foundation stones were other blocks of stone that were cut according to the sizes they needed, and cedar beams. <verse eid="1KI 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 7:12"/>The palace courtyard, the inner courtyard in front of the temple, and the entrance room of the temple had walls made by putting down three layers of cut stones between each layer of cedar beams.<verse eid="1KI 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Other things for the temple area</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13-14" style="v" sid="1KI 7:13-14"/>There was a man who lived in Tyre <char style="add">city</char> whose name was Huram. He knew how to make very nice things from bronze. His father had also lived in Tyre and had also been very skilled at making things from bronze, but Huram’s father was no longer living. His mother was from the tribe of Naphtali. Huram was very wise and intelligent and was very skilled at making things from bronze. Solomon invited him to come <char style="add">to Jerusalem and supervise</char> all the work of making things from bronze, and Huram agreed.<verse eid="1KI 7:13-14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 7:15"/>He made two bronze pillars. Each one was 27 feet tall and 18 feet around. Each was hollow, and the walls of the pillars were 3 in./7.4 cm. thick. <verse eid="1KI 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 7:16"/>He also made two bronze caps to be put on top of the pillars. Each cap was 7-1/2 feet tall. <verse eid="1KI 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 7:17"/>Then he made bronze wreaths of chains to decorate the top part of each pillar. <verse eid="1KI 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 7:18"/>He also made bronze <char style="add">figures that resembled</char> pomegranates. He put two rows of pomegranates over the top parts of each pillar. <verse eid="1KI 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 7:19"/>The top part over each pillar was shaped like a lily. Each <char style="add">lily leaf</char> was six feet tall. <verse eid="1KI 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 7:20"/>These top parts were placed on a bowl-shaped section around which was draped the wreaths of chains. He made 200 <char style="add">figures that represented</char> pomegranates and put them in two rows around the top/head of each pillar. <verse eid="1KI 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 7:21"/>His <char style="add">helpers</char> set up the pillars in front of the entrance of the temple. The pillar on the south side was named Jakin, and the pillar on the north side was named Boaz. <verse eid="1KI 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 7:22"/>The bronze top parts that were shaped like lilies were placed on top of the pillars.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 7:22">So Huram and his helpers finished making the bronze pillars.<verse eid="1KI 7:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 7:23"/>Huram also constructed a very large round bronze tank that was made of metal and cast <char style="add">in a clay mold</char>. It was 7-1/2 ft./2.3 meters high, 30 feet/9 meters across/wide, and 45 feet/13.5 meters around it. <verse eid="1KI 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 7:24"/>Around the outer edge of the rim of the tank were two rows of gourds that were made of bronze. <char style="add">But</char> the gourds <char style="add">were not cast separately; they</char> were cast in the same mold as the rest of the tank. For each foot of length around the rim of the tank there were six <char style="add">figures of</char> gourds.<verse eid="1KI 7:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 7:25"/>Huram <char style="add">also cast</char> twelve <char style="add">bronze statues of</char> oxen. He placed them to face outward. He placed three of them to face north, three to face west, three to face south, and three to face east. His helpers put the bronze tank on the backs of <char style="add">the statues of</char> the oxen. <verse eid="1KI 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 7:26"/>The sides <char style="add">of the tank</char> were 3 in./8 cm. thick. The rim was like the rim of a cup. It <char style="add">curved outward,</char> like the petals of a lily. <char style="add">When the tank was full,</char> it held about 10,000 gallons <char style="add">of water</char>.<verse eid="1KI 7:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 7:27"/>Huram also made ten bronze carts. Each was six feet long and six feet wide and 4-1/2 feet tall. <verse eid="1KI 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 7:28"/><char style="add">On the sides of the carts</char> there were panels which were set in frames. <verse eid="1KI 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 7:29"/>On those panels were <char style="add">bronze figures of</char> lions, bulls, and winged creatures. Below and above the lions and bulls there were decorations of bronze wreaths. <verse eid="1KI 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 7:30"/>Each cart had four bronze wheels and two axles made of bronze. At the top corners of each cart were bronze supports to hold up a basin. On these supports were also decorations of bronze wreaths. <verse eid="1KI 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 7:31"/>On top of each cart, <char style="add">under each basin,</char> was a frame <char style="add">that resembled</char> a circular collar. The top of each circular frame was 18 inches above the top of the cart, and the bottom of it was nine inches below the top of the cart. There were also decorations of bronze wreaths on the frame engraved within square panels. <verse eid="1KI 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 7:32"/>The wheels were 27 inches high. They were below the panels. The wheels were connected to axles that had been cast in the same mold as the rest of the cart. <verse eid="1KI 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 7:33"/>The wheels of the carts were like the wheels of chariots. The axles, the rims, the spokes, and the hubs were all cast <char style="add">from bronze</char>.<verse eid="1KI 7:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 7:34"/>At the top corners of each cart there were handles. These were cast in the same mold as the rest of the cart. <verse eid="1KI 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 7:35"/>There was a nine-inch bronze band around the top of each cart. There were braces attached to the corners of each cart. The bands and the braces were cast in the same mold as the rest of the cart. <verse eid="1KI 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 7:36"/>The braces and the panels <char style="add">on the sides of the carts</char> were also decorated with <char style="add">figures of</char> winged creatures, lions, and palm trees, whenever there was space for them, and there were bronze wreaths all around them. <verse eid="1KI 7:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 7:37"/>That is how Huram made the ten carts. They <char style="add">were all cast in the same mold, so they</char> were all alike: They all were the same size and had the same shape.<verse eid="1KI 7:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 7:38"/>Huram also made ten bronze basins, one for each cart. Each basin was six feet across and held 200 gallons <char style="add">of water</char>. <verse eid="1KI 7:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 7:39"/>Huram placed five of the carts on the south side of the temple and five on the north side. He put the big tank at the southeast corner. <verse eid="1KI 7:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 7:40"/>Huram also made pots, shovels <char style="add">for carrying ashes</char>, and bowls <char style="add">for carrying the blood of the animals that would be sacrificed</char>. He completed all the work that King Solomon requested him to do for the temple. <char style="add">This is a list of the bronze things he made</char>:<verse eid="1KI 7:40"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1KI 7:41"/>the two pillars;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:41">the two top parts to be put over the pillars;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:41">the two wreaths of chains to decorate the tops of the pillars;<verse eid="1KI 7:41"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="1KI 7:42"/>the 400 <char style="add">figures of</char> pomegranates, in two rows, with 100 in each row, that were placed over the top parts of the pillars;<verse eid="1KI 7:42"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 7:43"/>the ten carts;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:43">the ten basins;<verse eid="1KI 7:43"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="1KI 7:44"/>the big tank;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:44">the twelve <char style="add">statues of</char> oxen on whose backs the tank was placed;<verse eid="1KI 7:44"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1KI 7:45"/>the pots, shovels <char style="add">for the ashes of the altar</char>, and bowls.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="1KI 7:45"/>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 7:45">Huram <char style="add">and his workers</char> made all these things for King Solomon and put them outside the temple. They were all made of polished bronze.<verse eid="1KI 7:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="1KI 7:46"/>They made them by pouring melted bronze into the clay molds that Huram had set up near the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley, between <char style="add">the cities of</char> Succoth and Zarethan.<verse eid="1KI 7:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="1KI 7:47"/>Solomon did not <char style="add">tell his workers to</char> weigh those bronze objects, because there were many items. So no one ever knew what they weighed.<verse eid="1KI 7:47"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="1KI 7:48"/>Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> also made all the gold items for the temple:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:48">the altar;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:48">the table on which the priests put the sacred bread placed before God;<verse eid="1KI 7:48"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="1KI 7:49"/>the ten lampstands <char style="add">that were put</char> in front of the Very Holy Place, five on the south side and five on the north side;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:49">the <char style="add">decorations that resembled</char> flowers;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:49">the lamps;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:49">the tongs <char style="add">to grasp the hot coals</char>;<verse eid="1KI 7:49"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="1KI 7:50"/>the cups, the gold lamp wick snuffers, the small lamp bowls, the dishes for incense, the pans <char style="add">for carrying the hot coals</char>, and the hinges for the doors at the entrance to the Very Holy Place and for the doors at the entrance <char style="add">to the main room</char> of the temple.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="1KI 7:50">Those things were all made of gold.<verse eid="1KI 7:50"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="1KI 7:51"/>So Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> finished all the work for the temple. Then they placed in the temple storerooms all the things that his father David had dedicated to Yahweh—all the silver and gold, and the other valuable items.<verse eid="1KI 7:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="1KI 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The sacred chest was brought to the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 8:1"/>Solomon then summoned to Jerusalem all the elders of Israel, all the leaders of the tribes, and the leaders of the clans. He wanted them to join in bringing Yahweh’s Sacred Chest from Zion <char style="add">Hill to the temple</char>, where it was in the part of the city called ‘The City of David’. <verse eid="1KI 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 8:2"/>So all the Israeli leaders came to King Solomon during the Festival of <char style="add">Living in Temporary</char> Shelters, in October.<verse eid="1KI 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 8:3"/>When they had all arrived, the priests lifted up the Sacred Chest <verse eid="1KI 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 8:4"/>and brought it to the temple. The descendants of Levi <char style="add">who assisted the priests</char> helped them to carry to the temple the Sacred Tent and all the sacred things that had been in the tent. <verse eid="1KI 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 8:5"/>Then King Solomon and many of the Israeli people who had gathered in front of Yahweh’s Sacred Chest sacrificed a huge amount of sheep and oxen. No one was able to count the sacrifices <char style="add">because there were so many</char>.<verse eid="1KI 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 8:6"/>The the priests then brought the Sacred Chest into the Very Holy Place in the temple, and they placed it under the wings of the <char style="add">statues of the</char> winged creatures. <verse eid="1KI 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 8:7"/>The wings of those statues spread out over the Sacred Chest and over the poles by which it was carried. <verse eid="1KI 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 8:8"/>The poles were so long that the ends of the poles could be seen <char style="add">by people who were standing</char> at the entrance to the Most Holy Place, but they could not be seen <char style="add">by people standing</char> outside the temple. Those poles are still there. <verse eid="1KI 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 8:9"/>The only things that were in the Sacred Chest were the two stone tablets that Moses had put there at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char>, where Yahweh made an agreement with the people after they left Egypt.<verse eid="1KI 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 8:10"/>When the priests came out of the temple, <char style="add">suddenly</char> it was filled with a cloud. <verse eid="1KI 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 8:11"/>It was the glory/radiance of Yahweh that filled the temple, with the result that the priests were not able to continue their work.<verse eid="1KI 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 8:12"/>Then Solomon prayed this:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1KI 8:12">“Yahweh, you have placed the sun in the sky,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1KI 8:12">but you have decided that you would live in very dark <char style="add">clouds</char>.<verse eid="1KI 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 8:13"/>I have built for you a magnificent temple,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1KI 8:13">a place for you to live in forever.”<verse eid="1KI 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 8:14"/>Then, while all the people stood there, the king turned around and faced them, and he <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless them. <verse eid="1KI 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 8:15"/>He said, “Praise Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis belong! By his own power he has done what he promised to give to my father David. What he promised was this:<verse eid="1KI 8:15"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 8:16"/>‘From the time that I brought my people out of Egypt, I have never chosen any city in Israel in which a temple should be built for my people to worship me there. But I chose you, David, to rule my people.”<verse eid="1KI 8:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 8:17"/>
    <char style="add">Then Solomon said</char>, “My father David wanted to build a temple in order that we Israeli people could worship Yahweh our God there. <verse eid="1KI 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 8:18"/>But Yahweh said to him, ‘You have wanted to build a temple for me, and what you wanted to do was good. <verse eid="1KI 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 8:19"/>However, you are not the one <char style="add">who I want</char> to build it. It is one of your sons, who <char style="add">I want to</char> build a temple for me.’<verse eid="1KI 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 8:20"/>And now Yahweh has done what he promised to do. I have become the king of Israel to succeed my father, and I am ruling my people, like Yahweh promised. I have <char style="add">arranged for</char> this temple <char style="add">to be</char> built for us Israelis to worship Yahweh, the God, to whom we Israelis belong. <verse eid="1KI 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 8:21"/>I have also provided a place <char style="add">in the temple</char> for the Sacred Chest in which are the two stone tablets <char style="add">on which are engraved the Ten Commandments of</char> the agreement that Yahweh made with our ancestors when he brought them out of Egypt.”<verse eid="1KI 8:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s prayer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 8:22"/>Then Solomon stood in front of the altar which was facing the Israeli people who had gathered there. He spread out his arms toward heaven, <verse eid="1KI 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 8:23"/>and he prayed,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="1KI 8:23">“Yahweh, the God whom we Israeli people <char style="add">belong to/worship</char>, there is no god like you up in heaven or down here on the earth. You solemnly promised that you would faithfully love us. And that is what you have done for us who earnestly do what you want us to do.<verse eid="1KI 8:23"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 8:24"/>You have done the things that you promised my father David, who served you <char style="add">very well</char>, that you would do. Truly, you promised to do these things for him, and today we see that by your power you have done them.<verse eid="1KI 8:24"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 8:25"/>So now, Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">belong to/worship</char>, please do the things that you promised my father that you would do. You told him that there would always be some of his descendants who would rule Israel, if they would conduct their lives as he did. <verse eid="1KI 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 8:26"/>So now, God of us Israeli people, cause what you promised to do for my father David, who served you <char style="add">well</char>, to happen.<verse eid="1KI 8:26"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 8:27"/>But God, you cannot really live on the earth. There is surely not enough space for you in the sky, or even in the heaven. So there is surely not enough space for you to live in this temple that my workers have built. <verse eid="1KI 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 8:28"/>But Yahweh, my God, please listen to me while I am praying to you this day, <verse eid="1KI 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 8:29"/>Please keep protecting this temple night and day. This is the place about which you have said, ‘I will always be there.’ I request that you listen to me whenever I turn toward this temple and pray. <verse eid="1KI 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 8:30"/>I request that when I pray to you and your people pray to you while they turn toward this place, that in your home in heaven you will hear us and forgive us <char style="add">for the sins that we have committed</char>.<verse eid="1KI 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 8:31"/>If someone is accused of doing something wrong to another person, and they bring him to your altar outside this holy temple, and if he says, ‘I did not do that; may God punish me if I am not telling the truth,’ <verse eid="1KI 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 8:32"/>then you listen from heaven, and decide who is telling the truth. Then punish the person who is guilty as he deserves to be punished, and declare that the other person is innocent.<verse eid="1KI 8:32"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 8:33"/>And when your Israeli people are defeated by their enemies <char style="add">in a battle</char> because they have sinned against you, <char style="add">and if they are forced to go to some distant country,</char> if they turn away from their sinful behavior and turn toward this temple and admit that you <char style="add">have justly punished them</char>, and if they plead <char style="add">that you will forgive them</char>, <verse eid="1KI 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 8:34"/>listen to them from heaven, and forgive your Israeli people for the sins that they <char style="add">have committed</char>, and bring them back to this land that you gave to our ancestors.<verse eid="1KI 8:34"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 8:35"/>And when you do not allow any rain to fall on the land because your people have sinned against you, if they turn toward this temple and admit that you <char style="add">have justly punished them</char>, if they turn away from their sinful behavior and <char style="add">humbly</char> pray to you, <verse eid="1KI 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 8:36"/>listen to them from heaven, and forgive your Israeli people for the sins <char style="add">that they have committed</char>. Teach them the right way to conduct their lives. Then send rain on this land that you have given to your people to belong to them <char style="add">permanently</char>.<verse eid="1KI 8:36"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 8:37"/>And when the people of this land experience famines, or if there is a plague/illness that causes many people to become sick, or if <char style="add">their crops are destroyed by</char> very hot winds or <char style="add">by </char> mildew or <char style="add">by </char> locusts or grasshoppers, or when their enemies surround any of their cities <char style="add">in order to attack them</char>, if any of those bad things happen to them, <verse eid="1KI 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 8:38"/>when your Israeli people earnestly plead with you knowing that they are suffering because they <char style="add">have sinned</char>, and if they stretch out their arms toward this temple and pray, <verse eid="1KI 8:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 8:39"/>listen to them from your home in heaven, and forgive them, and help them. You are the only one who knows what people are thinking, so act toward everyone as they deserve, <verse eid="1KI 8:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 8:40"/>in order that your people may then have an awesome respect for you, all the years that they live in this land that you gave to our ancestors.<verse eid="1KI 8:40"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="41-42" style="v" sid="1KI 8:41-42"/>There will be some foreigners who do not belong to your Israeli people who have come here from countries far away because they have heard that you are very great and that you perform great miracles. If they come here to this temple to worship you and pray, <verse eid="1KI 8:41-42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 8:43"/>in your home in heaven, listen to their prayers, and do for them what they request you to do. Do that so that all the people-groups in the world will know about you and revere you, like we your Israeli people do. And then they will know that this temple that I have <char style="add">caused to be</char> built to honor you, is where you <char style="add">should be worshiped</char>.<verse eid="1KI 8:43"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="1KI 8:44"/>And if you send your people to go to fight against their enemies, if they pray to you, wherever they are, if they turn toward this city that you have chosen and toward this temple that I have caused to be built for you, <verse eid="1KI 8:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1KI 8:45"/>listen in heaven to their prayers; listen to what they plead for you to do, and assist them.<verse eid="1KI 8:45"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="1KI 8:46"/>
    <char style="add">It is true that</char> everyone sins. So, if your people sin against you, and you become angry with them, you may allow their enemies to defeat them and capture them and take them away to their enemies’ country, even to countries that are far away. <verse eid="1KI 8:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1KI 8:47"/>If that happens, while they are in those countries to which they were forced to go, if they sincerely repent and plead with you there saying ‘We have sinned and have done things that are very wicked,’ <verse eid="1KI 8:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1KI 8:48"/>if they very sincerely repent, and turn toward this land that you gave to our ancestors, and toward this city that you have chosen <char style="add">to be the place where we should worship you</char>, and toward this temple that I have <char style="add">caused to be</char> built for you, and if they pray, <verse eid="1KI 8:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1KI 8:49"/>then from your home in heaven listen to them while they plead <char style="add">for your help</char>, and assist them. <verse eid="1KI 8:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="1KI 8:50"/>Forgive them for all the sins that they <char style="add">have committed</char> against you, and cause their enemies to be kind to them. <verse eid="1KI 8:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1KI 8:51"/>Do not forget that the Israelis are your people; they are your special possession; you brought <char style="add">our ancestors</char> out of Egypt where <char style="add">they were greatly suffering as though</char> they were in a blazing furnace.<verse eid="1KI 8:51"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="1KI 8:52"/>I request that you always listen to your Israeli people and to me, their king, and heed their prayers whenever they call out to you <char style="add">to help them</char>. <verse eid="1KI 8:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1KI 8:53"/>You chose them from all the other people-groups in the world to belong to you, which is what you told Moses to tell them when you brought our ancestors out of Egypt.”<verse eid="1KI 8:53"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="1KI 8:54"/>After Solomon had finished praying and pleading to Yahweh <char style="add">for his help</char>, he stood up in front of the altar where he had been kneeling. He lifted up his arms. <verse eid="1KI 8:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="1KI 8:55"/>Then he <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless all the Israeli people. <char style="add">He prayed</char> loudly, saying,<verse eid="1KI 8:55"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="56" style="v" sid="1KI 8:56"/>“Praise Yahweh, who has given us his people peace, like he promised that he would do. He has done every one of the good things that he promised to Moses, the man who served him <char style="add">very well</char>. <verse eid="1KI 8:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="1KI 8:57"/>I pray that our God will be with us like he was with our ancestors, and that he will never abandon us. <verse eid="1KI 8:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="1KI 8:58"/>I pray that he will cause us to loyally serve him, to conduct our lives as he wants us to, and to obey all his commandments and statutes and laws that he gave to our ancestors. <verse eid="1KI 8:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="1KI 8:59"/>I pray that Yahweh our God will never forget these words that I have prayed, pleading for his help; I pray that he will think about them by day and by night. I pray that he will always help <char style="add">us</char> Israeli people and me, giving us the things that we need day by day. <verse eid="1KI 8:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="1KI 8:60"/>If he does that, all the people-groups in the world will know that he is the only one who is God, and that there is no other one who is God. <verse eid="1KI 8:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="1KI 8:61"/>I pray that you, <char style="add">his people,</char> will always be fully committed to Yahweh, and that you will obey all his statutes and commands, like you are doing now.”<verse eid="1KI 8:61"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon dedicated the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="62" style="v" sid="1KI 8:62"/>Then the king and all the Israeli people who were there offered sacrifices to Yahweh. <verse eid="1KI 8:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="1KI 8:63"/>They sacrificed 22,000 cattle and 120,000 sheep to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. Then the king and all the people dedicated the temple.<verse eid="1KI 8:63"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="64" style="v" sid="1KI 8:64"/>On that day, the king also dedicated/set apart the middle part of the courtyard that was in front of the temple. Then he offered sacrifices that would be completely burned <char style="add">in the courtyard</char>, the offerings of grain and the fat of the animals that were sacrificed to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. They sacrificed them there because the bronze altar was not big enough for all those sacrifices to be burned on it <char style="add">that day</char>.<verse eid="1KI 8:64"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="65" style="v" sid="1KI 8:65"/>Then Solomon and all the Israeli people celebrated the Festival of <char style="add">Living in Temporary</char> Shelters for seven days. There was a huge crowd of people there, some of whom had come from <char style="add">distant places like</char> Hamath <char style="add">in the far north</char> and the border of Egypt <char style="add">in the far south</char>. <verse eid="1KI 8:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="1KI 8:66"/>On the eighth day, Solomon sent the people to their homes. They all praised him and went home happy because of all the things that Yahweh had done to bless <char style="add">King</char> David and his Israeli people.<verse eid="1KI 8:66"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="1KI 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh’s reply to Solomon’s prayer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 9:1"/>After Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> had finished building the temple and his palace and everything else that Solomon wanted them to build, <verse eid="1KI 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 9:2"/>Yahweh appeared to him <char style="add">in a dream</char> a second time, like he had appeared to him at <char style="add">the city of</char> Gibeon. <verse eid="1KI 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 9:3"/>Yahweh said to him,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="1KI 9:3">“I heard what you prayed and what you pleaded for me to do. I have set apart/dedicated this temple which your <char style="add">workers</char> have built to be the place where people will worship me forever. I will always watch over it and protect it.<verse eid="1KI 9:3"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 9:4"/>“And as for you, if you conduct your life as I want you to, like your father David did, and if you very sincerely obey all the statutes and laws that I have commanded you to obey, <verse eid="1KI 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 9:5"/>I will do what I promised your father that I would do: I promised him that Israel would always be ruled by his descendants.<verse eid="1KI 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 9:6"/>“But if you or your descendants turn away from me and disobey the commands and decrees that I have given to you, and if you start to worship other gods, <verse eid="1KI 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 9:7"/>I will remove my Israeli people from the land that I have given to them. I will also abandon this temple that I have set apart/dedicated to be the place where people should worship me. Then people everywhere will despise <char style="add">the people of</char> Israel and make fun of them. <verse eid="1KI 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 9:8"/>This temple will become a heap of ruins. Everyone who passes by will be astonished <char style="add">when they see it</char>, and they will be shocked and say, ‘Why has Yahweh done this to this land and to this temple?’ <verse eid="1KI 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 9:9"/>And other people will reply, ‘It happened because the Israeli people abandoned Yahweh their God, the one who brought their ancestors out of Egypt. They started to accept and worship other gods. And that is why Yahweh has caused them to experience all these disasters.’ ”<verse eid="1KI 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Other things that Solomon did</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 9:10"/>Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> labored for 20 years to build the temple and the palace. <verse eid="1KI 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 9:11"/>Hiram, the king of Tyre had <char style="add">arranged for his workers to</char> give Solomon all the cedar and pine <char style="add">logs</char> and all the gold that he needed <char style="add">for this work</char>. After it was all finished, King Solomon gave to Hiram 20 cities in the Galilee region. <verse eid="1KI 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 9:12"/>But when Hiram went from Tyre <char style="add">to Galilee</char> to see the cities that Solomon had given to him, he was not pleased with them. <verse eid="1KI 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 9:13"/>He said to Solomon, “My friend, those cities that you gave me are worthless!” So, that area is still called ‘Worthless’. <verse eid="1KI 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 9:14"/>Hiram paid Solomon only five tons of gold <char style="add">for those cities</char>.<verse eid="1KI 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 9:15"/>This is a record of the work that King Solomon forced men to do. He forced them to build the temple and his palace and the terraces/landfills <char style="add">on the east side of the city</char>, and the wall around Jerusalem, and <char style="add">to rebuild the cities of</char> Hazor and Megiddo and Gezer. <verse eid="1KI 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 9:16"/><char style="add">The reason they needed to rebuild Gezer was that the army of</char> the king of Egypt had attacked Gezer and captured it. Then they had burned <char style="add">the houses in</char> the city and killed all the people of the Canaan people-group who lived there. The king of Egypt gave that city to his daughter as a gift when she married Solomon. <verse eid="1KI 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 9:17"/>So Solomon’s workers also rebuilt Gezer, and they also rebuilt Lower Beth-Horon <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="1KI 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 9:18"/>They also rebuilt Baalath and Tamar <char style="add">towns</char> in the desert in <char style="add">the southern part of</char> Judah. <verse eid="1KI 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 9:19"/>They also built cities where they kept the supplies for Solomon, the places where his horses and chariots were kept. They also built everything else that Solomon wanted them to build, in Jerusalem and in Lebanon, and in other places in the area over which he ruled.<verse eid="1KI 9:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 9:20"/>There were many people who belonged to the Amor people-group, the Heth people-group, the Periz people-group, the Hiv people-group, and the Jebus people-group who were not killed when the Israelis captured their land. <verse eid="1KI 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 9:21"/><char style="add">Their descendants still lived in Israel</char>. It was those people whom Solomon forced to become his slaves <char style="add">to build all those places</char>, and they are still slaves. <verse eid="1KI 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 9:22"/>But Solomon did not force any Israeli people to become slaves. Some Israelis became soldiers and army officers and commanders and drivers of his chariots and soldiers who rode on horses. <verse eid="1KI 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 9:23"/>There were 550 officials who supervised the slaves who worked <char style="add">to build all those places</char>.<verse eid="1KI 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 9:24"/>After <char style="add">Solomon’s wife, who was</char> the daughter of the king of Egypt, moved from <char style="add">the place outside Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’ to the palace that Solomon’s workers built for her, Solomon <char style="add">told his workers to</char> fill in the slopes on the east side of the city.<verse eid="1KI 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 9:25"/>Three times each year Solomon <char style="add">brought to the temple</char> offerings that were completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> and offerings to restore fellowship with Yahweh. He also brought incense to be burned in the presence of Yahweh.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 9:25">And so his men finished building the temple.<verse eid="1KI 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 9:26"/>King Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> also built a fleet of ships at Ezion-Geber <char style="add">city</char>, which is near Elath <char style="add">city</char>, on the shore of the Gulf of Aqaba, in the land belonging to the Edom people-group. <verse eid="1KI 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 9:27"/><char style="add">King</char> Hiram sent some very expert sailors to work on the ships with Solomon’s workers. <verse eid="1KI 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 9:28"/>They sailed to <char style="add">the</char> Ophir <char style="add">region</char> and brought back to Solomon about 16 tons of gold.<verse eid="1KI 9:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="1KI 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The queen of Sheba visited Solomon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 10:1"/>The queen <char style="add">who ruled the</char> Sheba <char style="add">area</char> heard that Yahweh had caused Solomon to become famous, so she traveled to Jerusalem to ask him questions that were difficult <char style="add">to answer</char>. <verse eid="1KI 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 10:2"/>She came with a large group of wealthy/influential people, and she brought camels that were loaded with spices, and valuable gems, and a lot of gold. When she met Solomon, she asked him questions about all the topics/things in which she was interested. <verse eid="1KI 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 10:3"/>Solomon answered all her questions. He explained everything that she asked about, even things that were very difficult. <verse eid="1KI 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 10:4"/>The queen realized that Solomon was very wise. She saw his palace; <verse eid="1KI 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 10:5"/>she saw the food that was served on his table <char style="add">every day</char>; she saw where his officials lived (OR, how his officials were seated at the table), their uniforms, the servants who served the food and wine, and the sacrifices that he took to the temple to be offered. She was extremely amazed.<verse eid="1KI 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 10:6"/>She said to King Solomon, “Everything that I heard in my own country about you and about how wise you are is true! <verse eid="1KI 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 10:7"/>But I did not believe it was true until I came here and saw it myself. But really, what they told me is only half <char style="add">of what they could have told me about you</char>. You are extremely wise and rich, more than what people told me. <verse eid="1KI 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 10:8"/>Your wives are very fortunate! Your officials who are constantly standing in front of you and listening to the wise things that you say are also fortunate! <verse eid="1KI 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 10:9"/>Praise Yahweh, your God, who has shown that he is pleased with you by causing you to become the king of Israel! God has always loved the Israeli people, and therefore he has appointed you to be their king, in order that you will rule them fairly and righteously.”<verse eid="1KI 10:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 10:10"/>Then the queen gave to the king <char style="add">the things that she had brought. She gave him</char> almost five tons of gold and a large amount of spices and valuable gems. Never again did King Solomon receive more spices than the queen gave him at that time.<verse eid="1KI 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 10:11"/>In the ships that belonged to King Hiram, in which they had previously brought gold from Ophir, they also brought a large amount of juniper wood and gems/valuable stones. <verse eid="1KI 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 10:12"/>King Solomon told his workers to use that wood to make railings/supports in the temple of Yahweh and in the king’s palace and also to make harps and lyres for the ◄musicians/men who played musical instruments►. That wood was the largest amount of (OR, the finest) wood that had ever been seen <char style="add">in Israel</char>. And no one since then has ever seen so much wood of that kind.<verse eid="1KI 10:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 10:13"/>King Solomon gave to the queen from Sheba everything that she wanted. He gave her those gifts in addition to the gifts that he always gave <char style="add">to other rulers who visited him</char>. Then she and the people who came with her returned to her own land.<verse eid="1KI 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s wealth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 10:14"/>Each year there was brought to Solomon a total of 25 tons of gold. <verse eid="1KI 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 10:15"/>That was in addition to <char style="add">the taxes</char> paid to him by the merchants and traders, and the annual taxes paid by the kings of Arabia and by the governors of <char style="add">the regions in</char> Israel.<verse eid="1KI 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 10:16"/>King Solomon’s workers <char style="add">took this</char> gold and hammered it into thin sheets and covered 200 large shields with those thin sheets of gold; they put ◄almost 15 pounds/more than 6 kg.► of gold on each shield. <verse eid="1KI 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 10:17"/>His workers made 300 smaller shields. They covered each of them with ◄almost 4 pounds/1.5 kg.► of gold. Then the king put those shields in the Hall of the Forest of Lebanon.<verse eid="1KI 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 10:18"/>His workers also made for him a large throne. <char style="add">Part of it was</char> covered with ◄ivory <char style="add">decorations made from►</char> tusks of elephants and <char style="add">part of it was covered</char> with very fine gold. <verse eid="1KI 10:18"/><verse number="19-20" style="v" sid="1KI 10:19-20"/>There were six steps in front of the throne. There was a statue of a lion on both sides of each step. So altogether there were twelve statues of lions. The back of the throne was rounded at the top. At each side of the throne there was an armrest, and alongside each armrest there was a small statue of a lion. No throne like that had ever existed in any other kingdom. <verse eid="1KI 10:19-20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 10:21"/>All of Solomon’s cups were made of gold, and all the various dishes in the Hall of the Forest of Lebanon were made of gold. They did not make things from silver, because during the years that Solomon <char style="add">ruled</char>, silver was not considered to be valuable. <verse eid="1KI 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 10:22"/>The king had a ◄fleet/large number► of ships that sailed with the ships that King Hiram owned. Every three years the ships returned <char style="add">from the places to which they had sailed</char>, bringing gold, silver, ivory, monkeys, and baboons (OR, peacocks).<verse eid="1KI 10:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 10:23"/>King Solomon became richer and wiser than any other king. <verse eid="1KI 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 10:24"/>People from all over the world wanted to come and listen to the wise things that Solomon said, things that God had put into his mind. <verse eid="1KI 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 10:25"/>All the people who came to him brought presents: They brought things made from silver or gold, or robes, or weapons (OR, myrrh), or spices, or horses, or mules. The people continued to do this every year.<verse eid="1KI 10:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 10:26"/>Solomon acquired 1,400 chariots and 12,000 men who rode <char style="add">on the horses</char> (OR, <char style="add">in the chariots</char>). Solomon put some of them in Jerusalem and some of them in other cities where he kept his chariots. <verse eid="1KI 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 10:27"/>During the years that Solomon was king, silver became as common in Jerusalem as stones; and <char style="add">lumber from</char> cedar trees in the foothills of Judah was as plentiful as <char style="add">lumber from</char> fig trees. <verse eid="1KI 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 10:28"/>Solomon’s agents bought horses and supervised the men who brought them into Israel from the areas of Musri and Cilicia <char style="add">that were famous for breeding horses</char>. <verse eid="1KI 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 10:29"/>In Musri they bought chariots and horses; they paid 600 pieces of silver for each chariot and 150 pieces of silver for each horse. They brought them to Israel. Then they sold many of them to the kings of the Heth people-group and the kings of Syria.<verse eid="1KI 10:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="1KI 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s many wives</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 11:1"/>King Solomon married many foreign women. First he married the daughter of the king of Egypt. He also married women from the Heth people-group and from the Moab, Ammon, and Edom people-groups, and from Sidon <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 11:2"/>He married them even though Yahweh had commanded the Israeli people, “Do not marry people from those areas, because if you do that, they will surely persuade you [IDM] to worship the gods that they worship!” <verse eid="1KI 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 11:3"/>Solomon married 700 women who were kings’ daughters. He also had 300 wives who were his slaves/servants. And his wives caused him to turn away <char style="add">from worshiping God</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 11:4"/>By the time that Solomon became old, they had persuaded him to worship the gods from their countries. He was not completely dedicated/committed to Yahweh his God like his father [SYN] David had been. <verse eid="1KI 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 11:5"/>Solomon worshiped Astarte, the goddess that the people of Sidon <char style="add">worshiped</char>, and he worshiped Molech, the disgusting god that the Ammon people-group <char style="add">worshiped</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 11:6"/>That’s how Solomon did things that Yahweh said were evil. He did not conduct his life like his father David had done; he did not conduct his life as Yahweh wanted him to.<verse eid="1KI 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 11:7"/>On the hill to the east of Jerusalem he built a place to worship Chemosh, the disgusting god that the Moab people-group <char style="add">worshiped</char>, and a place to worship Molech, the disgusting god that the Ammon people-group <char style="add">worshiped</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 11:8"/>He also built places where all his foreign wives could burn incense and offer sacrifices to the gods from their own countries.<verse eid="1KI 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9-10" style="v" sid="1KI 11:9-10"/>Even though Yahweh, the God whom the Israelis <char style="add">worshiped</char>, had appeared to Solomon two times, and had commanded him to not worship foreign gods, Solomon refused to obey Yahweh. So Yahweh was angry with Solomon, <verse eid="1KI 11:9-10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 11:11"/>and said to him, “You have chosen to break the agreement that I made with you and to disobey what I commanded you. So I am surely not going to allow you to rule all of your kingdom. I am going to allow one of your officials to rule it. <verse eid="1KI 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 11:12"/>But, because of <char style="add">what I promised</char> your father David, I will allow you to rule all your kingdom while you are still <char style="add">living</char>. <char style="add">After you die</char>, I will not allow your son to rule the whole kingdom [MTY]. <verse eid="1KI 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 11:13"/>But I will not take all the kingdom away from him. Instead, I will allow him to rule one tribe <char style="add">besides the tribe of Judah</char>, because of what I promised to David, who served me <char style="add">well</char>, and because <char style="add">I want David’s descendants to rule in</char> Jerusalem, <char style="add">where my temple is located</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s enemies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 11:14"/>Yahweh caused Hadad, from the family of the kings in the Edom people-group, to rebel against Solomon. <verse eid="1KI 11:14"/><verse number="15-16" style="v" sid="1KI 11:15-16"/>What happened was that previously, when David’s <char style="add">army</char> had conquered the Edom people-group, his army commander Joab had gone there to <char style="add">help</char> bury the <char style="add">Israeli soldiers</char> who had been killed <char style="add">in the battle</char>. Joab and his army remained in the Edom area for six months, and during that time they killed all the males of that area. <verse eid="1KI 11:15-16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 11:17"/>Hadad was a young child <char style="add">at that time</char>, and he had escaped to Egypt, along with some of his father’s servants from the Edom area. <verse eid="1KI 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 11:18"/>They <char style="add">went to the</char> Midian <char style="add">region</char>, and then they went to <char style="add">the desert area at</char> Paran. Some other men joined them there. Then they all traveled to Egypt and went to see the king of Egypt. The king gave Hadad some land and ordered his servants to give him some food regularly. <verse eid="1KI 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 11:19"/>The king liked Hadad. As a result he gave him the sister of his own wife, Queen Tahpenes, to be Hadad’s wife.<verse eid="1KI 11:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 11:20"/>Later Hadad’s wife gave birth to a son named Genubath. The sister of Tahpenes ◄raised him/brought him up► in the palace, where he lived with the king’s sons.<verse eid="1KI 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 11:21"/>While Hadad was in Egypt, he heard that David had died [EUP], and that Joab, the commander of David’s army, was also dead. So he said to the king of Egypt, “Please allow me to return to my own country.”<verse eid="1KI 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 11:22"/>But the king said to him, “Why do you want to go back to your country? Is there something that you lack that you want me to give to you?” Hadad replied, “No, but please just allow me to go.” <char style="add">So the king allowed him to leave, and he returned to his own country and became the king of Edom</char>.<verse eid="1KI 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 11:23"/>God also caused another man named Rezon, the son of Eliada, to rebel against Solomon. Rezon had run away from his master, King Hadadezer of <char style="add">the</char> Zobah <char style="add">area north of Damascus</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 11:24"/>Rezon then became the leader of a group of outlaws. That happened after David’s <char style="add">army had defeated Hadadezer and</char> had <char style="add">also</char> killed all <char style="add">his soldiers</char>. Rezon and his men went to Damascus and started to live there, and <char style="add">the people there</char> appointed him to be their king. <verse eid="1KI 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 11:25"/>All during the time that Solomon was alive, while Rezon was ruling <char style="add">not only Damascus but all of</char> Syria, he was an enemy of Israel and caused trouble for Israel like Hadad did.<verse eid="1KI 11:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">What Yahweh promised to Jeroboam</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 11:26"/>Another man who rebelled against [IDM] Solomon was one of his officials named Jeroboam, the son of Nebat. He was from Zeredah <char style="add">town</char> in <char style="add">the region where the tribe of</char> Ephraim <char style="add">lives</char>. His mother was a widow named Zeruah.<verse eid="1KI 11:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 11:27"/>This is what happened. Solomon’s workers were filling in the land/ground on the east side of Jerusalem and repairing the walls <char style="add">around the city</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 11:28"/>Jeroboam was a very capable young man. So, when Solomon saw that he worked very hard, he appointed him to supervise all the men who were forced to work in the areas where the tribes of Manasseh and Ephraim live.<verse eid="1KI 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 11:29"/>One day when Jeroboam was walking alone along the road outside of Jerusalem, the prophet Ahijah from Shiloh <char style="add">city</char> met him. Ahijah was wearing a new robe, <verse eid="1KI 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 11:30"/>which he took off and tore into twelve pieces. <verse eid="1KI 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 11:31"/>He said to Jeroboam, “Take ten of these pieces for yourself, because Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, says to you, ‘I am going to tear the kingdom from Solomon, and I am going to enable you to become the ruler of ten of the tribes <char style="add">of Israel</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 11:32"/>Solomon’s <char style="add">descendants</char> will still rule one tribe (OR, two tribes), because of <char style="add">what I promised </char> David, a man who served me <char style="add">very well</char>, and because of Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen from all the cities in Israel <char style="add">to be the city where my people will worship me</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 11:33"/>I am going to do this because Solomon has rejected me and has been worshiping Astarte, the goddess that the people of Sidon worship, Chemosh, the god that the Moab people-group worship, and Milcom, the god that the Ammon people-group worship. He has not conducted his life as I wanted him to. He has not obeyed my statutes and laws, like his father David did.<verse eid="1KI 11:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 11:34"/>‘But I will not take the entire kingdom away from him. I will enable him to rule <char style="add">Judah</char> all during the years that he is alive. I will do that because of <char style="add">what I promised to do for</char> David, whom I chose <char style="add">to be the king</char>, and who served me <char style="add">well</char>, and who always obeyed my commandments and laws. <verse eid="1KI 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 11:35"/>But I will take the <char style="add">other</char> ten tribes of his kingdom and give them to you <char style="add">to rule</char>. <verse eid="1KI 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 11:36"/>I will allow Solomon’s son to rule one tribe, in order that descendants [MET] of David will always rule in Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen to be the place where <char style="add">my people worship</char> me [MTY]. <verse eid="1KI 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 11:37"/>I will enable you to become the king of Israel, and you will rule over all the territory that you want to. <verse eid="1KI 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 11:38"/>If you obey all that I command you to do, and conduct your life as I want you to, and if you do what I say is right by obeying my laws and commandments like David did, I will help you. I will make sure that your descendants will rule after you <char style="add">die</char>, like I <char style="add">promised to</char> do for David. <verse eid="1KI 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 11:39"/>Because of <char style="add">Solomon’s sins</char>, I will punish David’s descendants, but I will not continue to punish them forever.’”<verse eid="1KI 11:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 11:40"/>Solomon <char style="add">found out what Ahijah told Jeroboam</char>, so he tried to kill Jeroboam. But Jeroboam escaped and went to Egypt. He went to Shishak, the king of Egypt, and stayed with him until after Solomon died.<verse eid="1KI 11:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1KI 11:41"/>
    <char style="add">A record of</char> all the other things that Solomon did, and all the wise things that he <char style="add">said and wrote</char>, was written in the Book Telling what Solomon Did. <verse eid="1KI 11:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1KI 11:42"/>He was the king in Jerusalem who ruled over all of Israel for 40 years. <verse eid="1KI 11:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 11:43"/>Then Solomon died [EUP], and was buried in the <char style="add">part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. And his son Rehoboam became the king.<verse eid="1KI 11:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="1KI 12"/>
  <para style="s1">The ten tribes rebelled against Rehoboam</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 12:1"/>All [HYP] the people of <char style="add">northern</char> Israel went to Shechem <char style="add">city</char> in order to appoint Rehoboam to be their king. So Rehoboam also went there. <verse eid="1KI 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 12:2"/>When Jeroboam, who was still in Egypt, heard about that, he returned from Egypt <char style="add">to Israel</char>. <verse eid="1KI 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 12:3"/>The <char style="add">leaders of the northern tribes</char> summoned him, and they went together <char style="add">to talk</char> to Rehoboam. They said to him, <verse eid="1KI 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 12:4"/>“Your father <char style="add">Solomon</char> forced us to work very hard [MET] for him. If you ◄lighten these loads/do not force us to work that hard►, and if you charge us less taxes than we were paying to him, we will serve you <char style="add">faithfully</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 12:5"/>He replied, “Go away, and come back three days from now <char style="add">and I will give you my answer</char>.” So those leaders and Jeroboam left.<verse eid="1KI 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 12:6"/>Then King Rehoboam consulted the older men who had advised his father Solomon while he was still living. He asked them, “What shall I say to answer those men?”<verse eid="1KI 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 12:7"/>They replied, “If you want to serve your people well, speak kindly to those men when you reply to them. If you do that, your people will always serve you faithfully.”<verse eid="1KI 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 12:8"/>But he ignored what the older men advised him to do. Instead, he consulted the younger men who had grown up with him, who were now ◄his advisors/the ones who told him what would be good to do►. <verse eid="1KI 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 12:9"/>He said to them, “What should I say to the men who are asking me to reduce the <char style="add">work and taxes</char> that my father required from them?”<verse eid="1KI 12:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 12:10"/>They replied, “This is what you should tell them: ‘My little finger is thicker than my father’s waist. <verse eid="1KI 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 12:11"/>What I mean is that my father required you <char style="add">to work hard and pay high taxes</char>. But I will make those loads heavier. <char style="add">It was as though</char> my father whipped you, but <char style="add">it will be as though</char> I will whip you with whips that have pieces of metal in them.’ ”<verse eid="1KI 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 12:12"/>So three days later, Jeroboam and all the leaders came to Rehoboam again, as he had told them to do. <verse eid="1KI 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 12:13"/>The king ignored the advice of the older men and spoke harshly to the Israeli leaders. <verse eid="1KI 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 12:14"/><char style="add">He told them what the younger men had advised.</char> He said, “My father put heavy burdens <char style="add">of work and taxes</char> on you, but I will put heavier burdens on you. <char style="add">It was as though</char> he beat you with whips, but I will beat you with whips that have pieces of metal in them!” <verse eid="1KI 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 12:15"/>So the king did not pay any attention to the Israeli leaders. But this happened in order that what Yahweh wanted would occur, what he had told the prophet Ahijah about Jeroboam <char style="add">becoming king of the ten tribes</char>.<verse eid="1KI 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 12:16"/>When the Israeli leaders realized that the king did not pay any attention to what they said, they shouted,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1KI 12:16">“We do not [RHQ] want anything to do with this descendant of King David!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1KI 12:16">We will not pay attention to what this grandson of Jesse says!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1KI 12:16">You people of Israel, let’s go home!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1KI 12:16">As for this descendant of David [MTY], he can rule his own kingdom [MTY]!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 12:16">So the Israeli leaders returned to their homes. <verse eid="1KI 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 12:17"/>And <char style="add">after that,</char> the <char style="add">only Israeli</char> people whom Rehoboam ruled over were those who lived in the territory of <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Judah.<verse eid="1KI 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 12:18"/>Then King Rehoboam sent Adoniram <char style="add">to talk to the Israeli people</char>. Adoniram was the man who supervised <char style="add">all the men who were</char> forced to work <char style="add">for Rehoboam</char>. But the Israeli people killed him by throwing stones at him. When that happened, King Rehoboam quickly got in his chariot and escaped to Jerusalem. <verse eid="1KI 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 12:19"/>Ever since that time, the people of <char style="add">the northern tribes of</char> Israel have been rebelling against the descendants [MTY] of <char style="add">King</char> David.<verse eid="1KI 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 12:20"/>When the Israeli people heard that Jeroboam had returned <char style="add">from Egypt</char>, they invited him to come to a meeting, and there they appointed him to be the king of Israel. Only the people of the tribes of Judah <char style="add">and Benjamin</char> continued to be loyal to <char style="add">the kings descended from King</char> [MTY] David.<verse eid="1KI 12:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 12:21"/>When Rehoboam arrived in Jerusalem, he gathered 180,000 of the best soldiers from the tribes [MTY] of Judah and Benjamin. He wanted them to fight against the northern tribes of [MTY] Israel <char style="add">and defeat them</char>, in order that he could <char style="add">rule all the tribes of</char> his kingdom again.<verse eid="1KI 12:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 12:22"/>But God spoke to the prophet Shemaiah and said this to him: <verse eid="1KI 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 12:23"/>“Go and tell this to <char style="add">Solomon’s son</char> Rehoboam, the king of Judah, and to all the people of the tribes of Judah and Benjamin and the people from the northern tribe who live in Judah: <verse eid="1KI 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 12:24"/>‘Yahweh says that you must not go to fight against your own relatives, the people of Israel. All of you must go home. What has happened is what Yahweh wanted to happen.’ ” <char style="add">So Shemaiah went and told that to them,</char> and they all paid attention to what Yahweh had commanded them to do, and they went home.<verse eid="1KI 12:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jeroboam’s sins</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 12:25"/>Then Jeroboam’s workers built <char style="add">walls around</char> Shechem <char style="add">city</char> in the hilly area <char style="add">where the descendants</char> of Ephraim <char style="add">lived</char>, and he ruled from there for a while. He and his workers then left there and went to Peniel <char style="add">town</char>, and they built walls around that town.<verse eid="1KI 12:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26-27" style="v" sid="1KI 12:26-27"/>Then Jeroboam said to himself, “If my people <char style="add">continue to</char> go to Jerusalem and offer sacrifices to Yahweh at the temple there, soon they will again become loyal to Rehoboam, the king of Judah [DOU], and they will kill me.”<verse eid="1KI 12:26-27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 12:28"/>So he consulted <char style="add">his advisors, and then he did what they suggested</char>. He <char style="add">told his workers to</char> make gold <char style="add">statues of</char> two calves. Then he said to the people, “You have been going to Jerusalem <char style="add">to worship</char> for a long time. It is a big trouble for you to continue going there. You people of Israel, look! These statues are the gods that brought our <char style="add">ancestors</char> up from Egypt! <char style="add">So you can worship these, here!</char>” <verse eid="1KI 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 12:29"/>He <char style="add">told his workers to</char> place one of the statues in Bethel <char style="add">city in the south</char> and one in Dan <char style="add">city in the north</char>. <verse eid="1KI 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 12:30"/>So <char style="add">what Jeroboam did caused</char> the people <char style="add">to</char> sin. Some of them went and worshiped the calf at Bethel, and others went and worshiped the other calf at Dan.<verse eid="1KI 12:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 12:31"/>
    <char style="add">Moses had declared that only men from the tribe of Levi would be priests, but</char> Jeroboam also told his workers to build shrines on hilltops, and then he appointed men who were not from the tribe of Levi to be priests. <verse eid="1KI 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 12:32"/>He also appointed Adonijah and two priests, Elishama and Jehoram. They had a celebration at the end of October, like the celebration <char style="add">of Living in Temporary Shelters</char> that occurred in Judah <char style="add">each year</char>. On the altar <char style="add">that they built</char> in Bethel, he offered sacrifices to the gold statues of calves that they had made, and he stationed the priests there at the shrines that his workers had built. <verse eid="1KI 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 12:33"/>Jeroboam went up to that altar on that day in October which he himself had chosen. There on that altar he burned incense <char style="add">to be a sacrifice</char>. And he declared that the people should celebrate that festival <char style="add">on that same day every year</char>.<verse eid="1KI 12:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="1KI 13"/>
  <para style="s1">A prophet condemned the altar at Bethel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 13:1"/>One day a prophet, obeying what Yahweh commanded him to do, went from Judah <char style="add">north</char> to Bethel. He arrived there right at the time that Jeroboam was standing at the altar, ready to burn incense. <verse eid="1KI 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 13:2"/>Saying what Yahweh told him to say, the prophet shouted, “This is what Yahweh says <char style="add">about this</char> altar [APO]: ‘I want you to know that <char style="add">some day</char> a descendant [MTY] of King David will be born. His name will be Josiah, and he will come here. He will slaughter at this altar the priests who are burning incense for sacrifices on the hills <char style="add">in this area</char>, and he will burn the bones of dead people on this altar.’” [APO] <verse eid="1KI 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 13:3"/>Then the prophet also said, “This is what will prove to you that Yahweh has said this: This altar will be split apart, and the ashes that are on it will be scattered.’”<verse eid="1KI 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 13:4"/>When King Jeroboam heard the prophet say that, he pointed his finger at him and said to his servants, “Seize that man!” But immediately the king’s arm became paralyzed/stiff, with the result that he could not move it. <verse eid="1KI 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 13:5"/>And the altar immediately split apart, and the ashes spilled out <char style="add">on the ground</char>, which is what the prophet said that Yahweh [MTY] had predicted would happen.<verse eid="1KI 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 13:6"/>Then the king said to the prophet, “Please pray that Yahweh will be merciful to me and heal my arm!” So the prophet prayed, and Yahweh completely healed the king’s arm.<verse eid="1KI 13:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 13:7"/>Then the king said to the prophet, “Come home with me and eat some food. And I will also give you a reward <char style="add">for what you have done</char>!”<verse eid="1KI 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 13:8"/>But the prophet replied, “Even if you would <char style="add">promise to</char> give me half of everything that you own [MTY], I will not go with you, and I will not eat or drink anything with you here, <verse eid="1KI 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 13:9"/>because Yahweh commanded me not to eat or drink anything here. He also commanded me not to return home on the road on which I came here.” <verse eid="1KI 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 13:10"/>So he started to return home, but he did not go on the road on which he came to Bethel. He went on a different road.<verse eid="1KI 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The old prophet from Bethel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 13:11"/>At that time there was an old man living in Bethel who was a prophet. His sons came and told him what the prophet <char style="add">from Judah</char> had done there on that day, and they also told him what the prophet had said to the king. <verse eid="1KI 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 13:12"/>Their father said, “On which road did he go?” So his sons showed him the road on which the prophet from Judah had gone <char style="add">when he left Bethel</char>. <verse eid="1KI 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 13:13"/>Then he said to his sons, “Put a saddle on my donkey.” So they did that, and he got on the donkey. <verse eid="1KI 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 13:14"/>He went along the road to ◄find/catch up with► the prophet from Judah. He found him sitting under an oak tree. He said to him, “Are you the prophet who came from Judah?” He replied, “Yes, I am.”<verse eid="1KI 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 13:15"/>The old prophet said to him, “Come home with me and eat some food.”<verse eid="1KI 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 13:16"/>He replied, “No, I am not allowed to go with you into your house, or to eat or drink anything with you, <verse eid="1KI 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 13:17"/>because Yahweh told me, ‘Do not eat or drink anything here, and do not return home on the road on which you came.’ ”<verse eid="1KI 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 13:18"/>Then the old prophet said to him, “I also am a prophet, like you are. Yahweh sent an angel to tell me that I should take you home with me and give you some food and drink.” But the old man was lying <char style="add">when he said that</char>. <verse eid="1KI 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 13:19"/>But because of what the old prophet said, the prophet from Judah returned with him to his home and ate some food and drank some water with him.<verse eid="1KI 13:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 13:20"/>While they were sitting at the table, Yahweh spoke to the old man. <verse eid="1KI 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 13:21"/>Then he cried out to the prophet from Judah, “This is what Yahweh says: ‘You have disobeyed him, and you have not done what he commanded you to do. <verse eid="1KI 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 13:22"/>Instead, you have come back here and had things to eat and drink in a place where he commanded you not to do that. As a result, you will be killed, and your body will not be buried in the grave where your ancestors are buried.’ ”<verse eid="1KI 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 13:23"/>When they had finished eating, the old man put a saddle on the donkey for the prophet from Judah, <char style="add">and the prophet from Judah left</char>. <verse eid="1KI 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 13:24"/>But as he was going, a lion met him and killed him. The prophet’s corpse was lying on the road, and the donkey was standing beside it, and the lion was also standing beside the corpse. <verse eid="1KI 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 13:25"/>Some men passed by and were surprised to see the corpse on the road and the lion standing next to the corpse. So they went into Bethel and reported what they had seen.<verse eid="1KI 13:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 13:26"/>When the old man who had brought the prophet from Judah to his home heard about it, he said, “That is the prophet who disobeyed what Yahweh told him to do! That is why Yahweh allowed the lion to attack him and kill him. That is what Yahweh said would happen!”<verse eid="1KI 13:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 13:27"/>Then he said to his sons, “Put a saddle on my donkey.” So they did that. <verse eid="1KI 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 13:28"/>Then he rode on the donkey and found the prophet’s corpse on the road, and his donkey and the lion were still standing there alongside the corpse. But the lion had not eaten any of the flesh of the prophet and had not attacked the donkey. <verse eid="1KI 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 13:29"/>The old man picked up the corpse of the prophet and put it on his donkey and brought it back to Bethel, in order to mourn for him and to bury his corpse. <verse eid="1KI 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 13:30"/>He buried the prophet’s corpse in the grave where other people in his family <char style="add">had been buried</char>. Then he and his sons mourned for him, saying, “<char style="add">We are very sorry</char>, my brother!”<verse eid="1KI 13:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 13:31"/>After they had buried him, the old man said to his sons, “When I die, bury my corpse in the grave where we buried the prophet from Judah. Lay my corpse next to his corpse. <verse eid="1KI 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 13:32"/><char style="add">And do not forget what he said, because </char> the things that Yahweh told him to say about the altar in Bethel, and about the shrines on the hills in the towns in Samaria, will surely happen.”<verse eid="1KI 13:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 13:33"/>But King Jeroboam still did not turn away from continuing to do evil things. Instead, he appointed more priests <char style="add">who were not descended from Levi</char>. Anyone who wanted to be a priest, he appointed to be a priest, in order that he could offer sacrifices on the hills. <verse eid="1KI 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 13:34"/>Because he committed that sin, <char style="add">a few years later</char> God got rid of most of Jeroboam’s descendants and did not allow them to become kings of Israel.<verse eid="1KI 13:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="1KI 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Jeroboam’s son died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 14:1"/>At that time, Jeroboam’s son Abijah became very sick. <verse eid="1KI 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 14:2"/>Jeroboam said to his wife, “Disguise yourself, in order that no one will recognize that you are my wife. Then go to Shiloh <char style="add">city</char>, where the prophet Ahijah <char style="add">lives</char>. He is the one who predicted/prophesied that I would become the king of Israel. <verse eid="1KI 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 14:3"/>Take with you ten <char style="add">loaves of</char> bread and some small flat cakes, and a jar of honey, <char style="add">and give them</char> to him. <char style="add">Tell him about</char> our son, <char style="add">and</char> he will tell you what will happen to him.” <verse eid="1KI 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 14:4"/>So his wife went to Shiloh, to Ahijah’s house. Ahijah was unable to see, because he was very old and had become blind.<verse eid="1KI 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 14:5"/>But <char style="add">before she got there,</char> Yahweh told Ahijah that Jeroboam’s wife was coming to inquire about their son, who was very sick. And Yahweh told Ahijah what he should tell her.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 14:5">When she came to him, she pretended to be another woman. <verse eid="1KI 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 14:6"/>But when Ahijah heard her footsteps as she entered the doorway, he said to her, “Come in, wife of Jeroboam! ◄Why do you pretend that you are someone else?/It will not help you to pretend that you are someone else.► [RHQ] <char style="add">Yahweh</char> has given me bad news to tell you. <verse eid="1KI 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 14:7"/>Go and tell Jeroboam that this is what Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, says to you: ‘I chose you from among the common people and enabled you to become the king of my Israeli people. <verse eid="1KI 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 14:8"/>I took <char style="add">most of</char> the kingdom of Israel away from David’s descendants and gave it to you. But you have not been like David, who served me <char style="add">very well</char>. He obeyed all my commandments very sincerely, doing only things that I considered to be right. <verse eid="1KI 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 14:9"/>But you have done more evil things/deeds than all those <char style="add">who ruled</char> before you. You have rejected me, and you have caused me to become very angry by making metal images of other gods so that you <char style="add">and others</char> could worship them.<verse eid="1KI 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 14:10"/>‘So, I am going to cause terrible things to happen to your family. I will cause all your male descendants to die, young ones and old ones. I will completely get rid of your family [MTY]. I will get rid of your family [MTY] just like a man completely burns dung <char style="add">to cook his food</char>. <verse eid="1KI 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 14:11"/><char style="add">The corpses of</char> any members of your family who die in cities will be eaten by dogs. And <char style="add">the corpses of</char> any members of your family who die in the open fields will be eaten by vultures. <char style="add">This will surely happen because</char> I, Yahweh, have said <char style="add">that it will happen</char>.’<verse eid="1KI 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 14:12"/>So go back home. And as soon as you enter the city, your son will die. <verse eid="1KI 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 14:13"/>All the Israeli people will mourn for him and bury him. He is the only one of Jeroboam’s family who will be buried <char style="add">properly</char>, because he is the only one of Jeroboam’s family with whom Yahweh is pleased.<verse eid="1KI 14:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 14:14"/>Furthermore, Yahweh will appoint for himself a king to rule over Israel who will get rid of Jeroboam’s descendants. And that <char style="add">will start to happen</char> today! <verse eid="1KI 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 14:15"/>Yahweh will punish the people of Israel; he will shake them like <char style="add">the wind</char> shakes the reeds <char style="add">that grow in</char> a stream. He will expel the Israeli people from this good land that he gave to our ancestors. He will scatter them into countries east of <char style="add">the Euphrates</char> River, because they have caused him to become very angry by <char style="add">worshiping statues of</char> the goddess Asherah. <verse eid="1KI 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 14:16"/>Yahweh will abandon the Israeli people because of the sins that Jeroboam committed, sins which led the Israeli people to commit them.”<verse eid="1KI 14:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 14:17"/>Jeroboam’s wife returned home to Tirzah <char style="add">city, the new capital of Israel</char>. And just as she entered her house, her son died. <verse eid="1KI 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 14:18"/>All the Israeli people mourned for him and buried him, which is what Yahweh had told his servant, the prophet Ahijah, would happen.<verse eid="1KI 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 14:19"/>Everything else that Jeroboam did, and the record of wars that his <char style="add">army</char> fought, and how he ruled, is written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’. <verse eid="1KI 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 14:20"/>Jeroboam ruled for 22 years; then he died [EUP] and his son Nadab became king.<verse eid="1KI 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Rehoboam died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 14:21"/>Solomon’s son Rehoboam ruled Judah. He was 41 years old when he started to rule, and he ruled for 17 years. He ruled in Jerusalem, which is the city that Yahweh chose out of all the tribes of Israel to be the place where he should be worshiped [MTY]. Rehoboam’s mother’s name was Naamah; she was from the Ammon people-group.<verse eid="1KI 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 14:22"/>The people of Judah did things that Yahweh considered to be evil. They caused him to become angry because they committed more sins than their ancestors had committed: They worshiped many other gods instead of worshiping only Yahweh. <verse eid="1KI 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 14:23"/>They built places to worship those gods; on high hills, and under big trees they set up <char style="add">stone</char> pillars to worship the goddess Asherah. <verse eid="1KI 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 14:24"/>Also, there were male prostitutes at these places of worship. The Israeli people did the same disgraceful things that had been done by the people whom Yahweh had expelled while the Israelis were advancing through the land.<verse eid="1KI 14:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 14:25"/>When Rehoboam had been ruling for almost five years, King Shishak of Egypt came <char style="add">with his army</char> to attack Jerusalem. <verse eid="1KI 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 14:26"/>They took away all the valuable things in the temple and in the king’s palace, including the gold shields that Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> had made. <verse eid="1KI 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 14:27"/>King Rehoboam’s <char style="add">workers</char> made bronze shields to replace them and entrusted them to officers who guarded the entrance to the king’s palace. <verse eid="1KI 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 14:28"/>Every time that the king went into the temple, those guards carried those shields; and <char style="add">when he left the temple</char> they returned the shields to the storeroom.<verse eid="1KI 14:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 14:29"/>Everything else that Rehoboam did is written [RHQ] in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Judah’. <verse eid="1KI 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 14:30"/>There were wars continually between <char style="add">the armies of</char> Rehoboam and Jeroboam. <verse eid="1KI 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 14:31"/>Then Rehoboam died [EUP], and he was buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’, where his ancestors were buried. Then his son Abijah became the king.<verse eid="1KI 14:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="1KI 15"/>
  <para style="s1">King Abijah of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 15:1"/>After Jeroboam had been the king of Israel for almost 18 years, Abijah became the king of Judah. <verse eid="1KI 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 15:2"/>He ruled for three years in Jerusalem. His mother’s name was Maacah, the granddaughter of <char style="add">David’s son</char> Absalom.<verse eid="1KI 15:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 15:3"/>Abijah committed the same kind of sins that his father had committed. He was not fully dedicated/committed to Yahweh his God, as his grandfather David had been. <verse eid="1KI 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 15:4"/>But, because of <char style="add">what Yahweh his God had promised to</char> David, Yahweh gave Abijah a son [MET] to rule in Jerusalem after him, and in order to protect Jerusalem <char style="add">from their enemies</char>. <verse eid="1KI 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 15:5"/>Yahweh did that because David had always done what pleased Yahweh and because David had always obeyed Yahweh. The only time when he disobeyed Yahweh was when he caused Uriah <char style="add">to be killed</char>.<verse eid="1KI 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 15:6"/>There were wars between <char style="add">the armies of</char> Rehoboam and Jeroboam all during the time that Abijah ruled. <verse eid="1KI 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 15:7"/>Everything else that Abijah did is written [RHQ] in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Judah’. <verse eid="1KI 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 15:8"/>Abijah died [EUP] and was buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’, and his son Asa became king.<verse eid="1KI 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Asa of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 15:9"/>After Jeroboam had been the king of Israel for almost 20 years, Asa started to rule Judah. <verse eid="1KI 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 15:10"/>He ruled in Jerusalem for 41 years. His grandmother was Maacah, the granddaughter of Absalom.<verse eid="1KI 15:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 15:11"/>Asa did what was pleasing to Yahweh, as his ancestor David had done. <verse eid="1KI 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 15:12"/>He got rid of the male prostitutes that were at the places where the people worshiped idols, and he also got rid of all the idols that his ancestors had made. <verse eid="1KI 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 15:13"/>He also removed his grandmother Maacah so that she no longer had influence in the government <char style="add">because of</char> being the mother of a previous king. He did that because she had made a disgusting <char style="add">wooden</char> statue of the goddess Asherah. Asa <char style="add">told his workers to</char> cut down the statue and burned it in the Kidron Valley. <verse eid="1KI 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 15:14"/>He was not able to destroy all the places where the people worshiped <char style="add">idols</char> on the high hills, but he continued to be dedicated/committed to Yahweh his entIre life. <verse eid="1KI 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 15:15"/>He <char style="add">told his workers to</char> place in the temple all the items that his father had dedicated to God, and all the gold and silver things that he had dedicated to God.<verse eid="1KI 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 15:16"/>There were wars between <char style="add">the armies of</char> Asa and Baasha, the king of Israel, all during the time that they ruled. <verse eid="1KI 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 15:17"/>Baasha’s army invaded Judah. They captured Ramah <char style="add">town north of Jerusalem</char>. Then they started to build a wall around it in order to prevent people from entering or leaving the area in Judah that was ruled by King Asa.<verse eid="1KI 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 15:18"/>So Asa <char style="add">told</char> his workers <char style="add">to</char> take all the silver and gold that was still in the storerooms in the temple and in the palace. He told them to take it to Damascus and give it to King Ben-Hadad who ruled Syria. Ben-Hadad was the son of Tabrimmon and grandson of Hezion. He told the workers to say this to Ben-Hadad: <verse eid="1KI 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 15:19"/>“I want there to be a peace treaty between you and me, like there was between your father and my father. For that reason, I am giving you this silver and gold. So now please cancel the treaty that you made with Baasha, the king of Israel, in order that he will take his soldiers away from attacking mine, <char style="add">because he will be afraid of your army</char>.” <verse eid="1KI 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 15:20"/><char style="add">So the workers went and gave the message to</char> Ben-Hadad, <char style="add">and he</char> did what Asa suggested. He sent his army commanders <char style="add">and their soldiers</char> to attack some of the towns in Israel. They captured Ijon, Dan, Abel-Beth-Maacah, the area near Galilee Lake, and all the land of <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Naphtali. <verse eid="1KI 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 15:21"/>When Baasha heard about that, he <char style="add">told his soldiers to</char> stop working at Ramah. He <char style="add">and his soldiers returned to</char> Tirzah <char style="add">and</char> stayed there. <verse eid="1KI 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 15:22"/>Then King Asa sent a message to all the <char style="add">people in the</char> towns in Judah, stating that they all were required to go to Ramah and carry away the stones and timber that Baasha’s soldiers had been using to build a wall around the city. With those stones and timber they fortified Mizpah <char style="add">city north of Jerusalem</char>, and Geba, <char style="add">a town</char> in the territory of the tribe of Benjamin.<verse eid="1KI 15:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 15:23"/>Everything else that Asa did, the armies that his soldiers defeated, and the names of the cities that he caused to be fortified, are [RHQ] written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Judah’. But when Asa became old, he got a disease in his feet. <verse eid="1KI 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 15:24"/>He died [EUP] and was buried where his ancestors were buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. Then his son Jehoshaphat became king.<verse eid="1KI 15:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Nadab of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 15:25"/>After Asa had been the king of Judah for almost two years, King Jeroboam’s son Nadab started to rule Israel. He ruled for two years. <verse eid="1KI 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 15:26"/>He did things that Yahweh considered to be evil. His behavior was sinful like his father’s behavior had been, and what he did led the people of Israel to sin.<verse eid="1KI 15:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 15:27"/>
    <char style="add">A man named</char> Baasha, from the tribe of Issachar, planned to harm him. He killed Nadab when Nadab and his army had surrounded Gibbethon <char style="add">city</char> in the Philistia area. <verse eid="1KI 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 15:28"/>That [DOU] was when Asa had been <char style="add">the king ruling</char> Judah for almost three years. Then Baasha became the king of Israel.<verse eid="1KI 15:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 15:29"/>As soon as Baasha became king, <char style="add">he commanded his soldiers to</char> kill all of Jeroboam’s family. Doing what Yahweh had told the prophet Ahijah from Shiloh would happen, they killed all of Jeroboam’s family. None of them ◄was left/remained alive►. <verse eid="1KI 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 15:30"/>That happened because Yahweh had become very angry with Jeroboam because of all the sins that Jeroboam had committed, and because of the sins that he had persuaded the people of Israel to commit.<verse eid="1KI 15:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 15:31"/>Everything else that Nadab did is written [RHQ] in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’. <verse eid="1KI 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 15:32"/>There were wars between <char style="add">the armies of</char> King Asa and King Baasha all the time that they ruled.<verse eid="1KI 15:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Baasha of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 15:33"/>After Asa had been the king of Judah for almost three years, Baasha, the son of Ahijah, started to rule Israel at Tirzah <char style="add">city</char>. He ruled for 24 years. <verse eid="1KI 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 15:34"/>He did things that Yahweh considered to be evil, and his behavior was sinful like his father’s had been, and he led the people of Israel to sin.<verse eid="1KI 15:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="1KI 16"/>
  <para style="s1">When Baasha ruled Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 16:1"/>During the time that Baasha <char style="add">was king of Israel</char>, <char style="add">the prophet</char> Jehu, Hanani’s son, gave Baasha this message that he had received from Yahweh: <verse eid="1KI 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 16:2"/>“You were very insignificant/unimportant [IDM] when I caused you to become the ruler of my Israeli people. But you have caused me to become very angry by doing [IDM] the kinds of evil things that King Jeroboam did. You have also caused me to become angry by causing my people to sin. <verse eid="1KI 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 16:3"/>So now I will get rid of you and your family [MTY]. I will do to you just like I did to Jeroboam and his family. <verse eid="1KI 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 16:4"/><char style="add">The bodies of</char> those in your family who die in this city <char style="add">will not be buried; they</char> will be eaten by dogs; and <char style="add">the corpses of</char> those who die in the fields will be eaten by vultures.”<verse eid="1KI 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 16:5"/>The other things that happened during the time that Baasha ruled Israel, and the things that he did, are written [RHQ] in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’. <verse eid="1KI 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 16:6"/>When Baasha died, he was buried in Tirzah, <char style="add">the capital city</char>. Then his son Elah became king.<verse eid="1KI 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 16:7"/>Yahweh gave that message about Baasha and his family to the prophet Jehu. Baasha had done many things that Yahweh considered to be evil, which caused Yahweh to become angry. Baasha did the same kind of things that King Jeroboam and his family had done previously. Yahweh was also angry with Baasha because he had killed all of Jeroboam’s family.<verse eid="1KI 16:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When Elah ruled Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 16:8"/>After Asa had been the king of Judah for almost 26 years, Elah became the king of Israel. Elah ruled in Tirzah for <char style="add">only</char> two years.<verse eid="1KI 16:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 16:9"/>
    <char style="add">A man named</char> Zimri was one of Elah’s army officers. He commanded the drivers of half of Elah’s army’s ◄chariots/two-wheeled vehicles pulled by horses►. He made plans to kill Elah while Elah was in Tirzah, getting drunk at the house of <char style="add">a man named</char> Arza. Arza was the man who took care of the things in the king’s palace. <verse eid="1KI 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 16:10"/>Zimri went into Arza’s house and killed Elah. Then Zimri became the king of Israel. That was when Asa had been the king of Judah for 27 years.<verse eid="1KI 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 16:11"/>As soon as Zimri became king [MTY], he killed all of Baasha’s family [MTY]. That included every male [IDM] in Baasha’s family and all of Baasha’s male friends. <verse eid="1KI 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 16:12"/>That was just what Yahweh told the prophet Jehu would happen. <verse eid="1KI 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 16:13"/>Baasha and his son Elah had sinned and led the Israeli people to sin. They caused Yahweh, the God whom the Israeli people worshiped, to become angry, because they both urged the people <char style="add">to worship</char> worthless idols.<verse eid="1KI 16:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 16:14"/>Everything else that Elah did is written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’.<verse eid="1KI 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When Zimri ruled Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 16:15"/>So Zimri became the king of Israel after Asa had been king of Judah for 27 years. But Zimri ruled in Tirzah for only seven days. The Israeli army was beseiging/surrounding Gibeah, a town which belonged to the Philistine people-group. <verse eid="1KI 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 16:16"/>The men in the Israeli army camp heard that Zimri had secretly planned to kill King Elah, and then had killed him. So on that day the soldiers chose Omri, the commander of their army, to become the king of Israel. <verse eid="1KI 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 16:17"/>The Israeli army was camped near Gibbethon <char style="add">city</char>. When they heard what Zimri had done, they left there and went to Tirzah, and surrounded the city. <verse eid="1KI 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 16:18"/>When Zimri realized that the city was <char style="add">about to be</char> captured, he went into his palace and set it on fire. So the palace burned down, and he died <char style="add">in the fire</char>. <verse eid="1KI 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 16:19"/>He died because he had sinned by doing the things that Yahweh considered to be evil. Jeroboam had led the Israeli people to sin, and Zimri sinned just like Jeroboam had sinned.<verse eid="1KI 16:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 16:20"/>All the other things that Zimri did, and the record of how he rebelled <char style="add">against King Elah</char>, are written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’.<verse eid="1KI 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When Omri ruled Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 16:21"/>After Zimri died, the Israeli people were divided. One group wanted Tibni, the son of Ginath, to be their king. The other group wanted Omri <char style="add">to be the king</char>. <verse eid="1KI 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 16:22"/>Those who supported Omri ◄were stronger than/defeated► those who supported Tibni. So Tibni was killed, and Omri became king.<verse eid="1KI 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 16:23"/>Omri became king when Asa had been king of Judah for almost 31 years. Omri ruled Israel for 12 years. For the first six years he ruled in Tirzah. <verse eid="1KI 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 16:24"/>Then he bought a hill from <char style="add">a man named</char> Shemer and paid him about ◄150 pounds/70 kg.► of silver for it. Then Omri ordered his men to build a city on that hill, and he called it Samaria, to honor Shemer, the man who owned it previously.<verse eid="1KI 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 16:25"/>But Omri did many things that Yahweh considered to be evil. He did more evil deeds than any of the kings who ruled Israel before he did. <verse eid="1KI 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 16:26"/><char style="add">When</char> Jeroboam <char style="add">was previously the king, he</char> had led the Israeli people to sin, and Omri committed the same kind of sins that Jeroboam did. The Israeli people caused Yahweh, the God the Israeli people had worshiped, to become very angry, because they worshiped worthless idols.<verse eid="1KI 16:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 16:27"/>Everything that Omri did, and the record of the victories that his <char style="add">army</char> won, are written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’. <verse eid="1KI 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 16:28"/>After Omri died, he was buried in Samaria, and his son Ahab became king.<verse eid="1KI 16:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When Ahab ruled Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 16:29"/>Ahab became king of Israel when Asa had ruled Judah for almost 38 years. Ahab ruled in Samaria <char style="add">city</char> for 22 years. <verse eid="1KI 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 16:30"/>Ahab did many things that Yahweh considered to be evil. He did more evil things than any of the kings who ruled Israel before he did. <verse eid="1KI 16:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 16:31"/>He committed the same kind of sins that Jeroboam did, but he did things that were worse than the things that Jeroboam did. He married <char style="add">a woman named</char> Jezebel, the daughter of Ethbaal, the king of Sidon <char style="add">city</char>. Then Ahab started to worship Baal, <char style="add">the god that the Canaan people-group worshiped</char>. <verse eid="1KI 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 16:32"/>He built a temple in Samaria in order that the Israeli people could worship Baal there, and he put an altar there for <char style="add">making sacrifices to</char> Baal. <verse eid="1KI 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 16:33"/>He also made an idol that represented Asherah, <char style="add">Baal’s wife</char>. He did many more things that caused Yahweh to become angry. He did more evil things than any of the previous kings of Israel had done.<verse eid="1KI 16:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 16:34"/>During the years that Ahab <char style="add">ruled</char>, Hiel, a man from Bethel <char style="add">city</char>, rebuilt Jericho <char style="add">city</char>. But when he started to rebuild the city, his oldest son Abiram died. And <char style="add">when the city was finished,</char> while Hiel was building the city gates, his youngest son Segub died. They died just like Yahweh had told Joshua would happen <char style="add">to the sons of anyone who would rebuild Jericho</char>.<verse eid="1KI 16:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="1KI 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Crows fed Elijah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 17:1"/>Elijah was <char style="add">a prophet</char> who lived in Tishbe <char style="add">town</char> in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>. One day he <char style="add">went to</char> King Ahab and said to him, “Yahweh is the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char> and the God whom I worship and serve. Just as certainly as Yahweh lives, there will be no dew or rain for the next few years, if I do not command rain to fall!”<verse eid="1KI 17:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 17:2"/>Then Yahweh said to Elijah, <verse eid="1KI 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 17:3"/>“<char style="add">Because you have made the king angry with you, escape from the king and,</char> go to the east, to the Kerith Brook, east of where it flows into the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="1KI 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 17:4"/>You will be able to drink water from the brook, and <char style="add">you will be able to eat what</char> the crows <char style="add">bring to you, because</char> I have commanded them to bring food to you.”<verse eid="1KI 17:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 17:5"/>So Elijah did what Yahweh commanded him to do. He went and camped alongside Kerith Brook. <verse eid="1KI 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 17:6"/>Crows bought bread and meat to him every morning and every evening, and he drank <char style="add">water</char> from the brook.<verse eid="1KI 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 17:7"/>But after a while, the water in the brook dried up, because rain did not fall anywhere in the land. <verse eid="1KI 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 17:8"/>Then Yahweh said to Elijah, <verse eid="1KI 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 17:9"/>“Go and live in Zarephath <char style="add">village</char>, near Sidon <char style="add">city</char>. There is a widow there who will give you food to eat. I have <char style="add">already</char> told her what to do about that.” <verse eid="1KI 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 17:10"/>So <char style="add">Elijah did what God said</char>. He went to Zarephath. As he arrived at the gates of the village, he saw a widow who was gathering sticks. He said to her, “Would you please bring me a cup of water?” <verse eid="1KI 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 17:11"/>While she was going to get it, he called out to her, “Bring me a piece of bread, too!”<verse eid="1KI 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 17:12"/>But she replied, “Your God knows that what I am telling you is true: I do not have even one piece of bread in my house. I have only a handful of flour in a jar, and a little <char style="add">olive</char> oil in a jug. I was gathering a few sticks to use these to <char style="add">make a fire and</char> cook one more meal, and then after my son and I eat that, we will die <char style="add">from hunger</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 17:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 17:13"/>But Elijah said to her, “Do not be worried! Go home and do what you said that you were going to do. But first, bake me a little loaf of bread and bring it to me. After you do that, take what is left and prepare some food for you and your son. <verse eid="1KI 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 17:14"/><char style="add">I know that you will be able to do that,</char> because Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, says this: ‘There will always be plenty of flour and <char style="add">olive</char> oil left in your containers, until the time when I send rain again <char style="add">and the crops grow again</char>!’ ”<verse eid="1KI 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 17:15"/>So the woman did exactly what Elijah told her to do. And she and her son and Elijah had enough food every day, <verse eid="1KI 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 17:16"/>because the flour in the jar was never finished, and the jug of oil was never empty. That happened just like Yahweh had told Elijah that it would happen.<verse eid="1KI 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Elijah restored to life the widow’s son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 17:17"/>Some time later, the woman’s son became sick. He continued to get worse, and finally he died. <verse eid="1KI 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 17:18"/>So the woman went to Elijah and said to him, “You are a prophet; so why have you done this to me? Have you come here to punish me for my sins by causing my son to die?”<verse eid="1KI 17:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 17:19"/>But Elijah replied, “Give your son to me.” So she gave her son to him, and he took the boy’s <char style="add">body</char> from her and carried it up <char style="add">the steps</char> to the room where he stayed. He laid the boy’s <char style="add">body</char> on his bed. <verse eid="1KI 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 17:20"/>Then Elijah cried out to Yahweh, “O Yahweh my God, this widow <char style="add">has kindly allowed</char> me to stay in her home. So why have you brought this tragedy to her and caused her son to die?” [RHQ] <verse eid="1KI 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 17:21"/>Then Elijah stretched himself on top of the boy’s <char style="add">body</char> and called out to Yahweh saying, “Yahweh my God, please allow this boy to become alive again!” He did this three times.<verse eid="1KI 17:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 17:22"/>Yahweh heard what Elijah prayed, and <char style="add">he caused</char> the boy <char style="add">to </char> become alive again [DOU]. <verse eid="1KI 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 17:23"/>Elijah carried the boy down <char style="add">the steps</char> and gave him to his mother. He said, “Look, your son is alive!”<verse eid="1KI 17:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 17:24"/>The woman said to Elijah, “Now I know <char style="add">for certain</char> that you are a prophet and that the words that you speak are truly from Yahweh!”<verse eid="1KI 17:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="1KI 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Elijah met with Obadiah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 18:1"/>For almost three years there was no rain in Samaria. Then Yahweh said this to Elijah: “Go and meet with King Ahab and <char style="add">tell him that</char> I will soon send rain.” <verse eid="1KI 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 18:2"/>So Elijah went to talk to Ahab.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 18:2">In Samaria there was almost no food for anyone to eat. <verse eid="1KI 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 18:3"/>There was a man there named Obadiah. He was in charge of the king’s palace. He greatly revered Yahweh. <verse eid="1KI 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 18:4"/>One time when <char style="add">Queen</char> Jezebel had <char style="add">tried to</char> kill all Yahweh’s prophets, Obadiah hid 100 of them in two caves. He put 50 prophets in each cave, and he brought food and water to them.<verse eid="1KI 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 18:5"/>
    <char style="add">By this time, the ◄famine/lack of food and water► had become very severe in Samaria</char>. So Ahab summoned Obadiah and said to him, “We must check/look near every spring and in every valley to see if we can find enough grass to give to some of my horses and mules, so that they will not all die.” <verse eid="1KI 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 18:6"/>So they both started walking throughout the land. Obadiah went in one direction by himself, and Ahab went in another direction by himself.<verse eid="1KI 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 18:7"/>While Obadiah was walking along, he saw Elijah coming toward him. Obadiah recognized Elijah and bowed down in front of him and said, “Is it really you, Elijah, my master?”<verse eid="1KI 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 18:8"/>Elijah replied, “Yes. Now go and tell <char style="add">Ahab,</char> your master, that I am here.”<verse eid="1KI 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 18:9"/>Obadiah objected. He said, “Sir, I have not [RHQ] harmed you at all. So why are you sending me back to Ahab? He will kill me! <verse eid="1KI 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 18:10"/>Yahweh your God <char style="add">knows that I am telling the truth when</char> I solemnly declare that King Ahab has searched in every kingdom all over the world [HYP] to find you. Each time that some king said to him, ‘Elijah is not here,’ Ahab demanded that the king of that country solemnly swear/declare that the king was telling the truth. <verse eid="1KI 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 18:11"/>Now you say to me, ‘Go and tell your master that Elijah is here!’ <verse eid="1KI 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 18:12"/>But as soon as I leave you, the Spirit of Yahweh will carry you away, and I will not know where he will take you. So when <char style="add">I tell</char> Ahab <char style="add">that you are here and he</char> comes to me and he does not find you here, he will kill me! But <char style="add">I do not deserve to die because</char> I have revered Yahweh since I was a boy. <verse eid="1KI 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 18:13"/>My master, have you not heard about what I did when Jezebel wanted to kill all of Yahweh’s prophets? I hid 100 of them in two caves and took food and water to them. <verse eid="1KI 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 18:14"/>Now, sir, you say, ‘Go and tell your master that Elijah is here.’ But if I do that, <char style="add">and he comes and you are not here,</char> he will kill me!”<verse eid="1KI 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 18:15"/>But Elijah replied, “Yahweh, the Almighty One whom I serve [IDM], knows that <char style="add">I am telling the truth as</char> I solemnly declare that I will go to meet with Ahab today.”<verse eid="1KI 18:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Elijah killed the prophets of Baal</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 18:16"/>So Obadiah went to tell Ahab that Elijah had come. Ahab went to meet with him. <verse eid="1KI 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 18:17"/>When he saw Elijah, he said to him, “Is that you, the one who causes trouble for <char style="add">the people of</char> Israel?”<verse eid="1KI 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 18:18"/>Elijah replied, “It is not I who have caused trouble for the people of Israel! You and your family are the ones who have caused trouble! You have refused to obey Yahweh’s commands, and you have worshiped the idols of Baal instead. <verse eid="1KI 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 18:19"/>So now, command all the Israeli people to come to Carmel Mountain, and <char style="add">be sure to</char> bring all the 450 prophets who worship Baal and the 400 prophets who worship <char style="add">the goddess</char> Asherah, the ones to whom <char style="add">your wife</char> Jezebel brings food and water.”<verse eid="1KI 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 18:20"/>So Ahab summoned all his prophets and all the other <char style="add">Israeli</char> people to the top of Carmel Mountain, <char style="add">and Elijah went up there too.</char> <verse eid="1KI 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 18:21"/>Then Elijah stood in front of them and said, “How long [RHQ] are you going to be undecided <char style="add">about who is truly God</char>? If Yahweh is <char style="add">truly</char> God, then worship/serve him. If Baal is truly God, then worship/serve him!” But the people said nothing <char style="add">in reply, because they were afraid of what Jezebel would do to them if they admitted that they worshiped Yahweh</char>.<verse eid="1KI 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 18:22"/>Then Elijah said to them, “I am the only true prophet of Yahweh who is left, but Baal has 450 prophets. <verse eid="1KI 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 18:23"/>Bring two bulls. The prophets of Baal may choose the one that they want. They must <char style="add">kill it and</char> cut it into pieces and lay the pieces on the wood that is on the altar that they have made. But they must not light a fire <char style="add">under the wood</char>. <char style="add">I will kill the other bull and cut it in pieces and lay the pieces on the altar that I make</char>. <verse eid="1KI 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 18:24"/>Then they must call to their god [MTY], and I will call to Yahweh. The god who answers by lighting a fire <char style="add">to the wood that is on that altar</char> is <char style="add">the true</char> God!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 18:24">Then all the people thought that Elijah’s suggestion was good.<verse eid="1KI 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 18:25"/>Then Elijah said to the prophets of Baal, “You call to Baal first, because there are many of you. Choose one of the bulls and prepare it, and then call to your god. But do not light a fire under the wood!” <verse eid="1KI 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 18:26"/>So they killed one of the bulls and cut it up and placed the pieces on the altar. Then they called out to Baal all morning. They shouted, “Baal, answer us!” But no one answered. There was no reply at all [DOU].</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 18:26">Then they danced wildly around the altar that they had made.<verse eid="1KI 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 18:27"/>About noontime, Elijah started to make fun of them. He said, “<char style="add">Surely</char> Baal is a god, so it seems that you must shout louder! Perhaps he is thinking about something, or perhaps he has gone to the toilet. Or perhaps he is traveling somewhere, or perhaps he is asleep and you need to wake him up!” <verse eid="1KI 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 18:28"/>So they shouted louder. Then, doing one of the things that they frequently did <char style="add">when they worshiped Baal</char>, they slashed/cut themselves with knives and swords until a lot of blood flowed. <verse eid="1KI 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 18:29"/>They continued calling out to Baal all afternoon. But there was no reply, no answer, no god who paid attention.<verse eid="1KI 18:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 18:30"/>Then Elijah called to the people saying, “Come closer!” So they all crowded around him. Then Elijah repaired the altar of Yahweh that had previously been ◄ruined/torn down► <char style="add">by the prophets of Baal</char>. <verse eid="1KI 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 18:31"/>Then he took twelve <char style="add">large</char> stones, each one to represent one of the Israeli tribes. The names of those tribes were given to them by their ancestor Jacob. <verse eid="1KI 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 18:32"/>With these stones he rebuilt Yahweh’s altar. Then around the altar he dug a little ditch that was large enough to hold about ◄three gallons/12 liters► of water. <verse eid="1KI 18:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 18:33"/>He piled wood on top of the stones. He killed the bull and cut it in pieces. Then he laid the pieces on top of the wood. Then he said, “Fill four large jars with water, and pour the water on top of the pieces of meat and the wood.” So they did that.<verse eid="1KI 18:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 18:34"/>Then he said, “Do the same thing again!” So they did it again. Then he said “Do it a third time!” So they did it again.<verse eid="1KI 18:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 18:35"/>As a result, the water flowed down below the altar and filled the ditches.<verse eid="1KI 18:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 18:36"/>When it was time to offer the evening sacrifices, Elijah walked close <char style="add">to the altar</char> and prayed. He said, “Yahweh, you who are the God that <char style="add">our ancestors</char> Abraham and Isaac and Jacob <char style="add">worshiped</char>, prove today that you are the God whom the Israeli people <char style="add">should worship</char>, and prove that I am your servant. Prove that I have done all these things because you told me to do them. <verse eid="1KI 18:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 18:37"/>Yahweh, answer me! Answer me in order that these people will know that you, Yahweh God, <char style="add">have the power to do what you say that you will do</char>, and that you have caused them to trust in [IDM] you again!”<verse eid="1KI 18:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 18:38"/>Immediately a fire from Yahweh flashed down from the sky. The fire burned up the pieces of meat, the wood, the stones, and the dirt <char style="add">that was around the altar</char>. It even dried up all the water in the ditch!<verse eid="1KI 18:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 18:39"/>When the people saw that, they prostrated themselves on the ground and shouted, “Yahweh is God! Yahweh is God!”<verse eid="1KI 18:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 18:40"/>Then Elijah commanded them, “Seize all the prophets of Baal! Do not allow any of them to escape!” So the people seized all the prophets of Baal, and took them down the mountain to the Kishon Valley, and Elijah killed them all there.<verse eid="1KI 18:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Elijah prayed for rain</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1KI 18:41"/>Then Elijah said to Ahab, “Go and get something to eat and drink. <char style="add">But do it quickly, because</char> it is soon going to rain very hard!” <verse eid="1KI 18:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1KI 18:42"/>So Ahab <char style="add">and his men</char> left to prepare a big meal. But Elijah went back up to the top of Carmel Mountain and prayed.<verse eid="1KI 18:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 18:43"/>Then he said to his servant, “Go and look out toward the sea, <char style="add">to see if there are any rain clouds.</char>” So his servant went and looked, <char style="add">and came back</char> and said, “I do not see anything.” This happened six times. <verse eid="1KI 18:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1KI 18:44"/>But when the servant went the seventh time, he came back and said, “I saw a very small cloud above the sea. <char style="add">As I extend my arm,</char> the cloud is about the size of my hand/fist.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 18:44">Then Elijah shouted to him, “Go and tell King Ahab to get his chariot ready and go home immediately! If he does not do that, the rain will stop him!” <verse eid="1KI 18:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1KI 18:45"/>Very soon the sky was full of black clouds. There was a strong wind, and then it began to rain very hard. Ahab got into his chariot and started to return to Jezreel <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="1KI 18:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1KI 18:46"/>Yahweh gave extra strength to Elijah. He tucked his cloak into his belt <char style="add">in order to run fast</char>, and he ran ahead of Ahab’s <char style="add">chariot</char> all the way <char style="add">17 miles/26 km.</char> to Jezreel.<verse eid="1KI 18:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="1KI 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Elijah fled to the desert and then to Sinai Mountain</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 19:1"/>When Ahab got home, he told <char style="add">his wife</char> Jezebel what Elijah had done. He told her that Elijah had killed all the prophets of Baal. <verse eid="1KI 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 19:2"/>So Jezebel sent this message to Elijah: “By this time tomorrow I will have <char style="add">killed</char> you, just like you <char style="add">killed all those prophets of Baal</char>. If I do not do that, I hope the gods will kill me.”<verse eid="1KI 19:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 19:3"/>When Elijah received <char style="add">her message</char>, he was afraid. So <char style="add">taking his servant with him</char>, he fled in order that he would not be killed. He went <char style="add">far south</char> to Beersheba, in Judah. He left his servant there. <verse eid="1KI 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 19:4"/>Then he went by himself further <char style="add">south</char> into the desert. He walked all day. He sat down under a broom tree and prayed that <char style="add">Yahweh</char> would allow him to die. He said, “Yahweh, I’ve had enough. So allow me to die, because for me to live is no better than <char style="add">being with</char> my ancestors <char style="add">who have died</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 19:5"/>Then he lay down under the broom tree and slept. But while he was sleeping, an angel touched him and <char style="add">woke him up and</char> said to him, “Get up and eat some food!”<verse eid="1KI 19:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 19:6"/>Elijah looked around and saw some bread which had been baked on hot stones, and he also saw a jar of water. So he ate some bread and drank some water and lay down <char style="add">to sleep</char> again.<verse eid="1KI 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 19:7"/>Then the angel <char style="add">who had been sent by</char> Yahweh came again and touched him, and said, “Get up and eat some <char style="add">more</char> food, because you need <char style="add">more strength</char> to go on a long journey.” <verse eid="1KI 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 19:8"/>So he got up and ate and drank some more, and because of doing that, he got enough strength to enable him to travel for forty days and nights to Sinai Mountain, the mountain <char style="add">that was dedicated to</char> God. <verse eid="1KI 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 19:9"/>He went into a cave there and slept there that night.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="1KI 19:9">Yahweh gave instructions to Elijah</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 19:9">
    <char style="add">The next morning,</char> Yahweh said to him “Elijah, why are you here?” <verse eid="1KI 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 19:10"/>Elijah replied, “I have zealously served you, Yahweh, God Almighty. But the Israeli people have broken the agreement that they made with you. They have torn down your altars, and they have killed all of your prophets. I am the only one whom they have not killed, and now they are trying to kill me, too. <char style="add">So I am running away from them</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 19:11"/>Yahweh said to him, “Go out and stand in front of me on this mountain while I pass by.” <char style="add">Suddenly</char> a strong windstorm struck the mountain. As a result, rocks were loosened from the mountainside. But Yahweh was not in the wind. Then there was an earthquake, but Yahweh was not in the earthquake.<verse eid="1KI 19:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 19:12"/>Then there was a fire, but Yahweh was not in the fire. Then there was a sound like someone whispering quietly. <verse eid="1KI 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 19:13"/>When Elijah heard that, he wrapped his cloak around his face. He went out of the cave and stood at its entrance. And he heard Yahweh speaking to him, saying again, “Elijah, why are you here?”<verse eid="1KI 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 19:14"/>He replied again, “I have zealously served you, Yahweh, God Almighty. But the Israeli people have broken the agreement that they made with you. They have torn down your altars, and they have killed all of your prophets. I am the only one whom they have not killed, and now they are trying to kill me, too. <char style="add">So I am running away from them</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 19:15"/>Then Yahweh told him, “Go back to the desert near Damascus. When you arrive there, anoint <char style="add">with olive oil</char> a man named Hazael, <char style="add">to appoint him</char> to be the king of Syria. <verse eid="1KI 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 19:16"/>Then anoint Jehu, the son of Nimshi, to be the king of Israel, and also anoint Elisha the son of Shaphat, from Abel-Meholah <char style="add">town</char>, to become my prophet after you are dead. <verse eid="1KI 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 19:17"/>Hazael’s army <char style="add">will kill many people, and</char> those who escape from <char style="add">being killed by</char> his army will be killed by Jehu’s <char style="add">army</char>, and those who escape from <char style="add">being killed by</char> Jehu’s army will be killed by Elisha. <verse eid="1KI 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 19:18"/>But <char style="add">you need to know that</char> there are still 7,000 people in Israel who have never bowed to <char style="add">worship</char> Baal or kissed his <char style="add">idol</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 19:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Elijah summoned Elisha</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 19:19"/>So Elijah went <char style="add">to Syria</char> and found Elisha as he was plowing a field with a team of oxen. There were eleven other men who were in front of him, plowing with teams of oxen in the same field. Elijah went to Elisha, and took off his own coat and put it on Elisha, <char style="add">to show Elisha that he wanted him to take his place as a prophet. Then he started to walk away</char>. <verse eid="1KI 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 19:20"/>Elisha left the oxen standing there and ran after Elijah, and said to him, “I will go with you, but first let me kiss my parents goodbye.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 19:20">Elijah replied, “Okay, go home. But do not forget why I have <char style="add">given my cloak</char> to you!” <verse eid="1KI 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 19:21"/>So Elisha went back <char style="add">to his oxen</char>. He killed them <char style="add">and cut them in pieces</char> and used the wood from the plow to build a fire to roast the meat. He distributed the meat to the other people <char style="add">in his town</char>, and they all ate some. Then he went with Elijah and became his helper.<verse eid="1KI 19:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="1KI 20"/>
  <para style="s1">The Syrian army attacked Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 20:1"/>Ben-Hadad, the king of Syria, gathered all his army, and he persuaded 32 other kings to join him with their armies and horses and chariots. They marched to Samaria <char style="add">city, the capital of Israel</char>, and surrounded it, and <char style="add">prepared to</char> attack it. <verse eid="1KI 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 20:2"/>Ben-Hadad sent messengers into the city to King Ahab, to say this to him: “This is what King Ben-Hadad says: <verse eid="1KI 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 20:3"/>‘<char style="add">You must give to</char> me all your silver and gold, your ◄good-looking/most beautiful► wives/women and strongest children.’”<verse eid="1KI 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 20:4"/>The king of Israel replied to them, “Tell this to King Ben-Hadad: ‘I agree to do what you requested. You can have me and everything that I own.’”<verse eid="1KI 20:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 20:5"/>
    <char style="add">The messengers told that to</char> Ben-Hadad, and he <char style="add">sent them back with</char> another message: “I sent a message to you saying that you must give me all your silver and gold and your wives and your children. <verse eid="1KI 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 20:6"/>But <char style="add">in addition to that</char>, about this time tomorrow, I will send some of my officials to search your palace and the houses of your officials, and to bring to me everything that pleases them.”<verse eid="1KI 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 20:7"/>King Ahab summoned all the leaders of Israel, and said to them, “You can see/realize for yourselves that this man is trying to cause much trouble. He sent me a message insisting that I must give him my wives and my children, my silver and my gold, and I agreed to do that.”<verse eid="1KI 20:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 20:8"/>The leaders and all the other people said to him, “Do not pay any attention to him! Do not do what he is requesting!”<verse eid="1KI 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 20:9"/>So Ahab said to Ben-Hadad’s messengers, “Tell the king that I agree to give him the things that he first requested, but I do not agree to allow his officials to take anything that they want from my palace and from the houses of my officials.” So the messengers <char style="add">reported that to King Ben-Hadad, and they</char> returned with another message from Ben-Hadad.<verse eid="1KI 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 20:10"/>In that message he said, “<char style="add">We will destroy</char> your city <char style="add">completely, with the result that</char> there will not be enough dust and rubble left for each of my soldiers to have one handful! I hope/wish that the gods will strike me dead if we do not do that!”<verse eid="1KI 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 20:11"/>King Ahab replied <char style="add">to the messengers</char>, “Tell King Ben-Hadad that a soldier who is putting on his armor <char style="add">preparing to fight a battle</char> [MTY] should not boast at that time; he <char style="add">should wait until</char> after he wins the battle.”<verse eid="1KI 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 20:12"/>Ben-Hadad heard that message while he and the other rulers were drinking <char style="add">wine</char> in their temporary shelters. He told his men to prepare to attack [MTY] the city. So his men did that.<verse eid="1KI 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ahab’s soldiers won their first victory over the Syrians</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 20:13"/>At that moment, a prophet came to King Ahab and said to him, “This is what Yahweh says: ‘<char style="add">Do not be at all afraid of</char> [RHQ] the large enemy army that you see! I will enable your army to defeat them today, and you will know that it is I, Yahweh, <char style="add">who have the power to do what I say that I will do</char>.’”<verse eid="1KI 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 20:14"/>Ahab asked, “What group <char style="add">of our army</char> will defeat them?” The prophet replied, “The young soldiers who are commanded by the district governors will do it.” The king asked, “Who should lead the attack?” The prophet replied, “You should!”<verse eid="1KI 20:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 20:15"/>So Ahab gathered the young soldiers who were commanded by the district governors. There were 232 of those men. Then he also summoned all the Israeli army. There were <char style="add">only</char> 7,000 soldiers. <verse eid="1KI 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 20:16"/>They started to attack at noon, while Ben-Hadad and the other rulers were getting drunk in their temporary shelters. <verse eid="1KI 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 20:17"/>The young soldiers advanced first. Some scouts who had been sent out by Ben-Hadad reported to him, “There are men coming out of Samaria <char style="add">city</char>”!<verse eid="1KI 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 20:18"/>He said, “It does not matter whether they are coming to fight against us or to ask for peace. Capture them, but do not kill them<verse eid="1KI 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 20:19"/>The young Israeli soldiers went out of the city to attack <char style="add">the Syrian army</char>, and the other soldiers in the Israeli army followed them. <verse eid="1KI 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 20:20"/>Each <char style="add">Israeli soldier</char> killed a <char style="add">Syrian</char> soldier. The rest of the Syrian army then ran away, and the Israeli soldiers pursued them. But King Ben-Hadad escaped riding his horse, along with some other men riding horses. <verse eid="1KI 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 20:21"/>Then the king of Israel went out <char style="add">of the city</char>, and he and his soldiers captured <char style="add">all</char> the <char style="add">other Syrian</char> horses and chariots, and also killed a large number of Syrian soldiers.<verse eid="1KI 20:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 20:22"/>Then that same prophet went to King Ahab and said to him, “Go back and prepare your soldiers, and think carefully about what will be necessary for you to do, because the king of Syria with attack with his army again in the springtime of next year.”<verse eid="1KI 20:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 20:23"/>
    <char style="add">After the Syrian army was defeated,</char> Ben-Hadad’s officials said to him, “The gods that the Israelis <char style="add">worship</char> are gods <char style="add">who live</char> in the hills. <char style="add">Samaria is built on a hill, and</char> that is why their soldiers were able to defeat us. But if we fight against them in the plains/lowlands, we certainly will be able to defeat them. <verse eid="1KI 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 20:24"/>So, this is what you should do: You must remove the 32 kings <char style="add">who are leading your troops</char> and replace them with army commanders. <verse eid="1KI 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 20:25"/>Then gather an army like the army that was defeated. Gather an army that has as many horses and chariots as the first army had. Then we will fight the Israelis in the plains/lowlands, and we will surely defeat them.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 20:25">Ben-Hadad agreed with them, and he did what they suggested. <verse eid="1KI 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 20:26"/>In the spring of the following year, he gathered his soldiers and marched <char style="add">with them</char> to Aphek <char style="add">city east of Galilee Lake</char>, to fight against the Israeli army. <verse eid="1KI 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 20:27"/>The Israeli army was also gathered together, and they were equipped with the things that they needed <char style="add">for the battle</char>. Then they marched out and formed two groups facing the Syrian army. Their army was very small; they resembled two small flocks of goats, whereas the Syrian army <char style="add">was very large and</char> spread all over the countryside.<verse eid="1KI 20:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 20:28"/>A prophet came to King Ahab and said to him, “This is what Yahweh says: ‘The Syrians say that I am a god who lives in the hills, and that I am not a god who lives in the valleys. So I will <char style="add">show that they are wrong by</char> enabling your men to defeat this huge army [IDM] <char style="add">in the valley</char>, and you will know that I, Yahweh, <char style="add">have done it</char>.’”<verse eid="1KI 20:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 20:29"/>The two armies stayed in their tents for seven days, in groups that faced each other. Then, on the seventh day, they started fighting. The Israeli army killed 100,000 Syrian soldiers. <verse eid="1KI 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 20:30"/>The other Syrian soldiers ran away into Aphek City. Then the wall of the city collapsed and killed 27,000 more Syrian soldiers.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 20:30">Ben-Hadad also escaped into the city, and hid in the back room of a house. <verse eid="1KI 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 20:31"/>His officials went to him and said, “We have heard a report that the Israelis act mercifully. So allow us to go to the king of Israel, wearing coarse sacks around our waists and ropes on our heads/necks <char style="add">to indicate that we will be his slaves</char>. Perhaps <char style="add">if we do that,</char> he will allow you to remain alive.”<verse eid="1KI 20:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 20:32"/>
    <char style="add">The king permitted them to do that,</char> so they wrapped coarse sacks around their waists and put ropes on their heads/necks, and they went to the king of Israel and said to him, “Ben-Hadad, who greatly respects you, says, ‘Please do not kill me.’” Ahab replied, “Is he still alive? He is like a brother to me!”<verse eid="1KI 20:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 20:33"/>Ben-Hadad’s officials were trying to find out if Ahab would act mercifully, and when Ahab said “brother,” they ◄were optimistic/thought that Ahab would be merciful►. So they replied, “Yes, he is like your brother!” Ahab said, “Go and bring him to me.” So they <char style="add">went and</char> brought Ben-Hadad to him. <char style="add">When Ben-Hadad arrived,</char> Ahab told him to get in his chariot <char style="add">and sit with him</char>.<verse eid="1KI 20:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 20:34"/>Ben-Hadad said to him, “I will give back to you the towns that my father’s army took from your father. And I will allow you to set up market areas for your merchants in Damascus <char style="add">my capital</char>, just as my father did in Samaria <char style="add">your capital</char>.” Ahab replied, “Because you agree to do that, I will not execute you.” So Ahab made an agreement with Ben-Hadad, and allowed him to go home.<verse eid="1KI 20:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 20:35"/>Then Yahweh spoke to a member of a group of prophets and said to him, “Ask one of your fellow prophets to strike and wound you.” <char style="add">So he did what Yahweh told him to do</char>. <char style="add">He said to one of his fellow prophets, ‘Strike me and wound me</char>.’ But that man refused to do it.<verse eid="1KI 20:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 20:36"/>So the prophet said to him, “Because you refused to obey what Yahweh told you to do, a lion will kill you as soon as you leave me.” And as soon as he left that prophet, a lion suddenly pounced on him and killed him.<verse eid="1KI 20:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 20:37"/>Then the prophet found another prophet, and said to him, “Strike me!” So that man hit him <char style="add">very hard</char> and injured him. <verse eid="1KI 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 20:38"/>Then the prophet put a large bandage/cloth over his face so that no one would recognize him. Then he went and stood alongside the road, waiting for the king to come by. <verse eid="1KI 20:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 20:39"/>When the king passed by, the prophet cried out to him, saying “Your majesty, <char style="add">after I was wounded</char> while I was fighting in a battle, a soldier brought to me one of our enemies that he had captured, and said to me, ‘Guard this man! If he escapes, you must pay me 3,000 pieces of silver, and if you do not pay that, you will be executed!’ <verse eid="1KI 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 20:40"/>But while I was busy doing other things, the man escaped!” The king of Israel said to him, “That is your problem! You yourself have said that you deserve to be punished.”<verse eid="1KI 20:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1KI 20:41"/>The prophet immediately took off the bandage, and the king of Israel recognized that he was one of the prophets. <verse eid="1KI 20:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1KI 20:42"/>And the prophet said to him, “This is what Yahweh says: ‘You have allowed that man <char style="add">Ben-Hadad</char> to escape after I commanded you to be sure to execute him! Since you did not do that, you will be killed instead. And your army will be destroyed because you allowed <char style="add">some of</char> his army to escape!’” <verse eid="1KI 20:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 20:43"/>The king went back home to Samaria, very angry and depressed/dejected.<verse eid="1KI 20:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="1KI 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Jezebel arranged for Naboth to be killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 21:1"/>King Ahab had a palace in Jezreel <char style="add">city</char>. Near the palace was a vineyard owned by a man from that city whose name was Naboth. <verse eid="1KI 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 21:2"/>One day, Ahab <char style="add">went to</char> Naboth and said to him, “Your vineyard is close to my palace. I would like to buy it, so that I can plant some vegetables there. In exchange, I will give you a better vineyard <char style="add">somewhere else</char>, or if you prefer, I will pay you for your vineyard.”<verse eid="1KI 21:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 21:3"/>But Naboth replied, “That land belonged to my ancestors, <char style="add">so I want to keep it</char>. I hope that Yahweh will never allow me to give that land to you!”<verse eid="1KI 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 21:4"/>So Ahab became very sullen and angry because of what Naboth had said. He went home and lay down on his bed. He turned his face toward the wall, and he refused to eat anything.<verse eid="1KI 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 21:5"/>His wife Jezebel came in and asked him, “Why are you so depressed? Why are you refusing to eat anything?”<verse eid="1KI 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 21:6"/>Ahab replied, “I talked to Naboth, that man from Jezreel. I told him that <char style="add">I wanted</char> his vineyard. <char style="add">I said,</char> ‘I will buy it from you, or I will give you another vineyard for it.’ But he refused <char style="add">to let me have it</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 21:7"/>His wife replied, “You are [RHQ] the king of Israel, <char style="add">so you can get whatever you want</char> Get up, and eat some food and do not worry <char style="add">about what Naboth said</char>. I will get Naboth’s vineyard for you.”<verse eid="1KI 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 21:8"/>Then Jezebel wrote some letters, and she signed Ahab’s name on them. She used his official seal to seal them. Then she sent them to the older leaders and other important men who lived in Naboth’s town. <verse eid="1KI 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 21:9"/>This is what she wrote in the letters: “Proclaim a day when all the people will <char style="add">gather together and</char> ◄fast/abstain from eating food►. Give to Naboth an important place to sit among them. <verse eid="1KI 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 21:10"/>Then find two men who always cause trouble. Give them places to sit opposite/facing him. Tell these men to testify that they heard Naboth say things that criticized God and the king. Then take Naboth out of the city and kill him by throwing stones at him.”<verse eid="1KI 21:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 21:11"/>The leaders <char style="add">received the letters and</char> did what Jezebel had written in the letters for them to do. <verse eid="1KI 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 21:12"/>They declared a day on which the people would all ◄fast/abstain from food►. And they gave Naboth a seat in a place where honored people sat, in front of the people. <verse eid="1KI 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 21:13"/>Two men who always caused trouble sat opposite/facing Naboth. While everyone was listening, they stated that they had heard Naboth say things that criticized God and the king. So the people seized Naboth. They took him outside the city and killed him <char style="add">by throwing</char> stones at him. <verse eid="1KI 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 21:14"/>Then those leaders sent a message to Jezebel, saying “We have executed Naboth.”<verse eid="1KI 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 21:15"/>When Jezebel found out that Naboth had been killed, she told Ahab, “Naboth is dead. Now you can go and take possession of the vineyard that he refused to sell to you.” <verse eid="1KI 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 21:16"/>When Ahab heard that Naboth was dead, he got up and went to the vineyard to claim that he now owned it.<verse eid="1KI 21:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 21:17"/>Then Yahweh spoke to Elijah the prophet. He said, <verse eid="1KI 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 21:18"/>“Go to Samaria and talk to Ahab, the king of Israel. He is in the vineyard of a man named Naboth. He has gone there to claim that he now owns it. <verse eid="1KI 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 21:19"/>Tell Ahab that this is what I, Yahweh, say to him: ‘You have murdered Naboth and taken his land.’ So I am telling you this: ‘In the same place where <char style="add">Naboth died and</char> dogs came and licked up Naboth’s blood, <char style="add">you will die and</char> the dogs will lick up your blood, too!’ ”<verse eid="1KI 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 21:20"/>So when Elijah met with Ahab, Ahab said to him, “You, my enemy, have found me!” [RHQ] Elijah answered, “Yes, I have found you. You have never stopped doing the things that Yahweh says are wrong.<verse eid="1KI 21:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 21:21"/>So this is what Yahweh says to you: ‘I will soon get rid of you. I will kill you, and I will also kill every male in your household, including those who are slaves and those who are not slaves. <verse eid="1KI 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 21:22"/>Your family will all be killed, just like the family of King Jeroboam and like the family of King Baasha were killed. I will get rid of you because you have caused me to become very angry, and you have also led the Israeli people to sin.’<verse eid="1KI 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 21:23"/>Yahweh has also told me that <char style="add">your wife</char> Jezebel <char style="add">will be killed, and</char> dogs in Jezreel will eat her corpse. <verse eid="1KI 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 21:24"/>The <char style="add">dead bodies of the</char> members of your family who die in this city <char style="add">will not be buried, they</char> will be eaten by dogs, and <char style="add">the corpses of</char> those who die in the fields will be eaten by vultures.”<verse eid="1KI 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 21:25"/>There was no man no man like Ahab who always did things that Yahweh considered to be evil. His wife Jezebel incited/urged him to do <char style="add">many of</char> those things. <verse eid="1KI 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 21:26"/>The most abominable/detestable thing that Ahab did was to worship idols, just like the Amor people-group had done. And that is why Yahweh took the Amor people’s land from them and gave it to the Israelis.<verse eid="1KI 21:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 21:27"/>After Elijah finished talking to Ahab, Ahab tore his clothes <char style="add">to show that he was sorry for all the sins that he had committed</char>. He put on rough clothes that were made from sacks, and he refused to eat anything. He even wore those rough clothes made from sacks when he slept, to show that he was sorry.<verse eid="1KI 21:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 21:28"/>Then Yahweh said this to Elijah: <verse eid="1KI 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 21:29"/>“I have seen [RHQ] that Ahab is now very sorry for all the evil things that he has done. So the things that I promised to do to his <char style="add">family</char> will not happen while he is still alive. I will cause them to happen after his son becomes king. Then those things will happen to his family.” [MTY]<verse eid="1KI 21:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="1KI 22"/>
  <para style="s1">Jehoshaphat talked with Ahab</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1KI 22:1"/>For almost three years there was no war between Syria and Israel. <verse eid="1KI 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1KI 22:2"/>Then King Jehoshaphat, who ruled Judah, went to <char style="add">visit</char> King Ahab, who ruled Israel. <verse eid="1KI 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1KI 22:3"/><char style="add">While they were talking,</char> Ahab said to his officials, “Do you realize that the Syrians are still occupying our city of Ramoth in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>? And we are doing nothing to retake that city!” <verse eid="1KI 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1KI 22:4"/>Then he turned to Jehoshaphat and asked, “Will your <char style="add">army</char> join my <char style="add">army</char> to fight against the people of Ramoth <char style="add">and retake that city</char>?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 22:4">Jehoshaphat replied, “<char style="add">Certainly</char> I <char style="add">will do whatever</char> you <char style="add">want</char>, and you may command my troops. You may take my horses into battle, also.” <verse eid="1KI 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1KI 22:5"/>Then he added, “But we should ask Yahweh first, to find out what he wants us to do.” <verse eid="1KI 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1KI 22:6"/>So Ahab summoned about 400 of his prophets together, and he asked them, “Should my <char style="add">army</char> go to fight the people in Ramoth and retake that city, or not?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 22:6">They answered, “Yes, go <char style="add">and attack them</char>, because God will enable your <char style="add">army</char> to defeat them.”<verse eid="1KI 22:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1KI 22:7"/>But Jehoshaphat asked, “Is there no prophet of Yahweh here whom we can ask?”<verse eid="1KI 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1KI 22:8"/>The King of Israel replied, “There is one man we can talk to. We can ask him if he can find out what Yahweh wants. His name is Micaiah; he is the son of Imlah. But I hate him, because when he ◄prophesies/tells what God says to him► he never says <char style="add">that</char> anything good <char style="add">will happen</char> to me. He always predicts <char style="add">that</char> bad things <char style="add">will happen to me</char>.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 22:8">Jehoshaphat replied, “King Ahab, you should not say that!”<verse eid="1KI 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1KI 22:9"/>So the king of Israel told one of his officers to summon Micaiah immediately.<verse eid="1KI 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Micaiah prophesied against Ahab</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1KI 22:10"/>The king of Israel and the king of Judah were wearing their ◄royal robes/robes that showed that they were kings►. They were sitting on thrones at the place where people threshed grain, near the gate of Samaria <char style="add">city</char>. All of Ahab’s prophets were standing in front of the kings, ◄prophesying/predicting what was going to happen►. <verse eid="1KI 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1KI 22:11"/>One of them, whose name was Zedekiah, the son of Kenaanah, had made from iron <char style="add">something that resembled</char> horns of a bull. Then he proclaimed <char style="add">to Ahab</char>, “This is what Yahweh says: ‘With horns like these your <char style="add">army</char> will keep attacking the Syrians <char style="add">like a bull attacks another animal</char> [MET], until you completely destroy them!’”<verse eid="1KI 22:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1KI 22:12"/>All the <char style="add">other</char> prophets <char style="add">of Ahab</char> agreed. They said, “Yes! If you go up to attack Ramoth <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, you will be successful, because Yahweh will enable you to defeat them!”<verse eid="1KI 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1KI 22:13"/>Meanwhile, the messenger who went to summon Micaiah said to him, “Listen to me! All the other prophets are predicting that the king’s army will defeat the Syrians. So be sure that you agree with them and say ◄what will be favorable/that the king’s army will be successful►.”<verse eid="1KI 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1KI 22:14"/>But Micaiah replied, “As surely as Yahweh lives, I will tell him only what Yahweh tells me to say.”<verse eid="1KI 22:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1KI 22:15"/>When Micaiah came to Ahab, Ahab asked him, “Micaiah, should we go to fight against <char style="add">the people of</char> Ramoth, or not?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 22:15">Micaiah replied, “Sure, go! Yahweh will enable your army to defeat them!” <verse eid="1KI 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1KI 22:16"/>But King Ahab <char style="add">realized that Micaiah was ◄lying/being sarcastic►, so he</char> said to Micaiah, “I have told you [RHQ] many times that you must always tell only the truth when you say what Yahweh <char style="add">has revealed to you</char>!”<verse eid="1KI 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1KI 22:17"/>So Micaiah said to him, “<char style="add">The truth is that</char> in a vision I saw all the troops of Israel scattered on the mountains. They seemed to be like sheep that did not have a shepherd. And Yahweh said, ‘Their master has been killed. So tell them all to go home peacefully.’ ”<verse eid="1KI 22:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1KI 22:18"/>Ahab said to Jehoshaphat, “I told you [RHQ] that he never predicts <char style="add">that</char> anything good <char style="add">will happen to me</char>! He <char style="add">always</char> predicts <char style="add">that</char> bad things <char style="add">will happen to me</char>.”<verse eid="1KI 22:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1KI 22:19"/>But Micaiah continued, saying, “Listen to what Yahweh showed to me! <char style="add">In a vision</char> I saw Yahweh sitting on his throne, with all the armies of heaven surrounding him, on his right side and on his left side. <verse eid="1KI 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1KI 22:20"/>And Yahweh said, ‘Who can persuade Ahab to go to fight against the people of Ramoth, in order that he may be killed there?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 22:20">Some suggested one thing, and others suggested something else. <verse eid="1KI 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1KI 22:21"/>Finally one <char style="add">evil</char> spirit came to Yahweh and said, ‘I can do it!’<verse eid="1KI 22:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1KI 22:22"/>Yahweh asked him, ‘How will you do it?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1KI 22:22">The spirit replied, ‘I will go and inspire all of Ahab’s prophets to tell lies.’ Yahweh said, ‘You will be successful; go and do it!’ <verse eid="1KI 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1KI 22:23"/>So now <char style="add">I tell you that</char> Yahweh has caused all of your prophets to lie to you. Yahweh has decided that something terrible will happen to you.”<verse eid="1KI 22:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1KI 22:24"/>Then Zedekiah walked over to Micaiah and slapped him on his face. He said, “Do you think that Yahweh’s Spirit left me in order to speak to you?” [RHQ]<verse eid="1KI 22:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1KI 22:25"/>Micaiah replied, “You will find out for yourself <char style="add">which of us Yahweh’s Spirit has truly spoken to</char> on the day when you go into a room of some house to hide <char style="add">from the Syrian troops</char>!”<verse eid="1KI 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1KI 22:26"/>King Ahab commanded <char style="add">his soldiers</char>, “Seize Micaiah and take him to Amon, the governor of this city, and to my son Joash. <verse eid="1KI 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1KI 22:27"/>Tell them that I have commanded that they should put this man in prison and give him only bread and water. Do not give him anything else to eat until I return safely from the battle!”<verse eid="1KI 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1KI 22:28"/>Micaiah replied, “If you return safely, <char style="add">it will be clear that</char> it was not Yahweh who told me what to say to you!” Then he said <char style="add">to all those who were standing there</char>, “Do not forget what I have said <char style="add">to King Ahab</char>!”<verse eid="1KI 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ahab died in the battle</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1KI 22:29"/>So the King of Israel and the King of Judah <char style="add">led their armies</char> to Ramoth, in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>. <verse eid="1KI 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1KI 22:30"/>King Ahab said to Jehoshaphat, “I will put on different clothes, <char style="add">in order that no one will recognize that I am the king</char>. But you should wear your ◄royal robe/robe that shows that you are a king►.” So Ahab disguised himself, and they both went into the battle.<verse eid="1KI 22:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1KI 22:31"/>The King of Syria told this to his thirty-two men who were driving the chariots: “Attack only the king of Israel!” <verse eid="1KI 22:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1KI 22:32"/>So when the men who were driving the Syrian chariots saw Jehoshaphat <char style="add">wearing ◄his royal robes/clothes that showed he was the king►</char>, they pursued him. They shouted, “There is the king of Israel!” But when Jehoshaphat cried out, <verse eid="1KI 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1KI 22:33"/>they realized that he was not the king of Israel. So they stopped pursuing him.<verse eid="1KI 22:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1KI 22:34"/>But one <char style="add">Syrian</char> soldier shot an arrow at Ahab, without knowing that it was Ahab. The arrow struck Ahab between the places where the parts of his armor joined together. Ahab told the driver of his chariot, “Turn the chariot around and take me out of here! I have been severely wounded!” <verse eid="1KI 22:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1KI 22:35"/>The battle continued all the day. Ahab was sitting propped up in his chariot, facing the Syrian troops. The blood from his wound ran down to the floor of the chariot. And late in the afternoon he died. <verse eid="1KI 22:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1KI 22:36"/>Just as the sun was going down, someone among the Israeli troops shouted, “<char style="add">The battle is ended!</char> Everyone should return home!”<verse eid="1KI 22:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="1KI 22:37"/>So king Ahab died, and they took his body <char style="add">in the chariot</char> to Samaria <char style="add">city</char> and buried his body there. <verse eid="1KI 22:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1KI 22:38"/>They washed his chariot alongside the pool in Samaria, a pool where the prostitutes bathed. And dogs <char style="add">came and</char> licked the king’s blood, just like Yahweh had predicted would happen.<verse eid="1KI 22:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1KI 22:39"/>The account/record of the other things that happened while Ahab was ruling, and about the palace decorated with much ivory <char style="add">that they built for him</char>, and the cities that were built for him, was written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’. <verse eid="1KI 22:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1KI 22:40"/>When Ahab died, his body was buried where his ancestors were buried. Then his son Ahaziah became king.<verse eid="1KI 22:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoshaphat ruled in Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1KI 22:41"/>Before King Ahab died, when he had been ruling in Israel for four years, Asa’s son Jehoshaphat started to rule in Judah. <verse eid="1KI 22:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1KI 22:42"/>Jehoshaphat was thirty-five years old when he started to rule, and he ruled in Jerusalem for twenty-five years. His mother was Azubah, the daughter of Shilhi. <verse eid="1KI 22:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1KI 22:43"/>Jehoshaphat was a good king, just like his father Asa had been. He did things that pleased Yahweh. But while he was king, he did not remove all the pagan altars <char style="add">that the people had built</char> on the hilltops. So the people continued to offer sacrifices <char style="add">to idols</char> on those altars and burned incense there. <verse eid="1KI 22:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1KI 22:44"/>Jehoshaphat also made <char style="add">a</char> peace <char style="add">agreement</char> with the king of Israel.<verse eid="1KI 22:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1KI 22:45"/>All the other things that happened while Jehoshaphat was ruling, and the great things that he did and the victories his <char style="add">troops</char> won, are written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Judah’. <verse eid="1KI 22:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1KI 22:46"/>Jehoshaphat’s father Asa <char style="add">had tried to expel</char> the male prostitutes that stayed at the pagan shrines, but some of them were still there. Jehoshaphat got rid of them.<verse eid="1KI 22:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="1KI 22:47"/>At that time, there was no king in Edom; a ruler who had been appointed by Jehoshaphat ruled there.<verse eid="1KI 22:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="1KI 22:48"/>Jehoshaphat <char style="add">ordered some Israeli men to</char> build a fleet/group of ships to sail <char style="add">south</char> to <char style="add">the</char> Ophir <char style="add">region</char> to get gold. But they were wrecked at Ezion-Geber/Elath, so the ships never sailed. <verse eid="1KI 22:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1KI 22:49"/>Before the ships were wrecked, Ahab’s son Ahaziah suggested to Jehoshaphat, “Allow my sailors to go with your sailors,” but Jehoshaphat refused.<verse eid="1KI 22:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="1KI 22:50"/>When Jehoshaphat died, his <char style="add">body</char> was buried where his ancestors were buried in <char style="add">Jerusalem,</char> the city where King David <char style="add">had ruled</char>. Then Jehoshaphat’s son Jehoram became king.<verse eid="1KI 22:50"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ahaziah ruled in Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="1KI 22:51"/>Before King Jehoshaphat died, when he had been ruling in Judah for 17 years, Ahab’s son Ahaziah began to rule in Israel. Ahaziah ruled in Samaria for two years. <verse eid="1KI 22:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="1KI 22:52"/>He did many things that Yahweh considered to be evil, doing the <char style="add">evil</char> things that his father and mother had done and the evil things that Jeroboam had done—the king who had led all the Israeli people to sin <char style="add">by worshiping idols</char>. <verse eid="1KI 22:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1KI 22:53"/>Ahaziah bowed in front of Baal’s idol and worshiped it. That caused Yahweh, the God who was the true God of the Israeli people, to become very angry, just as Ahaziah’s father had caused Yahweh to become angry.<verse eid="1KI 22:53"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1KI 22"/>
</usx>
