<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="1SA" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">1 SAMUEL</para>
  <para style="toc1">1 Samuel</para>
  <para style="toc2">1 Samuel</para>
  <para style="toc3">1Sam</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of what happened in Israel from the birth of Samuel to the death of King Saul. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">1 Samuel</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1SA 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel was born</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 1:1"/>There was a man named Elkanah who lived in Ramah <char style="add">town</char> in the hilly area where <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Ephraim lived. His father was Jeroham, his grandfather was Elihu, and his great-grandfather was Tohu. He belonged to the Zuph clan. <verse eid="1SA 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 1:2"/>He had two wives: Hannah and Peninnah. Peninnah had several children, but Hannah had no children.<verse eid="1SA 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 1:3"/>Once every year Elkanah went up <char style="add">with his family</char> from Ramah to Shiloh <char style="add">city</char>. He went there to worship Yahweh, <char style="add">the commander </char> of the armies <char style="add">of angels</char>, and to offer sacrifices to him. The two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, <char style="add">helped their father to do the work as</char> priests of Yahweh there. <verse eid="1SA 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 1:4"/>Each time Elkanah offered sacrifices there, he gave some of the meat to Peninnah and some to each of her sons and daughters. <verse eid="1SA 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 1:5"/>But even though he loved Hannah very much, he gave her only one special amount of meat because Yahweh had not permitted her to give birth to any children. <verse eid="1SA 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 1:6"/>And his other wife, Peninnah, would ridicule Hannah to make her feel miserable, because Yahweh had not allowed her to bear children. <verse eid="1SA 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 1:7"/>This happened every year. When they went up to the temple of Yahweh <char style="add">at Shiloh</char>, Peninnah ridiculed Hannah so much that Hannah cried and would not eat. <verse eid="1SA 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 1:8"/>Then Elkanah would say to her, “Hannah, ◄why are you crying?/please quit crying!► [RHQ] ◄Why are you not eating?/Please eat something!► [RHQ] Why are you so upset/sad? You have me; is that not more important to you than if you had ten sons? (OR, I <char style="add">love you</char> more than your sons <char style="add">would love you</char>, even if you had ten sons.)”<verse eid="1SA 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 1:9"/>One year, after they had finished eating and drinking at Shiloh, Hannah stood up <char style="add">to pray</char>. Eli the priest was nearby, sitting on a chair by the doorway of the sacred tent of Yahweh. <verse eid="1SA 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 1:10"/>Hannah was very distressed, and she cried very sorrowfully as she prayed to Yahweh. <verse eid="1SA 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 1:11"/>She made a vow saying, “O Almighty Commander of the armies of angels, if you will look at me and see how miserable I am, and think about me and allow me to give birth to a son, then I will dedicate him to you <char style="add">to serve you</char> for the rest of his life. And <char style="add">to show that he is dedicated to you</char>, ◄no one will ever <char style="add">be allowed to</char> cut his hair/his hair will never be cut►.”<verse eid="1SA 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 1:12"/>As she was praying like that to Yahweh, Eli the priest saw Hannah’s lips <char style="add">moving as she was praying</char>. <verse eid="1SA 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 1:13"/>But Hannah was only praying silently; she was not making any sound. So Eli thought that she was drunk. <verse eid="1SA 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 1:14"/>He said to her, “How long will you continue to get drunk [RHQ]? ◄Throw away your wine/Quit drinking wine►!”<verse eid="1SA 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 1:15"/>Hannah replied, “Sir, I am not drunk! I have not been drinking wine or any other alcoholic drink. I feel very distressed and I have been telling Yahweh about how I feel. <verse eid="1SA 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 1:16"/>Do not think that I am a worthless/wicked woman! I have been praying like this because I am very distressed [DOU].”<verse eid="1SA 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 1:17"/>Eli replied, “I wish/desire that things will go well for you. I desire that God, the one we Israeli people <char style="add">worship</char>, will give you what you requested from him.”<verse eid="1SA 1:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 1:18"/>She replied, “I want you to think highly/well about me.” Then she returned <char style="add">to her family</char> and after she ate something, her face no longer looked sad.<verse eid="1SA 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 1:19"/>Early the next morning, Elkanah and his family got up and worshiped Yahweh <char style="add">again</char>, and then they returned to their home at Ramah. Elkanah ◄slept with/had sex with► Hannah. Then Yahweh answered her prayer, <verse eid="1SA 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 1:20"/>and she became pregnant and gave birth to a son. She named him Samuel, <char style="add">which sounds like the words in the Hebrew language that mean ‘heard by God’</char>, because she said “Yahweh <char style="add">heard me when</char> I requested from him <char style="add">a son</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hannah dedicated Samuel to Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 1:21"/>The following year, Elkanah again went up <char style="add">to Shiloh</char> with his family to make the kind of sacrifice he made each year, and also to give a special offering to God that he had promised <char style="add">to give him previously</char>. <verse eid="1SA 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 1:22"/>But Hannah did not go <char style="add">with them</char>. She said to her husband, “After I have weaned the baby, I will take him <char style="add">to Shiloh and present him</char> to Yahweh, and he will stay there for the rest of his life.”<verse eid="1SA 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 1:23"/>Elkanah said, “Do what seems the best to you. Stay here until you have weaned him. What I desire is that Yahweh will <char style="add">enable you to</char> do what you have promised.” So Hannah stayed at home and nursed her son until she weaned him.<verse eid="1SA 1:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 1:24"/>After she weaned him, even though Samuel was very young, she took him to the temple/house of Yahweh at Shiloh. <char style="add">To offer as a sacrifice</char>, she took along a three-year-old bull, <char style="add">a sack containing</char> ◄20 pounds/9 kg.► of flour, and a container of wine. <verse eid="1SA 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 1:25"/>After the priest had slaughtered the bull <char style="add">and offered it to Yahweh on the altar</char>, Hannah and Elkanah brought the boy to Eli. <verse eid="1SA 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 1:26"/>Then Hannah said to him, “Sir, ◄Do you remember me?/I solemnly affirm►, I am the woman who prayed as I stood here beside you <char style="add">several years ago</char>. <verse eid="1SA 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 1:27"/>I prayed that Yahweh would enable me to give birth to a child, and this is the child whom I requested Yahweh to give me. <verse eid="1SA 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 1:28"/>So now I am presenting him to Yahweh. He will belong to Yahweh as long as he lives.” Then Elkanah <char style="add">and his family</char> worshiped Yahweh there.<verse eid="1SA 1:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1SA 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 2:1"/>Then Hannah prayed, saying,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:1">“I rejoice in <char style="add">what</char> you, Yahweh<char style="add">, have done</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:1">I am strong [MET] because I belong to you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:1">I ◄laugh at/ridicule► my enemies,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:1">because you, Yahweh have rescued me <char style="add">from being taunted by them</char>.<verse eid="1SA 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 2:2"/>There is no one who is holy like you, Yahweh.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:2">There is no other god like you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:2">There is no one like you, our God, who can protect us <char style="add">as though you were putting us beneath</char> a huge rock <char style="add">where we can hide from danger</char>.<verse eid="1SA 2:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 2:3"/>
    <char style="add">You people who oppose God</char>, stop boasting!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:3">Yahweh is a God who knows <char style="add">everything</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:3">and he will evaluate/judge everyone’s actions.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:3">So don’t speak so arrogantly!<verse eid="1SA 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 2:4"/>Yahweh, you break the bows/weapons of mighty soldiers,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:4">and you give strength to those who stumble <char style="add">because of being weak</char>.<verse eid="1SA 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 2:5"/>Many people who previously had plenty to eat, now have to work for other people <char style="add">to earn money</char> to buy food,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:5">but many who were always hungry are not hungry any more.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:5">The woman who did not have any children before, now has given birth to many/seven children,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:5">and the woman who had many children before, now is very lonely <char style="add">because they have all died</char>.<verse eid="1SA 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 2:6"/>Yahweh, you cause some people to die,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:6">and you restore some people who are almost dead.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:6">For some people, <char style="add">it seems that they will soon</char> go to where the dead people are, but you cause them to become healthy again.<verse eid="1SA 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 2:7"/>Yahweh, you cause some people to be poor and you cause some people to be rich,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:7">you humble some people and you honor some people.<verse eid="1SA 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 2:8"/>
    <char style="add">Sometimes</char> you lift poor people up so that they are no longer <char style="add">despondent, sitting in the dust,</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:8">or sitting on heaps of ashes;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:8">you cause them to sit next to princes;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:8">you cause them to sit on chairs/thrones where people who are highly honored sit.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:8">Yahweh, you are the one who laid the foundations of the earth,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:8">and you have set the whole world on those foundations.<verse eid="1SA 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 2:9"/>You will protect your loyal/faithful people [SYN],</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:9">but you will cause the wicked to die [EUP] and descend to the dark <char style="add">place where dead people are</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:9">We do not defeat <char style="add">our enemies</char> by our own strength;<verse eid="1SA 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 2:10"/>Yahweh, you will break into pieces those who oppose you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:10">You will cause thunder in the sky to show that you ◄oppose/are angry with► them.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 2:10">Yahweh, you will judge <char style="add">people everywhere, even those who live in</char> the most remote places on the earth.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 2:10">You will give strength to the king whom you will appoint, and give him great power <char style="add">over his enemies</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 2:11"/>Then Elkanah <char style="add">and his family</char> returned to Ramah, but Samuel, the little boy, stayed to help Eli the priest serve Yahweh.<verse eid="1SA 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Eli’s sons were wicked</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 2:12"/>Eli’s two sons<char style="add">, who were also priests,</char> were very wicked. They did not revere (OR, respect/obey) Yahweh. <verse eid="1SA 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 2:13"/>While the people were boiling the meat from their sacrifices <char style="add">in the huge pot at the temple</char>, one of Eli’s sons, <char style="add">would send his servant to come with a large three-pronged fork in his hand</char>. <verse eid="1SA 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 2:14"/><char style="add">He</char> would stick the fork into <char style="add">the meat in</char> the pot, and whatever meat fastened onto the fork, he would take <char style="add">and give it</char> to the priest who sent him. Eli’s sons did this to all the Israeli people who came to Shiloh <char style="add">to offer sacrifices</char>. <verse eid="1SA 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 2:15"/>Furthermore, before the fat <char style="add">on the meat</char> was <char style="add">cut off and</char> and burned <char style="add">as a sacrifice to Yahweh</char>, the servant of the priest would <char style="add">sometimes</char> come to the man who was making the sacrifice and say to him, “Give me some meat <char style="add">now to take</char> to the priest for him to roast! He wants raw meat; he does not want boiled meat.”<verse eid="1SA 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 2:16"/>If the man said to the servant, “Let the priests <char style="add">cut off and</char> burn the fat first; then you can take what you want,” the servant would reply, “No, give it to me now; if you do not give it to me, I will take it forcefully!”<verse eid="1SA 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 2:17"/>Yahweh considered that the young <char style="add">sons of Eli</char> were committing a very great sin, because they were treating very disrespectfully the offerings that were being given to Yahweh.<verse eid="1SA 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 2:18"/>As for Samuel, who was still a very young boy, he continued to do work for Yahweh, wearing a little sacred linen vest <char style="add">like the Supreme Priest wore</char>. <verse eid="1SA 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 2:19"/>Each year his mother made a <char style="add">new</char> little robe for him and took it to him when she went up <char style="add">to Shiloh</char> with her husband to offer a sacrifice. <verse eid="1SA 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 2:20"/>Then Eli would <char style="add">ask God to</char> bless Elkanah and his wife, and he would say to Elkanah, “I hope/desire that Yahweh will enable your wife to give birth to other children, to take the place of the one whom she dedicated to Yahweh.” Then Elkanah and his family would return home. <verse eid="1SA 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 2:21"/>And Yahweh was very kind to Hannah, and enabled her to give birth to three <char style="add">other</char> sons and two daughters. Their son Samuel grew up while he was doing work for Yahweh <char style="add">in the Sacred Tent</char>.<verse eid="1SA 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Eli warned his sons</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 2:22"/>Eli became very old. He often heard about all the <char style="add">evil</char> things that his sons were doing to the Israeli people. He heard that they <char style="add">sometimes</char> ◄slept with/had sex with► the women who worked at the entrance to the tent where <char style="add">God</char> spoke to <char style="add">his people</char>. <verse eid="1SA 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 2:23"/>He said to them, “◄It is terrible that you do such things!/Why do you do such things?► [RHQ] Many people keep telling me about the evil things that you do. <verse eid="1SA 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 2:24"/>My sons, stop it! The reports <char style="add">about you</char> that the people who belong to Yahweh tell others are terrible [EUP]! <verse eid="1SA 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 2:25"/>If one person sins against another person, God can ◄intercede/act as a referee► between them. But if someone sins against Yahweh, no one can [RHQ] ◄intercede/act as a referee► between them!” But Eli’s sons would not listen to what their father said. This was because Yahweh had decided <char style="add">that someone should </char>kill them.<verse eid="1SA 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A prophet warned what would happen to Eli and his family</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 2:26"/>The boy Samuel continued to grow up, and the things that he did pleased Yahweh and the people. <verse eid="1SA 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 2:27"/>One day, a prophet came to Eli and told him, “This is what Yahweh has told me: ‘When your ancestors were slaves of the king of Egypt, I appeared to Aaron. <verse eid="1SA 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 2:28"/>From all the tribes of the Israeli people, I chose him <char style="add">and his male descendants</char> to be priests for me. I appointed them to go up to my altar, to burn incense, to wear a sacred apron <char style="add">as they worked</char> for me. And I declared that they could take <char style="add">and eat some of the meat</char> that the Israeli people burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="1SA 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 2:29"/>So why do you show disrespect for the sacrifices and offerings that I commanded <char style="add">the people to bring</char> to me [RHQ]? You are honoring your sons more than you are honoring me, by allowing them to get fat from eating the best parts of all the sacrifices that the Israeli people bring to me!’<verse eid="1SA 2:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 2:30"/>“Therefore, this is what Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, declares: ‘I definitely promised that Aaron and his descendants would continue to serve [IDM] me forever.’ But now I declare this: ‘It will not continue like that! I will honor those who honor me, but I will despise those who despise me. <verse eid="1SA 2:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 2:31"/>Listen carefully! There will soon be a time when I will cause all the strong <char style="add">young men</char> in your family to die. The result will be that no men in your family will <char style="add">live long enough to</char> become old men. <verse eid="1SA 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 2:32"/>You will be distressed and envious as you see the blessings that I will give to <char style="add">the other people in</char> Israel. And <char style="add">I repeat that</char> no men in your family will ever live long enough to become old men. <verse eid="1SA 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 2:33"/>There is one of your descendants whom I will spare, and not prevent him from serving me as a priest. But he will become blind, and then he will always be sad and grieving. But all your other descendants will die violently. <verse eid="1SA 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 2:34"/>And your two sons, Hophni and Phinehas, will both die on the same day. And that will prove to you <char style="add">that all that I have said will come true/happen</char>.<verse eid="1SA 2:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 2:35"/>‘ have chosen another man to be my priest. He is one who will serve me faithfully: He will do everything I want [DOU] him to do. And I will enable him to have many descendants [IDM] who will be priests and will always serve me by helping the king whom I will choose. <verse eid="1SA 2:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 2:36"/>All of your descendants who remain alive will have to go to that priest and ask him to give them money and food, and they will each have to say, “Please allow me to help the other priests, in order that I may <char style="add">earn some money to</char> buy some food.”’”<verse eid="1SA 2:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1SA 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh Called Samuel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 3:1"/>
    <char style="add">While he was still a</char> boy, Samuel was working for Yahweh while Eli supervised him. At that time there were very few messages <char style="add">that anyone received</char> from Yahweh, and very few people saw visions <char style="add">that Yahweh gave them</char>.<verse eid="1SA 3:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 3:2"/>By that time Eli’s eyes were very weak; he was almost blind. <char style="add">One night</char> he was sleeping in his room, <verse eid="1SA 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 3:3"/>and Samuel was sleeping in the sacred tent, where the chest that contained the Ten Commandments was kept. While the sacred lamp was still burning, <verse eid="1SA 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 3:4"/>Yahweh called, “Samuel! Samuel!” Samuel replied, “I’m here!”<verse eid="1SA 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 3:5"/>Then he <char style="add">got up and</char> ran to Eli. He said to him, “I am here, because you called me!” But Eli replied, “No, I did not call you. Go back to your bed.” So Samuel went and lay down again.<verse eid="1SA 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 3:6"/>Then Yahweh called again, “Samuel!” So Samuel got up again and went to Eli and said, “I am here, because you called me!” But Eli said, “No, my son, I did not call you. Go back and lie down.”<verse eid="1SA 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 3:7"/>At that time Samuel did not yet know <char style="add">that </char> Yahweh <char style="add">could speak to him</char>, because Yahweh had not previously revealed anything to him.<verse eid="1SA 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 3:8"/>
    <char style="add">After Samuel lay down again</char>, Yahweh called him a third time. So again Samuel got up and went to Eli and said, “I am here, because you called me!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 3:8">Then Eli realized that it was Yahweh who was calling the boy. <verse eid="1SA 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 3:9"/>So he said to Samuel, “Go and lie down again. If someone calls you again, say ‘Speak to me, Yahweh, because I am listening!’ ” So Samuel went and lay down again. <verse eid="1SA 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 3:10"/>Then Yahweh came and stood there and called as he had done the other times, “Samuel! Samuel!” Then Samuel said, “Speak to me, because I am listening!”<verse eid="1SA 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 3:11"/>Then Yahweh said to Samuel, “Listen carefully. I am about to do something here in Israel that will shock/horrify [IDM] everyone who hears about it. <verse eid="1SA 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 3:12"/>When that happens, I will punish Eli and his family. I will do to them everything that I said that I would do. <verse eid="1SA 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 3:13"/>His sons have shown great disrespect for me by the disgraceful things they have done, and Eli did not restrain them. So I told him that I would punish his family forever. <verse eid="1SA 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 3:14"/>I solemnly promised to Eli’s family, ‘You will never be able to avoid the consequences for your sin, even if you give me sacrifices or offerings.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 3:15"/>Samuel lay down again until morning. Then he got up and opened the doors of the Sacred Tent <char style="add">as usual</char>. He was afraid to tell Eli about the vision <char style="add">that Yahweh had given him</char>. <verse eid="1SA 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 3:16"/>But Eli called him and said, “Samuel, my son!” Samuel answered, “I am here!”<verse eid="1SA 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 3:17"/>Eli asked him, “What was it that Yahweh told you? Do not conceal it! I want God to punish you severely if you do not tell me everything that he said to you.”<verse eid="1SA 3:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 3:18"/>So Samuel told him everything. He did not refuse to tell him anything. Then Eli said, “He is Yahweh. I am willing for him to do what he thinks is best.”<verse eid="1SA 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 3:19"/>As Samuel grew up, Yahweh helped him, and caused everything to ◄come true/happen► that Samuel predicted. <verse eid="1SA 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 3:20"/>So all the people of Israel, from the northern end of the country to the southern end, realized that Samuel was truly a prophet of Yahweh. <verse eid="1SA 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 3:21"/>Yahweh continued to appear to Samuel in Shiloh and give messages to him.<verse eid="1SA 3:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1SA 4"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 4:1"/>And Samuel told to all the people of Israel the messages that God gave him.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="1SA 4:1">The Philistines captured the sacred chest</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 4:1">At that time the Israeli army went to fight against the army of the Philistine people. The Israeli army set up their tents at Ebenezer, and the Philistine army set up their tents at Aphek. <verse eid="1SA 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 4:2"/>The Philistine army attacked the Israeli army, and as the battle continued, the Philistines defeated the Israelis and killed about 4,000 of their soldiers. <verse eid="1SA 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 4:3"/>When the remaining Israeli soldiers returned to their camp, the Israeli elders/leaders said, “Why did Yahweh allow the Philistine army to defeat us today? We should bring the chest that contains the Ten Commandments here from Shiloh, in order that Yahweh will go with us <char style="add">when we go to the battle again, and</char> in order that our enemies will not defeat us again!”<verse eid="1SA 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 4:4"/>So the soldiers did that. They sent some men to Shiloh, and those men brought back the chest that contained the Ten Commandments. <char style="add">They thought that if they did that, Yahweh would help them. They believed that</char> Yahweh sat on a throne between the statues of winged creatures <char style="add">that were on top of</char> the chest that Yahweh Almighty <char style="add">had given them</char>. The two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, went with them.<verse eid="1SA 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 4:5"/>When the Israeli people saw <char style="add">the men bringing</char> the box into their camp, they were so happy that they shouted loudly. They shouted so loudly that they made the ground shake! <verse eid="1SA 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 4:6"/>The Philistines asked, “What are the people in the Hebrew camp shouting about?” Someone told them that they were shouting because the chest that contained the Ten Commandments of Yahweh had been brought to them. <verse eid="1SA 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 4:7"/>Then the Philistines became very afraid. They said, “One of the Israelis’ gods has come into their camp <char style="add">to help them</char> We are in big trouble now! Nothing like this has happened to us before! <verse eid="1SA 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 4:8"/>◄Who can/Can anyone► save us from their powerful gods [RHQ]? They are the gods who struck the people of Egypt with many plagues <char style="add">before the Israelis left Egypt and traveled</char> through the desert. <verse eid="1SA 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 4:9"/>You Philistine men, be courageous! Fight very hard! If you do not do that, <char style="add">they will defeat us, and then</char> you will become their slaves, just like they have been our slaves previously!”<verse eid="1SA 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 4:10"/>So the Philistine men fought very hard, and they defeated the Israelis. They killed 30,000 Israeli soldiers, and the other Israeli soldiers fled and ran away to their tents. <verse eid="1SA 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 4:11"/>The Philistines captured the sacred chest, and they killed Eli’s two sons, Hophni and Phinehas.<verse eid="1SA 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Eli died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 4:12"/>On that same day, one man of the tribe <char style="add">descended from</char> Benjamin tore his clothes and threw dirt on his head <char style="add">to show that he was very sad</char>. He ran from the place where the armies were fighting, and he arrived at Shiloh late <char style="add">that afternoon</char>. <verse eid="1SA 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 4:13"/>Eli was waiting beside the road. <char style="add">He wanted to hear news about the battle, and</char> he was also very anxious to know if anything bad had happened to God’s sacred chest. When the messenger arrived and told people what had happened, everyone in the town started to cry loudly.<verse eid="1SA 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 4:14"/>Eli asked, “Why are they making all that noise?” The messenger ran over to Eli and told him the news.<verse eid="1SA 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 4:15"/>At that time, Eli was 98 years old, and he was blind. <verse eid="1SA 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 4:16"/>The messenger said to Eli, “I have just come from where the armies were fighting. I left there earlier today.” Eli asked, “What happened?”<verse eid="1SA 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 4:17"/>The man replied, “The Philistines defeated our Israeli army. They killed thousands of our soldiers, and the others ran away. The Philistines killed your two sons, Hophni and Phinehas. They also captured God’s sacred chest.”<verse eid="1SA 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 4:18"/>Eli was very old, and he was very fat; and when he heard what had happened to the sacred chest, he fell backward from his chair beside the town gate. His neck was broken and he died. He had led the Israeli people for 40 years before he died.<verse eid="1SA 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 4:19"/>The wife/widow of Eli’s son Phinehas was pregnant, and it was almost time for her to give birth to her baby. When she heard that God’s sacred chest had been captured and that her husband and her father-in-law were dead, her labor pains suddenly began. She quickly gave birth to a boy. <verse eid="1SA 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 4:20"/>The women who were helping her tried to encourage her by saying to her, “You have given birth to a son!” But she did not pay any attention [DOU] to what they said.<verse eid="1SA 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 4:21"/>She named the boy Ichabod, which means ‘no glory’, because she said, “<char style="add">God’s</char> glory has departed from Israel.” She said that because God’s sacred chest had been captured and because her husband and her father-in-law had died. <verse eid="1SA 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 4:22"/>She said, “<char style="add">God’s</char> glory has left Israel, because God’s sacred chest has been captured!” And then she died.<verse eid="1SA 4:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1SA 5"/>
  <para style="s1">What happened when the sacred chest stayed among the Philistines</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 5:1"/>After the army of the Philistia people-group captured God’s sacred chest in Ebenezer <char style="add">town</char>, they took it to Ashdod <char style="add">which is one of their biggest cities</char>. <verse eid="1SA 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 5:2"/>They carried it into the temple of <char style="add">their god</char> Dagon, and placed it alongside a statue of Dagon. <verse eid="1SA 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 5:3"/>But early the next morning, when the people of Ashdod <char style="add">went to see it, they saw that</char> the statue had fallen on its face in front of Yahweh’s sacred chest! So they set the statue up in its place again. <verse eid="1SA 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 5:4"/>But the following morning, <char style="add">they saw that</char> it had fallen down in front of the sacred chest again. But this time, the statue’s head and hands had broken off, and were lying in the doorway. Only its body remained intact/unbroken. <verse eid="1SA 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 5:5"/>That is the reason that since that time, the priests of Dagon and everyone else who enters the temple of Dagon in Ashdod do not step on the doorsill <char style="add">where the hands and head of Dagon fell</char>.<verse eid="1SA 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 5:6"/>Then Yahweh [SYN] powerfully caused the people of Ashdod and the people who lived in nearby villages to have ◄a very great plague/serious illness► of tumors. <verse eid="1SA 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 5:7"/>The men of Ashdod realized why this was happening, and they cried out, “The god of the Israeli people is punishing us and is also punishing our god Dagon. So we cannot allow the sacred chest of the god of the Israelis to remain here!” <verse eid="1SA 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 5:8"/>They summoned the five kings of the Philistia people-group, and asked them, “What should we do with the sacred chest of the god of the Israelis?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 5:8">The kings replied, “Take the sacred chest to Gath <char style="add">city</char>.” So they moved it to Gath. <verse eid="1SA 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 5:9"/>But after they took it to Gath, Yahweh powerfully struck the people of that city also, with the result that many men, including young men and old men, got tumors on their skin. Then the people became very afraid. <verse eid="1SA 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 5:10"/>So they took the sacred chest to Ekron <char style="add">city</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 5:10">But when the men carried the sacred chest into Ekron, the people there cried out, “Why are you bringing the sacred chest of the God of the Israelis into our city [RHQ]? <char style="add">By doing that</char> you will cause us and the rest of our people to die!” <verse eid="1SA 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 5:11"/>The people were terrified/in panic because <char style="add">they knew that</char> God was starting to punish them severely. So they summoned the <char style="add">five</char> kings of the Philistia people-group again, and <char style="add">pleaded with them</char>, saying, “Take this sacred chest of the god of the Israelis back to its own place! If you do not do that quickly, we will all die!” <verse eid="1SA 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 5:12"/>Some of the people in Ekron had already died, and the rest of the people were suffering because of tumors on their skin. So they all cried out to their gods [MTY] <char style="add">to help them</char>.<verse eid="1SA 5:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="1SA 6"/>
  <para style="s1">They returned the sacred chest to the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 6:1"/>The people of Philistia kept God’s sacred chest in their area for seven months. <verse eid="1SA 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 6:2"/>Then they summoned their priests and their ◄diviners/men who practice rituals to find out what would happen in the future►. They asked them, “What should we do with the sacred chest of Yahweh? Tell us how we should send it back to its own land.”<verse eid="1SA 6:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 6:3"/>Those men replied, “Send with it an offering <char style="add">to show Yahweh that you know that you are</char> guilty <char style="add">for having captured the chest</char>, in order that the plague will stop. If you do that, and then if you are healed, you will know that Yahweh is the one who caused you to experience the plague.”<verse eid="1SA 6:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 6:4"/>The people of Philistia asked, “What kind of offering should we send?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 6:4">The men replied, “Make five gold models of the tumors on your skin, and five gold models of rats. Make five of each because that is the same number as the number of your kings, and because the plague has struck both you people and your five kings. <verse eid="1SA 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 6:5"/>Make models that represent the rats and the tumors that are ruining your land. Make them in order to honor the god of the Israeli people. If you do that, perhaps he will stop punishing [IDM] you, and your gods, and your land. <verse eid="1SA 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 6:6"/>Do not be [RHQ] stubborn [IDM] like the Egyptians and their king were. <char style="add">They did not do what the Israelis’ god told them to do, so he punished them</char>. After the Israelis’ god finished punishing them very severely, they were glad to allow the Israelis to leave their country [RHQ].<verse eid="1SA 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 6:7"/>“So you must build a new cart. Then get two cows that have very recently given birth to calves. They must be cows that have never been hitched to a cart [MTY]. Hitch those cows to the new cart, and take the calves away from their mothers. <verse eid="1SA 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 6:8"/>Put the Israelis’ god’s sacred chest on the cart. Also put in the cart the five gold models of the tumors on your skin and the five gold models of rats. Put them in a small box alongside the sacred chest. They will be an offering to show that you know that you deserved to be punished <char style="add">for capturing the sacred chest</char>. Then send <char style="add">the cows</char> down the road, <char style="add">pulling</char> the cart. <verse eid="1SA 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 6:9"/><char style="add">Watch the cart as the cows pull it</char>. If they pull it to Beth-Shemesh <char style="add">town</char> in Israel, we will know that it was the Israelis’ god who caused us to experience this plague. But if they do not take it there, we will know that it was not the god [MTY] of the Israelis who has punished us. We will know that it just happened.”<verse eid="1SA 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 6:10"/>So the people did what the priests and men who predicted what would happen in the future told them to do. They <char style="add">made</char> a cart <char style="add">and</char> hitched two cows to it. They took the calves from their mothers. <verse eid="1SA 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 6:11"/>They put in the cart Yahweh’s sacred chest and the box with the models of the gold rats and the tumors. <verse eid="1SA 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 6:12"/>Then the cows started walking, and they went straight toward Beth-Shemesh. They stayed on the road, and were mooing all the time. They did not turn to the left or to the right. The five kings of the Philistia area followed the cows until they reached the edge of Beth-Shemesh.<verse eid="1SA 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 6:13"/>At that time, the people of Beth-Shemesh were harvesting wheat in the valley <char style="add">outside the city</char>. <char style="add">When the cows came along the road</char>, they looked up and saw the sacred chest. They were extremely happy to see it. <verse eid="1SA 6:13"/><verse number="14-15" style="v" sid="1SA 6:14-15"/>The cows pulled the cart into the field of a man named Joshua, and they stopped alongside a large rock. Several men from the tribe of Levi lifted from the cart the sacred chest and the box containing the gold models of the rats and the tumors, and they put them all on the large rock. Then the people smashed the cart and kindled a fire with the wood <char style="add">from which the cart had been made</char>. They slaughtered the cows and burned their bodies/carcasses on the fire to be an offering for Yahweh that would be completely burned. That day the people of Beth-Shemesh offered to Yahweh <char style="add">many</char> sacrifices that were completely burned, and <char style="add">other</char> sacrifices. <verse eid="1SA 6:14-15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 6:16"/>The five kings from the Philistia area watched all this, and then they returned to Ekron, that same day.<verse eid="1SA 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 6:17"/>The five gold models of tumors that they sent to be an offering to Yahweh to show that they knew that they deserved to be punished were gifts from <char style="add">those five kings who were rulers of</char> Ashdod, Gaza, Ashkelon, Gath, and Ekron <char style="add">cities</char>. <verse eid="1SA 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 6:18"/>The models of the five gold rats were gifts from the people of those five cities and the surrounding towns. The large rock at Beth-Shemesh, on which the <char style="add">men of the tribe of Levi</char> set the sacred chest, is still there in the field that belonged to Joshua. When people see it, they remember <char style="add">what happened there</char>.<verse eid="1SA 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 6:19"/>But seventy men from Beth-Shemesh looked into Yahweh’s sacred chest, and because of that, Yahweh caused them to die. Then the people mourned very much because Yahweh punished [IDM] those men like that. <verse eid="1SA 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 6:20"/>They said, “No one [RHQ] can ◄resist the power of/stand in the presence of► Yahweh, our holy God, <char style="add">and remain alive</char>! Where can we send the sacred chest?”<verse eid="1SA 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 6:21"/>They sent messengers to the people of Kiriath-Jearim <char style="add">city</char> to tell them, “The people of Philistia have returned Yahweh’s sacred chest to us! Come here and take it away!”<verse eid="1SA 6:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="1SA 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 7:1"/>
    <char style="add">When</char> the men of Kiriath-Jearim <char style="add">received that message, they</char> came to Beth-Shemesh and took the sacred chest of Yahweh. They took it to the house of Abinadab, which was on a hillside. They appointed Abinadab’s son Eleazar to take care of the chest.<verse eid="1SA 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 7:2"/>The sacred chest stayed in Kiriath-Jearim for a long time—a total of 20 years. During that time all the people of Israel mourned <char style="add">because it seemed that</char> Yahweh <char style="add">had abandoned them</char> (OR, <char style="add">and then they asked</char> Yahweh <char style="add">to help them</char>).<verse eid="1SA 7:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh rescued the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 7:3"/>Then Samuel said to all the Israeli people, “If you truly [IDM] want to act like Yahweh’s people should, you must get rid of your statues of <char style="add">the goddess</char> Astarte and the idols/statues of all the other foreign gods. You must decide to serve/worship only Yahweh. If you do that, he will rescue you from <char style="add">the power of</char> [MTY] the Philistia people.” <verse eid="1SA 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 7:4"/>So the Israelis got rid of all their statues of the gods Baal and Astarte, and they worshiped only Yahweh.<verse eid="1SA 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 7:5"/>Then Samuel told them, “All you Israeli people must gather with me at Mizpah. Then I will pray to Yahweh for you.” <verse eid="1SA 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 7:6"/>So they gathered at Mizpah, which was the town where Samuel previously was the leader of the Israeli people. They had a big ceremony there. They drew water <char style="add">from a well</char>, and poured the water on the ground while Yahweh watched. <char style="add">To show that they were sorry for having worshiped idols</char>, they did not eat any food on that day, and they confessed that they had sinned against Yahweh.<verse eid="1SA 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 7:7"/>When the kings of the Philistia area heard that the Israeli people had gathered at Mizpah, they led their armies there to attack the Israelis. When the Israelis found out that the Philistia army was approaching them, they became very afraid. <verse eid="1SA 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 7:8"/>They told Samuel, “Pray to Yahweh to rescue us from the Philistia army [MTY], and do not stop pleading!” <verse eid="1SA 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 7:9"/>So Samuel took a very young lamb <char style="add">and killed it</char> and offered it to Yahweh to be a sacrifice that was completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. Then he prayed and pleaded that Yahweh <char style="add">would help</char> the Israelis, and Yahweh did help them.<verse eid="1SA 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 7:10"/>While Samuel was burning the offering, the Philistia army came near to attack the Israelis. But Yahweh caused it to thunder very loudly. The soldiers of the Philistia army became very frightened, and then they ◄became confused/did not know what to do►. So the Israelis were able to defeat them. <verse eid="1SA 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 7:11"/>The Israeli men ran out of Mizpah and pursued the Philistia soldiers almost to Beth-Car <char style="add">town</char>, and killed many Philistia soldiers while they were trying to run away.<verse eid="1SA 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 7:12"/>After that happened, Samuel took a large stone and set it up between Mizpah and Jeshanah <char style="add">towns</char>. He named the stone ‘Ebenezer’, <char style="add">which means ‘stone of help’</char>, because he said “Yahweh has helped us until the present time.” <verse eid="1SA 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 7:13"/>So the Philistia people were defeated, and for a long time they did not enter the Israeli land <char style="add">to attack them</char> again. During the time that Samuel was alive, Yahweh powerfully protected [MTY] <char style="add">the Israeli people</char> from <char style="add">being attacked by</char> the Philistia army.<verse eid="1SA 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 7:14"/>The Israeli army was able to capture again the Israeli villages between Ekron and Gath that the Philistia army had captured before. The Israelis were also able to take again the other areas around those cities that the Philistia army had taken <char style="add">from the Israelis</char> previously. And there was peace between the Israelis and the Amor people-group.<verse eid="1SA 7:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 7:15"/>Samuel continued to be the leader of the Israeli people until he died. <verse eid="1SA 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 7:16"/>As long as he was alive, every year he traveled back and forth between Bethel and Gilgal and Mizpah <char style="add">cities</char>. In those cities he listened to disputes between people and made decisions about them. <verse eid="1SA 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 7:17"/>After he listened to disputes and made decisions in each of those towns, he returned to his home at Ramah, and he would listen to people’s disputes there, also, <char style="add">and make decisions about them</char>. And he built an altar at Ramah <char style="add">to offer sacrifices</char> to Yahweh.<verse eid="1SA 7:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="1SA 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis asked for a king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 8:1"/>When Samuel became old, he appointed his two sons, Joel and Abijah, to lead/rule the people of Israel. <verse eid="1SA 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 8:2"/>They judged people’s disputes/cases in Beersheba <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="1SA 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 8:3"/>But they were not like their father. They wanted only to get a lot of money. They accepted bribes, and they did not make honest decisions about people’s disputes/cases.<verse eid="1SA 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 8:4"/>Finally, the Israeli leaders met at Ramah <char style="add">town to discuss the matter</char> with Samuel. <verse eid="1SA 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 8:5"/>They said to him, “Listen! You are now old, and your sons are not like you. Appoint a king to rule over us, like the kings that other countries have!”<verse eid="1SA 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 8:6"/>Samuel was very unhappy with them for requesting that, so he prayed to Yahweh about it. <verse eid="1SA 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 8:7"/>Yahweh replied, “Do what they have requested you to do. But ◄<char style="add">do not think/the truth is not</char>► that you are the one whom they are really rejecting. I have been their king, and I am the one they are really rejecting. <verse eid="1SA 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 8:8"/>Ever since I brought them out of Egypt, they have rejected me, and they have worshiped other gods. And now they are also rejecting you in the same way. <verse eid="1SA 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 8:9"/>Do what they are asking you to do. But warn/tell them about how their kings will act toward them!”<verse eid="1SA 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 8:10"/>So Samuel told those people what Yahweh had said. <verse eid="1SA 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 8:11"/>He said, “If a king rules over you, this is what he will do to you: He will force many of your sons to join the army. He will make <char style="add">some of</char> them run in front of his chariots <char style="add">to clear people out of his way</char>. <verse eid="1SA 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 8:12"/><char style="add">Some of</char> them will be commanders of his soldiers, but others will work for him like slaves. He will force some of them to plow his fields and <char style="add">then later</char> harvest his crops. He will force others to make his weapons and equipment for his chariots. <verse eid="1SA 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 8:13"/>The king will take <char style="add">some of</char> your daughters <char style="add">from you and force them</char> to make perfumes for him and cook food for him and bake <char style="add">bread for him</char>. <verse eid="1SA 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 8:14"/>He will take your best fields and vineyards and olive tree groves/orchards, and give them to his own officials. <verse eid="1SA 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 8:15"/>He will take a tenth of your harvests and distribute it among the officers and servants <char style="add">who work in</char> his <char style="add">palace</char>. <verse eid="1SA 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 8:16"/>He will take from you your male and female servants, your best cattle and donkeys, and force them to work for him. <verse eid="1SA 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 8:17"/>He will take one tenth of your sheep and goats. And you will become his slaves! <verse eid="1SA 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 8:18"/>When that time comes, you will complain loudly to the king, the king that you yourselves have chosen, but Yahweh will not ◄pay attention to/help► you.”<verse eid="1SA 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 8:19"/>But the people refused to pay attention to what Samuel said. They said, “We do not <char style="add">care what you say</char>! We want a king! <verse eid="1SA 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 8:20"/>We want to be like the other nations. We want a king to rule us and to lead our soldiers when they go to fight.”<verse eid="1SA 8:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 8:21"/>When Samuel told Yahweh what the people had said, <verse eid="1SA 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 8:22"/>Yahweh replied, “Do what they are telling you to do. Give them a king!” <char style="add">So Samuel agreed</char>, and then he sent the people home.<verse eid="1SA 8:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="1SA 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul met Samuel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 9:1"/>There was a rich and influential man whose name was Kish. He belonged to the tribe descended from Benjamin. Kish was the son of Abiel and the grandson of Zeror. He was from the family of Becorath and from the clan of Aphiah. <verse eid="1SA 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 9:2"/>Kish had a son whose name was Saul. He was more handsome than any of the other Israeli men, and he was a head/foot taller than any of the other Israeli men.<verse eid="1SA 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 9:3"/>One day, some of Kish’s female donkeys wandered off. So Kish told Saul, “Take one of my servants with you, and go and search for the donkeys!” <verse eid="1SA 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 9:4"/>So Saul did that. He took a servant, and they walked through the hilly area where the descendants of Ephraim lived, and then they went through the areas named Shalishah and Shaalim, and then they went through all the area where the descendants of Benjamin lived, but they could not find the donkeys.<verse eid="1SA 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 9:5"/>Finally, they came to the area of Zuph. Then Saul said to the servant, “Let’s go back home. If we do not do that, my father will stop worrying about the donkeys and start worrying about us.”<verse eid="1SA 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 9:6"/>But the servant said, “I have another idea [IDM]. There is one of God’s prophets who lives in this town. People respect him very much, because everything he predicts comes true. Let’s go <char style="add">talk</char> to him. Perhaps he can tell us where we can go <char style="add">to find the donkeys</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 9:7"/>Saul replied to the servant, “If we go talk with him, <char style="add">we should give a gift to him, but</char> what can we give to him? We have no more food in our sacks. Do we have anything else to give to him?”<verse eid="1SA 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 9:8"/>The servant replied, “Look <char style="add">at this</char>! I have a small silver coin. I can give this to him, and then he will tell us where to go <char style="add">to find the donkeys</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 9:8"/><verse number="9-11" style="v" sid="1SA 9:9-11"/>Saul said, “Okay, let’s go <char style="add">talk to him.”</char> So they went to the town where the prophet lived. As they were going up the hill into the town, they met some young women who were coming out of the town to get some water <char style="add">from a well</char>. One of them asked the women, “Is the seer in the town <char style="add">today</char>?” <char style="add">They said that because</char> previously, if people <char style="add">in Israel</char> wanted a message from God, they would say, “Let’s go to the seer,” and people who now are called prophets were at that time called ‘those who see <char style="add">◄visions from God/all that God sees►</char>.’ <verse eid="1SA 9:9-11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 9:12"/>The women replied, “Yes, he is in the town. In fact, he is <char style="add">walking on the road</char> ahead of you. He has just arrived in the town, because the people are going to offer a sacrifice on the altar where the people gather <char style="add">to worship God</char>. <verse eid="1SA 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 9:13"/>If you go quickly, you will <char style="add">have time to talk to him</char> before he goes there. The people who have been invited will not start eating until he arrives there and ◄blesses/asks God to bless► the sacrifice.”<verse eid="1SA 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 9:14"/>So Saul and the servant entered the town. As they went through the gates, they saw Samuel as he was coming toward them, on the way to where people were going to offer sacrifices.<verse eid="1SA 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 9:15"/>On the previous day, Yahweh had told Samuel, <verse eid="1SA 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 9:16"/>“At this time tomorrow, I will send to you a man from the land where the descendants of Benjamin live. Pour olive oil on his <char style="add">head</char> to <char style="add">indicate that he will</char> be the leader of my Israeli people. I have seen that my people are suffering <char style="add">because the Philistine people are oppressing them</char>, and I have heard my people as they have called out to me <char style="add">for help</char>. The man on whose <char style="add">head</char> you pour olive oil will rescue my people from the [MTY] Philistine people.”<verse eid="1SA 9:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 9:17"/>When Samuel saw Saul, Yahweh said to him, “This is the man I told you about yesterday! He is the one who will rule my people!”<verse eid="1SA 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 9:18"/>Saul saw Samuel as he was sitting at the town gateway <char style="add">but he did not know that it was Samuel</char>. He went over to him and asked him, “Can you tell me, where is the house of the man who sees <char style="add">◄visions from God/all that God sees►</char>?”<verse eid="1SA 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 9:19"/>Samuel replied, “I am that man. Go ahead of me with your servant to the place where the people make sacrifices. Both of you will eat with me today. Tomorrow morning I will tell you what you are wanting to know, and then I will send you home. <verse eid="1SA 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 9:20"/>Also, do not worry any more about those donkeys that wandered away three days ago. ◄Someone has found them/They have been found►. But <char style="add">what you need to know is that</char> it is you and your family that all the Israeli people are wanting!” [RHQ]<verse eid="1SA 9:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 9:21"/>Saul replied, “I am from the tribe of Benjamin [RHQ]. That is the smallest tribe in Israel [RHQ]! And my family is the least important family in our tribe! So why are you talking to me like this, <char style="add">about the Israeli people wanting me and my family</char>?”<verse eid="1SA 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 9:22"/>Then Samuel brought Saul and the servant into the big dining room, and told them to sit at the head <char style="add">of the table, indicating that he was</char> honoring them more than he was honoring the 30 people who had been invited. <verse eid="1SA 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 9:23"/>Then Samuel told the cook, “Bring to me the special piece <char style="add">of meat</char> that I told you to set aside.”<verse eid="1SA 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 9:24"/>So the cook brought the leg and the meat that was on it, and set it in front of Saul, <char style="add">even though those portions were for only the priest to eat</char>. Samuel said to Saul, “Start eating it. I told the cook to save this for you, so that you could eat it at this time, when all these people whom I invited are here.” So Saul and Samuel ate together.<verse eid="1SA 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 9:25"/>After they finished eating, they returned to the town. Then Samuel took Saul up to the <char style="add">flat</char> roof <char style="add">of his house</char>, and fixed a bed for him.<verse eid="1SA 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 9:26"/>As the sun was rising the next morning, Samuel called up to Saul, “Get up! It is time for me to send you on the road back home.” So Saul got up, and <char style="add">later</char> Samuel and Saul left the house together.<verse eid="1SA 9:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 9:27"/>When they got to the edge of the town, Samuel told Saul to send his servant ahead. After the servant left, Samuel said to Saul, “Stay here for a few minutes, in order that I can give you a message I received from God.”<verse eid="1SA 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="1SA 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel appointed Saul to be king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 10:1"/>Then Samuel took a small jar of olive oil and poured <char style="add">some of</char> it on Saul’s head. Then he kissed Saul <char style="add">on the cheek</char>, and told him, “I am doing this because Yahweh has chosen you to be the leader of his Israeli people. <verse eid="1SA 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 10:2"/><char style="add">And this will prove it to you</char>: When you leave me today, when you arrive near Rachel’s tomb at Zelzah, in the area where the descendants of Benjamin live, you will meet two men. They will say to you, ‘The donkeys have been found, but now your father is worrying about you, and he is asking people, “Have you seen my son?’ ”<verse eid="1SA 10:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 10:3"/>When you arrive at the <char style="add">large</char> oak tree at Tabor <char style="add">town</char>, you will see three men coming toward you. They will be on their way to <char style="add">worship</char> God at Bethel <char style="add">town</char>. One of them will be leading three young goats, one will be carrying three loaves of bread, and one will be carrying a container of wine. <verse eid="1SA 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 10:4"/>They will greet you, and they will offer you two of the loaves of bread. Accept them.<verse eid="1SA 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 10:5"/>When you arrive at the hill <char style="add">where people worship</char> God near Gibeah <char style="add">town</char>, where there is the camp where the Philistine soldiers stay, you will meet a group of prophets who will be coming down from the altar on top of the hill. There will be people in front of them who will be playing <char style="add">various musical instruments</char>: a harp, a tambourine, a flute, and a lyre. And all of them will be speaking messages that come directly from God. <verse eid="1SA 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 10:6"/>At that time the Spirit of Yahweh will come upon you, and you also will speak messages that come directly from God. ◄You will be changed/The Spirit of Yahweh will change you►, so that you will become like a different person. <verse eid="1SA 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 10:7"/>After those things occur, do whatever you think is right to do, and God will ◄be with/help► you.<verse eid="1SA 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 10:8"/>Then go ahead of me, down to Gilgal <char style="add">city</char>, and wait for me there, for seven days. Then I will join you there, to burn sacrifices and offer other sacrifices to enable you to maintain fellowship with God. When I arrive there, I will tell you what <char style="add">other</char> things you should do.”<verse eid="1SA 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">What Samuel prophesied came true</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 10:9"/>As Saul started to leave there, God changed Saul’s inner being. And all the things that Samuel had predicted happened on that day. <verse eid="1SA 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 10:10"/>When Saul and his servant arrived at Gibeah, they saw some prophets who were <char style="add">speaking messages that came directly from God. As the prophets were</char> approaching Saul and his servant, God’s Spirit came upon Saul powerfully, and he also began to speak messages from God. <verse eid="1SA 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 10:11"/>When people who had known Saul previously heard him speaking messages from God as the prophets were doing, they said to each other, “What has happened to this son of Kish? Is he now really one of the ◄prophets/men who speak messages from God►?”<verse eid="1SA 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 10:12"/>One of the men who lived there replied, “<char style="add">Saul cannot be a prophet, because</char> all prophets receive their power to speak messages from God, not from their parents.” And that is why, <char style="add">when people hear about a report of someone prophesying, they think about what happened to Saul and</char> say, “<char style="add">We are surprised about that person becoming a prophet, like</char> we were surprised to hear that Saul had really become one of the prophets.” <verse eid="1SA 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 10:13"/>When Saul finished speaking the messages that God gave him, he went to the place where the people offered sacrifices.<verse eid="1SA 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 10:14"/>Later, Saul’s uncle <char style="add">saw him there, and</char> asked him, “Where did you go?” Saul replied, “We went to look for the donkeys. When we could not find them, we came here to ask Samuel <char style="add">if he could tell us where they were</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 10:15"/>Saul’s uncle replied, “What did Samuel tell you?”<verse eid="1SA 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 10:16"/>Saul replied, “He assured us that the donkeys had been found.” But he did not tell his uncle what Samuel had said about him becoming the king <char style="add">of Israel</char>.<verse eid="1SA 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 10:17"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char> Samuel summoned the people of Israel to gather at Mizpah to <char style="add">hear a message from</char> Yahweh. <verse eid="1SA 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 10:18"/>After they arrived, he said to them, “This is what Yahweh, the God we Israeli people <char style="add">worship</char>, says: I brought you Israeli people out of Egypt. I rescued your <char style="add">ancestors</char> from the power of the rulers of Egypt and from all the other kings who oppressed them. <verse eid="1SA 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 10:19"/>I am the one who saves you from all your troubles and difficulties. But today you have rejected me, your God, and you have said, ‘We don’t care! Give us a king!’ So <char style="add">I will do what you want</char>. Now have <char style="add">representatives of</char> your tribes and <char style="add">of </char> your clans stand here in the presence of Yahweh.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 10:20"/>When those representatives came near to Samuel, <char style="add">God indicated that</char> he had chosen someone from the tribe descended from Benjamin. <verse eid="1SA 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 10:21"/>Then Samuel told representatives of the tribe of Benjamin to come forward, and God indicated that <char style="add">from that tribe</char> he had chosen someone from the family of Matri, and then God indicated that <char style="add">from the family of Matri</char> he had chosen Saul, the son of Kish. But when they looked for Saul, they could not find him. <verse eid="1SA 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 10:22"/>So they asked Yahweh, “Where is Saul?” Yahweh replied, “He is hiding among the army equipment.”<verse eid="1SA 10:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 10:23"/>So they quickly went there <char style="add">and found him,</char> and brought him <char style="add">in front of all the people</char>. They could see that <char style="add">truly</char> he was a head taller than anyone else. <verse eid="1SA 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 10:24"/>Then Samuel said to all the people there, “This is the man whom Yahweh has chosen to be your king. Among all us Israeli people, there is no one like him!” Then all the people shouted, “We hope that this king will live a long time!”<verse eid="1SA 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 10:25"/>Then Samuel told the people what things the king would force them to do, and all the things the king was required to do. He wrote all those things on a scroll, and then he put it in a sacred place in the temple. Then Samuel sent all the people home.<verse eid="1SA 10:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 10:26"/>When Saul returned to his home in Gibeah <char style="add">town</char>, a group of men decided to continually accompany Saul. They did that because God ◄motivated them/put it in their minds► to do that. <verse eid="1SA 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 10:27"/>But some worthless men said, “◄How can this man save us <char style="add">from our enemies</char>?/This man will not be able to save us <char style="add">from our enemies</char>.►” [RHQ] They despised him, and refused to give him any gifts <char style="add">to show that they would be loyal to him</char>. But Saul did not say anything <char style="add">to rebuke them</char>.<verse eid="1SA 10:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="1SA 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul’s army rescued the people of Jabesh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 11:1"/>About a month later, King Nahash of Ammon <char style="add">led his army across the Jordan River, and they</char> surrounded Jabesh <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>. But all the men of Jabesh <char style="add">went and</char> said to Nahash, “Make an agreement/treaty with us <char style="add">not to kill us</char>, and then we will let you rule us.”<verse eid="1SA 11:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 11:2"/>Nahash replied, “I will do that if you do one thing. Allow us to gouge out all the right eyes of your people. By doing that we will cause the people <char style="add">in other countries</char> to despise all you Israeli people.”<verse eid="1SA 11:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 11:3"/>The leaders of Jabesh replied, “Do not attack us for the next seven days. During that time, we will send messengers throughout Israel <char style="add">to tell them what you are demanding</char>. If no one will help us, then we will ◄surrender to you/allow you to do to us whatever you want►.”<verse eid="1SA 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 11:4"/>
    <char style="add">Being very confident that his army was very superior, Nahash agreed. So the leaders of Jabesh sent messengers throughout Israel</char>. When the messengers came to Gibeah, which was <char style="add">the city</char> where Saul lived, and they told the people there about the situation, everyone started to cry. <verse eid="1SA 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 11:5"/>At that time, Saul was plowing in the field. When he returned home, he asked, “Why are all the people <char style="add">crying</char>?” So they told him what the messengers from Jabesh had reported.<verse eid="1SA 11:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 11:6"/>Then God’s Spirit came powerfully upon Saul, and he became very angry <char style="add">because of what Nahash wanted to do</char>. <verse eid="1SA 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 11:7"/>He took two of his oxen <char style="add">and killed them</char> and cut them into pieces. Then he sent messengers <char style="add">carrying those pieces</char> throughout Israel to tell people this message: “Saul says that <char style="add">he cut this ox in pieces, and that he </char> will do the same thing to the oxen of anyone who refuses to come with him and Samuel to fight <char style="add">the army from Ammon</char>!” Then Yahweh caused all the people of Israel to be afraid of what Saul might do to them (OR, of what Yahweh might do to them) <char style="add">if they did not go and help Saul</char>. So the men all gathered together. <verse eid="1SA 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 11:8"/>When Saul gave them all weapons at Bezek, he saw that there were 300,000 Israeli men there, as well as 30,000 men from the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="1SA 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 11:9"/>So Saul sent messengers back to the people at Jabesh to tell them, “We will rescue/save you by noontime tomorrow.” When the people of Jabesh heard that message, they were very joyful/happy. <verse eid="1SA 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 11:10"/>Then the men of Jabesh told <char style="add">Nahash</char>, “Tomorrow we will surrender to you, and then you can do to us whatever you want to.”<verse eid="1SA 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 11:11"/>But before the sun rose the next morning, Saul <char style="add">and his army arrived. He</char> divided them into three groups. They rushed into the camp of the soldiers from Ammon, and attacked them. By noontime they had killed most of them, and those who were not killed scattered. Each of them who ran away ran away alone.<verse eid="1SA 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The people proclaimed Saul as king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 11:12"/>Then the people <char style="add">of Jabesh</char> said to Samuel, “Where are those men who said that they did not want Saul to be our king? Bring them here, and we will kill them!”<verse eid="1SA 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 11:13"/>But Saul replied, “<char style="add">No</char>, we are not going to execute anyone today, because this is the day that Yahweh has saved us Israeli people. <char style="add">It is a day to rejoice, not to kill anyone</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 11:14"/>Then Samuel said to the people, “Let’s all go to Gilgal, and there we will again proclaim <char style="add">that Saul is</char> our king.” <verse eid="1SA 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 11:15"/>So they went to Gilgal. There, knowing that Yahweh was watching, they proclaimed that Saul was their king. Then they offered sacrifices to enable them to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. And Saul and all the other Israeli people were very happy.<verse eid="1SA 11:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="1SA 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel’s final speech</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 12:1"/>Then Samuel said this to all the Israeli people: “I have done everything that you told me to do, and I have given/appointed a king to rule you. <verse eid="1SA 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 12:2"/>My own sons <char style="add">are grown up and</char> with you now, but I have appointed Saul <char style="add">instead of one of them</char>, and he is now your leader. I am now old, and my hair is gray. I have been your leader ever since I was a boy. <verse eid="1SA 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 12:3"/>Now tell me, while Yahweh is listening, and while the king whom he has chosen is listening: whose ox or donkey have I stolen <char style="add">during all those years</char>? Whom have I cheated? Whom have I oppressed/treated badly? From whom have I accepted a bribe, in order that I would ignore <char style="add">the evil things he had done</char>? If I have done any of those things, tell me, and I will pay back what I owe.”<verse eid="1SA 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 12:4"/>They replied, “<char style="add">No,</char> you have never cheated anyone or oppressed anyone or accepted a bribe from anyone.”<verse eid="1SA 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 12:5"/>Then Samuel said, “Today Yahweh can testify, and the king whom you chose can testify, that I have not taken a bribe from anyone.” They replied, “Yes, Yahweh can say that he knows that is true.”<verse eid="1SA 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 12:6"/>Samuel continued by saying, “Yahweh is the one who appointed Moses and Aaron <char style="add">to lead</char> our ancestors. He is the one who brought them out of Egypt. <char style="add">And he is the one who will testify that what I am saying is true</char>. <verse eid="1SA 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 12:7"/>Now while Yahweh is listening, stand here quietly while I accuse you <char style="add">and tell you that your requesting a king instead of trusting Yahweh to lead you was wrong</char>. I will do that by reminding you of all the great miracles that Yahweh performed for you and your ancestors.<verse eid="1SA 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 12:8"/>
    <char style="add">“Many years</char> after Jacob went to Egypt, our ancestors pleaded to Yahweh to help them. So Yahweh sent Moses and Aaron to them, and they led our ancestors out of Egypt, and eventually they settled in this land.<verse eid="1SA 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 12:9"/>“But our ancestors soon forgot about Yahweh, their God. So he allowed Sisera, the commander of the army from Hazor, to defeat them. He also allowed the Philistines and the army of the king of Moab to fight our ancestors and defeat them. <verse eid="1SA 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 12:10"/>Then our ancestors pleaded with Yahweh again to help them. They admitted, ‘Yahweh, we have sinned, and we have forsaken you. We have worshiped <char style="add">idols that represent the god</char> Baal and <char style="add">the goddess</char> Astarte. But if you rescue us from our enemies, we will worship you only.’ <verse eid="1SA 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 12:11"/>So Yahweh sent men such as Gideon, Barak, Jephthah, and me to save you. And as a result, you did not have to worry about any enemies attacking you.<verse eid="1SA 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 12:12"/>“But now, when king Nahash of Ammon came <char style="add">with his army</char> to attack you, <char style="add">you were afraid. So</char>, you <char style="add">came to me, and</char> said, ‘We want a king to rule us,’ even though Yahweh was already your king! <verse eid="1SA 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 12:13"/>So now, look, here is the king whom you have chosen. You asked for a king, and Yahweh has now appointed a king for you. <verse eid="1SA 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 12:14"/>If you will revere Yahweh and if you serve him, and if you listen to what he says and obey what he commands, and if you and the king who rules over you do what Yahweh your God wants you to do, <char style="add">◄things will go well for you all/Yahweh will bless you►</char>. <verse eid="1SA 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 12:15"/>But if you do not listen to what Yahweh says, if you disobey what he commands, then he will punish [MTY] you all, just as he punished our ancestors.<verse eid="1SA 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 12:16"/>“Now stand here quietly and see the great thing that Yahweh is about to do. <verse eid="1SA 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 12:17"/>You know that [RHQ] <char style="add">it does not rain at this time of the year</char>, during the time when you harvest wheat. But I will ask Yahweh to send thunder <char style="add">and lightning</char> and rain today. When he does that, you will realize that Yahweh considers that you have done a very wicked thing by requesting a king.”<verse eid="1SA 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 12:18"/>Then Samuel prayed to Yahweh, and Yahweh caused it to thunder <char style="add">and lightning</char> and rain. So all the people became very afraid of Yahweh and of Samuel.<verse eid="1SA 12:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 12:19"/>They cried out to Samuel, “Pray for us! We have added to our previous sins by requesting a king! Pray to Yahweh, your God, in order that we will not die <char style="add">because of having done that</char>!”<verse eid="1SA 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 12:20"/>Samuel replied, “Do not be afraid! You have done this evil thing, but do not turn away from doing the things that Yahweh wants you to do. Instead, serve Yahweh wholeheartedly. <verse eid="1SA 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 12:21"/>Do not abandon <char style="add">Yahweh</char> and worship useless idols. They cannot help you or save you <char style="add">from your enemies</char>, because they are truly useless. <verse eid="1SA 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 12:22"/>Yahweh decided to make us his people. So he will not abandon us people whom he has chosen, because he would injure his own reputation <char style="add">of being completely faithful</char> if he did that. <verse eid="1SA 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 12:23"/>But as for me, I have solemnly promised that I will not sin against Yahweh by ceasing to pray for you. And I will continue to teach you what things are good and right <char style="add">for you to do</char>. <verse eid="1SA 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 12:24"/>But you must revere Yahweh and serve him wholeheartedly. Never forget all the great things that he has done for you. <verse eid="1SA 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 12:25"/>But if you keep doing wicked things, he will get rid of you and your king!”<verse eid="1SA 12:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="1SA 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul disobeyed God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 13:1"/>Saul was no longer a young man when he became the king. He ruled Israel for 42 years.<verse eid="1SA 13:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 13:2"/>
    <char style="add">Several years after he became king</char>, he chose three thousand men from the Israeli army to go with him <char style="add">to fight the Philistines</char>. Then he sent the other soldiers back home. Of the men he chose, 2,000 stayed with Saul at Micmash and in the hilly area near Bethel, and 1,000 stayed with <char style="add">Saul’s son</char> Jonathan at Gibeah, in the area where the descendants of Benjamin lived.<verse eid="1SA 13:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 13:3"/>Jonathan <char style="add">and the men who were with him</char> attacked the Philistine soldiers who were camped at Geba. The <char style="add">other</char> Philistines heard about that. <char style="add">So Saul realized that the army of Philistia would probably come to fight the Israelis again</char>. So Saul <char style="add">sent messengers to</char> blow trumpets throughout Israel <char style="add">to gather the people together and</char> proclaim to them, “All you Hebrews need to hear <char style="add">that now the Philistines will start a war with us</char>!” <verse eid="1SA 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 13:4"/>The messengers told the rest of the army to gather together with Saul at Gilgal. And all the people in Israel heard the news. People were saying, “Saul’s army has attacked the Philistine camp, with the result that now the Philistines hate us Israelis very much.”<verse eid="1SA 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 13:5"/>The Philistines gathered together and were given equipment to fight the Israelis. The Philistines had 3,000 chariots, and 6,000 chariot-drivers. Their soldiers <char style="add">seemed to be as many</char> as grains of sand on the seashore [HYP]. They went up and set up their tents at Micmash, to the east of Beth-Aven (<char style="add">which means ‘house of wickedness’, and really referred to Bethel town</char>). <verse eid="1SA 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 13:6"/>The Philistines attacked the Israelis very strongly, and the Israeli soldiers realized that they were in a very bad situation. So many of the Israeli soldiers hid in caves and holes in the ground, or among the rocks, or in pits, or in wells. <verse eid="1SA 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 13:7"/>Some of them crossed the Jordan River at a place where it was very shallow. Then they went to the area where the descendants of Gad lived and to <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 13:7">But Saul stayed at Gilgal. All the soldiers who were with him were shaking <char style="add">because they were so afraid</char>. <verse eid="1SA 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 13:8"/>Saul waited seven days, which was the number of days that Samuel had told him to wait for him. But Samuel did not come to Gilgal <char style="add">during that time</char>, so many of the men in Saul’s army began to leave him and run away. <verse eid="1SA 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 13:9"/>So Saul said to the soldiers, “Bring to me an animal to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> and one for the offering to enable us to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with God</char>.” <char style="add">So the men did that</char>. <verse eid="1SA 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 13:10"/>And just as he was finished burning those offerings, Samuel arrived. Saul went to greet him.<verse eid="1SA 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 13:11"/>Samuel <char style="add">saw what Saul had done, and he</char> said to Saul, “Why have you done this?” Saul replied, “I saw that my men were leaving me and running away, and that you did not come here during the time that you said that you would come, and that the Philistine army was gathering together at Micmash.<verse eid="1SA 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 13:12"/>“So I thought, ‘The Philistine army is going to attack us here at Gilgal, and I have not yet asked Yahweh to bless/help us.’ So I felt it was necessary to offer the burnt offerings <char style="add">to seek God’s blessings</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 13:13"/>Samuel replied, “What you did was very foolish! You have not obeyed what Yahweh, your God, commanded <char style="add">about sacrifices</char>. If you had obeyed him, God would have allowed you and your descendants to rule <char style="add">Israel</char> for a long time. <verse eid="1SA 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 13:14"/>But now <char style="add">because of what you have done, you will die, and after you die,</char> none of your descendants will rule. Yahweh is seeking for a man <char style="add">to be king</char> who will be just the kind of person that he wants him to be, so that he can appoint him to be the leader of his people. Yahweh will do this because you have not obeyed what he commanded.”<verse eid="1SA 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 13:15"/>Then Samuel left Gilgal and went up to Gibeah. Saul stayed at Gilgal with his soldiers. There were only about 600 of them left <char style="add">who had not run away</char>.<verse eid="1SA 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul’s army had difficulties</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 13:16"/>Saul and his son Jonathan and the soldiers who were with them went to Geba <char style="add">city</char> in the area of the tribe of Benjamin <char style="add">and set up their tents there</char>. The Philistine army set up their tents at Micmash. <verse eid="1SA 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 13:17"/>Three groups of Philistia men soon left the place where their army was staying, and went and ◄raided the Israeli towns/attacked the Israelis and took their possessions►. One group went <char style="add">north</char> toward Ophrah <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the </char> Shual <char style="add">region</char>. <verse eid="1SA 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 13:18"/>One group went <char style="add">west</char> to Beth-Horon <char style="add">city</char>. The third group went toward the <char style="add">Israeli</char> border, above Zeboim Valley, near the desert.<verse eid="1SA 13:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 13:19"/>At that time, there were no men in Israel who ◄were blacksmiths/could make things from iron►. <char style="add">The people of Philistia would not permit the Israelis to do that, because they were afraid that</char> they would make iron swords and spears for the Hebrews to fight with. <verse eid="1SA 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 13:20"/>So <char style="add">whenever the Israelis needed</char> to sharpen the blades of their plows, or picks, or axes, or sickles, they were forced to take those things to a Philistia man who could sharpen those things. <verse eid="1SA 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 13:21"/>They needed to pay ◄one fourth of an ounce/8 grams► of silver for sharpening a plow, and ◄an eighth of an ounce/4 grams► of silver to sharpen an axe, or a sickle, or ◄an ox goad/a pointed rod to jab an ox to make it walk►.<verse eid="1SA 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 13:22"/>So <char style="add">because the Israelis could not make weapons from iron</char>, on the day that the Israelis fought <char style="add">against the men of Philistia</char>, Saul and Jonathan were the only Israeli men who had swords. None of the others had a sword; <char style="add">they had only bows and arrows</char>.<verse eid="1SA 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 13:23"/>Before the battle started, some Philistia men went to ◄the pass/a narrow place between two cliffs► outside Micmash to guard it.<verse eid="1SA 13:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="1SA 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Jonathan and his armor-bearer killed many Philistines</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 14:1"/>One day, Jonathan said to the young man who carried his weapons, “Come with me; we will go over to where the Philistia soldiers have put up their tents.” <char style="add">So they went</char>, but Jonathan did not tell his father <char style="add">what they were going to do</char>.<verse eid="1SA 14:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 14:2"/>On that day, Saul and the 600 soldiers who were with him were sitting around a pomegranate tree at a place where the people threshed grain, near Gibeah. <verse eid="1SA 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 14:3"/>Ahijah the priest was also there. He was wearing the sacred vest. Ahijah was the son of Ahitub, who was a brother of Ichabod. Ichabod and Ahitub were the sons of Phinehas, who was the son of Eli, who had been Yahweh’s priest at Shiloh.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:3">No one knew that Jonathan had left <char style="add">the Israeli camp</char>.<verse eid="1SA 14:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 14:4"/>Jonathan planned that he and the young man would go through a narrow ◄pass/place between two cliffs► to get to where the Philistia army was. The cliff on one side of the pass was named Bozez, and the other cliff was named Seneh. <verse eid="1SA 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 14:5"/>One cliff faced north toward Micmash, and the cliff on the other side faced south toward Geba <char style="add">town</char>.<verse eid="1SA 14:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 14:6"/>Jonathan said to the young man who carried his weapons, “Come with me. We will go to where those ◄pagans/people who do not believe in Yahweh► [MTY] have set up their tents. Perhaps Yahweh will help us. It does not matter whether we are only two men or many people; nothing can hinder Yahweh from enabling us to defeat them.”<verse eid="1SA 14:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 14:7"/>The young man who was carrying Jonathan’s weapons said, “Do what you think is the best thing for us to do. I will help you.”<verse eid="1SA 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 14:8"/>Then Jonathan said, “Okay, come with me. We will cross the valley to where the Philistia army is, and allow them to see us. <verse eid="1SA 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 14:9"/>If they then say to us, ‘You two stay there until we come down to you,’ we will stay there and not go up to them. <verse eid="1SA 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 14:10"/>But if they say to us, ‘Come up here <char style="add">and fight against</char> us,’ that will show us that Yahweh will enable us to defeat them. Then we will go up and fight them.”<verse eid="1SA 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 14:11"/>When the two of them crossed the valley, the Philistia soldiers saw them coming. They said, “Look! The Hebrews are crawling out of the holes in which they have been hiding!” <verse eid="1SA 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 14:12"/>Then the Philistia soldiers who were closest to Jonathan and the young man who carried his weapons said, “Come up here, and we will teach you something <char style="add">about how to fight</char> [IDM]!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:12">Jonathan said to the young man who was with him, “Come behind me and climb up, because Yahweh is going to help us to defeat them!” <verse eid="1SA 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 14:13"/>So Jonathan climbed up, using his hands and his feet <char style="add">because it was very steep</char>. The young man climbed up following him. As Jonathan climbed, he struck and killed many Philistia soldiers, and the young man who was with him killed many more as he followed behind Jonathan. <verse eid="1SA 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 14:14"/>In that first battle the two of them killed about 20 Philistia soldiers in an area that was about half an acre.<verse eid="1SA 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 14:15"/>Then all the other Philistia soldiers, the ones in the camp and the ones who had been attacking the Israeli towns, ones who were out in the field much closer, panicked. Then God caused the ground to shake, and they all became terrified/very afraid.<verse eid="1SA 14:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis defeated the Philistia army</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 14:16"/>Saul’s ◄lookouts/men who were watching to see if enemies were coming► were in Gibeah <char style="add">town</char> in the land of the tribe of Benjamin. They saw that the soldiers of the Philistia army were running away in all directions. <verse eid="1SA 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 14:17"/>Saul <char style="add">realized that some of his soldiers must have attacked the Philistia army. So he </char> said to the soldiers who were with him, “Check to see if any of our men are not here.” So they checked, and they found out that Jonathan and the man who carried his weapons were gone.<verse eid="1SA 14:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 14:18"/>So Saul said to Ahijah <char style="add">the Supreme Priest</char>, “Bring the sacred vest here <char style="add">and find out what we should do</char>.” On that day Ahijah was wearing the sacred vest, going in front of the Israelis. <verse eid="1SA 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 14:19"/>But while Saul was talking to the priest, <char style="add">he saw that</char> the Philistia soldiers were becoming more panicked/confused. So Saul said to Ahijah, “Take your hand down <char style="add">from the sacred vest. Do not waste any more time using the marked stones in the vest to find out what Yahweh wants us to do.”</char><verse eid="1SA 14:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 14:20"/>Then Saul gathered his men and they went toward the battle. They found that the Philistia soldiers were so confused that they were striking each other with their swords. <verse eid="1SA 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 14:21"/>Before that, some of the Hebrew men had deserted their army and gone to join with the Philistia army. But now those men <char style="add">revolted and</char> joined with Saul and Jonathan and the other Israeli soldiers. <verse eid="1SA 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 14:22"/>Some of the Israeli soldiers had previously run away and hidden in the mountains where the tribe of Ephraim lived. But when they heard that the Philistia soldiers were running away, they <char style="add">came down and</char> joined the other Israeli soldiers and pursued the Philistia soldiers. <verse eid="1SA 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 14:23"/>So Yahweh rescued the Israelis on that day. The Israeli soldiers continued to pursue their enemies beyond Beth-Aven <char style="add">town</char>.<verse eid="1SA 14:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The dispute about Jonathan eating honey</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 14:24"/>Before Saul’s soldiers went to the battle, Saul declared to them solemnly, “I do not want any of you to eat any food before this evening, before we have defeated all our enemies. If anyone eats anything, <char style="add">Yahweh</char> will curse/punish him.” So none of the Israeli soldiers ate any food, and they became faint/weak because they were very hungry.<verse eid="1SA 14:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 14:25"/>The Israeli army went into the forest, and they found honeycombs on the ground, but they did not eat any honey. <verse eid="1SA 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 14:26"/>They were afraid to eat any, because they had solemnly promised that they would not eat any food. <verse eid="1SA 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 14:27"/>But Jonathan did not hear what his father commanded <char style="add">because he had left the camp very early in the morning</char>. So <char style="add">when he saw</char> a honeycomb, he dipped the end of his walking stick into it and ate some honey. After he ate the honey, he felt stronger.<verse eid="1SA 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 14:28"/>But one of the Israeli soldiers saw him and said to him, “Your father solemnly declared to us that <char style="add">Yahweh</char> would curse/punish anyone who ate any food today. So now we are <char style="add">very tired and</char> weak from being hungry <char style="add">because we obeyed him</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 14:29"/>Jonathan exclaimed, “My father has caused trouble for all of us! See how refreshed/strong I am after eating a little honey! <verse eid="1SA 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 14:30"/>If he had permitted all of us to eat from the food we took from our enemies while we were pursuing them, we would have been able to kill many more of their soldiers!”<verse eid="1SA 14:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 14:31"/>The Israelis pursued and killed Philistia soldiers all that day, from Micmash <char style="add">town west</char> to Aijalon. But they continued to become weaker from being hungry. <verse eid="1SA 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 14:32"/>They had taken <char style="add">many</char> sheep and cattle that the Philistia soldiers had abandoned. Now, because they were extremely hungry, they butchered some of those animals and ate the meat without draining the blood from the animals. <verse eid="1SA 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 14:33"/>One of the soldiers told Saul, “Look! The men are sinning against Yahweh by eating meat that still has blood in it!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:33">Saul replied <char style="add">to the men who were near him</char>, “They have disobeyed Yahweh! Roll a large stone over here!”<verse eid="1SA 14:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 14:34"/>After they did that, he said to those men, “Go and tell all the soldiers that each of them must bring an ox or a sheep to me, and kill it here on this stone, <char style="add">and drain the blood</char> before he eats any of the meat. They should not sin against Yahweh by eating meat <char style="add">from some animal</char> without draining its blood.” So that night all the soldiers brought animals and slaughtered them there. Then Saul built an altar to <char style="add">worship</char> Yahweh. <verse eid="1SA 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 14:35"/>That was the first <char style="add">time that he built an</char> altar for Yahweh.<verse eid="1SA 14:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The soldiers rescued Jonathan from Saul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 14:36"/>Then Saul said <char style="add">to the Israeli soldiers</char>, “Let’s pursue the Philistia soldiers tonight. We can attack them all night. We will not allow any of them to escape alive.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:36">The Israeli soldiers answered, “We will do whatever you think is the best thing for us to do.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:36">But the priest said, “We should ask Yahweh <char style="add">what he thinks we should do</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 14:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 14:37"/>So Saul asked God, “Should we pursue the Philistine soldiers? Will you enable us to defeat them?” But God did not answer Saul that day.<verse eid="1SA 14:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 14:38"/>Then Saul summoned all the leaders of his army. He said to them, “<char style="add">I am sure that God has not answered me because</char> someone has sinned. We must find out what sin someone has committed. <verse eid="1SA 14:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 14:39"/>Yahweh has rescued us <char style="add">from the Philistia army</char>. Just as certain as Yahweh lives, whoever has sinned must be executed. Even if it is my son Jonathan who has sinned, he must be executed.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:39">
    <char style="add">His men knew who was guilty</char>, but none of them said anything <char style="add">to Saul</char>. <verse eid="1SA 14:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 14:40"/>Then Saul said to all the Israeli soldiers, “You stand on one side. My son Jonathan and I will stand on the other side.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:40">His men replied, “Do whatever you think is best.” <verse eid="1SA 14:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 14:41"/>Then Saul prayed to Yahweh, the Israelis’ God, “Tell me who is guilty and who is not guilty.” Then the priest ◄cast lots/threw the stones that were marked►, and they indicated that it was <char style="add">either</char> Jonathan or Saul who was the guilty one, and that the other men were not guilty. <verse eid="1SA 14:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 14:42"/>Then Saul said to the priest, “Throw the stones again to indicate which of us two is guilty.” So he did, and the stones indicated that Jonathan was the guilty one.<verse eid="1SA 14:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="1SA 14:43"/>Then Saul said to Jonathan, “Tell me what you have done <char style="add">that was wrong</char>.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:43">Jonathan replied, “I ate a little bit of honey. It was only a little bit that was on the end of my stick. Do I <char style="add">deserve to be</char> executed <char style="add">because of doing that</char>?” <verse eid="1SA 14:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1SA 14:44"/>Saul replied, “Yes, you must be executed! I hope/wish that God will strike me and kill me if you are not executed for having done that!”<verse eid="1SA 14:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1SA 14:45"/>But the Israeli soldiers said to Saul, “Jonathan has won a great victory for all us Israelis. Should he be executed for eating some honey [RHQ]? Certainly not! Just as surely as Yahweh lives, we will not allow you to injure him in any manner [IDM], <char style="add">because</char> today God helped Jonathan <char style="add">to kill many soldiers of the Philistia army</char>!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 14:45">So <char style="add">by saying that</char> the Israeli soldiers rescued Jonathan, and he was not executed. <verse eid="1SA 14:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1SA 14:46"/>Then Saul ordered his soldiers to stop pursuing the Philistia army, so the Philistia soldiers returned to their homes.<verse eid="1SA 14:46"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul’s army defeated many of their enemies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="1SA 14:47"/>After Saul became the ruler/king of the Israeli people, his army fought against their enemies in many areas. They fought against armies of the Moab people-group, the Ammon people-group, the Edom people-group, the kings of Zobah <char style="add">city/area</char>, and the Philistia people-group. Wherever the Israeli army fought, they defeated their enemies. <verse eid="1SA 14:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1SA 14:48"/>Saul’s army fought bravely and defeated the <char style="add">very tall</char> descendants of Amalek. His army rescued the Israelis from those who had ◄plundered/forcefully taken things from► them.<verse eid="1SA 14:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="1SA 14:49"/>Saul’s sons were Jonathan, Ishbosheth, and Malchishua. He also had two daughters, Merab and her younger sister Michal. <verse eid="1SA 14:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="1SA 14:50"/>Saul’s wife was Ahinoam, the daughter of Ahimaaz. The commander of Saul’s army was Abner, who was the son of Saul’s uncle Ner. <verse eid="1SA 14:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1SA 14:51"/>Saul’s father Kish and Abner’s father Ner were both sons of Abiel.<verse eid="1SA 14:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="1SA 14:52"/>All the time that Saul was alive, his army fought against the Philistia army. And whenever Saul saw a young man who was ◄brave/not afraid to fight► and strong, he forced him to join his army.<verse eid="1SA 14:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="1SA 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul’s army defeated the Amalekites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 15:1"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> Samuel said to Saul, “Yahweh sent me to appoint you to be the king of the Israeli people. So now listen to this message from Yahweh: <verse eid="1SA 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 15:2"/>Yahweh, <char style="add">the commander </char> of the armies <char style="add">of angels</char> has declared this: ‘I am going to punish <char style="add">the descendants of</char> Amalek for <char style="add">attacking</char> the Israeli people after the Israelis left Egypt. <verse eid="1SA 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 15:3"/>So now go <char style="add">with your army</char> and attack the Amalek people-group. Destroy them completely—destroy them and everything that belongs to them—the men and women, their children and infants, their cattle and sheep and camels and donkeys. Do not ◄spare any of them/allow any of them to remain alive►!’”<verse eid="1SA 15:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 15:4"/>So Saul summoned the army, and they gathered at Telaim <char style="add">town</char>. There were 200,000 soldiers. 10,000 of them were from Judah, <char style="add">and the others were from the other Israeli tribes</char>. <verse eid="1SA 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 15:5"/>Then Saul went <char style="add">with his army</char> to a town where some of the Amalek people-group lived. <char style="add">His army prepared to attack them suddenly by</char> hiding in the valley. <verse eid="1SA 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 15:6"/>Then Saul sent this message to the Ken people-group <char style="add">who lived in that area</char>: “You acted kindly toward all our Israeli <char style="add">ancestors</char> when they left Egypt. But we are going to kill all of the Amalek people-group, <char style="add">because they opposed/attacked our ancestors</char>. So move away from where the Amalek people-group live. <char style="add">If you do not move away</char>, you will be killed when they are killed.” So <char style="add">when </char> the Ken people-group <char style="add">heard that, they immediately</char> left that area.<verse eid="1SA 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 15:7"/>Then Saul’s <char style="add">army</char> slaughtered the Amalek people-group, from Havilah <char style="add">town in the east</char> to Shur <char style="add">town in the west</char>. Shur was at the border <char style="add">between Israel and</char> Egypt. <verse eid="1SA 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 15:8"/>Saul’s army captured Agag, the king of the Amalek people-group, but they killed everyone else. <verse eid="1SA 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 15:9"/>They not only ◄spared/did not kill► Agag, but they also took the best sheep and goats and cattle. They took everything that was good. They destroyed only the animals that they considered to be worthless.<verse eid="1SA 15:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh rejected Saul as king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 15:10"/>Then Yahweh said to Samuel, <verse eid="1SA 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 15:11"/>“I am sorry that I appointed Saul to be your king, because he has turned away from me and has not obeyed what I commanded him to do.” Samuel was very disturbed/upset <char style="add">when he heard that</char>, and he cried out to Yahweh all that night.<verse eid="1SA 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 15:12"/>Early the next morning, Samuel got up and went to talk with Saul. But someone told Samuel, “Saul went to Camel <char style="add">city</char>, where he has set up a monument to honor himself. Now he has left there and gone down to Gilgal.”<verse eid="1SA 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 15:13"/>When Samuel arrived <char style="add">at Gilgal</char> he approached Saul, and Saul said to him,, “I wish/desire that Yahweh will bless you! I have obeyed what Yahweh told me to do.”<verse eid="1SA 15:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 15:14"/>But Samuel replied, “If that is true, why is it that I hear cattle mooing and I hear sheep bleating?”<verse eid="1SA 15:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 15:15"/>Saul replied, “The soldiers took them from the Amalek people-group. They saved the best sheep and cattle, in order to offer them as sacrifices to Yahweh, your God. But we have completely destroyed all the others.”<verse eid="1SA 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 15:16"/>Samuel said to Saul, “Stop <char style="add">talking</char>! Allow me to tell you what Yahweh said to me last night.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 15:16">Saul replied, “Tell me <char style="add">what he said</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 15:17"/>Samuel said, “Previously you did not think that you were important. But now you have become [RHQ] the leader of the tribes of Israel. Yahweh appointed you to be their king. <verse eid="1SA 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 15:18"/>And Yahweh sent you to do something <char style="add">for him</char>. He said to you, ‘Go and get rid of all those sinful people, the Amalek people-group. Attack them and kill all of them.’ <verse eid="1SA 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 15:19"/>So why did you not obey Yahweh [RHQ]? Why did your men take the best animals [RHQ]? Why did you do what Yahweh said was evil?” [RHQ]<verse eid="1SA 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 15:20"/>Saul replied to Samuel, “Hey, I did what Yahweh sent me to do! I brought back King Agag, but we killed everyone else! <verse eid="1SA 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 15:21"/>My men brought back only the best sheep and cattle and other things, in order to sacrifice them to Yahweh your God here at Gilgal.”<verse eid="1SA 15:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 15:22"/>But Samuel replied,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:22">“Which <char style="add">do you think</char> pleases Yahweh more, animals that are completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> and other sacrifices,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:22">or people obeying him [SYN]?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:22">It is better to obey <char style="add">Yahweh</char> than <char style="add">to offer</char> sacrifices <char style="add">to him</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:22">It is better to pay attention to what he says than <char style="add">to burn</char> the fat of rams, <char style="add">even though God said they should be sacrificed to him</char>.<verse eid="1SA 15:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 15:23"/>To rebel <char style="add">against God</char> is as sinful as doing sorcery/black magic,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:23">and being stubborn is as sinful as worshiping idols.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 15:23">So, because you disobeyed what Yahweh told you to do,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:23">he has declared that you will no longer be king.”<verse eid="1SA 15:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul asks to be forgiven</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 15:24"/>Then Saul said to Samuel, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, I have sinned. I disobeyed what you told me to do, which is what Yahweh commanded. I did that because I was ◄afraid of/worried about► what my men would say <char style="add">if I did not do what they wanted</char>. So I did what they demanded. <verse eid="1SA 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 15:25"/>But now, please forgive me for having sinned. And come back with me <char style="add">to where the people are</char> in order that I may worship Yahweh.”<verse eid="1SA 15:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 15:26"/>But Samuel replied, “No, I will not go back with you. You have rejected/disobeyed what Yahweh commanded you to do. So he has rejected you, <char style="add">and declared that you will no longer</char> be the king of Israel. <char style="add">So I do not want to talk any more with you</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 15:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 15:27"/>As Samuel turned to leave, Saul tried to stop him by grabbing the edge of Samuel’s robe, and it tore. <verse eid="1SA 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 15:28"/>Samuel said to him, “<char style="add">You tore my robe! And</char> today Yahweh has torn away from you the kingdom of Israel! He will appoint someone else to be king, someone who is a better man than you are. <verse eid="1SA 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 15:29"/>And since the one who is the glorious <char style="add">God</char> of the Israeli people does not lie, he will not change ◄his mind/what he has said►. Humans sometimes change their minds, but God does not do that, because he is not a human.”<verse eid="1SA 15:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 15:30"/>Then Saul <char style="add">pleaded again. He</char> said, “I know that I have sinned. But please honor me in front of the leaders of the Israeli people and in front of all the other Israeli people by coming back <char style="add">to them</char> with me in order that I may worship Yahweh your God.” <verse eid="1SA 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 15:31"/>So Samuel finally agreed to do that, and they went together back <char style="add">to where the people were</char>, and Saul worshiped Yahweh there.<verse eid="1SA 15:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Samuel executed King Agag</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 15:32"/>Then Samuel said, “Bring King Agag to me.” So they brought Agag to him. Agag was confidently expecting that they would spare him/not kill him. He was thinking, “Surely I will not have to endure an agonizing death!”<verse eid="1SA 15:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 15:33"/>But Samuel said to him,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 15:33">“You have killed the sons of many women with your sword,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 15:33">so now your mother will no longer have a son.”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="1SA 15:33">And Samuel cut Agag into pieces <char style="add">with his sword</char>, there at Gilgal, in the presence of Yahweh.<verse eid="1SA 15:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 15:34"/>Then Samuel left there and returned to his home in Ramah, and Saul went to his home in Gibeah. <verse eid="1SA 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 15:35"/>Samuel never saw Saul again, but he was very sad about <char style="add">what</char> Saul <char style="add">had done</char>. And Yahweh was very sorry that he had appointed Saul to be the king of Israel.<verse eid="1SA 15:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="1SA 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel appointed David to be king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 16:1"/>Finally, Yahweh said to Samuel, “I have decided that I will not allow Saul to continue to be the king. So you should not [RHQ] keep feeling sad <char style="add">about what he has done</char>. Put some olive oil in a small container and go to Bethlehem <char style="add">to anoint someone with the oil, and appoint him to be king</char>. I am sending you there to a man named Jesse, because I have chosen one of his sons to be the king <char style="add">of Israel</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 16:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 16:2"/>But Samuel said, “I am afraid [RHQ] to do that! If Saul hears about it, he will kill me!” Yahweh said, “Take a ◄heifer/young female cow► with you, and say to people that you have come to <char style="add">kill it and</char> offer it as a sacrifice to me.<verse eid="1SA 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 16:3"/>“Invite Jesse to come to the sacrifice. <char style="add">When he comes,</char> I will show you what you should do. And I will show you which of his sons <char style="add">I have chosen to be the king</char>. Then you should anoint that one <char style="add">with the olive oil to be the king</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 16:4"/>Samuel did what Yahweh told him to do. He went to Bethlehem. When the town leaders came to him, they trembled, <char style="add">because they were worried that Samuel had come to rebuke them about something</char>. One of them asked him, “Have you come <char style="add">to speak</char> peacefully <char style="add">to us</char>?”<verse eid="1SA 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 16:5"/>Samuel replied, “Yes. I have come peacefully, to make a sacrifice to Yahweh. <char style="add">Perform the rituals to</char> make yourselves acceptable to Yahweh, and then come with me to where they will offer the sacrifice.” Then Samuel performed the ritual to make Jesse and his sons acceptable to God, and he also invited them to the sacrifice.<verse eid="1SA 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 16:6"/>When they arrived there, Samuel looked at <char style="add">Jesse’s oldest son</char> Eliab, and thought, “Surely this is the one whom Yahweh has appointed <char style="add">to be king</char>!”<verse eid="1SA 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 16:7"/>But Yahweh said to Samuel, “No, he is not the one whom I have chosen. Don’t pay attention to his being handsome and very tall, because I have not chosen him. I do not evaluate people as people do. You people evaluate people by their appearance, but I evaluate people by what is in their inner beings.”<verse eid="1SA 16:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 16:8"/>Then Jesse told <char style="add">his next oldest son</char> Abinadab to step forward and walk in front of Samuel. <char style="add">But when he did that</char>, Samuel said, “Yahweh has not chosen this one, either.” <verse eid="1SA 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 16:9"/>Then Jesse told <char style="add">his next oldest son</char> Shammah to step forward. He stepped forward, but Samuel said, “Yahweh has not chosen this one, either.” <verse eid="1SA 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 16:10"/>Similarly, Jesse told his other four sons to walk in front of Samuel. But Samuel said to Jesse, “Yahweh has not chosen any of these sons of yours.” <verse eid="1SA 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 16:11"/>Then Samuel asked Jesse, “Do you have any other sons?” Jesse replied, “My youngest son <char style="add">is not here</char>; he is out <char style="add">in the fields</char> taking care of the sheep.” Samuel said, “Send someone to bring him here! We will not sit down <char style="add">to eat</char> until he gets here.”<verse eid="1SA 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 16:12"/>So Jesse sent <char style="add">someone</char> to bring <char style="add">David there. And when David arrived, Samuel saw that</char> he was handsome and healthy, and had bright eyes. Then Yahweh said, “This is the one <char style="add">whom I have chosen</char>; anoint him <char style="add">to be king</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 16:13"/>So as David <char style="add">stood there</char> in front of his older brothers, Samuel took the container of oil that he had brought and poured some of it on David’s head <char style="add">to set him apart to serve God. After they all ate, Samuel left </char> and returned to Ramah. But Yahweh’s Spirit came on David powerfully, and stayed with David for the rest of his life.<verse eid="1SA 16:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David played the harp for Saul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 16:14"/>But Yahweh’s Spirit left Saul. Instead <char style="add">of his Spirit staying with Saul</char>, Yahweh sent an evil spirit to Saul to terrify him <char style="add">repeatedly</char>.<verse eid="1SA 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 16:15"/>One of his servants said to him, “It is evident that an evil spirit sent by God is terrifying you. <verse eid="1SA 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 16:16"/>So <char style="add">we suggest that you</char> allow us, your servants here, to search for a man who plays the harp well. He can play the harp whenever the evil spirit bothers you. Then <char style="add">you will calm down and</char> you will be okay again.”<verse eid="1SA 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 16:17"/>Saul replied, “<char style="add">Fine/Okay</char>, find for me a man who can play <char style="add">the harp</char> well, and bring him to me.”<verse eid="1SA 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 16:18"/>One of his servants said to him, “A man named Jesse, in Bethlehem <char style="add">town</char>, has a son who plays the harp very well. Furthermore, he is a brave man, and is a capable soldier. He is handsome and he always speaks wisely. And Yahweh always protects him.”<verse eid="1SA 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 16:19"/>So Saul sent this message to Jesse: “Send your son David to me, the one who takes care of sheep.” <verse eid="1SA 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 16:20"/><char style="add">So after they went to</char> Jesse <char style="add">and told him that, he agreed. He </char> got a young goat, a container of wine, a donkey on which he put some loaves of bread, and gave them to David to take to Saul <char style="add">as a present</char>.<verse eid="1SA 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 16:21"/>Then David went to Saul and started to work for him. Saul liked David very much, and he became the man who carried Saul’s weapons <char style="add">when Saul went to fight in battles</char>. <verse eid="1SA 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 16:22"/>Then Saul sent <char style="add">a messenger </char> to Jesse to tell him, “I am pleased with David. Please let him stay here and work for me.”<verse eid="1SA 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 16:23"/>
    <char style="add">Jesse agreed, and after that</char>, whenever the evil spirit whom God sent tormented Saul, David played the harp. Then Saul would become calm, and the evil spirit would leave him.<verse eid="1SA 16:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="1SA 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Goliath challenged the Israeli army</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 17:1"/>The Philistines gathered their army <char style="add">to fight the Israeli army</char>. They gathered together near Socoh, in the area where the descendants of Judah lived. They set up their tents at Ephes-Dammim, which is between Socoh and Azekah. <verse eid="1SA 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 17:2"/>Saul gathered the Israeli army near Elah Valley, and they set up their tents. Then they all took their places, ready to fight the Philistines. <verse eid="1SA 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 17:3"/>So the Philistine and Israeli armies faced each other. They were on two hills, with a valley between them.<verse eid="1SA 17:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 17:4"/>Then Goliath, from Gath <char style="add">city</char>, came out from the Philistine camp. He was a champion warrior/soldier. He was ◄over 9 feet/3 meters► tall. <verse eid="1SA 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 17:5"/>He wore a helmet made of bronze <char style="add">to protect his head</char>, and he wore a coat made of metal plates <char style="add">to protect his body</char>. The coat weighed ◄125 pounds/56 kg.►. <verse eid="1SA 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 17:6"/>He wore bronze guards/protectors on his legs. He had a long bronze dagger fastened on his back. <verse eid="1SA 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 17:7"/>He also had a big spear. It had a cord on it to enable him to throw it better (OR, which was as thick as a weaver’s beam). The tip of the spear was made of iron and weighed ◄15 pounds/almost 7 kg.►. A soldier carrying a huge shield walked in front of him.<verse eid="1SA 17:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 17:8"/>Goliath stood there and shouted to the Israeli army, “Why are you all lined up for battle? I am the great Philistine <char style="add">soldier</char>, and I think [RHQ] you are <char style="add">merely</char> Saul’s slaves. Choose one man to fight for all of you, and send him down here to me! <verse eid="1SA 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 17:9"/>If he fights with me and kills me, then my fellow Philistines will all be your slaves. But if I defeat him and kill him, then you Israelis will all be our slaves. <verse eid="1SA 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 17:10"/>I defy/challenge you men of the Israeli army. Send me a man who will fight with me!” <verse eid="1SA 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 17:11"/>When Saul and all the Israeli soldiers heard that, they were extremely terrified [DOU].<verse eid="1SA 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David went to Saul’s camp</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 17:12"/>David was the son of Jesse. Jesse was from the clan of Ephrath. He lived in Bethlehem, in the area where the descendants of Judah lived. Jesse had eight sons. When Saul <char style="add">was king</char>, Jesse had already become a very old man [DOU]. <verse eid="1SA 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 17:13"/>Jesse’s three oldest sons, Eliab and Abinadab and Shammah, had gone with Saul to fight <char style="add">the Philistines</char>. <verse eid="1SA 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 17:14"/>David was Jesse’s youngest son. While his three oldest brothers were with Saul, <verse eid="1SA 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 17:15"/>David went back and forth: Sometimes he went to Saul’s camp, and sometimes he stayed in Bethlehem to take care of his father’s sheep.<verse eid="1SA 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 17:16"/>For 40 days Goliath came out from the Philistine camp and stood there <char style="add">taunting the Israeli army/telling the Israelis to choose one man to fight with him</char>. He did it twice each day, once in the morning and once in the evening.<verse eid="1SA 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 17:17"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char>, Jesse said to David, “Here is a sack of roasted grain and ten loaves of bread. Take these quickly to your <char style="add">older</char> brothers. <verse eid="1SA 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 17:18"/>And here are ten large chunks of cheese. Take them to their commander. And see how things are going with your <char style="add">older</char> brothers. Then <char style="add">if they are okay,</char> bring back something to show they are all right.”<verse eid="1SA 17:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 17:19"/>His brothers were with Saul and all the other Israeli soldiers, camped alongside Elah Valley, <char style="add">preparing to</char> fight the Philistines. <verse eid="1SA 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 17:20"/>So David arranged for another shepherd to take care of the sheep. Early the next morning he took the food and went to the Israeli camp, as Jesse told him to do. He arrived there just as the Israeli soldiers were forming their ranks and going out to the battlefield. As they went, they were shouting a war cry. <verse eid="1SA 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 17:21"/>The Philistine army and the Israeli army stood <char style="add">on the hillsides</char>, facing each other, ready for the battle. <verse eid="1SA 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 17:22"/>David gave the food to the man who was taking care of the war equipment. <char style="add">He told him to take care of the food that he brought</char>, and then he went and greeted his older brothers. <verse eid="1SA 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 17:23"/>While he was talking with them, he saw Goliath coming out from among the Philistine soldiers, shouting <char style="add">to the Israelis</char>, challenging them <char style="add">to send a man to fight him</char>. David heard what Goliath was saying. <verse eid="1SA 17:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 17:24"/>When all the Israeli soldiers saw Goliath, they were terrified and started to ran away. <verse eid="1SA 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 17:25"/>They were saying to each other, “Look at him coming up toward us! And listen to him as he defies us Israelis! The king says that he will give a big reward to whoever kills this man. He also says that he will give his daughter to that man for him to marry her, and that he will no longer require that man’s family to pay taxes.”<verse eid="1SA 17:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 17:26"/>David talked to some of the men who were standing near him. He said, “What will be given to whoever kills this Philistine and frees us Israelis from this shame/disgrace? And who <char style="add">does </char> this heathen Philistine <char style="add">think he</char> is, defying/ridiculing the army that serves the all-powerful God?”<verse eid="1SA 17:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 17:27"/>They told him the same thing that the other men had said, about what the king would do for anyone who killed Goliath.<verse eid="1SA 17:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 17:28"/>But when David’s oldest brother Eliab heard David talking to the men, he was angry. He said to David, “Why have you come down here? Is someone taking care of those few sheep that you left in the desert? I know you are just a ◄smart-aleck/brat►! You just want to watch the battle!”<verse eid="1SA 17:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 17:29"/>David replied, “Have I done something wrong? I was merely asking a question!” <verse eid="1SA 17:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 17:30"/>Then he walked over to another man and asked him the same question, but the man gave him the same answer. Each time he asked someone, he received the same answer. <verse eid="1SA 17:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 17:31"/>Finally, someone told king Saul what David had asked, and Saul sent someone to bring David to him.<verse eid="1SA 17:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 17:32"/>David told king Saul, “No one should ◄worry/become a coward► because of that Philistine man. I will go and fight with him!”<verse eid="1SA 17:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 17:33"/>Saul said to David, “You are only a young man, and he has been a very capable soldier all his life. So you are not able to go and fight with him!”<verse eid="1SA 17:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 17:34"/>David replied, “I have been taking care of my father’s sheep <char style="add">for many years</char>. Whenever a lion or a bear came and carried away a lamb, <verse eid="1SA 17:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 17:35"/>I went after the lion or the bear and attacked it and rescued the lamb from the wild animal’s mouth. Then I grabbed the animal by its jaw/throat and struck it and killed it. <verse eid="1SA 17:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 17:36"/>I have killed both lions and bears. And <char style="add">I will do</char> the same to this heathen Philistine, because he has defied/ridiculed the army of the all-powerful God! <verse eid="1SA 17:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 17:37"/>Yahweh has rescued me from paws of lions and bears, and he will rescue me from this Philistine!” Then Saul said to David, “All right, go <char style="add">and fight him</char>, and <char style="add">I hope/desire</char> that Yahweh will help you!”<verse eid="1SA 17:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 17:38"/>Then Saul gave to David his own clothes that he always wore in battles, and he gave him a bronze helmet and a coat made of metal plates. <verse eid="1SA 17:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 17:39"/>David <char style="add">put these things on. Then he</char> fastened his sword over them, and tried to walk. But he could not walk, because he was not accustomed to wearing those things. So David said to Saul, “I cannot fight wearing all these things, because I am not accustomed to <char style="add">wearing</char> them!” So he took them off.<verse eid="1SA 17:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 17:40"/>Then he took his walking/shepherd’s stick, and he picked up five smooth stones from the brook/stream. He put them in the pouch of his shoulder-bag. Then he put his sling in his hand and started walking toward Goliath.<verse eid="1SA 17:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David killed Goliath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 17:41"/>Goliath walked toward David, with the soldier who was carrying his shield walking in front of him. When he got near David, <verse eid="1SA 17:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 17:42"/>he looked at David closely. He saw that David had a handsome face and healthy body, but that he was only a young man. So he sneered at David. <verse eid="1SA 17:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1SA 17:43"/>He said to David, “Are you coming to me with a stick because <char style="add">you think that</char> I am a dog?” Then he called out to his gods to harm David. <verse eid="1SA 17:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1SA 17:44"/>He said to David, “Come here to me, and I will <char style="add">kill you and</char> give your dead body to the birds and wild animals to eat!”<verse eid="1SA 17:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="1SA 17:45"/>David replied, “You are coming to me with a sword and a dagger and a spear. But I am coming to you ◄in the name/with the authority► of almighty Yahweh. He is the God whom the army of Israel <char style="add">worships</char>, and he is the God whom you have defied/ridiculed. <verse eid="1SA 17:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1SA 17:46"/>Today Yahweh will enable me to defeat you. I will strike you down and cut off your head. And <char style="add">we Israelis will kill</char> many Philistine <char style="add">soldiers and</char> give their bodies to the birds and wild animals to eat. And everyone in the world will <char style="add">hear about it and</char> know that we Israeli people worship an <char style="add">all-powerful</char> God. <verse eid="1SA 17:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1SA 17:47"/>And everyone here will know that Yahweh can rescue people without a sword or a spear. Yahweh always wins his battles, and he will enable us to defeat all of you <char style="add">Philistines</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 17:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="1SA 17:48"/>As Goliath came closer to attack David, David ran quickly toward him. <verse eid="1SA 17:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1SA 17:49"/>He put his hand into his shoulder-bag and took out one stone. He <char style="add">put it in his sling and</char> hurled it toward Goliath. The stone hit Goliath on the forehead and penetrated his skull, and he fell face down onto the ground.<verse eid="1SA 17:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50-51" style="v" sid="1SA 17:50-51"/>Then David ran and stood over Goliath. He pulled Goliath’s sword from its sheath and killed him with it, and then cut off his head. In that way David defeated the Philistine without having his own sword. He used <char style="add">only</char> a sling and a stone!</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 17:50-51">When the other Philistines saw that their great warrior was dead, they ran away. <verse eid="1SA 17:50-51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="1SA 17:52"/>The Israeli men shouted and ran after them. They pursued them all the way to Gath and to the gates of Ekron <char style="add">city</char>. They struck them as they went, with the result that dead/wounded Philistines were lying on the road all the way from Shaaraim to Gath and Ekron <char style="add">towns</char>. <verse eid="1SA 17:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1SA 17:53"/>When the Israelis returned from chasing the Philistines, they ◄plundered/took everything from► the Philistine camp. <verse eid="1SA 17:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="1SA 17:54"/>David later took the head of Goliath to Jerusalem, but he kept Goliath’s weapons in his own tent.<verse eid="1SA 17:54"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="1SA 17:55"/>As Saul watched David going toward Goliath, he said to Abner, the commanded of his army, “Abner, whose son is that young man?” Abner replied, “◄As sure as you are alive/Truly► [IDM], I do not know.”<verse eid="1SA 17:55"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" sid="1SA 17:56"/>Then the king said, “Find out whose son he is!”<verse eid="1SA 17:56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="1SA 17:57"/>
    <char style="add">Later,</char> as David returned from killing Goliath, Abner took him to Saul. David was carrying Goliath’s head.<verse eid="1SA 17:57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="1SA 17:58"/>Saul asked him, “Young man, whose son are you?” David replied, “<char style="add">Sir, perhaps you have forgotten that</char> I am the son of your servant Jesse, who has served you faithfully, who lives in Bethlehem.”<verse eid="1SA 17:58"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="1SA 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul became jealous of David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 18:1"/>After David finished talking with Saul, <char style="add">he met Saul’s son, Jonathan.</char> Jonathan <char style="add">immediately</char> liked David; in fact, he began to love/like him as much as he loved/liked himself. <verse eid="1SA 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 18:2"/>From that day, Saul kept David with him, and did not let him return home. <verse eid="1SA 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 18:3"/>Because Jonathan loved David so much, he made a solemn agreement with David. <char style="add">They promised each other that they would always be loyal friends</char>. <verse eid="1SA 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 18:4"/>Jonathan took off his own outer robe and gave it to David. He also gave David his soldier’s tunic, his sword, his bow <char style="add">and arrows</char>, and his belt.<verse eid="1SA 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 18:5"/>
    <char style="add">David went wherever Saul sent him. And</char> whatever Saul told him to do, David did it very successfully. As a result, Saul appointed David to be a commander in the army. All the officers and other men in the army ◄approved of/were very pleased with► that.<verse eid="1SA 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 18:6"/>But, when the men in the army were returning home after David had killed Goliath, the women came out from many [HYP] towns in Israel to meet/greet King Saul. They were singing and dancing very joyfully, playing tambourines and lyres. <verse eid="1SA 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 18:7"/>As they danced, they sang this song to each other:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 18:7">“Saul has killed 1,000 <char style="add">enemy soldiers</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 18:7">But David has killed 10,000 <char style="add">of them</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 18:8"/>
    <char style="add">When</char> Saul <char style="add">heard them singing that, he</char> did not like it. He became very angry. He said <char style="add">to himself</char>, “They are saying that David <char style="add">killed</char> 10,000 men, but that I <char style="add">have killed</char> only 1,000. Soon they will want to make him their king!” [RHQ] <verse eid="1SA 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 18:9"/>From that time, Saul watched David very closely because he was suspicious <char style="add">that David would try to become king</char>.<verse eid="1SA 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 18:10"/>The next day, an evil spirit sent by God suddenly took control of Saul. He began to act like a madman, inside his house. David was playing the lyre for him, as he did every day. Saul was holding a spear in his hand, <verse eid="1SA 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 18:11"/>and he hurled it <char style="add">at David</char>, saying to himself, “I will fasten David to the wall with the spear!” He did that two times, but David jumped aside <char style="add">both times</char>.<verse eid="1SA 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 18:12"/>Because <char style="add">it became evident that</char> Yahweh had abandoned Saul but <char style="add">that</char> he was helping David, Saul was afraid of David. <verse eid="1SA 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 18:13"/>So he appointed David as a commander of 1,000 soldiers and sent David away from him, <char style="add">hoping that David would be killed in a battle</char>. But when David led his soldiers <char style="add">in their battles</char>, <verse eid="1SA 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 18:14"/>he always had great success, because Yahweh was helping him. <verse eid="1SA 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 18:15"/>When Saul heard that David <char style="add">and his soldiers were</char> very successful, he became more afraid of David. <verse eid="1SA 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 18:16"/>But all the people of Israel and of Judah loved David, because he led the soldiers very successfully <char style="add">in the battles</char>.<verse eid="1SA 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David married Saul’s daughter</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 18:17"/>One day Saul said to David, “I am ready to give you my oldest daughter, Merab, to be your wife. I will do that if you serve me bravely by fighting battles for Yahweh <char style="add">against the Philistines</char>”. He said that because he thought, “I will not try to get rid of David by myself. I will allow the Philistines to do that.”<verse eid="1SA 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 18:18"/>But David said to Saul, “I am not [RHQ] a very important person, and my family is not very important, and my clan is not a very important Israeli clan. So I do not deserve to become your son-in-law.” [RHQ] <verse eid="1SA 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 18:19"/>So, when it was time for Merab to be given to David to become his wife, instead, Saul gave her to a man named Adriel, from Meholah <char style="add">town</char>.<verse eid="1SA 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 18:20"/>But Saul’s other daughter, Michal, fell in love with David. When they told Saul about that, he was pleased. <verse eid="1SA 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 18:21"/>He thought, “I will let Michal marry him, in order that she may trap him, and the Philistines will be able to kill him.” So he said to David, <char style="add">“You can marry Michal</char>,” and by saying that, he indicated for the second time that David would become his son-in-law.<verse eid="1SA 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 18:22"/>Saul told his servants, “Talk to David privately, and say to him, ‘Listen, the king is pleased with you, and all of us his servants love you. So now <char style="add">we think that</char> you should <char style="add">marry Michal and</char> become the king’s son-in-law.’ ”<verse eid="1SA 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 18:23"/>So they told that to David. But David said, “It would be a great honor [RHQ] to become the king’s son-in-law. But <char style="add">I do not think that I should do that, because</char> I am only a poor and insignificant man.”<verse eid="1SA 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 18:24"/>When the servants told Saul what David had said, <verse eid="1SA 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 18:25"/>Saul replied, “Go and say to David, ‘<char style="add">In order for </char> the king <char style="add">to allow you to marry Michal, he</char> wants <char style="add">you to kill</char> 100 Philistines <char style="add">and cut off</char> their foreskins <char style="add">and bring the foreskins to him to prove that you have killed them</char>. In that way he will get revenge on his enemies.’ ” But what Saul wanted was that the Philistines would kill David <char style="add">while David was trying to kill them</char>.<verse eid="1SA 18:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 18:26"/>When the servants told that to David, he was very pleased that he could become the king’s son-in-law <char style="add">by doing that. The king had said how many days he would allow for David to do that</char>. But before that time ended, <verse eid="1SA 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 18:27"/>David and his men went and killed, <char style="add">not 100, but</char> 200 Philistines! He brought their foreskins to Saul, and counted them <char style="add">while Saul was watching</char>, in order to prove that he had <char style="add">done what the king required so that he could become Saul’s son-in-law. So then Saul was obligated</char> to allow David to marry his daughter Michal.<verse eid="1SA 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 18:28"/>But when Saul realized that Yahweh was helping David, and that his daughter loved David, <verse eid="1SA 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 18:29"/>he became more afraid of David. So, as long as Saul lived, he was David’s enemy.<verse eid="1SA 18:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 18:30"/>The Philistine armies repeatedly came to fight the Israelis, but every time they fought, David and his soldiers were more successful than any of Saul’s other army commanders. As a result, David became very famous.<verse eid="1SA 18:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="1SA 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul tried to kill David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 19:1"/>Then Saul urged all his servants and his son Jonathan to kill David. But Jonathan liked David very much. <verse eid="1SA 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 19:2"/>So he warned David, “My father Saul is seeking for a way to kill you. So be careful. Tomorrow morning go and find a place to hide <char style="add">in the field</char>. <verse eid="1SA 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 19:3"/>I will ask my father to go out there with me. <char style="add">While we are out there</char>, I will talk to him about you. Then I will tell you everything that he tells me.” <char style="add">So David did what Jonathan told him to do</char>.<verse eid="1SA 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 19:4"/>
    <char style="add">The next morning</char>, Jonathan spoke with his father, saying many good things about David. He said, “You should never do anything to harm your servant David! He has never done anything to harm you! Everything that he has done has helped you very much. <verse eid="1SA 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 19:5"/>He was in danger of being killed when he fought against <char style="add">Goliath, the champion of</char> the Philistia <char style="add">army. By enabling David to kill him</char>, Yahweh won a great victory for all the people of Israel. You were very happy when you saw that. Why would you want to do anything now to harm David [RHQ]? There is no reason for you to kill him, because he has not done anything wrong!”<verse eid="1SA 19:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 19:6"/>Saul listened to what Jonathan said. Then Saul said, “I solemnly promise that just as certain as Yahweh lives, I will not kill David.”<verse eid="1SA 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 19:7"/>Afterward, Jonathan summoned David and told him what he and Saul had said. Then Jonathan brought David to Saul, and David served Saul as he had done before.<verse eid="1SA 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 19:8"/>One day a war started again, and David <char style="add">led his soldiers to</char> fight against the Philistia army. David’s <char style="add">army</char> attacked them very furiously, with the result that the Philistia army ran away.<verse eid="1SA 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 19:9"/>But one day when sitting in his house, an evil spirit <char style="add">sent</char> from Yahweh <char style="add">suddenly</char> came upon Saul. While David was playing his harp <char style="add">for Saul</char>, <verse eid="1SA 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 19:10"/>Saul hurled his spear at David to try to fasten him to the wall. David ◄dodged/jumped to one side►, and the spear did not hit him. The spear stuck in the wall, but that night David escaped.<verse eid="1SA 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Michal helped David escape</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 19:11"/>Then Saul sent messengers to David’s house. He told them to watch the house and to kill David <char style="add">while he was leaving the house</char> the following morning. But David’s wife Michal <char style="add">saw them and</char> warned him, “To survive, you must run away tonight, because if you do not do that, you will be killed tomorrow!” <verse eid="1SA 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 19:12"/>So she enabled David to climb out through a window, and he ran away and escaped. <verse eid="1SA 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 19:13"/>Then Michal took an idol and put it in the bed. She covered it with some <char style="add">of David’s</char> clothes, and put some goat’s hair on the head of the idol.<verse eid="1SA 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 19:14"/>When the messengers came <char style="add">to the house the next morning</char>, she told them that David was sick <char style="add">and could not get out of bed</char>.<verse eid="1SA 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 19:15"/>
    <char style="add">When they reported that to</char> Saul, he told them to go back to David’s house. He said to them, “Bring him to me lying on his bed, in order that I can kill him!” <verse eid="1SA 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 19:16"/>But when those men entered David’s house, they saw that there was only an idol in the bed, with goat’s hair on its head.<verse eid="1SA 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 19:17"/>
    <char style="add">When they reported that to Saul,</char> Saul <char style="add">summoned</char> Michal <char style="add">and</char> said to her, “Why did you trick me like that? You allowed my enemy to escape!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 19:17">Michal replied to Saul, “David told me that if I did not help him escape, he would kill me!” [RHQ]<verse eid="1SA 19:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s spirit took possession of Saul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 19:18"/>After David had escaped from Saul, he went to Samuel, who was <char style="add">at his home</char> at Ramah. He told Samuel everything that Saul had done to <char style="add">try to kill</char> him. Then David and Samuel went to Naioth, <char style="add">which was a section</char> of <char style="add">Ramah city</char>, and they stayed there. <verse eid="1SA 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 19:19"/>Someone told Saul that David was in Naioth. <verse eid="1SA 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 19:20"/>So Saul sent some messengers to capture David. <char style="add">When</char> those messengers <char style="add">arrived in Ramah, they</char> met some men who were proclaiming ecstatic messages, and Samuel was there, as their leader. When Saul’s messengers met them, the Spirit of God took control of Saul’s men, and they also spoke ecstatically. <verse eid="1SA 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 19:21"/>When Saul heard about that, he sent messengers a third time, but they also started to speak ecstatically. <verse eid="1SA 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 19:22"/>Finally, Saul himself went to Ramah. When he arrived at the well at <char style="add">a place named</char> Secu, he asked people there, “Where are Samuel and David?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 19:22">The people replied, “They are at Naioth in Ramah <char style="add">city</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 19:23"/>While Saul was walking toward Naioth, the Spirit of God also took control of him. <char style="add">While he walked on</char>, he continued speaking ecstatic messages until he came to Naioth. <verse eid="1SA 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 19:24"/>There he took off his clothes, and he spoke messages from God in front of Samuel. He lay on the ground doing that all day and all night. That is the reason that <char style="add">when people see someone doing something that is very unexpected, they think about what happened to Saul, and</char> they say, “We are surprised, like the people were surprised to see Saul <char style="add">acting like</char> a prophet?” [RHQ]<verse eid="1SA 19:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="1SA 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Jonathan helped David escape from Saul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 20:1"/>David ran away from <char style="add">the</char> Naioth <char style="add">section</char> of Ramah <char style="add">city</char>. He went to Jonathan and asked him, “What have I done <char style="add">to displease your father</char>? What did I do that was wrong? Why is he trying to kill me?”<verse eid="1SA 20:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 20:2"/>Jonathan replied, “My father is surely not trying to kill you! He always tells me before he does anything that he is planning. He tells me about important things and unimportant things that he plans to do. ◄Why would he refuse to tell me <char style="add">if he were planning to kill me</char>?/I am sure that he would not refuse to tell me <char style="add">if he were planning to kill you</char>.► [RHQ] So what you are saying cannot be true.”<verse eid="1SA 20:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 20:3"/>Then David solemnly declared this to Jonathan: “Your father knows very well that you and I are very good friends, so he says to himself, ‘I will not tell Jonathan <char style="add">what I am going to do</char>. If I tell Jonathan, he will be upset/distressed, <char style="add">and then he will tell David</char>.’ But just as certain as Yahweh lives and you live, I am only one step away from being killed.”<verse eid="1SA 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 20:4"/>Jonathan said to David, “I will do whatever you tell me to do.”<verse eid="1SA 20:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 20:5"/>David replied, “Tomorrow we will celebrate the Festival of the New Moon. I always eat with the king at that festival. But tomorrow I will hide in the field, and I will stay there for one night. I will stay there until the evening of the day after tomorrow. <verse eid="1SA 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 20:6"/>If your father asks why I am not there at the festival, say to him, ‘David requested me to allow him to go to his home in Bethlehem, where his family will offer the sacrifice that they offer <char style="add">during this festival</char> every year.’ <verse eid="1SA 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 20:7"/>If your father says ‘That is okay’, then I know I will be safe. But if he becomes extremely angry, you will know that he is determined to harm me. <verse eid="1SA 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 20:8"/>Please be kind to me. Yahweh heard you when you made a solemn agreement with me <char style="add">that you and I will always be loyal friends</char>. If I deserve to be punished [MTY], kill me yourself. I do not want [RHQ] you to allow your father to punish [IDM] me.”<verse eid="1SA 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 20:9"/>Jonathan replied, “I will never do that! But if I find out that my father is determined to harm/kill you, I will certainly warn you.” [RHQ]<verse eid="1SA 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 20:10"/>David asked him, “How will I find out if your father answers you harshly?” <verse eid="1SA 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 20:11"/>Jonathan replied, “Come with me. We will go out into the field.” So they went together out into the field.<verse eid="1SA 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 20:12"/>There Jonathan said to David, “I promise this while Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, is listening: At this time the day after tomorrow, I will find out what my father <char style="add">is thinking about you</char>. If he is saying good things about you, I will certainly send a message to you to tell that to you [RHQ]. <verse eid="1SA 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 20:13"/>But if he is planning to hurt/kill you, I will enable you to know [IDM] that, and enable you to go away safely. I desire that Yahweh will punish me severely if I do not do that <char style="add">for you</char>. I desire/hope that Yahweh will be with you <char style="add">and help you</char> like he has helped my father. <verse eid="1SA 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 20:14"/>But while I am still alive, please be kind to me in the same way that Yahweh is kind to me, and do not kill me <char style="add">when you become king</char>. <verse eid="1SA 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 20:15"/>But <char style="add">if I die,</char> never stop being kind to my family, <char style="add">even</char> after Yahweh has gotten rid of all your enemies all over the earth.”<verse eid="1SA 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 20:16"/>
    <char style="add">David agreed</char>. So Jonathan made a solemn agreement with David. And he said, “I hope/desire that Yahweh will get rid of all your enemies.” <verse eid="1SA 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 20:17"/>And Jonathan requested David to repeat his solemn promise to be his close friend, because Jonathan loved David as much as he loved himself.<verse eid="1SA 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 20:18"/>Then Jonathan said, “Tomorrow we will celebrate the Festival of the New Moon. When you are not sitting at your place when we eat, my father will ◄miss you/see that you are not there►. <verse eid="1SA 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 20:19"/>The day after tomorrow, in the evening, go to the place where you hid before. Wait by the pile of stones. <verse eid="1SA 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 20:20"/>I will come out and shoot three arrows as though I were trying to shoot at a target. <char style="add">The arrows will hit the ground</char> close to the pile of stones. <verse eid="1SA 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 20:21"/>Then I will send a boy to bring the arrows back to me. If you hear me say to him, ‘They are closer to me’, then as surely as Yahweh lives, you will know that everything is fine, <char style="add">and that Saul will not kill you</char>. <verse eid="1SA 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 20:22"/>But if I tell him, ‘The arrows are farther away’, you will know that you must leave immediately, because Yahweh wants you to run away. <verse eid="1SA 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 20:23"/>I hope/desire that Yahweh will watch you and me and enable us to never forget what we have promised each other.”<verse eid="1SA 20:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 20:24"/>So David went and hid in the field. When the Festival of the New Moon started, the king sat down to eat. <verse eid="1SA 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 20:25"/>He sat where he usually sat, close to the wall. Jonathan sat across from him, and Abner <char style="add">the army commander</char> sat next to Saul. But no one was sitting in the place where David <char style="add">usually sat</char>. <verse eid="1SA 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 20:26"/>On that day, Saul did not say anything about David, because he was thinking, “Something must have happened that caused David to become unacceptable <char style="add">to worship God</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 20:27"/>But the next day, when David was not sitting at the place where he usually sat, Saul asked Jonathan, “Why has that son of Jesse not been here to eat with us yesterday and today?”<verse eid="1SA 20:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 20:28"/>Jonathan replied, “David earnestly requested me that I permit him to go to Bethlehem. <verse eid="1SA 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 20:29"/>He said, ‘Please allow me to go, because our family is going to offer a sacrifice. My <char style="add">older</char> brother insisted that I be there. So please allow me to go to be with my <char style="add">older</char> brothers.’ <char style="add">I allowed David to go</char>, and that is the reason that he is not here eating with you.”<verse eid="1SA 20:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 20:30"/>Saul was ◄furious/very angry► with Jonathan. He yelled at him, “You stupid bastard [EUP]! I know that you are being loyal to that son of Jesse. By doing that, you will bring shame to yourself and to your mother. <verse eid="1SA 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 20:31"/>As long as Jesse’s son is living, you will never become the king, and you will never rule over a kingdom! So now, summon David, and bring him to me. He must be executed!”<verse eid="1SA 20:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 20:32"/>Jonathan asked his father, “Why should David be executed? What wrong has he done?” <verse eid="1SA 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 20:33"/>Then Saul threw his spear at Jonathan in order to kill him, <char style="add">but the spear did not hit him</char>. So Jonathan knew that his father really wanted to kill David.<verse eid="1SA 20:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 20:34"/>Jonathan was very angry, and he left the room. On that second day of the festival, he refused to eat anything. He was disgusted about what his father had done, and he was worried about David.<verse eid="1SA 20:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 20:35"/>The following morning Jonathan went out to the field to give a message to David, like he had agreed that he would do. He took a young boy with him. <verse eid="1SA 20:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 20:36"/>Jonathan said to the boy, “Run and find the arrows that I shoot.” The boy started running, and Jonathan shot an arrow ahead of the boy. <verse eid="1SA 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 20:37"/>When the boy ran to the place where the arrow hit the ground, Jonathan called out, “The arrow is further away!” [RHQ] <verse eid="1SA 20:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 20:38"/>Then he shouted to the boy, “Act quickly; do not wait! Do not stop!” The boy picked up the arrow and brought it back to Jonathan. <verse eid="1SA 20:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 20:39"/>But the boy did not understand the meaning of what Jonathan had said; only Jonathan and David knew. <verse eid="1SA 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 20:40"/>Then Jonathan gave his bow and arrows to the boy and told him, “Go back to the town.”<verse eid="1SA 20:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 20:41"/>When the boy left, David came out from the south side of the pile of stones behind which he had been hiding. He went to Jonathan and bowed <char style="add">in front of Jonathan</char> three times, with his face touching the ground. Then David and Jonathan kissed each other <char style="add">on the cheek/neck</char>, and they cried together. But David cried more than Jonathan.<verse eid="1SA 20:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 20:42"/>Jonathan said to David, “May things go well for you as you go. Yahweh has heard what we solemnly promised to always do for each other, and what we said that our descendants must do for each other.” Then David left, and Jonathan went back to the town.<verse eid="1SA 20:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="1SA 21"/>
  <para style="s1">David and his men hid in a cave</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 21:1"/>David fled from there and went to Nob <char style="add">city to see</char> Ahimelech the priest. Ahimelech trembled when he saw David <char style="add">because he was afraid that something bad had happened</char>. He said to David, “Why are you alone? Why have no men come with you?”<verse eid="1SA 21:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 21:2"/>David <char style="add">deceived Ahimelech</char> by replying, “The king sent me. But he does not want anyone to know anything about what he sent me to do. I have told my men where <char style="add">they should meet me</char>. <verse eid="1SA 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 21:3"/>Now <char style="add">I want to know</char>, do you have any <char style="add">food here for me to eat</char> [IDM]? Could you give me five loaves of bread, or whatever <char style="add">other food</char> that you can find?”<verse eid="1SA 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 21:4"/>The priest answered David, “There is no ordinary bread here, but I have some of the sacred bread <char style="add">that was placed before Yahweh</char>. Your men may eat it if they have not slept with [EUP] women <char style="add">recently</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 21:5"/>David replied, “They have not been near women for many days. I do not allow my men to defile themselves by sleeping with women while they are preparing to fight in battles. They must continue to keep themselves acceptable to God when they are on ordinary trips, and <char style="add">today they have kept themselves acceptable to God</char> because now we are doing something very special/important.” <verse eid="1SA 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 21:6"/>The only bread that the priest had was the sacred bread that had been placed in Yahweh’s presence <char style="add">in the Sacred tent</char>. So the priest gave David some of that bread. On that day the priest had taken those loaves from the table and replaced them with ◄fresh/newly baked► loaves.<verse eid="1SA 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 21:7"/>It happened that Doeg, from the Edom people-group, was there on that day to make himself acceptable to Yahweh, <char style="add">and he saw what Ahimelech did</char>. He was one of Saul’s officials and the leader of Saul’s shepherds.<verse eid="1SA 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 21:8"/>David asked Ahimelech, “Do you have a spear or a sword <char style="add">that I could use</char>? The king <char style="add">appointed us to do</char> this task <char style="add">and told us to leave</char> immediately, so I did not have time to bring any weapons.”<verse eid="1SA 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 21:9"/>Ahimelech replied, “I have only the sword that belonged to Goliath <char style="add">the giant</char> from the Philistia people-group whom you killed in Elah Valley. It is wrapped in a cloth, and is behind the sacred vest <char style="add">in the Sacred Tent</char>. If you want it, take it, because I have no other <char style="add">weapon</char> here.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 21:9">David replied, “Truly, there is no other sword that is <char style="add">as good</char> as that one! Give it to me.” <verse eid="1SA 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 21:10"/><char style="add">So Ahimelech gave it to him</char>, and David left there. He <char style="add">and his men</char> and went to Gath <char style="add">city in the Philistia region</char>, to stay with King Achish. <verse eid="1SA 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 21:11"/>But the officers of King Achish <char style="add">objected to David being there. They</char> said to King Achish, “This man is [RHQ] David, the king of Israel! He is the one [RHQ] whom <char style="add">our enemies</char>, the <char style="add">Israeli</char> people, <char style="add">honored by</char> dancing and singing,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 21:11">‘Saul has killed thousands <char style="add">of his enemies</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 21:11">but David has killed tens of thousands of them!’”<verse eid="1SA 21:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 21:12"/>David heard what those men were saying, so he was afraid of <char style="add">what</char> King Achish <char style="add">might do to him</char>. <verse eid="1SA 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 21:13"/>So he pretended that he was insane. He started scratching on the gates <char style="add">of the city</char> and allowing his saliva to run down his beard.<verse eid="1SA 21:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 21:14"/>Then King Achish said to his men, “Look at this man! He is acting like an insane man! Why have you brought him to me? <verse eid="1SA 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 21:15"/>Have you brought him because I do not have enough insane men here already [RHQ]? I do not want [RHQ] him to come into my house!”<verse eid="1SA 21:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="1SA 22"/>
  <para style="s1">David and his men hid in a cave at Adullam</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 22:1"/>David <char style="add">and his men</char> left Gath and went <char style="add">east</char> to hide in a cave on a hill at Adullam <char style="add">city</char>. Soon his <char style="add">older</char> brothers and all his other relatives came and stayed with him there. <verse eid="1SA 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 22:2"/>Then other men came there. Some were men who had caused trouble, some were men who owed money, and some were men who were not content [IDM] <char style="add">with the government</char>. They continued to come until there were 400 men there, and David was their leader.<verse eid="1SA 22:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 22:3"/>Later they left there and went <char style="add">east</char> to Mizpah <char style="add">city</char> in the Moab region. There David requested the king of Moab, “Please allow my father and mother to live here with you until I know what God is going to do for me.” <verse eid="1SA 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 22:4"/><char style="add">The king gave him permission,</char> so David’s parents stayed with the king of Moab all the time that David and the men who were with him were hiding <char style="add">in that area</char>.<verse eid="1SA 22:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 22:5"/>One day the prophet Gad told David, “Leave ◄your fortress/this area► and return to Judah.” So David and his men went to Hereth forest <char style="add">in Judah</char>.<verse eid="1SA 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul killed Ahimelech and many other priests</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 22:6"/>One day, someone told Saul that David and his men had arrived in Judah. On that day, Saul was sitting underneath the tamarisk tree on a hill at Gibeah <char style="add">town</char>. He was holding his spear, and was surrounded by his army officers. <verse eid="1SA 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 22:7"/>He shouted to them, “You men of the tribe of Benjamin, listen to me! Do you think that the son of Jesse will give all of you fields and vineyards <char style="add">if he becomes your king</char>? Will he appoint all of you to become generals and captains <char style="add">in his army</char> [RHQ]? <verse eid="1SA 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 22:8"/>Is that why you have all conspired against me [RHQ]? None of you told me when my son <char style="add">Jonathan</char> made a solemn agreement with that son of Jesse. None of you feels sorry for me. That son of Jesse was my servant, but now my son is encouraging him to hide in order to ◄ambush me/attack me suddenly►, as he is doing today!”<verse eid="1SA 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 22:9"/>Doeg, a man from the Edom people-group, was standing there with Saul’s officers. He said to Saul, “When I was at Nob, I saw that son of Jesse talking to Ahimelech, the priest. <verse eid="1SA 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 22:10"/>Ahimelech asked Yahweh what David should do. Then Ahimelech gave to David some food and the sword of Goliath, <char style="add">the giant</char> from the Philistia people-group.”<verse eid="1SA 22:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 22:11"/>Then Saul summoned Ahimelech and all Ahimelech’s relatives who were priests at Nob. So they all came to the king. <verse eid="1SA 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 22:12"/>Saul said to Ahimelech, “You son of Ahitub, listen to me!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 22:12">Ahimelech answered, “Yes, sir!” <verse eid="1SA 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 22:13"/>Saul said, “Why are you and Jesse’s son conspiring to get rid of me? You gave him some bread and a sword. You requested God to tell David what he should do. David has rebelled against me, and right now he is <char style="add">hiding somewhere</char>, waiting <char style="add">to attack me</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 22:14"/>Ahimelech replied, “<char style="add">I do not understand why you are saying that, because</char> David, your son-in-law, the captain of your bodyguards, is very loyal to you. No one is more loyal to you than David! Everyone in your household respects him very much. <verse eid="1SA 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 22:15"/>Furthermore, this was certainly not [RHQ] the first time that I requested God to say what he wanted David to do. And it is not right for you to accuse me or any of my relatives <char style="add">of trying to get rid of you</char>, because I do not know anything about <char style="add">anyone wanting to do that</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 22:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 22:16"/>The king then shouted, “Ahimelech, you and your all your relatives are going to be executed right now!”<verse eid="1SA 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 22:17"/>Then he commanded his bodyguards, “Kill these priests of Yahweh, because they are allies of David, and they are conspiring with David against me! They knew that David was trying to run away from me, but they did not tell me!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 22:17">But Saul’s bodyguards refused to kill Yahweh’s priests.<verse eid="1SA 22:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 22:18"/>Then the king said to Doeg, “You kill them!” So Doeg, the man from the Edom people-group, went out and struck them with his sword. On that day he killed eighty-five men who were wearing the sacred vests <char style="add">because they were God’s priests</char>. <verse eid="1SA 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 22:19"/>He also went and killed many people in Nob, the city where the priests lived. He killed men, women, children, babies, cattle, donkeys, and sheep there.<verse eid="1SA 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 22:20"/>But Abiathar, Ahimelech’s son, escaped. He ran away and joined David <char style="add">and the men who were with him</char>. <verse eid="1SA 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 22:21"/>He told David that Saul had commanded <char style="add">Doeg</char> to kill Yahweh’s priests. <verse eid="1SA 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 22:22"/>Then David said to him, “That man from the Edom people-group, Doeg, was there at Nob on the day <char style="add">that I was there</char>. I knew that he would surely tell Saul <char style="add">what happened</char>. So it is my fault that your father and all of his family have been killed. <verse eid="1SA 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 22:23"/>You stay with me, and do not be afraid. The man who wants to kill you wants to kill me also, but you will be safe if you stay with me.”<verse eid="1SA 22:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="1SA 23"/>
  <para style="s1">David saved the people of Keilah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 23:1"/>One day someone told David, “You need to know that the Philistia army is attacking Keilah <char style="add">town</char> and they are stealing grain from where men are threshing it.” <verse eid="1SA 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 23:2"/>David asked Yahweh, “Should my men and I go to fight against those men from the Philistia people-group?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 23:2">Yahweh answered, “Yes, go. Attack them, and rescue the people of Keilah.” <verse eid="1SA 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 23:3"/>But David’s men said to him, “We are afraid <char style="add">that Saul will attack us</char> here in Judah. We will be more afraid if we go to Keilah where the Philistia army is!”<verse eid="1SA 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 23:4"/>So David asked Yahweh again <char style="add">if they should go to Keilah</char>. Yahweh answered, “Yes, go down to Keilah. I will help you to defeat the men of the Philistia people-group.” <verse eid="1SA 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 23:5"/>So David and his men went to Keilah. They fought against the men of the Philistia people-group and captured many of their cattle. David and his men killed many of the Philistia men and rescued the people of Keilah.<verse eid="1SA 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 23:6"/>Abiathar, the son of Ahimelech, fled to be with David at Keilah, and he brought the sacred vest with him <char style="add">to use it to determine what God wanted to be done</char>.<verse eid="1SA 23:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Saul pursued David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 23:7"/>Soon Saul found out that David was at Keilah. So he said, “That is good! God is enabling me to capture him! He has trapped himself in that town, because it has high walls with gates around it.”<verse eid="1SA 23:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 23:8"/>So Saul summoned his army, and they prepared to go down to Keilah to attack David and his men.<verse eid="1SA 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 23:9"/>But David found out that Saul was planning <char style="add">for his army</char> to attack him. So he said to Abiathar the priest, “Bring <char style="add">here</char> the sacred vest.” <verse eid="1SA 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 23:10"/><char style="add">So when Abiathar brought it,</char> David prayed, “Yahweh, God of us Israelis, I have heard that Saul is planning to come here <char style="add">with his army</char> and destroy Keilah because I am here. <verse eid="1SA 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 23:11"/>Will Saul come down <char style="add">here to Keilah</char>, as people reported to me? Will the leaders of Keilah enable Saul to capture me? Yahweh, God of us Israelis, please tell me!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 23:11">Yahweh answered, “Yes, Saul will come down.” <verse eid="1SA 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 23:12"/>Then David asked, “Will the leaders of Keilah enable Saul’s army to capture me and my men <char style="add">if we stay here</char>?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 23:12">
    <char style="add">By means of the stones in the sacred vest</char>, Yahweh replied, “Yes, they will.” <verse eid="1SA 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 23:13"/>So David and his 600 men left Keilah. They continued to move from one place to another, <char style="add">wherever they thought that Saul would not find them</char>. And when Saul found out that David had escaped from Keilah, he did not go there.<verse eid="1SA 23:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 23:14"/>David and his men stayed in hiding places in the desert and in the hills of Ziph Desert. Every day Saul <char style="add">sent men to</char> search for David, but Yahweh did not allow them to capture David.<verse eid="1SA 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 23:15"/>While David and his men were at <char style="add">a place named</char> Horesh in Ziph desert, he found out that Saul was coming there to kill him. <verse eid="1SA 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 23:16"/>But Saul’s son Jonathan went to David at Horesh, and encouraged him to continue to trust <char style="add">God</char>. <verse eid="1SA 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 23:17"/>Jonathan told him, “Do not be afraid, because my father will not be able to harm [IDM] you. <char style="add">Some day</char> you will be the king of Israel, and I will be the second <char style="add">most important man in Israel</char>. My father Saul also knows that.” <verse eid="1SA 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 23:18"/>Then the two of them repeated their solemn promise that Yahweh <char style="add">had heard them make previously, that they would always be loyal to each other</char>. Then Jonathan went home, but David stayed at Horesh.<verse eid="1SA 23:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 23:19"/>Some people from Ziph went to Saul when he was at Gibeah, and they told him, “David <char style="add">and his men</char> are hiding in our land [RHQ]! They are hiding in places at Horesh on Hakilah Hill, south of <char style="add">a place named</char> Jeshimon. <verse eid="1SA 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 23:20"/>So, O king, come down there any time that you want to. It is our duty to capture him and turn him over to you.”<verse eid="1SA 23:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 23:21"/>Saul replied, “I hope/desire that Yahweh will bless you <char style="add">for telling that to me</char>. <verse eid="1SA 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 23:22"/>Go back and find out more about him. Find out exactly where he is staying, and find out who has seen him there. People tell me that he is very clever, <char style="add">so we need to be clever also to be able to capture him</char>. <verse eid="1SA 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 23:23"/>Find out all the places where he and his men hide. Then come back and tell me everything that you have found out. Then I will <char style="add">take my army and</char> go there with you. If David is in any of the clans/caves of Judah, we will search for him <char style="add">and find him</char>!”<verse eid="1SA 23:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 23:24"/>So those people went back to Ziph before Saul went there. At that time David and his men were in Maon Desert, south of Jeshimon. <verse eid="1SA 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 23:25"/>Saul and his soldiers went to search for David, but David heard about that. So he and his men went further <char style="add">south</char> to a rocky hill/peak in the Maon Desert. When Saul heard about that, he and his men followed David and his men to the Maon Desert.<verse eid="1SA 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 23:26"/>Saul and his soldiers were walking along one side of the hill/peak, and David and his men were on the other side. David and his men were hurrying to escape from Saul’s soldiers, because Saul and his soldiers were coming much closer. <verse eid="1SA 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 23:27"/>But then a messenger came to Saul and said to him, “Come quickly! The Philistia army is attacking the people in our land!” <verse eid="1SA 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 23:28"/>So Saul stopped pursuing David, and he <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> went to fight against the Philistia army. That is the reason that people call that place ‘Escape Rock’. <verse eid="1SA 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 23:29"/>David and his men also left the Maon Desert and went to places to hide safely at En-Gedi.<verse eid="1SA 23:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="1SA 24"/>
  <para style="s1">David spared Saul’s life</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 24:1"/>After Saul <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> returned <char style="add">home</char> after fighting against the Philistia army, someone reported to Saul that David <char style="add">and his men</char> had gone into the desert near En-Gedi. <verse eid="1SA 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 24:2"/><char style="add">When </char> Saul <char style="add">heard that, he</char> chose 3,000 men from various areas in Israel, and they went to search for David and his men at a place named Rocks of Wild Goats.<verse eid="1SA 24:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 24:3"/>At a place where the road was alongside some sheep pens, Saul <char style="add">left the road and</char> entered a cave to defecate [EUP]. <char style="add">He did not know that</char> David and his men were hiding further inside that same cave! <verse eid="1SA 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 24:4"/>David’s men <char style="add">saw Saul and</char> whispered to David, “Today is the day that Yahweh spoke about when he said, ‘I will enable you to defeat your enemy.’ You can do to him whatever you want to!” So David crept toward the entrance of the cave and <char style="add">with his knife</char> he cut off a piece of Saul’s robe. <verse eid="1SA 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 24:5"/><char style="add">And then he returned to his men</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 24:5">But then David felt guilty for having cut off a piece of Saul’s robe. <verse eid="1SA 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 24:6"/>He said to his men, “I should not have done that to the king! I hope/desire that Yahweh will never allow me to attack the one whom God has appointed, because Yahweh is the one who chose him <char style="add">to be the king</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 24:7"/>By saying that, David restrained his men, and did not allow them to kill Saul.<verse eid="1SA 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 24:8"/>After Saul left the cave and started to walk on the road again, David came out of the cave and shouted to Saul, “King Saul!” Saul turned around and looked, and David bowed down with his face touching the ground. <verse eid="1SA 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 24:9"/>Then he said to Saul, “◄Why do you pay attention to people when they say ‘David wants to harm you’?/You should not pay attention to people when they say ‘David wants to harm you’.► [RHQ] <verse eid="1SA 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 24:10"/>Today you can see with your own eyes that <char style="add">what they say is not true</char>. Yahweh put you in a place where my men and I could have killed you when you were in this cave. Some of my men told me that I should do that, but I did not do that. I said to them, ‘I will not harm my master, because he is the king whom Yahweh appointed.’ <verse eid="1SA 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 24:11"/>Your majesty, look at this piece of your robe that is in my hand! I cut it from your robe, but I did not kill you. So now you should be able to understand that I am not planning to do anything evil to you. I have not done anything wrong to you, but you are searching for me to kill me. <verse eid="1SA 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 24:12"/>I hope/desire that Yahweh will judge and decide which of us ◄<char style="add">is doing what is right/pleases him</char>►. And I hope/desire that he will punish you for the wrong things that you have done to me. But I will not try to harm you. <verse eid="1SA 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 24:13"/>There is a proverb that has the words, ‘Evil things are done by evil people.’ But <char style="add">I am not evil, so</char> I will not do evil things to you.<verse eid="1SA 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 24:14"/>“You are the king of Israel. So ◄why are you pursuing me?/you should not be pursuing me.► [RHQ] I am <char style="add">as harmless as</char> [MET] a dead dog or a flea. <verse eid="1SA 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 24:15"/>I hope/desire that Yahweh will judge which of us <char style="add">is doing what ◄he wants/is right►</char>. I trust that he will <char style="add">act like a lawyer and</char> judge ◄my case/what I have done►, and that he will rescue me from your power [MTY].”<verse eid="1SA 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 24:16"/>When David finished speaking, Saul <char style="add">called out to him and</char> asked, “My son David, is that your voice <char style="add">that I am hearing</char>?” Then he began to cry loudly. <verse eid="1SA 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 24:17"/>He said, “You are a better man than I am. You have done something very good to me when I tried to do something very bad to you. <verse eid="1SA 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 24:18"/>When Yahweh put me in a place <char style="add">in that cave</char> where you could have easily killed me, you did not do that. <verse eid="1SA 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 24:19"/>◄Who else would/No one else would► find his enemy and allow his enemy to escape <char style="add">when he could kill him instead</char> [RHQ]. I hope/desire that Yahweh will reward you for being kindly to me today. <verse eid="1SA 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 24:20"/>I know that <char style="add">some day</char> you will surely become the king, and that your kingdom will prosper as you rule the Israeli people. <verse eid="1SA 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 24:21"/>Now while Yahweh is listening, solemnly promise to me that you will not kill my family and get rid of all my descendants.”<verse eid="1SA 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 24:22"/>David solemnly promised Saul that he would not <char style="add">harm Saul’s family</char>. Then Saul went back home, and David and his men went back up into the place where they had been hiding.<verse eid="1SA 24:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="1SA 25"/>
  <para style="s1">Samuel died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 25:1"/>
    <char style="add">Soon after that</char>, Samuel died, and all the Israeli people gathered and mourned for him. They buried his body outside his home in Ramah.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="1SA 25:1">Nabal insulted David</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 25:1">Then David and his men moved to the Maon Desert. <verse eid="1SA 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 25:2"/>In Maon <char style="add">town</char> there was a man who owned land in Carmel, <char style="add">a nearby village</char>. He was very rich; he owned 3,000 sheep and 1,000 goats. <verse eid="1SA 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 25:3"/>His name was Nabal; he was a descendant of Caleb. His wife Abigail was a wise and beautiful woman, but Nabal was very cruel and treated people very unkindly [IDM].<verse eid="1SA 25:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 25:4"/>One day while David <char style="add">and his men</char> were in the desert, someone told him that Nabal was cutting the wool from his sheep. <verse eid="1SA 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 25:5"/>So David told ten of his men, “Go to Nabal at Carmel and greet him for me. <verse eid="1SA 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 25:6"/>Then tell to him this message from me, ‘I wish/desire that things will go well for you and your family and for everything that you possess.<verse eid="1SA 25:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 25:7"/>‘ heard people say that you are cutting the wool from your sheep. Previously, when your shepherds were among us, we did not harm them. All the time that your shepherds were among us at Camel, we did not steal any sheep from them. <verse eid="1SA 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 25:8"/>You can ask your servants if this is true, and they will tell you <char style="add">that it is true</char>. We have come here at a time when you are celebrating, so I ask you to please be kind to us and give these men whatever extra food you have, for me, David, and my men to eat.’”<verse eid="1SA 25:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 25:9"/>When David’s men arrived where Nabal was, they gave David’s message to him, and they waited <char style="add">for him to reply</char>. But Nabal spoke harshly to them. <verse eid="1SA 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 25:10"/>He said to them, “Who <char style="add">does</char> this man, this son of Jesse, <char style="add">think that he</char> is? [DOU, RHQ] There are many slaves who are running away from their masters at the present time, <char style="add">and it seems to me that he is just one of them</char>. <verse eid="1SA 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 25:11"/>I give bread and water to the men who are cutting the wool from my sheep, and I give them meat from animals that I have slaughtered. Why should I take some of those things and give them to a group of outlaws [RHQ]? ◄Who knows where they have come from?/I do not even know where they have come from.►” [RHQ]<verse eid="1SA 25:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 25:12"/>Then David’s men returned and told him what Nabal had said. <verse eid="1SA 25:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 25:13"/>When David heard that, he told his men, “<char style="add">We are going to kill Nabal;</char> fasten your swords!” So he fastened on his sword and about 400 men fastened on their swords and went with David. There were 200 of his men who stayed with their supplies.<verse eid="1SA 25:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 25:14"/>One of Nabal’s servants <char style="add">found out what David and his men were planning to do, so he</char> went to Nabal’s wife Abigail and said to her, “David sent some messengers from the desert to greet our master Nabal, but Nabal only yelled at them. <verse eid="1SA 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 25:15"/>All the time that we were in the fields close to them, those men of David were very kind to us. They did not harm us. They did not steal anything from us. <verse eid="1SA 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 25:16"/>They protected us during the daytime and during the night. They were like a wall [MET] around us to protect us while we were taking care of our sheep. <verse eid="1SA 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 25:17"/>So now you should think about it and decide what you can do. <char style="add">If you do not do something,</char> terrible things will happen to our master and to all his family. Nabal is an extremely wicked man, with the result that <char style="add">he will not heed anyone when</char> that person tries to tell him anything <char style="add">that he should do</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 25:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 25:18"/>
    <char style="add">When</char> Abigail <char style="add">heard that, she</char> very quickly gathered 200 loaves <char style="add">of bread</char>, and also got two leather bags full of wine, the meat from five sheep, a bushel of roasted grain, 100 packs of raisins, and 200 packs of dried figs. She put all those things on donkeys. <verse eid="1SA 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 25:19"/>Then she told her servants, “Go ahead of me. I will follow you.” But she did not tell her husband <char style="add">what she was going to do</char>.<verse eid="1SA 25:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 25:20"/>David and his men <char style="add">had left the place where they were staying and were on the road to Nabal’s property. They</char> were coming down a hill when they met Abigail. <verse eid="1SA 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 25:21"/>David had been saying to his men, “It was useless for us to protect that man and all his possessions here in this desert. We did not steal anything that belonged to him, but he has done evil to me in return for our good <char style="add">things we did for him</char>. <verse eid="1SA 25:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 25:22"/>I hope/desire that God will strike me and kill me [IDM] if he or even one of his men [IDM] is still alive tomorrow morning!”<verse eid="1SA 25:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 25:23"/>When Abigail saw David, she quickly got down from her donkey and bowed before him, with her face touching the ground. <verse eid="1SA 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 25:24"/>Then she prostrated herself at David’s feet and said to him, “Sir, I deserve to be punished <char style="add">for what my husband has done</char>. Please listen to what I say to you. <verse eid="1SA 25:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 25:25"/>Please do not pay attention to [IDM] what this worthless man Nabal has said. His name means ‘fool’, and he surely is a foolish man. But I, who am <char style="add">willing to be</char> your servant, did not see the messengers whom you sent to him. <verse eid="1SA 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 25:26"/>Yahweh has prevented you from getting revenge on anyone and killing anyone. I hope/desire that as surely as Yahweh lives and as surely as you live, your enemies will be <char style="add">cursed</char> like Nabal will be. <verse eid="1SA 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 25:27"/>I have brought a gift for you and for the men who are with you. <verse eid="1SA 25:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 25:28"/>Please forgive me if I have done anything wrong to you. Yahweh will surely <char style="add">reward you by</char> allowing many of your descendants to become kings of Israel, because you are fighting the battles that Yahweh <char style="add">wants you to fight</char>. And <char style="add">I know that</char> throughout all your life you have not done anything wrong. <verse eid="1SA 25:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 25:29"/>Even when those who are trying to kill you pursue you, you are safe, because Yahweh your God takes care of you. You will be <char style="add">protected as though you were</char> [MET] a bundle that he has safely tied up. But your enemies will <char style="add">disappear as fast as stones</char> that are hurled from a sling. <verse eid="1SA 25:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 25:30"/>Yahweh has promised to do good things for you, and he will do what he has promised. And he will cause you to become the ruler of the Israeli people. <verse eid="1SA 25:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 25:31"/>When that happens, <char style="add">you will be glad that you did not kill any</char> people in Nabal’s household. You will not think that you deserve to be punished for having taken revenge yourself and killed innocent people. And when Yahweh enables you to successfully <char style="add">become the king</char>, please do not forget <char style="add">to be kind to</char> me.”<verse eid="1SA 25:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="1SA 25:32"/>David replied to Abigail, “I praise Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, because he sent you to <char style="add">talk with</char> me. <verse eid="1SA 25:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1SA 25:33"/>I hope/desire that Yahweh will bless you for being very wise. You have prevented me from taking revenge myself and killing many people [MTY] today. <verse eid="1SA 25:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1SA 25:34"/>Just as surely as Yahweh the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char> is alive, he has prevented me from harming you. If you had not come quickly to talk to me, neither Nabal nor even one of Nabal’s men [IDM] would be still alive tomorrow morning.”<verse eid="1SA 25:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="1SA 25:35"/>Then David accepted the gifts that Abigail had brought to him. He said to her, “I hope/desire that things will go well for you. I have heard what you said, and I will do what you have requested.”<verse eid="1SA 25:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Nabal died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="1SA 25:36"/>When Abigail returned to Nabal, he was in his house, having a big celebration like kings have. He was very drunk and feeling very happy. So Abigail did not say anything to him that night <char style="add">about her meeting with David</char>. <verse eid="1SA 25:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1SA 25:37"/>The next morning, when he was no longer drunk, she told him everything <char style="add">that had happened when she talked with David</char>. <char style="add">Immediately</char> ◄he had a stroke/a blood vessel burst in his brain► and he became paralyzed [MET]. <verse eid="1SA 25:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1SA 25:38"/>About ten days later Yahweh struck him <char style="add">again</char> and he died.<verse eid="1SA 25:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="1SA 25:39"/>After David heard that Nabal was dead, he said, “Praise Yahweh! Nabal insulted me, but Yahweh ◄vindicated me/got revenge for me►. He has prevented me from <char style="add">doing anything</char> wrong. And he has punished Nabal for the wrong that he did.”</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="1SA 25:39">David married Abigail</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 25:39">Then David sent <char style="add">messengers</char> to Abigail, to ask her if she would become his wife. <verse eid="1SA 25:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1SA 25:40"/>His servants went to Carmel and said to Abigail, “David sent us to take you to become his wife.” <verse eid="1SA 25:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1SA 25:41"/>Abigail bowed down with her face touching the ground. Then she told <char style="add">the messengers to tell David</char>, “<char style="add">I am happy to become your wife</char>. I will be your servant. And I am willing to wash the feet of your slaves.” <verse eid="1SA 25:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1SA 25:42"/>Abigail quickly got on her donkey and went with David’s messengers. Five of her maids went with her. <char style="add">When she arrived where David was,</char> she became his wife. <verse eid="1SA 25:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1SA 25:43"/>David had previously married Ahinoam, a woman from Jezreel <char style="add">town near Carmel</char>. So both Abigail and Ahinoam were now David’s wives. <verse eid="1SA 25:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1SA 25:44"/>King Saul’s daughter Michal was also David’s wife, but Saul had given her to Laish’s son Paltiel, who was from Gallim <char style="add">town</char>.<verse eid="1SA 25:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="1SA 26"/>
  <para style="s1">David spared Saul’s life again</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 26:1"/>One day <char style="add">some of</char> the people of Ziph <char style="add">town</char> went to Saul while he was at Gibeah, and they said to him, “David is hiding in a cave on Hakilah hill, across from Jeshimon <char style="add">town</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 26:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 26:2"/>So Saul chose 3,000 of the best Israeli soldiers and went with them to Ziph Desert to search for David. <verse eid="1SA 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 26:3"/>Saul and his men set up their tents close to the road on Hakilah hill, east of Jeshimon <char style="add">town</char>, but David <char style="add">and his men</char> stayed in the desert. When David heard that Saul was searching for him, <verse eid="1SA 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 26:4"/>he sent some spies to find out for certain that Saul had come to Hakilah.<verse eid="1SA 26:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 26:5"/>Then <char style="add">that evening</char> David went to the place where Saul had set up his tent. <char style="add">From a distance</char> he saw where Saul and his army commander, Abner, were sleeping. Saul was sleeping with all his army <char style="add">sleeping</char> around him.<verse eid="1SA 26:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 26:6"/>David <char style="add">went back to where his men were and</char> talked to Ahimelech, who was from the Heth people-group, and Joab’s brother Abishai, whose mother was <char style="add">David’s older sister</char> Zeruiah. He asked them, “Who will go with me down into the camp where Saul is?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:6">Abishai replied, “I will go with you.” <verse eid="1SA 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 26:7"/>So that night David and Abishai crept into Saul’s camp. They saw that Saul was asleep. His spear was stuck in the ground near his head. Saul was asleep in the middle of the camp. Abner <char style="add">the army commander</char> and the other soldiers were sleeping around Saul.<verse eid="1SA 26:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 26:8"/>Abishai whispered to David, “Today Yahweh has enabled us to kill your enemy! Allow me to fasten Saul to the ground <char style="add">by thrusting</char> my spear into him. It will be necessary for me to strike him only once. I will not <char style="add">need to</char> strike him twice.”<verse eid="1SA 26:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 26:9"/>But David whispered to Abishai, “No, do not kill Saul. Yahweh has appointed him to be king, so Yahweh will surely [RHQ] punish anyone who kills him. <verse eid="1SA 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 26:10"/>Just as surely as Yahweh lives, he himself will punish Saul. Perhaps Yahweh will strike him when it is Saul’s time to die, or perhaps Saul will be killed in a battle. <verse eid="1SA 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 26:11"/>But I hope/desire that Yahweh will prevent me from harming the king whom he has appointed. Let’s take Saul’s spear and water jug that are near his head. Then let’s get out of here!”<verse eid="1SA 26:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David taunted Abner and Saul</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 26:12"/>So David took the spear and the jug, and he and Abishai left. No one saw them or knew what they were doing, and no one woke up, because Yahweh had caused them to be sound asleep.<verse eid="1SA 26:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 26:13"/>David and Abishai went across the valley and climbed to the top of the hill, a long way from Saul’s camp.<verse eid="1SA 26:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 26:14"/>Then David shouted to Abner, “Abner, can you hear me?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:14">Abner <char style="add">woke up and</char> replied “Who are you, <char style="add">waking up</char> the king by calling out to him?” <verse eid="1SA 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 26:15"/>David replied, “<char style="add">I am sure that</char> you are the greatest man in Israel [IRO, RHQ]! So why did you not guard your master, the king? Someone came into your camp in order to kill your master, the king. <verse eid="1SA 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 26:16"/>You have done a very poor <char style="add">job of guarding Saul</char>. So just as surely as Yahweh lives, you and your men should be executed! You have not guarded your master whom Yahweh appointed to be the king. Where are the king’s spear and the water jug that were close to his head?”<verse eid="1SA 26:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 26:17"/>
    <char style="add">The shouting woke </char> Saul <char style="add">up and he</char> recognized that it was David’s voice. He called out, saying, “My son David, is that your voice?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:17">David replied, “Yes, your majesty it is my voice.”<verse eid="1SA 26:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 26:18"/>Then David added, “Sir, why are you pursuing me [RHQ]? What wrong have I done [RHQ]? <verse eid="1SA 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 26:19"/>Your majesty, listen to me! If Yahweh has caused you to be angry with me, I should offer a sacrifice <char style="add">in order to appease him</char>. But if it is people who have caused you to be angry with me, I hope/desire that Yahweh will curse them. They have forced me to leave the land that Yahweh gave to me. They have told me, ‘Go somewhere else and worship other gods!’ <verse eid="1SA 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 26:20"/>Now do not force me to die [MTY] far from <char style="add">where we worship</char> Yahweh. You, the king of Israel, have come here searching for me. <char style="add">But I do not want to harm you</char>! I am <char style="add">as harmless as</char> a flea [MET]. You are searching for me like people hunt for a bird in the mountains! [MET]”<verse eid="1SA 26:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 26:21"/>Then Saul said, “David, my son. I have sinned <char style="add">by trying to kill you</char>. So come back home. Today you have considered my life to be very valuable <char style="add">and so you have not killed me</char>. So I will not try to harm you. I have made a big mistake and have acted foolishly.”<verse eid="1SA 26:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 26:22"/>David replied, <char style="add">“ will leave</char> your spear here. Send one of your young men here to get it. <verse eid="1SA 26:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 26:23"/>Yahweh rewards us for the things that we do that are right and for being loyal <char style="add">to him</char>. Even when Yahweh placed me where I could easily have killed you, I refused to do that, because you are the one whom Yahweh has appointed [MTY] to be the king. <verse eid="1SA 26:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 26:24"/>Just like I considered your life to be valuable <char style="add">and spared your life</char> today, I hope/desire that Yahweh will consider my life to be valuable and <char style="add">spare my life and</char> save me from all my troubles.”<verse eid="1SA 26:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 26:25"/>Then Saul said to David, “My son David, I pray that Yahweh will bless you. You will do great things very successfully.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 26:25">Then David returned to his men, and Saul went back home.<verse eid="1SA 26:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="1SA 27"/>
  <para style="s1">David stayed among the Philistia people-group</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 27:1"/>But David thought, “Some day Saul will capture me <char style="add">if I stay around here</char>. So the best thing that I can do is to escape and go to the Philistia area. If I do that, Saul will stop searching for me here in Israel, and I will be safe.”<verse eid="1SA 27:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 27:2"/>So David and his 600 men left Israel and went to see Maoch’s son Achish, who was king of Gath <char style="add">city in the Philistia area</char>. <verse eid="1SA 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 27:3"/>David and his men and their families started to live there in Gath, the city where king Achish lived. David’s two wives were with him—Ahinoam from Jezreel, and Nabal’s widow Abigail, from Carmel. <verse eid="1SA 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 27:4"/>When someone told Saul that David had run away <char style="add">and was living</char> in Gath, he stopped searching for David.<verse eid="1SA 27:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 27:5"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> David said to Achish, “If you are pleased with us, give us a place in one of the small villages where we can stay. There is no need [RHQ] for us to stay in the city where you are the king.”<verse eid="1SA 27:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 27:6"/>
    <char style="add">Achish liked what David suggested</char>. So that day Achish gave to David Ziklag <char style="add">town</char>. As a result, Ziklag has belonged to the kings of Judah since that time.<verse eid="1SA 27:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 27:7"/>David <char style="add">and his men</char> lived in the Philistia area for 16 months. <verse eid="1SA 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 27:8"/><char style="add">During that time</char> David and his men raided the people who lived <char style="add">in the areas</char> where the Geshur, Girzi, and Amalek people-groups lived. Those people had lived there a long time. That area extended <char style="add">south</char> from Telam to the Shur <char style="add">Desert</char> and to <char style="add">the border of</char> Egypt. <verse eid="1SA 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 27:9"/>Whenever David’s men attacked them, they killed all the men and women, and they took all the people’s sheep and cattle and donkeys and camels, and even their clothes. Then they would bring those things back home, <char style="add">and David would go to talk</char> to Achish.<verse eid="1SA 27:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 27:10"/>Each time Achish would ask David, “Where did you go raiding today?” David <char style="add">would lie to him</char>. Sometimes he would reply that they had gone to the southern part of Judah, and sometimes he would say that they had gone to Jerahmeel, or to the area where the Ken people-group lived. <verse eid="1SA 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 27:11"/>David’s men never brought back to Gath any man or woman who was left alive. David thought, “If <char style="add">we do not kill everyone, some of</char> them <char style="add">who are still alive</char> will go and tell Achish <char style="add">the truth</char> about what we really did.” David did that all the time that he <char style="add">and his men</char> lived in the Philistia area. <verse eid="1SA 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 27:12"/>So Achish believed <char style="add">what</char> David <char style="add">told him</char>, and said to himself, “<char style="add">Because of what David has done,</char> his own people, the Israelis, must now hate him very much. So he will have to <char style="add">stay here and</char> serve me forever.”<verse eid="1SA 27:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="1SA 28"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul consulted a witch/medium</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 28:1"/>Some time later, the people of Philistia gathered their army to attack the Israelis <char style="add">again</char>. King Achish told David, “I am expecting that you and your men will join with my men to attack <char style="add">the Israelis</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 28:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 28:2"/>David replied, “<char style="add">We will go with you, and then</char> you will see for yourself what we can do!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:2">Achish said, “Okay, I will appoint you to be my bodyguard permanently.”<verse eid="1SA 28:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 28:3"/>
    <char style="add">While Samuel was still alive, Saul did many things that pleased Yahweh. One of the good things that</char> Saul <char style="add">did was to</char> expel from Israel all the people who were fortune-tellers or who talked to the spirits of dead people. But Samuel had died, and all the Israeli people had mourned for him. Then they had buried him in Ramah, his hometown. <char style="add">After that, Saul did not try to please Yahweh any more</char>.<verse eid="1SA 28:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 28:4"/>The army of Philistia gathered and set up their tents at Shunem <char style="add">city, in the north of Israel</char>. Saul gathered the Israeli army and set up their tents at Gilboa <char style="add">in the eastern part of the same valley</char>. <verse eid="1SA 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 28:5"/>When Saul saw the army of Philistia, he became so afraid that his heart pounded/shook. <verse eid="1SA 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 28:6"/>He prayed to Yahweh, but Yahweh did not answer him. Yahweh did not <char style="add">tell Saul what he should do by </char> giving him a dream, or by <char style="add">having the priest throw</char> the marked stones <char style="add">that were in his sacred vest</char>, or by <char style="add">giving a message about Saul to</char> any prophet. <verse eid="1SA 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 28:7"/>Then Saul said to his servants, “Find for me a woman who talks to the spirits of dead people, in order that I can ask her <char style="add">what will happen</char>.” His servants replied, “There is a woman in Endor <char style="add">town</char> who does that.”<verse eid="1SA 28:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 28:8"/>So Saul <char style="add">took off the clothes that showed that he was the king, and he</char> put on ordinary clothes ◄to disguise himself/so that people would not recognize who he was►. Then he and two of his men went during the night to talk to that woman. Saul said to her, “I want you to talk to a spirit <char style="add">of someone who has died</char>. Cause to appear the person whose name I will <char style="add">give to you</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 28:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 28:9"/>But the woman replied, “You surely know what Saul has done. He expelled from this land all the people who talk to spirits of dead people and all fortune-tellers. I think that you are trying to trap me, in order that I will be executed <char style="add">for doing something that is not permitted</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 28:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 28:10"/>Saul replied, solemnly asking Yahweh to listen to what he was saying, “Just as surely as Yahweh lives, you will not be punished for doing this.”<verse eid="1SA 28:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 28:11"/>Then the woman said, “Whom do you want me to cause to appear?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:11">Saul replied, “Cause Samuel to appear.”<verse eid="1SA 28:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 28:12"/>
    <char style="add">So</char> the woman <char style="add">did that. But</char> when she saw Samuel, she screamed. She said, “You have tricked me [RHQ]! You are Saul! <char style="add">You will execute me for doing this</char>!”<verse eid="1SA 28:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 28:13"/>Saul said to her, “Do not be afraid. What do you see?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:13">The woman said, “I see a god/spirit coming up out of the ground.” <verse eid="1SA 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 28:14"/>Saul said, “What does he look like?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:14">The woman replied, “An old man wearing a robe is appearing.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:14">Then Saul knew that it was Samuel. So he bowed down with his face touching the ground. <verse eid="1SA 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 28:15"/>Samuel said to Saul, “Why have you bothered/disturbed me by causing me to appear?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 28:15">Saul said, “I am very worried. The army of Philistia is about to attack my army, and God has abandoned me. He does not answer my questions any more. He does not give me dreams <char style="add">to tell me what to do</char> or give messages to prophets <char style="add">to tell me what to do</char>. That is the reason that I came to see you. So you tell me what I should do!” <verse eid="1SA 28:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 28:16"/>Samuel said, “Yahweh has abandoned you and has become your enemy. So why do you ask me <char style="add">what you should do</char>? [RHQ] <verse eid="1SA 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 28:17"/>He has done what he told me <char style="add">previously</char> that he would do to you. He has torn the kingdom away from you, and he is giving it to someone who is another Israeli—David. <verse eid="1SA 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 28:18"/>You did not obey Yahweh. Yahweh was very angry with the Amalek people-group. You did not <char style="add">kill all of their animals</char>, with the result that you did not show that he was very angry with them. That is the reason that he has done this to you today. <verse eid="1SA 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 28:19"/>Yahweh will enable the Philistia army to defeat you and all the other Israeli soldiers. And tomorrow you and your sons will be with me <char style="add">in the place where spirits of dead people are</char>. Yahweh will cause the whole Israeli army to be defeated by the Philistia army.” <char style="add">And after Samuel said that, he disappeared</char>.<verse eid="1SA 28:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 28:20"/>Saul immediately fell flat on the ground. He was so afraid because of what Samuel had said that he became paralyzed. He was also very weak because he had not eaten anything all that day and night.<verse eid="1SA 28:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 28:21"/>The woman saw that he was extremely worried/terrified. She said to him, “Listen to me! I have done what you requested me to do. I could be executed for doing that. <verse eid="1SA 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 28:22"/>So now please pay attention to what I say. Allow me to give you some food, in order that you will <char style="add">eat it and</char> get enough strength to go back <char style="add">to your army</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 28:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 28:23"/>But Saul refused. He said, “No, I will not eat anything.” Then Saul’s servants also urged him <char style="add">to eat something</char>, and finally he heeded what they said. He got up from the ground and sat on the bed.<verse eid="1SA 28:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 28:24"/>The woman had a fat calf close to her house. She quickly slaughtered it <char style="add">and cooked it</char>. She took some flour and mixed it <char style="add">with olive oil</char>, and baked it without putting in any yeast. <verse eid="1SA 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 28:25"/>She placed the food in front of Saul and his servants, and they ate some of it. Then that night they got up and left.<verse eid="1SA 28:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="1SA 29"/>
  <para style="s1">The king of Philistia sent David back home</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 29:1"/>The Philistia army gathered at Aphek <char style="add">Valley, which is near Shunem</char>. The Israelis set up their tents at Jezreel <char style="add">city, which was in the same valley</char>. <verse eid="1SA 29:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 29:2"/>The kings of Philistia divided their men into groups; some groups had 100 soldiers and some groups had 1,000 soldiers. David and his men were marching behind, with King Achish. <verse eid="1SA 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 29:3"/>But the Philistia commanders asked, “What are these Hebrews <char style="add">doing here, marching with us to battle</char>?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 29:3">Achish replied, “<char style="add">Their leader is</char> David. <char style="add">He</char> previously worked for King Saul of Israel, but now he has been living near me for more than a year. During all the time since he left Saul, I have not seen/found that he has any faults.” <verse eid="1SA 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 29:4"/>But the Philistia army commanders were angry with Achish <char style="add">for allowing David’s army to be going with them</char>. They said to him, “Send David <char style="add">and his men</char> back to the city that you gave to him! We do not want him to go with us into the battle. <char style="add">If he goes with us,</char> we will have an enemy in our own midst! He would please King Saul by killing our own soldiers [RHQ]! <verse eid="1SA 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 29:5"/><char style="add">Have you forgotten that</char> David is the one about whom the Israelis dance and sing, saying,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="1SA 29:5">‘Saul has killed 1000 of our enemies,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="1SA 29:5">but David has killed 10,000 of them!’?”<verse eid="1SA 29:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 29:6"/>So Achish summoned David, and said to him, “Just as surely as Yahweh lives, you have been loyal to me. I would like very much for you to fight along with my army. Since the day that you came to me, I have not found/seen that you have any faults. But the other Philistia rulers do not trust you. <verse eid="1SA 29:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 29:7"/>So all of you go back home, and I hope/desire that things will go well for you. I do not want you(sg) to do anything that the other rulers of Philistia will not be pleased with.”<verse eid="1SA 29:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 29:8"/>David replied, “What wrong have I done? Since the day that I first came to you until today, have I done anything that you think is evil? Your majesty, why will you not allow me to go and fight against your enemies?”<verse eid="1SA 29:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 29:9"/>Achish replied, “I know that you are as just as good as an angel from God. But the commanders of my army have said, ‘We will not allow David <char style="add">and his men</char> to go with us into the battle.’ <verse eid="1SA 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 29:10"/>So early tomorrow morning you and your men must leave. Get up as soon as it is light and leave.”<verse eid="1SA 29:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 29:11"/>So David and his men got up early the following morning and returned to the area where the Philistia people lived. And the Philistia army went up to Jezreel.<verse eid="1SA 29:11"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="1SA 30"/>
  <para style="s1">David’s army defeated the Amalekites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 30:1"/>Three days later, when David and his men arrived at Ziklag, <char style="add">they discovered that</char> men of the Amalek people-group had raided Ziklag and <char style="add">towns in</char> the southern part of Judah. They had destroyed Ziklag and burned down all the buildings. <verse eid="1SA 30:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 30:2"/>They had captured the women <char style="add">and the children</char> and everyone else, and had taken them away. But they had not killed anyone.<verse eid="1SA 30:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 30:3"/>When David and his men came to Ziklag, they saw that the town had been burned, and that their wives and sons and daughters had been captured and taken away. <verse eid="1SA 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 30:4"/>David and his men cried loudly, until <char style="add">they were so weak that</char> they could not cry <char style="add">any more</char>. <verse eid="1SA 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 30:5"/>David’s two wives, Ahinoam and Abigail, had also been taken away. <verse eid="1SA 30:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 30:6"/>David’s men were threatening to <char style="add">kill him by </char> throwing stones at him, because they were very angry because their sons and daughters <char style="add">had been taken away</char>. David was very distressed, but Yahweh his God gave him strength.<verse eid="1SA 30:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 30:7"/>David <char style="add">did not know what to do, so he</char> said to Abiathar the priest, “Bring to me the sacred vest.” So Abiathar brought it, <verse eid="1SA 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 30:8"/>and David asked Yahweh, “Should I <char style="add">and my men</char> pursue the men <char style="add">who took our families</char>? Will we <char style="add">be able to</char> catch up to them?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 30:8">Yahweh answered <char style="add">by means of the stones in Abiathar’s sacred pouch</char>, “Yes, pursue them. You will catch up to them, and you will be able to rescue <char style="add">your families</char>.” <verse eid="1SA 30:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 30:9"/>So David and the 600 men who were with him left, and they came to the Besor Ravine. Some of his men stayed there <char style="add">with some of their supplies</char>. <verse eid="1SA 30:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 30:10"/>David and 400 men continued to pursue <char style="add">the men who captured their families</char>. The other 200 men stayed there at the ravine, because they were so exhausted that they could not cross the ravine.<verse eid="1SA 30:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 30:11"/>
    <char style="add">As David and the 400 men were going</char>, they saw a man from Egypt in a field; so they took him to David. They gave the man some water to drink and some food to eat. <verse eid="1SA 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 30:12"/>They also gave him a piece of fig cake and two clusters/packs of raisins. The man had not had anything to eat or drink for three days and nights, but <char style="add">after he ate and drank</char> he felt refreshed.<verse eid="1SA 30:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 30:13"/>David asked him, “Who is your master? And where do you come from?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 30:13">He replied, “I am from Egypt. I am a slave of a man from the Amalek people-group. Three days ago my master left me here, because I was sick <char style="add">and I was not able to go with them</char>. <verse eid="1SA 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1SA 30:14"/>We had raided the southern part of Judah where the Kereth people-group live, and some other towns in Judah, and the area south <char style="add">of Hebron city</char> where the descendants of Caleb live. We also burned Ziklag <char style="add">town</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 30:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="1SA 30:15"/>David asked him, “Can you lead us to this group of raiders?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 30:15">He replied, “Yes, <char style="add">I will do that</char> if you ask God to listen while you promise that you will not kill me or give me back to my master. If you promise that, I will take you to them.” <verse eid="1SA 30:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1SA 30:16"/><char style="add">David agreed to do that,</char> so the man from Egypt led David <char style="add">and his men</char> to where the men from the Amalek people-group were. Those men were lying on the ground, eating and drinking and celebrating because of having captured many things from the Philistia and Judah areas. <verse eid="1SA 30:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1SA 30:17"/>David <char style="add">and his men</char> fought against them from sunset that day until the evening of the following day. Four hundred of them escaped and rode away on camels, but none of the others escaped. <verse eid="1SA 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1SA 30:18"/>David rescued his two wives, and he and his men got back everything else that the men of the Amalek people-group had taken. <verse eid="1SA 30:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1SA 30:19"/>Nothing was missing. They took all their people back <char style="add">to Ziklag</char>—young people and old people, <char style="add">their wives</char>, their sons and their daughters. They also recovered all the other things that the men of the Amalek people-group had taken from Ziklag. <verse eid="1SA 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1SA 30:20"/>They took with them the sheep and cattle that had been captured, and his men caused those animals to go in front of them, saying, “These are animals that we captured in the battle; they belong to David!”<verse eid="1SA 30:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="1SA 30:21"/>David and his men got back to where the other 200 men were waiting, the men who did not go with David because they were very exhausted. They had stayed at Besor Ravine. <char style="add">When they saw David and his men coming</char>, they went out to greet them. And David <char style="add">greeted them and</char> said to them, “I hope that things are going well with you!”<verse eid="1SA 30:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="1SA 30:22"/>But some of the men who had gone with David, men who were evil and troublemakers, said, “These 200 men did not go with us. So we should not give to them any of the things that we recovered/captured. Each of them should take only his wife and children and go <char style="add">back to their homes</char>.”<verse eid="1SA 30:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="1SA 30:23"/>David replied, “No, my fellow Israelis, it would not be right to divide up like that the things that Yahweh has allowed us to capture. Yahweh has protected us and enabled us to defeat the enemies who attacked our town. <verse eid="1SA 30:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1SA 30:24"/>◄Who will pay attention to you if you say things like that?/No one will pay attention to you if you say things like that.► [RHQ] The men who stayed here with our supplies will get the same amount that the men who went into the battle will get. They will all receive the same amount.” <verse eid="1SA 30:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1SA 30:25"/>David made that to be a law [DOU] for the Israeli people, and that is still a law in Israel.<verse eid="1SA 30:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="1SA 30:26"/>When David <char style="add">and all the others</char> arrived in Ziklag, David sent to his friends who were leaders in Judah some of the things that they had captured from the Amalek people-group. He said to them, “Here is a present for you. These are things that we took from Yahweh’s enemies.”<verse eid="1SA 30:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="1SA 30:27"/>
    <char style="add">Here is a list of the cities and towns to whose leaders David sent gifts:</char> Bethel, Ramoth in the southern part of Judah, Jattir, <verse eid="1SA 30:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1SA 30:28"/>Aroer, Siphmoth, Eshtemoa, <verse eid="1SA 30:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1SA 30:29"/>Racal, the cities where the descendants of Jehrameel lived and the cities where the Ken people-group lived, <verse eid="1SA 30:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1SA 30:30"/>Hormah, Bor-Ashan, Athach, <verse eid="1SA 30:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1SA 30:31"/>Hebron, and all the other places where David and his men had gone <char style="add">when they were hiding from Saul</char>.<verse eid="1SA 30:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="1SA 31"/>
  <para style="s1">Saul and his sons died in a battle</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="1SA 31:1"/>Later, the Philistines again fought against the Israelis. The Israelis ran away from them, and ◄many Israelis were killed/the Philistines killed many Israelis► on Gilboa Mountain. <verse eid="1SA 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1SA 31:2"/>The Philistines caught up with Saul and his three sons, and they killed <char style="add">all three of</char> his sons, Jonathan and Abinadab and Malchishua. <verse eid="1SA 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1SA 31:3"/>The fighting was very fierce around Saul. When the Philistine ◄archers/men with bows and arrows► caught up with Saul, they wounded him badly <char style="add">with their arrows</char>.<verse eid="1SA 31:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="1SA 31:4"/>Saul said to the man who was carrying his weapons, “Take out your sword and kill me with it, in order that these heathen Philistines will not be able to thrust their swords into me and make fun of me <char style="add">while I am dying</char>.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="1SA 31:4">But the man who was carrying Saul’s weapons was terrified, and refused to do that. So Saul took his own sword and fell on it. <char style="add">The sword pierced his body and he died</char>. <verse eid="1SA 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1SA 31:5"/>When the man carrying his weapons saw that Saul was dead, he also threw himself on his own sword and died. <verse eid="1SA 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1SA 31:6"/>So Saul, three of his sons, and the man who carried Saul’s weapons, all died on that same day.<verse eid="1SA 31:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="1SA 31:7"/>When the Israeli people on the north side of the <char style="add">Jezreel</char> Valley and on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> heard that the Israeli army had run away and that Saul and his sons had died, they left their towns and ran away. Then the Philistines came and occupied their towns.<verse eid="1SA 31:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="1SA 31:8"/>The next day, when the Philistines came to take away the weapons of the dead <char style="add">Israeli soldiers</char>, they found the bodies of Saul and his three sons on Gilboa Mountain. <verse eid="1SA 31:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1SA 31:9"/>They cut off Saul’s head and took his weapons. Then they sent messengers throughout their land, to proclaim the news, in the temple where they kept their idols, and to the other people, <char style="add">that their army had killed Saul</char>. <verse eid="1SA 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1SA 31:10"/>They put Saul’s weapons in the temple of <char style="add">their goddess</char> Astarte. They also fastened the bodies of Saul <char style="add">and his sons</char> to the wall <char style="add">that surrounded</char> Beth-Shan <char style="add">city</char>.<verse eid="1SA 31:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="1SA 31:11"/>When the people who lived in Jabesh in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> heard what the Philistines had done to Saul’s corpse, <verse eid="1SA 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1SA 31:12"/>all their bravest soldiers walked all night to Beth-Shan. They took the corpses of Saul and his sons down from the city wall, and they took them back to Jabesh and burned the corpses there. <verse eid="1SA 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1SA 31:13"/>They took the bones and buried them under a <char style="add">big</char> tamarisk tree. Then they ◄fasted/abstained from eating food► for seven days.<verse eid="1SA 31:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="1SA 31"/>
</usx>
