<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2CH" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">2 CHRONICLES</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Chronicles</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Ch</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of the reign of King Solomon and of the other kings of Judah until the Babylonians destroyed Jerusalem. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 Chronicles</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2CH 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Solomon prayed for wisdom</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 1:1"/>David’s son <char style="add">King</char> Solomon was able to gain complete control over his kingdom, because Yahweh his God helped him and enabled him to become very powerful.<verse eid="2CH 1:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2-5" style="v" sid="2CH 1:2-5"/>
    <char style="add">When</char> David <char style="add">was king, he had arranged for a new</char> Sacred Tent <char style="add">to be</char> made in Jerusalem. Then David <char style="add">and the Israeli leaders</char> had brought God’s Sacred Chest from Kiriath-Jearim <char style="add">city</char> to the new Sacred Tent in Jerusalem that he had prepared for it. But <char style="add">when Solomon became the king,</char> the first Sacred Tent was still at Gibeon <char style="add">city</char>. That was the tent that Moses, the man who served God <char style="add">well</char>, had <char style="add">arranged to be</char> made in the desert. And the bronze altar that Bezalel, the son of Uri and grandson of Hur, had made was also still in Gibeon, in front of the first Sacred Tent.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 1:2-5">
    <char style="add">One day</char> Solomon summoned the army commanders of 1,000 soldiers and the commanders of 100 soldiers and the judges and all the other leaders in Israel. He told them to go with him to Gibeon. So they all went to a hill in Gibeon <char style="add">where the Sacred Tent was</char>, and Solomon and all the others with him worshiped Yahweh there. <verse eid="2CH 1:2-5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 1:6"/>Then Solomon went up to the bronze altar in front of the Sacred Tent, and he offered 1,000 animals to be <char style="add">killed and</char> completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>.<verse eid="2CH 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 1:7"/>That night God appeared to Solomon <char style="add">in a dream</char> and said to him, “Request whatever you want me to give to you.”<verse eid="2CH 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 1:8"/>Solomon replied, “You were very kind to David my father, and now you have appointed me to be the king to succeed him. <verse eid="2CH 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 1:9"/>So Yahweh my God, you have caused me to become the king to rule people who are as many as the particles of dirt on the earth. So do what you promised my father David. <verse eid="2CH 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 1:10"/>Please enable me to be wise and to know <char style="add">what I should do</char>, in order that I may rule these people <char style="add">well</char>, because there is no one who can rule all this great nation of yours <char style="add">without your help</char>.”<verse eid="2CH 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 1:11"/>God replied, “<char style="add">I am pleased with what</char> you desire; you have not requested a huge amount of money or to be honored or that your enemies be killed. And you have not requested that you live for a long time. Instead, you have requested that <char style="add">I enable</char> you <char style="add">to</char> be wise and <char style="add">to</char> know <char style="add">what you should do</char> in order that you may govern <char style="add">well</char> my people whom I have appointed you to rule. <verse eid="2CH 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 1:12"/>Therefore I will enable you to be wise and to know <char style="add">what you should do to rule my people well</char>. But I will also enable you to have a huge amount of money and to be honored, more than anyone who was previously a king ever was honored, more than anyone who later becomes king will be honored.” <verse eid="2CH 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 1:13"/>Then Solomon <char style="add">and the people who were with him all</char> left from being in front of he Sacred Tent <char style="add">on the hill in Gibeon</char>, and they returned to Jerusalem. From there he ruled the Israeli people.<verse eid="2CH 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s wealth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 1:14"/>Solomon acquired 1,400 chariots and 12,000 men who rode <char style="add">on horses</char>. He put some of the chariots and horses in Jerusalem, and put some of them in various other cities. <verse eid="2CH 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 1:15"/>During the years that Solomon was king, silver and gold were as common in Jerusalem as stones, and <char style="add">lumber from</char> cedar trees were as plentiful as <char style="add">lumber from</char> ordinary sycamore trees in the foothills. <verse eid="2CH 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 1:16"/>Solomon’s horses were imported/brought from Egypt and from <char style="add">the</char> Kue <char style="add">region in Turkey</char>. <verse eid="2CH 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 1:17"/>In Egypt his men paid 15 pounds of silver for each chariot and 3-3/4 pounds of silver for each horse. They also exported/sold many of them to the kings of the Heth and Aram people-groups.<verse eid="2CH 1:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2CH 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Preparations for building the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 2:1"/>Solomon ordered that a temple should be built where Yahweh would be worshiped and also that a palace should be built for himself. <verse eid="2CH 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 2:2"/>He selected 70,000 men to carry the building supplies and 80,000 men to cut stones <char style="add">◄from quarries/walls of rock► in</char> the hills. He also chose 3,600 men to supervise them.<verse eid="2CH 2:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 2:3"/>Solomon sent this message to King Hiram of Tyre <char style="add">city</char>:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 2:3">“<char style="add">Many years ago</char> when my father David was building his palace, you sent to him cedar logs. Will you send me cedar logs, too?<verse eid="2CH 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 2:4"/>“We are about to build a temple where we will worship Yahweh our God. We want to dedicate it to be a place where we will burn fragrant incense to <char style="add">honor</char> him, and a place to put loaves of sacred bread, and for making sacrifices every morning and every evening and every Sabbath day, and to celebrate on the day of every new moon and at other special religious festivals to <char style="add">honor</char> Yahweh our God. We want to do those things forever, like Yahweh has commanded. <verse eid="2CH 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 2:5"/><char style="add">We want</char> this temple <char style="add">to</char> be a great temple, because our God is greater than all other gods. <verse eid="2CH 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 2:6"/>But no one can really build a temple that would be big enough for God <char style="add">to live in</char>, because even the highest heavens are not big enough for him. And I am worthy only to build a place where we can burn sacrifices to him.<verse eid="2CH 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 2:7"/>Therefore, please send me a man who knows well how to make things from gold and silver and bronze and iron, and to make things from purple and red and blue cloth. He should also know well how to engrave designs. I want him to work in Jerusalem and in other places in Judah with my skilled craftsmen, the ones whom my father David appointed.<verse eid="2CH 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 2:8"/>I know that your workers are skilled in cutting timber, so also please send me cedar logs, pine logs, and juniper logs from the Lebanon mountains. My workers will work with your workers. <verse eid="2CH 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 2:9"/>In that way, those workers will provide me with plenty of lumber. <char style="add">We will need plenty,</char> because I want the temple that we will build to be large and beautiful. <verse eid="2CH 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 2:10"/>I will pay your workers, the men who cut the logs, 100,000 bushels of ground wheat, 100,000 bushels of barley, 110,000 gallons of wine, and 110,000 gallons of olive oil.”<verse eid="2CH 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 2:11"/>
    <char style="add">When</char> Hiram <char style="add">received that message, he</char> replied by sending this message to Solomon:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 2:11">“Because Yahweh loves his people, he has appointed you to be their king.”<verse eid="2CH 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 2:12"/>
    <char style="add">And Hiram added,</char></para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 2:12">“Praise Yahweh, the God to whom the Israeli people belong, the one who created the sky and the earth! He has given King David a wise son, one who is very smart/intelligent and who has good skill and understanding. He wants to build a temple for Yahweh and a palace for himself.<verse eid="2CH 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 2:13"/>“I will be sending to you Huram-Abi, a man who is very skilled. <verse eid="2CH 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 2:14"/>His mother was from the tribe of Dan, and his father was from <char style="add">here in</char> Tyre. He is very able to make things from gold and silver and bronze and iron and stone and wood, but he also makes nice things from purple and blue and red cloth, and he does all kinds of engraving. He can make things using any design/pattern that you give to him. He will work with your craftsmen, and the craftsmen who did work for your father, King David.<verse eid="2CH 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 2:15"/>“Now please send us the wheat and barley and olive oil and wine that you promised to send to us. <verse eid="2CH 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 2:16"/>When you do that, my workers will cut from trees in the Lebanon mountains all the logs that you need <char style="add">and bring them down to the sea</char>. Then we will <char style="add">tie the logs together to</char> form rafts with them, and float them in the sea to Joppa <char style="add">city</char>. From there, you <char style="add">can arrange for</char> them <char style="add">to be</char> taken up to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 2:17"/>Solomon told his workers to count all the people from other countries who were living in Israel, similar to what his father David had done. There were 153,600 of them. <verse eid="2CH 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 2:18"/>Solomon assigned 70,000 of them to carry materials, and 80,000 to cut stone <char style="add">from quarries in</char> the hills, and 3,600 of them to supervise the others and be sure that they worked steadily.<verse eid="2CH 2:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2CH 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s workers built the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 3:1"/>Then Solomon’s workers started to build the temple for Yahweh in Jerusalem. They built it on Moriah Hill, where <char style="add">an angel from</char> Yahweh had appeared to his father David. They built it on the ground that Araunah, a descendant of the Jebus people-group, had sold to David and where David said that it should be built. <verse eid="2CH 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 3:2"/>They began the work in April, when Solomon had been ruling almost four years.<verse eid="2CH 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 3:3"/>The foundation of the temple was about 90 feet long and 30 feet wide. <verse eid="2CH 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 3:4"/>The entrance room across the front of the temple was 30 feet wide and 30 feet high.<verse eid="2CH 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 3:5"/>Solomon’s workers used <char style="add">panels/boards of</char> pine <char style="add">wood</char> to line the main hall of the temple. Then they covered those panels with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> pure gold. Then they decorated the walls with <char style="add">carved images of</char> palm trees and designs that resembled chains. <verse eid="2CH 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 3:6"/>They decorated the temple with very valuable stones. The gold that they used was from <char style="add">the land of</char> Parvaim.<verse eid="2CH 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 3:7"/>They covered the ceiling beams, the door frames, the walls and the doors of the temple with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> gold. They also carved <char style="add">statues of</char> winged creatures on the walls. <verse eid="2CH 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 3:8"/>They also built the Very Holy Place <char style="add">inside the temple</char>. It was 30 feet wide and 30 feet long. They covered its walls with sheets of pure gold that altogether weighed 23 tons. <verse eid="2CH 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 3:9"/>They used 1-1/4 pounds of gold to <char style="add">cover the heads of </char> the nails. They also covered the walls of the upper rooms with sheets of gold.<verse eid="2CH 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 3:10"/>Solomon’s workers made two statues of creatures with wings to put inside the Very Holy Place. They covered those statues with <char style="add">very thin sheets of</char> gold. <verse eid="2CH 3:10"/><verse number="11-12" style="v" sid="2CH 3:11-12"/><char style="add">Each statue had two long wings</char>. One wing of each statue touched one of the walls of the Temple. The other wing of each statue touched a wing of the other statue. It was 7-1/2 feet from the outer tip of one wing to the outer tip of the other wing. The inner wings of the two statues touched each other.<verse eid="2CH 3:11-12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 3:13"/>It was 30 feet from the outer wing of the one statue to the outer wing of the other statue. The statues faced the doorway to the main room.<verse eid="2CH 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 3:14"/>Solomon’s workers made a curtain <char style="add">to separate the main room from the Very Holy Place</char>. It was made of blue, purple, and red thread and fine linen. There were figures of winged creatures that were embroidered on the curtain. <verse eid="2CH 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 3:15"/>They made two <char style="add">bronze</char> pillars and put them at the entrance of the temple. They were each 27 feet high. Each had a top over it that was 7-1/2 feet high. <verse eid="2CH 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 3:16"/>The workers made <char style="add">carvings that resembled</char> chains and put them on top of the pillars. They made <char style="add">carvings that resembled</char> pomegranates and attached them to the chains. <verse eid="2CH 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 3:17"/>They set up the pillars in front of the temple, one on the south side <char style="add">of the entrance</char> and the other on the north side. The one on the south side was named Jakin and the one on the north side was named Boaz.<verse eid="2CH 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2CH 4"/>
  <para style="s1">The furnishings for the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 4:1"/>Solomon’s workers made a square bronze altar that was 10 yards wide on each side, and it was 5 yards high. <verse eid="2CH 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 4:2"/>They also made a very large round tank that was made of metal and cast <char style="add">in a clay mold</char>. It was 10 yards wide/across, and 5 yards high. It was 15 yards around it. <verse eid="2CH 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 4:3"/>Below the outer rim there were two rows of <char style="add">small figures of</char> bulls that were part of the metal of the basin. Each row had 300 figures of bulls.<verse eid="2CH 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 4:4"/>The basin was set on twelve <char style="add">statues of</char> bulls. There were three statues that faced north, three that faced west, three that faced south, and three that faced east. <verse eid="2CH 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 4:5"/>The sides of the tank were 3 inches thick, and its rim was shaped like a cup that curved outward like the petals of flowers. The basin held about 16,500 gallons <char style="add">of water</char>.<verse eid="2CH 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 4:6"/>They also made ten basins for washing the <char style="add">animals that were</char> to be sacrificed. The priests used the very large tank for washing themselves.<verse eid="2CH 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 4:7"/>They also made ten gold lampstands according to what Solomon had instructed them. They put them in the temple, five on the south side and five on the north side.<verse eid="2CH 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 4:8"/>They made ten tables and put them in the temple, five on the south side and five on the north side. They also made 100 gold bowls.<verse eid="2CH 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 4:9"/>They also constructed one courtyard for the priests, and a larger courtyard <char style="add">for the other people</char>. They made doors for the courtyards and covered them with <char style="add">thin sheets of</char> bronze. <verse eid="2CH 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 4:10"/>They placed the very large tank <char style="add">on the south side of the temple,</char> at the southeast corner.<verse eid="2CH 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 4:11"/>They also made pots and shovels <char style="add">for the ashes of the altar</char>, and other small bowls.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="2CH 4:11"/>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 4:11">So Huram <char style="add">and his workers</char> finished the work that King Solomon had given him to do at the temple of God. <verse eid="2CH 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 4:12"/><char style="add">These were the things that they made:</char></para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 4:12">the two large pillars,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 4:12">the two bowl-shaped top parts on top of the pillars,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 4:12">the two sets of carvings that resembled chains to decorate the tops of the two pillars,<verse eid="2CH 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 4:13"/>the 400 carvings that resembled pomegranates that were placed in two rows, that decorated the bowl-shaped tops of the two pillars,<verse eid="2CH 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 4:14"/>the stands, and the basins that were placed on them,<verse eid="2CH 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 4:15"/>the very large tank, and the <char style="add">statues of</char> twelve bulls underneath it,<verse eid="2CH 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 4:16"/>the pots, shovels, meat forks, and all the other things <char style="add">needed for the work at the altar</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 4:16">All those things that Huram <char style="add">and his workers</char> made for King Solomon were made of polished bronze. <verse eid="2CH 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 4:17"/>They made them by pouring melted bronze into the clay molds that Huram had set up near the Jordan <char style="add">river</char> between Succoth and Zarethan <char style="add">cities</char>. <verse eid="2CH 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 4:18"/>All of those things that Solomon <char style="add">told them to</char> make used a very large amount of bronze; no one tried to weigh it all.<verse eid="2CH 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 4:19"/>Solomon’s workers also made all these things that were put at the temple:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 4:19">the golden altar,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 4:19">the tables on which the priests put the sacred bread,<verse eid="2CH 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 4:20"/>the pure gold lampstands and the pure gold lamps, <char style="add">in which the priests put oil</char> to burn in front of the Most Holy Place as God had told <char style="add">Moses that the priests should do</char>,<verse eid="2CH 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 4:21"/>the pure gold decorations that resembled flowers, and the lamps and tongs,<verse eid="2CH 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 4:22"/>the pure gold wick trimmers and bowls for sprinkling, and dishes and lamp snuffers,</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 4:22">the gold doors of the temple</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 4:22">and the doors to the main hall.<verse eid="2CH 4:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="2CH 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 5:1"/>After Solomon’s workers had finished building the temple, Solomon put in the temple storage rooms everything that his father David had dedicated to Yahweh—all the silver and gold and all the other things that were used at the temple.<verse eid="2CH 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Sacred Chest was brought to the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 5:2"/>Then King Solomon summoned to Jerusalem all the elders of Israel, all the leaders of the tribes and of the families/clans. He wanted them to help to bring to the temple Yahweh’s Sacred Chest from Zion <char style="add">Hill</char>, where it was in <char style="add">the part of the city called</char> ‘The City of David’. <verse eid="2CH 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 5:3"/>So all the leaders of Israel gathered together along with the king, during the Festival of <char style="add">Living in Temporary</char> Shelters, in October.<verse eid="2CH 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 5:4"/>When they had all arrived, the descendants of Levi lifted up the Sacred Chest, <verse eid="2CH 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 5:5"/>and they carried it and the Sacred Tent and the sacred things that were inside it. The priests, who were also descended from Levi, carried them. <verse eid="2CH 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 5:6"/>King Solomon and many of the other people of Israel who had gathered there walked in front of the Sacred Chest. And they sacrificed a huge amount of sheep and cattle. No one was able to count them <char style="add">because there were very many</char>.<verse eid="2CH 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 5:7"/>The priests then brought the Sacred Chest into the Most Holy Place, the inner room of the temple, and they placed it under the wings of the statues of winged creatures. <verse eid="2CH 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 5:8"/>The wings of those statues spread out over the Sacred Chest and over the poles by which it was carried. <verse eid="2CH 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 5:9"/>The poles were very long, with the result that they could be seen by <char style="add">those who were standing</char> at the entrance to the Most Holy Place, but they could not be seen by anyone standing outside the temple. Those poles are still there. <verse eid="2CH 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 5:10"/>The only things that were inside the Sacred Chest were the two stone tablets that Moses had put there at Sinai Mountain, where Yahweh made an agreement with the Israeli people after they came out of Egypt.<verse eid="2CH 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 5:11"/>Then the priests left the Holy Place. All the priests who were there, from every group, had performed the rituals to cause them to be acceptable to God. <verse eid="2CH 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 5:12"/>All the descendants of Levi who were musicians—Asaph, Heman, Jeduthun, their sons and their other relatives—stood on the east side of the altar. They were wearing linen clothes, and they were playing cymbals, harps, and lyres. There were 120 other priests who were blowing trumpets. <verse eid="2CH 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 5:13"/>The men blowing trumpets, those playing the cymbals and other musical instruments, and the singers, made music together, praising Yahweh and singing this song:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 5:13">“Yahweh is good <char style="add">to us</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 5:13">he faithfully loves us forever.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 5:13">Then <char style="add">suddenly</char> the temple was filled with a cloud. <verse eid="2CH 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 5:14"/>The glorious radiance of Yahweh filled the temple, with the result that the priests were not able to continue doing their work.<verse eid="2CH 5:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="2CH 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 6:1"/>Then Solomon said, “Yahweh, you said that you would live in a dark cloud. <verse eid="2CH 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 6:2"/>But now I have built a glorious temple for you to live in forever!”<verse eid="2CH 6:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 6:3"/>Then while all the people stood there, Solomon turned toward the people and he <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless them. <verse eid="2CH 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 6:4"/>He said to them,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 6:4">“Praise Yahweh, the God to whom we Israelis belong, who has caused to happen what he promised to my father David. What he said to David was this:<verse eid="2CH 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 6:5"/>‘From the time that I brought my people out of Egypt, I have never chosen a city in Israel in which a temple should be built for people to <char style="add">worship</char> me there. Nor did I choose anyone to be the leader of my Israeli people. <verse eid="2CH 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 6:6"/>But now I have chosen Jerusalem to be the place for people to worship me, and I have chosen you to rule my Israeli people.’ ”<verse eid="2CH 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 6:7"/>
    <char style="add">Then Solomon said</char>, “My father David wanted to build a temple for Yahweh, the God to whom we Israelis belong. <verse eid="2CH 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 6:8"/>But Yahweh said to him, ‘You have wanted to build a temple for me, and what you wanted to do was good. <verse eid="2CH 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 6:9"/>However, you are not the one who I want to build the temple; it is one of your own sons who <char style="add">I want to</char> build a temple for me.’<verse eid="2CH 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 6:10"/>“And Yahweh has done what he promised to do. I have become the king of Israel to succeed my father, and I am ruling the people, like Yahweh promised, and I have arranged for this temple to be built for us to worship Yahweh, the God to whom we Israelis belong. <verse eid="2CH 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 6:11"/>I have put the Sacred Chest in the temple, in which are the stone tablets <char style="add">on which are engraved the Ten Commandments of</char> the agreement that Yahweh made with us Israeli people.”<verse eid="2CH 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s prayer to dedicate the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 6:12"/>Then Solomon stood in front of the altar which was in front of the people of Israel who had gathered there. <verse eid="2CH 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 6:13"/>His workers had built a bronze platform there <char style="add">for him to stand on</char>, which was 7-1/2 feet long and 7-1/2 feet wide and 4-1/2 feet high. They put it in the outer courtyard. Solomon stood on that platform and then knelt down in front of all the people of Israel who had gathered there, and he spread out his arms toward heaven, <verse eid="2CH 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 6:14"/>and he prayed,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 6:14">“Yahweh, the God to whom we Israeli people belong, there is no God like you in heaven or on the earth. You solemnly promised that you would faithfully love us, and that is what you have done for us who earnestly do what you want us to do.<verse eid="2CH 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 6:15"/>“You have done the things that you promised my father David, who served you <char style="add">very well</char>, that you would do. Truly, you promised to do those things for him, and today we see that by your power you have caused it all to happen.<verse eid="2CH 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 6:16"/>“So now, Yahweh, the God we Israelis belong to, please do the things that you promised to my father David that you would do. You said that there would always be some of his descendants to rule Israel, if they faithfully conduct their lives as he did. <verse eid="2CH 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 6:17"/>So now, God of us Israeli people, cause what you promised David, who served you <char style="add">well</char>, to happen.<verse eid="2CH 6:17"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 6:18"/>“But, my God, will you really live on earth among people? There is surely not enough space for you in the sky, or even in the heaven! So there is surely not enough space for you to live in this temple that my workers have built. <verse eid="2CH 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 6:19"/>But Yahweh, my God, please listen to my prayer, while I am pleading with you this day and do what I am requesting. <verse eid="2CH 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 6:20"/>Please protect this temple day and night. This is the place about which you have said, ‘I will always be there.’ Please listen to my prayer about this place. <verse eid="2CH 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 6:21"/>Listen to me when I pray, and listen to your Israeli people when they pray. Listen from heaven, where you live; and when you hear us pray, forgive us.<verse eid="2CH 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 6:22"/>“If someone is accused of doing something wrong to another person, and they bring him to testify in front of your altar outside this holy temple, and if he says, ‘I did not do that; may God punish me if I am not telling the truth,’ <verse eid="2CH 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 6:23"/>then you listen from heaven, and you decide who is telling the truth. Then punish the person who is guilty as he deserves to be punished, and declare that the other person is innocent.<verse eid="2CH 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 6:24"/>“And when your Israeli people are defeated by their enemies because they sinned against you, <char style="add">and forced to go to some distant country,</char> if they turn away from their sinful behavior and turn toward this temple and admit <char style="add">that</char> you <char style="add">have justly punished them</char>, and plead <char style="add">that you will forgive them</char>, <verse eid="2CH 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 6:25"/>listen to them from heaven and forgive your Israeli people for the sins that they <char style="add">have committed</char>, and bring them back to this land that you gave to our ancestors.<verse eid="2CH 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 6:26"/>“When you do not allow any rain to fall because your people have sinned against you, if they turn toward this temple and admit <char style="add">that</char> you <char style="add">have justly punished them</char>, and turn away from their sinful behavior and humbly pray to you, <verse eid="2CH 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 6:27"/>hear from heaven and forgive the sins of your Israeli people. Teach them the right way to conduct their lives. Then cause it to rain here on the land that you gave to your people to belong to them <char style="add">permanently</char>.<verse eid="2CH 6:27"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 6:28"/>“And when the people of this land experience famines or if there is a plague, or when their crops are destroyed by very hot winds or by mildew or by locusts or grasshoppers, or when their enemies surround any of their cities <char style="add">in order to attack them</char>, if any of those bad things happen to them, <verse eid="2CH 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 6:29"/>when your Israeli people earnestly plead with you, knowing in their inner beings that they are suffering <char style="add">because they have sinned</char>, if they stretch out their hands toward this temple and pray, <verse eid="2CH 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 6:30"/>hear from your home in heaven, and forgive them. You alone know what each person is thinking, so reward each person according to everything that he does, <verse eid="2CH 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 6:31"/>in order that they will revere you and conduct their lives as you want them to, all the time that they live in this land that you gave to our ancestors.<verse eid="2CH 6:31"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 6:32"/>“There will be some foreigners who do not belong to your Israeli people who have come here from countries far away because they have heard that you are very great and that you perform great miracles. If they turn toward this temple and pray, <verse eid="2CH 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 6:33"/>from your home in heaven listen to their prayer, and do for them what they request you to do. Do that in order that all the people-groups in the world will know about you and revere you, like we, your own Israeli people do. And then they will know that this is the temple that I have caused to be built for you.<verse eid="2CH 6:33"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 6:34"/>“When you send your people to go to places to attack their enemies, if they pray to you, wherever they are, if they turn toward this city that you have chosen and toward this temple that I have caused to be built to honor you, <verse eid="2CH 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 6:35"/>listen in heaven to their prayers; listen to what they plead for you <char style="add">to do</char>, and assist them.<verse eid="2CH 6:35"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 6:36"/>
    <char style="add">“It is true that</char> everyone sins. So, when your people sin against you, and you become angry with them, you may allow their enemies to capture them and take them to their countries, even to countries that are far away. <verse eid="2CH 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2CH 6:37"/>When that happens, while they are in the countries to which they were forced to go, if they are sorry for having sinned, if they say, ‘We have sinned; we have done things that are wrong and have done things that are very wicked,’ <verse eid="2CH 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="2CH 6:38"/>if they repent very sincerely, and if they turn toward this land that you gave to our ancestors, and toward this city that you have chosen <char style="add">to be the place where we should worship you</char>, and toward this temple that I have caused to be built for you and pray, <verse eid="2CH 6:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="2CH 6:39"/>then from your home in heaven hear their prayer, and listen to them while they plead <char style="add">for your help</char>, and do what they ask you to do, and forgive your people who have sinned against you.<verse eid="2CH 6:39"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="2CH 6:40"/>“Now, my God, look at us and listen to us as we pray to you in this place.<verse eid="2CH 6:40"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="2CH 6:41"/>Yahweh our God, come and stay in this place with the Sacred Chest,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 6:41">the chest that shows that you are powerful.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 6:41">Yahweh God, cause your priests to know clearly that you have blessed them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 6:41">Cause us your people to rejoice because of all the good things <char style="add">that you do for us</char>.<verse eid="2CH 6:41"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="2CH 6:42"/>Yahweh God, do not reject me <char style="add">the king</char> whom you have appointed <char style="add">to be the king of Israel</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 6:42">do not forget that you greatly loved David, who served you <char style="add">very well</char>.”<verse eid="2CH 6:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="2CH 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Solomon dedicated the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 7:1"/>When Solomon finished praying, fire came down from the sky and burned all the offerings and sacrifices <char style="add">that were on the altar</char>, and the glorious radiance of Yahweh filled the temple. <verse eid="2CH 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 7:2"/>The radiance <char style="add">was extremely bright</char>, with the result that the priests could not enter the temple of Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 7:3"/>When all the Israeli people <char style="add">who were there</char> saw the fire coming down and the glory of Yahweh above the temple, they prostrated themselves with their faces touching the ground. They worshiped and thanked Yahweh, singing,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 7:3">“Yahweh is always good to us;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 7:3">he faithfully loves us forever.”<verse eid="2CH 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="4-5" style="v" sid="2CH 7:4-5"/>Then the king and all the people who were there dedicated the temple to Yahweh by offering more sacrifices to him. King Solomon gave 22,000 cattle and 120,000 sheep and goats to be sacrificed. <verse eid="2CH 7:4-5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 7:6"/>The priests stood in their positions, and the other descendants of Levi stood in their positions holding the musical instruments <char style="add">to praise</char> Yahweh, instruments that King David had caused to be made for praising Yahweh and thanking him. <char style="add">They sang</char>, “He faithfully loves us forever.” Facing the other descendants of Levi the priests stood, blowing their trumpets, while all the Israeli people were standing <char style="add">and listening</char>.<verse eid="2CH 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 7:7"/>Solomon dedicated the middle part of the courtyard in front of the temple. Then he gave offerings to be completely burned there along with the fat of the animals to be sacrificed to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. The priests burned them there in the courtyard because in addition to those things there were offerings of grain, with the result that there was not enough space on the bronze altar to burn all those sacrifices.<verse eid="2CH 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 7:8"/>Solomon <char style="add">and the other people</char> celebrated the Festival of Living in Temporary Shelters for seven days. There was a huge group of people who celebrated with him. Some of them came from <char style="add">as far away as</char> Lebo-Hamath <char style="add">in the far north</char> and the border of Egypt <char style="add">in the far south</char>. <verse eid="2CH 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 7:9"/>On the eighth/next day they gathered again <char style="add">to worship Yahweh</char>. They had celebrated the dedication of the altar for seven days and the Festival of Living in Temporary Shelters for seven days. <verse eid="2CH 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 7:10"/>Then on the next day Solomon sent them to their homes. They were very joyful because of all the good things that Yahweh had done for David and Solomon and for all his Israeli people.<verse eid="2CH 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh appeared to Solomon again</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 7:11"/>Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> finished building the temple and Solomon’s palace. And Solomon finished doing everything else that he had planned to do. <verse eid="2CH 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 7:12"/>Then Yahweh appeared to him one night <char style="add">in a dream</char> and said to him,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 7:12">“I have heard your prayer, and I have chosen this temple to be the place where my people will offer sacrifices to me.<verse eid="2CH 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 7:13"/>“When I prevent any rain from falling, or when I command locusts to eat all the crops, or when I send a plague among my people, <verse eid="2CH 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 7:14"/>if the people who belong to me humble themselves and pray, and request me to help them, and if they turn away from their sinful behavior, then I will hear from heaven. I will forgive them for having sinned and I will cause them to prosper again. <verse eid="2CH 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 7:15"/>I [SYN] will see them and I [SYN] will hear them when they pray to me in this place. <verse eid="2CH 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 7:16"/>I have chosen and have ◄set apart/dedicated► this temple in order that people may worship [MTY] me there forever. I will always watch over [MTY] it and protect [IDM] it.<verse eid="2CH 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 7:17"/>“And as for you, if you obey me as David your father did, and if you do all that I command you to do, and obey all my laws and decrees, <verse eid="2CH 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 7:18"/>I will make sure that your descendants will always be kings, which is what I promised to David your father, saying, ‘Some of your descendants will always be the kings of Israel.’<verse eid="2CH 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 7:19"/>“But if you Israelis turn away from me and disobey the decrees and commands that I have given to you, and you start to worship other gods, <verse eid="2CH 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 7:20"/>I will cause you to be expelled from this land that I have given to you, and I will abandon this temple that I have set apart to be the place where people should worship me. I will cause it to be despised and ridiculed by people of all nations. <verse eid="2CH 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 7:21"/>Although this temple is now greatly respected, when that happens, all the people who pass by will be appalled, and they will say, ‘Why has Yahweh done terrible things like this to this country and to this temple?’ <verse eid="2CH 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 7:22"/>And others will reply, ‘It happened because they rejected Yahweh, the God to whom their ancestors belonged, the one who brought their ancestors out of Egypt, and they have been worshiping other gods and trying to please them. And that is why Yahweh has caused them to experience all these disasters.’ ”<verse eid="2CH 7:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="2CH 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Other things that Solomon did</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 8:1"/>Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> worked for 20 years to build the temple and the king’s palace. <verse eid="2CH 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 8:2"/>Then his <char style="add">workers</char> rebuilt the cities that <char style="add">King</char> Hiram had given back to Solomon, and Solomon sent Israelis to live in those cities. <verse eid="2CH 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 8:3"/>Solomon’s <char style="add">army</char> then went to Hamath-Zobah <char style="add">town</char> and captured it. <verse eid="2CH 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 8:4"/>His workers also rebuilt walls around Tadmor <char style="add">town</char> in the desert, and in <char style="add">the</char> Hamath <char style="add">region</char> in all the towns where they kept supplies. <verse eid="2CH 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 8:5"/>They rebuilt Upper Beth-Horon <char style="add">town</char> and Lower Beth-Horon <char style="add">city</char>, and built walls around them with gates <char style="add">in the walls</char> and bars <char style="add">to fasten the gates</char>. <verse eid="2CH 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 8:6"/>They also rebuilt Baalath <char style="add">town</char> and all the cities where supplies were kept and the cities where Solomon’s chariots and horses were kept. Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> built whatever he wanted them to build, in Jerusalem and in Lebanon, and in other places in the area that he ruled.<verse eid="2CH 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 8:7"/>Solomon forced people from many other groups who were not Israelis to work for him like slaves. They were people from the Heth, Amor, Periz, Hiv, and Jebus people-groups. <verse eid="2CH 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 8:8"/>They were descendants of groups whom the Israelis had not completely destroyed. Solomon forced them to become his slaves, and they are still slaves. <verse eid="2CH 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 8:9"/>But Solomon did not force Israelis to work for him. Israelis became his soldiers and commanders of his chariots and his chariot-drivers. <verse eid="2CH 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 8:10"/>They were also King Solomon’s chief officials. There were 250 of them, and they supervised the workers.<verse eid="2CH 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 8:11"/>Solomon moved his wife, who was the daughter of the king of Egypt, from <char style="add">the place outside Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’ to the place that his workers had built for her. He said, “I do not want my wife to live in the palace that <char style="add">my father</char> King David’s workers built, because the Sacred Chest <char style="add">was in that palace for a while</char>, and any place where the Sacred Chest has been is holy.”<verse eid="2CH 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 8:12"/>On the altar that Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> had built in front of the entrance <char style="add">to the temple</char>, Solomon sacrificed many offerings that were to be completely burned. <verse eid="2CH 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 8:13"/>He did that to obey the rules about what sacrifices Moses had declared should be made. These included sacrifices for every day and for the Sabbath days and to celebrate each day on which there was a new moon and for the three other festivals that were celebrated each year. Those festivals were the Festival of Eating Unleavened Bread, the Harvest Festival, and the Festival of Living in Temporary Shelters. <verse eid="2CH 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 8:14"/>Obeying what his father David had commanded, he appointed the groups of priests for their work, and he appointed the descendants of Levi to lead the people while they sang to praise Yahweh and while they assisted the priests in their daily work. He also appointed groups of them to guard all the gates, because that was also what David, the man who pleased God <char style="add">very well</char>, had commanded. <verse eid="2CH 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 8:15"/>The priests and other descendants of Levi obeyed completely everything that the king commanded, including <char style="add">taking care of</char> the storerooms.<verse eid="2CH 8:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 8:16"/>They did all the work <char style="add">of building the temple</char> that Solomon told them to do, until it was all completed. So they finishing building the temple.<verse eid="2CH 8:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 8:17"/>Then some of Solomon’s men went to Ezion-Geber and Elath <char style="add">cities</char> on the coast of the Red Sea, an area that belonged to the Edom people-group. <verse eid="2CH 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 8:18"/>King Hiram sent to Solomon from <char style="add">Tyre city</char> some ships that were commanded by his officers. They were men who were experienced sailors. These men went in the ships with Solomon’s men to <char style="add">the</char> Ophir <char style="add">region</char> and brought back about 17 tons of gold, which they delivered to King Solomon.<verse eid="2CH 8:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="2CH 9"/>
  <para style="s1">The queen of Sheba visited Solomon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 9:1"/>The queen who ruled <char style="add">the</char> Sheba <char style="add">area in Arabia</char> heard that Solomon had become famous, so she traveled to Jerusalem to ask him questions that were difficult <char style="add">to answer</char>. She came with a large group of servants, and she brought camels that were loaded with spices, and valuable gems, and a lot of gold. When she met Solomon, she asked him questions about all the things/topics in which she was interested. <verse eid="2CH 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 9:2"/>Solomon answered all her questions. He explained everything that she asked about, even things that were very difficult.<verse eid="2CH 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 9:3"/>The queen realized that Solomon was very wise. She saw his palace, <verse eid="2CH 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 9:4"/>she saw the food that was served on his table <char style="add">every day</char>; she saw how his officials were seated at the table, their uniforms, the servants who served the food and wine, and the sacrifices that he took to the temple to be completely burned on the altar. She was extremely amazed.<verse eid="2CH 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 9:5"/>She said to the king, “Everything that I heard in my own country about you and about how wise you are is true! <verse eid="2CH 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 9:6"/>But I did not believe it was true until I came here and saw it myself. You are <char style="add">extremely wise and rich,</char> more than what people told me. <verse eid="2CH 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 9:7"/>The men who work for you are very fortunate! Your officials who are constantly standing in front of you and listening to the wise things that you say are also fortunate! <verse eid="2CH 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 9:8"/>Praise Yahweh your God, who has shown that he is pleased with you by appointing you to be the king of Israel for him. God has always loved the Israeli people, and desires to assist them forever, and therefore he has appointed you to be their king, in order that you will rule them fairly and righteously.”<verse eid="2CH 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 9:9"/>Then the queen gave to Solomon about 4-1/2 tons of gold and a large amount of spices and gems. Never had King Solomon received more spices than the queen gave him at that time.<verse eid="2CH 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10-12" style="v" sid="2CH 9:10-12"/>King Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba everything that she wanted. He gave her more than she had given to him. Then she and those who came with her returned to her own land.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 9:10-12">
    <char style="add">In the ships that belonged to King Hiram,</char> Hiram’s workers and Solomon’s workers brought gold from Ophir. They also brought a large amount of juniper wood and gems. King Solomon <char style="add">told his workers</char> to use that wood to make railings in the temple and in his palace and also to make harps and lyres for the musicians. That wood was the the finest wood that had ever been seen in Israel.<verse eid="2CH 9:10-12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s wealth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 9:13"/>Each year there was brought to Solomon a total of 25 tons of gold. <verse eid="2CH 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 9:14"/>That was in addition to the <char style="add">taxes</char> paid to him by the merchants and traders. Also, the kings of Arabia and the governors of <char style="add">the districts in</char> Israel brought gold and silver to Solomon.<verse eid="2CH 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 9:15"/>King Solomon’s <char style="add">workers took this</char> gold <char style="add">and</char> hammered <char style="add">it</char> into thin sheets and covered 200 large shields with those thin sheets of gold; they put almost 7-1/2 pounds of gold on each shield. <verse eid="2CH 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 9:16"/>His <char style="add">workers</char> made 300 <char style="add">smaller</char> shields. They covered each of them with almost 4 pounds of gold. Then the king put those shields in the Hall of the Forest of Lebanon.<verse eid="2CH 9:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 9:17"/>His <char style="add">workers</char> also made for him a large throne. <char style="add">Part of</char> it was covered with <char style="add">decorations made from</char> ivory and <char style="add">part of it was covered</char> with very fine gold. <verse eid="2CH 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 9:18"/>There were six steps in front of the throne. There was a gold footstool that was attached to the throne. At each side of the throne there was an armrest, and alongside each armrest there was a <char style="add">small statue of a</char> lion. <verse eid="2CH 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 9:19"/>On the six steps there were twelve statues of lions, one on each side. No throne like that had ever existed in any other kingdom. <verse eid="2CH 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 9:20"/>All of Solomon’s cups were made of gold, and all the various dishes in the Hall of the Forest of Lebanon were made of gold. <char style="add">They did not make things from silver</char>, because during the years that Solomon <char style="add">ruled</char>, silver was not considered to be valuable. <verse eid="2CH 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 9:21"/>The king had a fleet of ships that sailed with the ships that King Hiram owned. Every three years the ships returned <char style="add">from the places to which they had sailed</char>, bringing gold, silver, ivory, monkeys, and baboons (OR, peacocks).<verse eid="2CH 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 9:22"/>King Solomon became richer and wiser than any other king on the earth. <verse eid="2CH 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 9:23"/>Kings from all over the world wanted to come and listen to the wise things that Solomon said, things that God had enabled him to know. <verse eid="2CH 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 9:24"/>All the people who came to him brought presents: They brought things made from silver or gold, or robes, or weapons, or spices, or horses, or mules. The people continued to do this every year.<verse eid="2CH 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 9:25"/>Solomon had 4,000 stalls for his horses and chariots, and 12,000 horses. Solomon put some of them in Jerusalem and some of them in other cities where he kept his chariots. <verse eid="2CH 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 9:26"/>Solomon ruled over all the kings in the area from the <char style="add">Euphrates</char> River <char style="add">in the northeast</char> to the Philistia area <char style="add">in the west</char> to the border of Egypt <char style="add">in the south</char>. <verse eid="2CH 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 9:27"/><char style="add">During the years that Solomon was</char> king, <char style="add">he</char> caused silver to become as common in Jerusalem as stones; and he caused cedar trees in the foothills of Judah to become as plentiful as fig trees. <verse eid="2CH 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 9:28"/>Solomon’s agents brought horses from <char style="add">the</char> Musri <char style="add">area</char> and other places.<verse eid="2CH 9:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Solomon’s death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 9:29"/>Lists of all the other things that Solomon did are recorded in the scrolls written by the prophet Nathan and by the prophet Ahijah from Shiloh <char style="add">city</char>, and in <char style="add">the scroll in which were written</char> the visions that the prophet Iddo saw concerning <char style="add">King</char> Jeroboam. <verse eid="2CH 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 9:30"/>Solomon ruled from Jerusalem all of Israel for 40 years. <verse eid="2CH 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 9:31"/>Then Solomon died and was buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. And his son Rehoboam became the king.<verse eid="2CH 9:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="2CH 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The people of Israel rebelled against Rehoboam</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 10:1"/>All the people of Israel went to Shechem <char style="add">city</char> in order to appoint Rehoboam to be their king. So Rehoboam also went there. <verse eid="2CH 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 10:2"/>Jeroboam, the son of Nebat, had fled to Egypt <char style="add">to escape</char> from King Solomon. But when he heard <char style="add">about the people wanting to appoint Rehoboam to be their king</char>, he returned <char style="add">to Israel</char> from Egypt <verse eid="2CH 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 10:3"/>So the <char style="add">leaders of the northern tribes</char> summoned him, and he went with them <char style="add">to talk</char> to Rehoboam. They said to Rehoboam, <verse eid="2CH 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 10:4"/>“Your father <char style="add">Solomon</char> forced us to work very hard for him. If you do not force us to work that hard, and if you charge us less taxes than we were paying to him, we will serve you <char style="add">faithfully</char>.”<verse eid="2CH 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 10:5"/>He replied, “Come back three days from now <char style="add">and I will give you my answer</char>.” So those leaders <char style="add">and Jeroboam</char> left.<verse eid="2CH 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 10:6"/>Then King Rehoboam consulted his older men who had advised his father Solomon while he was still alive. He asked them, “What shall I say to answer these men?”<verse eid="2CH 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 10:7"/>They replied, “If you will be kind to these people and do things that will please them, and if you say kind things to them when you answer them, they will always serve you.”<verse eid="2CH 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 10:8"/>But he ignored what the older men advised him to do. Instead, he consulted the younger men who had grown up with him, who were now his advisors. <verse eid="2CH 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 10:9"/>He said to them, “How should I answer the men who are asking me to reduce the <char style="add">work and taxes</char> that my father required from them?”<verse eid="2CH 10:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 10:10"/>The young men who had grown up with him replied, “<char style="add">Those men</char> have said that your father forced them to work very hard for him, so they want you to reduce the <char style="add">work and taxes</char> that your father required from them. But this is what you should tell them: ‘My little finger is thicker than my father’s waist. <verse eid="2CH 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 10:11"/>What I mean is that my father required you to <char style="add">work hard and pay high taxes</char>. But I will make those loads heavier. <char style="add">It was as though</char> my father whipped you, but I will whip you with whips that have pieces of metal in them.’”<verse eid="2CH 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 10:12"/>Three days later, Jeroboam and all the leaders came to King Rehoboam again, which is what he had told them to do. <verse eid="2CH 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 10:13"/>The king ignored the advice of the older men and spoke harshly to the Israeli leaders. <verse eid="2CH 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 10:14"/><char style="add">He told them what the younger men had advised.</char> He said, “My father put heavy burdens <char style="add">of work and taxes</char> on you, but I will put heavier burdens on you. <char style="add">It was as though</char> he beat you with whips, but I will beat you with whips that have pieces of metal in them!” <verse eid="2CH 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 10:15"/>So the king did not pay any attention to the Israeli leaders. But this happened in order that what Yahweh had told the prophet Ahijah about Jeroboam would happen.<verse eid="2CH 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 10:16"/>When the Israeli leaders realized that the king did not pay any attention to what they said, they shouted,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 10:16">“We do not want anything to do with this descendant of King David!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 10:16">We will not pay attention to what this grandson of Jesse says!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 10:16">You people of Israel, let’s go home!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 10:16">As for this descendant of David, he can rule his own kingdom!”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="2CH 10:16">So the Israeli leaders returned to their homes.<verse eid="2CH 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 10:17"/>And <char style="add">after that, the only Israeli</char> people whom Rehoboam ruled over were those who lived in the territory of <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Judah <char style="add">and Benjamin</char>.<verse eid="2CH 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 10:18"/>Then King Rehoboam went with Adoniram <char style="add">to talk to the Israeli people</char>. Adoniram was the man who supervised <char style="add">all the men who were</char> forced to work <char style="add">for Rehoboam</char>. But the Israeli people killed him by throwing stones at him. When that happened, King Rehoboam quickly got in his chariot and escaped to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 10:19"/>Ever since that time, <char style="add">the people of the northern tribes of</char> Israel have been rebelling against the descendants of <char style="add">King</char> David.<verse eid="2CH 10:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="2CH 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 11:1"/>When Rehoboam arrived in Jerusalem, he gathered 180,000 of the best soldiers from the tribes of Judah and Benjamin. He wanted them to fight against <char style="add">the northern tribes of</char> Israel <char style="add">and defeat them</char>, in order that he could rule <char style="add">all the tribes of</char> the kingdom again.<verse eid="2CH 11:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 11:2"/>But Yahweh spoke to the prophet Shemaiah and said this to him: <verse eid="2CH 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 11:3"/>“Go and tell this to <char style="add">Solomon’s son</char> Rehoboam, the king of Judah, and to all the Israeli people of the tribes of Judah and Benjamin: <verse eid="2CH 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 11:4"/>‘Yahweh says that you must not go to fight against <char style="add">the people of Israel; they are</char> your distant relatives. All of you must go home. What has happened is what Yahweh wanted to happen.’” <char style="add">So Shemaiah went and told that to them,</char> and they all heeded what Yahweh had commanded them to do, and they did not attack Jeroboam <char style="add">and his soldiers</char>.<verse eid="2CH 11:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Rehoboam fortified cities in Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 11:5"/>Rehoboam lived in Jerusalem, and his workers built walls around several of the cities and towns in Judah to protect them <char style="add">against enemy attacks</char>. <verse eid="2CH 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 11:6"/>In <char style="add">the area that belonged to</char> the tribes of Judah and Benjamin they built walls around Bethlehem, Etam, Tekoa, <verse eid="2CH 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 11:7"/>Beth-Zur, Soco, Adullam, <verse eid="2CH 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 11:8"/>Gath, Mareshah, <verse eid="2CH 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 11:9"/>Adoraim, Lachish, Azekah, <verse eid="2CH 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 11:10"/>Zorah, Aijalon, and Hebron. <verse eid="2CH 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 11:11"/>He also appointed an army commander in each of those cities and towns, and gave them supplies of food, olive oil, and wine <char style="add">to keep in storage</char>. <verse eid="2CH 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 11:12"/>He put shields and spears in all the cities and made them well-protected. So he continued to rule the tribes of Judah and Benjamin.<verse eid="2CH 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 11:13"/>The priests and other descendants of Levi throughout Israel supported Rehoboam. <verse eid="2CH 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 11:14"/>The descendants of Levi <char style="add">who lived outside the territory of Judah and Benjamin</char> abandoned their property and their pastureland, and they came to Jerusalem and <char style="add">to other places in</char> Judah, because Jeroboam and his sons would not allow them to do the work of priests of Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 11:15"/>Instead, Jeroboam appointed the priests that he wanted to work <char style="add">at the altars he commanded to be built</char> on the hilltops, <char style="add">to offer sacrifices to</char> the idols that he commanded to be made <char style="add">that resembled</char> goats and calves. <verse eid="2CH 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 11:16"/>And people from every tribe in Israel who wanted to worship Yahweh, the God to whom the Israelis belonged, went with the descendants of Levi to Jerusalem to live there and to offer sacrifices to Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>. <verse eid="2CH 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 11:17"/>They caused the kingdom of Judah to be strong, and for three years they were happy that Solomon’s son Rehoboam was the king. During that time they conducted their lives <char style="add">righteously</char> as David and Solomon had done previously.<verse eid="2CH 11:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Rehoboam’s family</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 11:18"/>Rehoboam married Mahalath. She was the daughter of David’s son Jerimoth, and her mother was Abihail, the daughter of Eliab and granddaughter of Jesse. <verse eid="2CH 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 11:19"/>Rehoboam and Mahalath had three sons: Jeush, Shemariah, and Zaham. <verse eid="2CH 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 11:20"/>Later Rehoboam married Maacah, the daughter of Absalom, and they had four sons: Abijah, Attai, Ziza, and Shelomith. <verse eid="2CH 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 11:21"/>Rehoboam loved Maacah more than he loved any other of his wives and slave wives. Altogether he had 18 wives and 60 slave wives, and 28 sons and 60 daughters.<verse eid="2CH 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 11:22"/>Rehoboam appointed his son Abijah to be the leader of his <char style="add">older and younger</char> brothers, because he wanted to appoint Abijah to be the next king. <verse eid="2CH 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 11:23"/>He very wisely sent some of his other sons to other cities in the areas of the tribes of Judah and Benjamin, and to all the other cities that had walls around them. He gave them plenty of supplies and many wives.<verse eid="2CH 11:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="2CH 12"/>
  <para style="s1">The army of King Shishak of Egypt invaded Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 12:1"/>After Rehoboam was in complete control of his kingdom, he and all <char style="add">the other people in</char> Judah stopped obeying the laws of Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 12:2"/>As a result, after Rehoboam had been king for almost five years, Yahweh sent Shishak, the king of Egypt, <char style="add">with his army</char> to attack Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 12:3"/>Along with his army he brought 1,200 chariots and 60,000 soldiers riding horses and a very large number of troops from two regions in Libya, and from Ethiopia. <verse eid="2CH 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 12:4"/>They captured many of the cities in Judah that had walls around them, and they came as far as Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 12:5"/>Then the prophet Shemaiah came to Rehoboam and the other leaders of Judah who had gathered in Jerusalem because they were afraid of <char style="add">the army of</char> Shishak. Shemaiah said to them, “Yahweh says this: ‘You have abandoned me; so now I am abandoning you, to <char style="add">allow you to be captured by the army of</char> Shishak.’”<verse eid="2CH 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 12:6"/>Then the king and the other Israeli leaders humbled themselves and said, “What Yahweh is doing to us is fair.”<verse eid="2CH 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 12:7"/>When Yahweh realized that they had humbled themselves, he gave this message to Shemaiah: “Because they have humbled themselves, I will not allow them to be destroyed. Instead, I will soon rescue them. I will not use Shishak’s army to completely destroy the people of Jerusalem, <verse eid="2CH 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 12:8"/>but they will conquer Jerusalem and force the people there to do what Shishak wants them to do. As a result, the people of Jerusalem will learn <char style="add">that it is better</char> to serve me than to serve the kings of other countries.”<verse eid="2CH 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 12:9"/>When Shishak’s <char style="add">army</char> attacked Jerusalem, they took/carried away the valuable things that were in the temple of Yahweh and the valuable things that were in the king’s palace. They took everything <char style="add">that was valuable</char>, including the gold shields that Solomon’s <char style="add">workers</char> had made. <verse eid="2CH 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 12:10"/>So King Rehoboam’s workers made bronze shields to be used instead of the gold ones and gave the bronze shields to the commanders of the men who guarded the entrance to his palace. <verse eid="2CH 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 12:11"/>After that, whenever the king went to the temple, the guards went with him, carrying those bronze shields. Then <char style="add">when the king left,</char> they would return the shields to the guards’ room.<verse eid="2CH 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 12:12"/>Because Rehoboam humbled himself, Yahweh stopped being angry with him and did not get rid of him. Instead, he caused good things to happen in Judah.<verse eid="2CH 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 12:13"/>King Rehoboam again was in complete control in Jerusalem and continued to be the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>. He was 41 years old when he became the king. He ruled for 17 years in Jerusalem, which is the city that Yahweh had chosen from all the tribes in Israel to be the place in which people were to worship him. <verse eid="2CH 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 12:14"/>Rehoboam’s mother’s name was Naamah. She was from the Ammon people-group. Rehoboam did evil things because he did not try to find out what Yahweh wanted him to do.<verse eid="2CH 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 12:15"/>An account of all the things that Rehoboam did while he was the king, and lists of the members of his family, are in the scrolls written by the prophets Shemaiah and Iddo. The armies of Rehoboam and Jeroboam were constantly fighting each other. <verse eid="2CH 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 12:16"/>When Rehoboam died, he was buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. Then his son Abijah became the king.<verse eid="2CH 12:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="2CH 13"/>
  <para style="s1">King Abijah’s rule in Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 13:1"/>When Jeroboam had been ruling <char style="add">Israel</char> for almost 18 years, Abijah became the king of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 13:2"/>He ruled in Jerusalem for three years. His mother was Micaiah (OR, Maacah), the daughter of Uriel from Gibeah <char style="add">town</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 13:2">There was a war between <char style="add">the armies of</char> Abijah and Jeroboam. <verse eid="2CH 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 13:3"/>Abijah went into the battle, taking 400,000 of his capable soldiers, and Jeroboam prepared to fight them, taking 800,000 of his capable troops.<verse eid="2CH 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 13:4"/>Abijah stood on the top of Zemaraim Mountain, which is in the hilly area that belonged to the tribe of Ephraim, and he shouted, “Jeroboam and all you other people of Israel, listen to me! <verse eid="2CH 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 13:5"/>You should know that Yahweh, the God to whom all we Israelis belong, has appointed David and his descendants to be the kings of Israel forever. He has confirmed that by making a permanent agreement. <verse eid="2CH 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 13:6"/>But Jeroboam, who was <char style="add">only</char> an official of David’s son King Solomon, rebelled against his king. <verse eid="2CH 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 13:7"/>And when Solomon’s son Rehoboam became king and was still young and inexperienced, a group of worthless scoundrels gathered around you, Jeroboam, and rebelled against Rehoboam.<verse eid="2CH 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 13:8"/>“And now you are planning to fight against the kingdom that Yahweh established to be governed by David’s descendants. It is true that you have a huge army, and you and your soldiers have brought with you the golden <char style="add">statues of</char> calves that Jeroboam’s workers made to be gods for all of you. <verse eid="2CH 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 13:9"/>But you expelled the priests that Yahweh <char style="add">appointed</char>, men who are descendants of Aaron <char style="add">the first Supreme Priest</char>, and you expelled the descendants of Levi, and you appointed the priests that you wanted, like the people of other countries do. You allow anyone to become a priest of idols that are not gods if he comes to dedicate himself to be a priest by sacrificing a young bull and seven rams.<verse eid="2CH 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 13:10"/>“As for us, Yahweh is our God, and we have not abandoned him. Our priests who serve Yahweh are descendants of Aaron, and the descendants of Levi assist them. <verse eid="2CH 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 13:11"/>Every morning and every evening they present to Yahweh offerings to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and they burn fragrant incense. <char style="add">Each week</char> they place the sacred bread on the sacred table, and each morning they light the lamps that are on the gold lampstand. We are obeying what Yahweh our God requires us to do. But you have abandoned him. <verse eid="2CH 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 13:12"/>Yahweh is with us; he is our leader. The priests whom he has appointed will blow their trumpets to signal <char style="add">that we are ready</char> to fight a battle against you. You Israeli men, do not fight against Yahweh, the God to whom your ancestors belonged, because you will not be successful and win the battle against him.”<verse eid="2CH 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 13:13"/>
    <char style="add">While he was speaking,</char> Jeroboam sent some of his troops around the army of Judah. So while the soldiers who were with Jeroboam were in front of the army of Judah, the other soldiers of Israel were behind the army of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 13:14"/>When the soldiers of Judah turned and saw that they were going to be attacked from the front and from the rear, they cried out to Yahweh. The priests blew their trumpets, <verse eid="2CH 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 13:15"/>and the men of Judah shouted a loud battle-cry. Then Yahweh <char style="add">enabled Abijah and the army of Judah to</char> defeat Jeroboam and <char style="add">the army of</char> Israel. <verse eid="2CH 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 13:16"/>The soldiers of Israel fled from the soldiers of Judah, and God enabled the army of Judah to defeat them. <verse eid="2CH 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 13:17"/>Abijah and his troops struck the capable soldiers of Israel and killed 500,000 of them.<verse eid="2CH 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 13:18"/>So the soldiers of Israel were defeated, and the soldiers of Judah won the battle because they trusted in Yahweh, the God to whom their ancestors belonged.<verse eid="2CH 13:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 13:19"/>Abijah’s army pursued the army of Jeroboam, and they captured from the people of Israel the cities of Bethel, Jeshanah, and Ephron, and the surrounding villages. <verse eid="2CH 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 13:20"/>During the remaining time that Abijah ruled, Jeroboam did not become powerful again. Then Yahweh caused him to become very ill, and he died.<verse eid="2CH 13:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 13:21"/>But Abijah became more powerful. He married 14 wives and had 22 sons and 16 daughters.<verse eid="2CH 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 13:22"/>An account of the other things that Abijah did while he was the king, including what he said and what he did, is in the scroll written by the prophet Iddo.<verse eid="2CH 13:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="2CH 14"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 14:1"/>When Abijah died, he was buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. His son Asa became the king. While Asa was ruling, there was peace in Judah for ten years.<verse eid="2CH 14:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Asa’s rule in Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 14:2"/>Asa did things that Yahweh his God considers to be right and good. <verse eid="2CH 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 14:3"/>His workers got rid of the altars to worship foreign gods that were on the high hills. They smashed the sacred stone pillars and cut down the poles for worshiping <char style="add">the goddess</char> Asherah. <verse eid="2CH 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 14:4"/>Asa commanded the people of Judah to worship <char style="add">only</char> Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors worshiped, and to obey his laws and commands. <verse eid="2CH 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 14:5"/>His workers destroyed all the shrines on the hilltops and the altars for burning incense <char style="add">to idols</char> in every town in Judah. As a result, there was peace while Asa ruled the kingdom <char style="add">of Judah</char>. <verse eid="2CH 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 14:6"/>His workers built cities and constructed walls around them. No army attacked Judah during that time, because Yahweh enabled them to have peace.<verse eid="2CH 14:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 14:7"/>Asa said to the people of Judah, “We should protect these towns by building walls around them, with watchtowers and gates that have bars. This country still belongs to us because we have requested Yahweh our God to help us. We requested him for his help, and he has given us peace in our entire country.” So they built buildings and prospered.<verse eid="2CH 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 14:8"/>Asa had an army of 300,000 men from Judah. They all carried large shields and spears. He also had 280,000 men from the tribe of Benjamin <char style="add">in his army</char>. They carried <char style="add">smaller</char> shields, and bows <char style="add">and arrows</char>. They were all brave soldiers.<verse eid="2CH 14:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 14:9"/>Zerah, a man from Ethiopia/Sudan, marched with a huge army and 300 chariots to attack <char style="add">the army of Judah and Benjamin</char>. They went as far as <char style="add">the town of</char> Mareshah <char style="add">about 25 miles/southwest of Jerusalem</char>. <verse eid="2CH 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 14:10"/>Asa went <char style="add">with his army</char> to fight against them, and both armies took their positions in the Zephathah Valley.<verse eid="2CH 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 14:11"/>Then Asa cried out to Yahweh his God, saying, “Yahweh, there is no one like you who can help those who have very little power to resist a mighty army. Yahweh our God, help us, because we are relying on you; and trusting in you we have come <char style="add">to fight</char> against this huge army. Yahweh, you are our God; do not allow anyone to defeat you.”<verse eid="2CH 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 14:12"/>Then Yahweh enabled Asa and the army of Judah to defeat the army from Ethiopia. They fled, <verse eid="2CH 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 14:13"/>and Asa and his army pursued them <char style="add">to the southwest</char> as far as Gerar. A huge number of the soldiers from Ethiopia were killed, with the result that those <char style="add">who were not killed</char> were unable to fight any more. They were greatly defeated by Yahweh and his army, and the men of Judah carried away a great amount of their possessions. <verse eid="2CH 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 14:14"/>The men of Judah were able to destroy the people in villages near Gerar because Yahweh had caused the people there to become terrified <char style="add">and unable to fight</char>. The army of Judah took away all the valuable things from those villages. <verse eid="2CH 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 14:15"/>They also attacked the places where the local people who took care of domestic animals had set up their tents, and they took away big herds of sheep and goats and camels. Then they returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 14:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="2CH 15"/>
  <para style="s1">The reforms that Asa introduced</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 15:1"/>The Spirit of God came upon Azariah, the son of Obed. <verse eid="2CH 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 15:2"/>Azariah went to talk with Asa, and said to him, “Asa and all <char style="add">you men of the tribes of</char> Judah and Benjamin, listen to me. Yahweh is with you whenever you are trusting in him. If you request him <char style="add">to help you</char>, he will help you, but if you abandon him, he will abandon you. <verse eid="2CH 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 15:3"/>For many years the Israeli people did not know the true God, and they did not have priests or God’s laws. <verse eid="2CH 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 15:4"/>But when they experienced trouble, they turned to Yahweh our God, and requested him to help them. And he helped them. <verse eid="2CH 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 15:5"/>At that time, people were not safe when they traveled, because all the people who lived in the nearby countries were experiencing many difficulties. <verse eid="2CH 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 15:6"/>The people of various nations were thoroughly defeated by <char style="add">armies of</char> other nations, and people in some cities were crushed by <char style="add">armies from</char> other cities, because God was allowing them to experience many difficulties. <verse eid="2CH 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 15:7"/>But you people, you must be strong and do not become discouraged, because <char style="add">God</char> will reward you for what you do <char style="add">to please him.”</char><verse eid="2CH 15:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 15:8"/>When Asa heard what the prophet Azariah said, he was encouraged. He <char style="add">commanded his workers to</char> remove all the detestable idols from everywhere in the land of the tribes of Judah and Benjamin, and from the towns that <char style="add">his soldiers</char> had captured in the hills of the tribe of Ephraim. Asa’s workers repaired the altar <char style="add">where people offered sacrifices </char> to Yahweh that was in front of the entrance to the temple <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>. <verse eid="2CH 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 15:9"/>Then he gathered all <char style="add">the people of the tribes of</char> Judah and Benjamin and many people from the tribes of Ephraim, Manasseh, and Simeon who were living among them. <char style="add">He was able to do that</char> because many people from <char style="add">those tribes in</char> Israel had come to me to Judah when they realized that Yahweh, the God that Asa <char style="add">worshiped</char>, was helping him.<verse eid="2CH 15:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 15:10"/>After Asa had been ruling for almost 15 years, in May of that year, those people gathered in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 15:11"/>At that time they sacrificed to Yahweh 700 bulls and 7,000 sheep and goats, from the animals that they had captured <char style="add">when they defeated the army of Ethiopia/Sudan</char>. <verse eid="2CH 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 15:12"/>They solemnly made an agreement to very sincerely worship Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>. <verse eid="2CH 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 15:13"/>They promised to execute all those who would not worship Yahweh, including those who were important and those who were not important, both men and women. <verse eid="2CH 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 15:14"/>They shouted and blew trumpets and other horns while they solemnly promised to do that. <verse eid="2CH 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 15:15"/>All the people who were living in Judah were happy with the agreement because they had solemnly and very sincerely promised to keep it. They eagerly requested help from Yahweh, and he helped them. So he enabled them to have peace throughout their country.<verse eid="2CH 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 15:16"/>King Asa’s grandmother Maacah had made a disgusting pole for <char style="add">worshiping the goddess</char> Asherah. So Asa <char style="add">commanded his workers to</char> cut down that pole and chop it into pieces and burn it in the Kidron Valley. He then did not allow Maacah to continue <char style="add">to influence the people because of her </char> being the mother of the previous king. <verse eid="2CH 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 15:17"/>Although Asa’s <char style="add">workers</char> did not get rid of the shrines on the hilltops in Israel, he was very determined to <char style="add">do what </char> pleased Yahweh all his life. <verse eid="2CH 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 15:18"/>He <char style="add">ordered his workers to</char> bring into God’s temple all the silver and gold and other valuable items that he and his father had dedicated <char style="add">to God</char>.<verse eid="2CH 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 15:19"/>There were no more wars <char style="add">in Judah</char> until Asa had been ruling Judah almost 35 years.<verse eid="2CH 15:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="2CH 16"/>
  <para style="s1">The final years that Asa ruled Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 16:1"/>When Asa had been ruling <char style="add">Judah</char> for almost 36 years, King Baasha of Israel went <char style="add">with his army</char> to attack Judah. They <char style="add">captured the town of</char> Ramah <char style="add">north of Jerusalem</char> and started to build a wall around <char style="add">it</char>, in order to prevent any people from entering or leaving the area in Judah that was ruled by King Asa <char style="add">because the only road into Judah from Israel went through Ramah</char>.<verse eid="2CH 16:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 16:2"/>So Asa told his workers to take all the silver and gold that was in the storerooms of the temple and in his own palace, and take and give it to Ben-Hadad, the king of Syria, who was ruling in Damascus. <char style="add">He sent him a message,</char> saying <verse eid="2CH 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 16:3"/>“I want there to be a peace treaty between me and you, like there was between my father and your father. Look, I am sending you <char style="add">a lot of</char> silver and gold. So please cancel the treaty that you have made with Baasha, the king of Israel, in order that he will take his soldiers away from attacking mine, <char style="add">because he will be afraid of your army</char>.”<verse eid="2CH 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 16:4"/>Ben-Hadad agreed to do what King Asa <char style="add">suggested</char>. He sent the commanders of his armies <char style="add">with their soldiers</char> to attack some of the towns in Israel. They captured Ijon, Dan, Abel-Beth-Maacah and all the cities in the area belonging to the tribe of Naphtali where supplies were kept. <verse eid="2CH 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 16:5"/>When Baasha heard about that, he <char style="add">commanded his troops to</char> stop fortifying Ramah and doing other work there. <verse eid="2CH 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 16:6"/>Then King Asa gathered all the men of Judah, and they took away from Ramah all the stones and timber that Baasha’s men had been using <char style="add">to build the wall around that town</char>. They took those materials to <char style="add">the town of</char> Geba and <char style="add">the city of</char> Mizpah <char style="add">north of Jerusalem</char> and built walls around them.<verse eid="2CH 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 16:7"/>At that time the prophet Hanani went to King Asa and said to him, “Because you relied on the king of Syria and not on Yahweh our God, you missed your opportunity to destroy the army of the king of Syria. <verse eid="2CH 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 16:8"/>The huge armies from Ethiopia and Libya with all their chariots and soldiers <char style="add">riding</char> on horses <char style="add">were certainly very powerful. But </char> when you relied on Yahweh, he enabled your army to defeat them. <verse eid="2CH 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 16:9"/>That happened because Yahweh sees <char style="add">what is happening</char> all over the earth, and he strengthens those who completely trust him. You have done a very foolish thing, so from now on other armies will be fighting your army.”<verse eid="2CH 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 16:10"/>Asa was very angry with the prophet because of what the prophet had said. So he <char style="add">commanded his officials to</char> put Hanani in prison. At that same time, he started to treat some of his people very cruelly.<verse eid="2CH 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 16:11"/>All the things that Asa did while he was ruling, from the time he started to rule until he died, are written in the scroll containing the record of the <char style="add">activities of the</char> kings of Judah and Israel. <verse eid="2CH 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 16:12"/>When Asa had been ruling for almost 39 years, he was afflicted with a disease in his feet. The disease was very severe, but in spite of that, he did not request help from Yahweh. Instead he sought help only from doctors. <verse eid="2CH 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 16:13"/>When he had been ruling for almost 40 years, he died. <verse eid="2CH 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 16:14"/>He was buried in the tomb that his workers had made for him in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. They laid his corpse on a bed covered with spices and various perfumes that had been mixed together. They also lit a huge fire to honor him.<verse eid="2CH 16:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="2CH 17"/>
  <para style="s1">King Jehoshaphat’s rule in Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 17:1"/>Asa’s son Jehoshaphat became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>, and he enabled his army to become very strong, with the result that they could resist attacks from <char style="add">the army of</char> Israel. <verse eid="2CH 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 17:2"/>He put soldiers in all the cities in Judah around which they had built walls, and he put soldiers in other places in Judah and in the towns in the area belonging to the tribe of Ephraim that <char style="add">soldiers of</char> his father Asa had captured.<verse eid="2CH 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 17:3"/>Yahweh helped Jehoshaphat because when he started <char style="add">to rule Judah</char>, he did the things that pleased Yahweh like his ancestor <char style="add">King</char> David had done. He did not worship the idols of Baal. <verse eid="2CH 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 17:4"/>Instead, he sought advice from the God whom his father <char style="add">had worshiped</char>, and he obeyed God’s commands, and did not do the <char style="add">evil things that the kings of</char> Israel continually did. <verse eid="2CH 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 17:5"/>Yahweh enabled him to completely control his kingdom. All <char style="add">the people of</char> Judah brought gifts to him, with the result that he became very rich and was greatly honored. <verse eid="2CH 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 17:6"/>He was completely devoted to doing what pleased Yahweh. His workers got rid of the shrines on the hilltops and the poles for <char style="add">worshiping the goddess</char> Asherah throughout Judah.<verse eid="2CH 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 17:7"/>When he had been ruling <char style="add">Judah</char> for almost three years, he sent some of his officials—Ben-Hail, Obadiah, Zechariah, Nethanel, and Micaiah—to teach the people in various towns in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 17:8"/>With them he sent several descendants of Levi—Shemaiah, Nethaniah, Zebadiah, Asahel, Shemiramoth, Jehonathan, Adonijah, Tobijah, and Tob-Adonijah—and two priests, Elishama and Jehoram. <verse eid="2CH 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 17:9"/>They took with them a scroll on which were written the laws of Yahweh and taught them to the people in all the towns throughout Judah,<verse eid="2CH 17:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 17:10"/>The people in all the kingdoms surrounding Judah became very afraid of <char style="add">what Yahweh might do to punish them if they fought against Judah</char>, so they did not start wars with Jehoshaphat’s army. <verse eid="2CH 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 17:11"/>Some people from Philistia brought gifts to Jehoshaphat, and they also brought to him the silver that he demanded that they pay to him. Some Arabs brought to him 7,700 rams and 7,700 goats.<verse eid="2CH 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 17:12"/>Jehoshaphat continued to become more powerful/influential. His workers built forts and places to store supplies in various towns in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 17:13"/>Then they put large amounts of supplies in those storehouses.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 17:13">Jehoshaphat also placed in Jerusalem soldiers who were experienced. <verse eid="2CH 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 17:14"/>The leaders and numbers from each tribe were as follows:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="2CH 17:14"/>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 17:14">From the tribe of Judah,</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="2CH 17:14">Adnah was the leader of the soldiers, and he commanded 300,000 soldiers.<verse eid="2CH 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 17:15"/>His assistant was Jehohanan, who commanded 280,000 soldiers.<verse eid="2CH 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 17:16"/>Next was Zicri’s son Amasiah, who volunteered to serve Yahweh in this way; he commanded 200,000 soldiers.<verse eid="2CH 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 17:17"/>From the tribe of Benjamin,</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="2CH 17:17">Eliada, who was a brave soldier, was the leader of the soldiers; he commanded 200,000 men who had bows <char style="add">and arrows</char> and shields.<verse eid="2CH 17:17"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 17:18"/>Next was Jehozabad, who commanded 180,000 men who had weapons for fighting battles.<verse eid="2CH 17:18"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 17:19"/>Those were the soldiers who served the king <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>, in addition to the men whom the king had placed in the other cities in Judah that had walls around them.<verse eid="2CH 17:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="2CH 18"/>
  <para style="s1">The prophet Micaiah warned King Ahab of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 18:1"/>Jehoshaphat became very wealthy and was greatly honored. But then he arranged for one of his family to marry someone from the family of King Ahab <char style="add">of Israel</char>. <verse eid="2CH 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 18:2"/>Several years later, he went down <char style="add">from Jerusalem</char> to Samaria to visit Ahab. Ahab welcomed him and the people who had come with him by slaughtering many sheep and cattle <char style="add">for a feast</char>. <verse eid="2CH 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 18:3"/>Then he asked Jehoshaphat, “Will you <char style="add">and your army</char> go with my army to attack Ramoth <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>?” Jehoshaphat replied, “My soldiers and I will go to the battle when you tell us to go.” <verse eid="2CH 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 18:4"/>Then he added, “But we should ask Yahweh first, to find out what he wants us to do.”<verse eid="2CH 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 18:5"/>So the king of Israel gathered all his 400 prophets and asked them, “Should we go to attack the people of Ramoth <char style="add">city</char>, or should we not do that?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 18:5">They replied, “Yes, go <char style="add">and attack them</char> because God will enable your army to defeat them.”<verse eid="2CH 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 18:6"/>But Jehoshaphat asked, “Is there no prophet of Yahweh here whom we can ask?”<verse eid="2CH 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 18:7"/>The king of Israel replied, “There is still one man here, whom we can ask to find out what Yahweh wants, his name is Micaiah, the son of Imlah. But I hate him because he never says anything good about me. He always predicts <char style="add">that</char> bad <char style="add">things will happen to me</char>.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 18:7">Jehoshaphat replied, “King Ahab, you should not say that!”<verse eid="2CH 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 18:8"/>So the king of Israel told one of his officials to summon Micaiah immediately.<verse eid="2CH 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 18:9"/>The king of Israel and the king of Judah were sitting there on their thrones, wearing their royal robes. They were at the place where people threshed grain, near the gate of Samaria <char style="add">city</char>. All of <char style="add">Ahab’s</char> prophets were standing in front of them, predicting what was going to happen.<verse eid="2CH 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 18:10"/>
    <char style="add">One of them whose name was</char> Zedekiah, the son of Kenaanah, had made from iron something that resembled the horns of a bull. He proclaimed to Ahab, “This is what Yahweh says: ‘With horns <char style="add">like these</char>, your <char style="add">army</char> will keep attacking the army of Syria <char style="add">like a bull attacks another animal</char>, until you completely destroy them.’” <verse eid="2CH 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 18:11"/>All the other prophets <char style="add">of Ahab</char> agreed. They said, “Yes! If you attack Ramoth <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, you will be successful, because Yahweh will enable you to defeat them.”<verse eid="2CH 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 18:12"/>The messenger who went to summon Micaiah said to him, “Listen to me! All the other prophets are unitedly predicting that the king will be successful <char style="add">in the battle</char>. So be sure to agree with them and say that the king’s army will be successful!”<verse eid="2CH 18:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 18:13"/>But Micaiah said, “As surely as Yahweh lives, I will tell the king only what Yahweh tells me to say.”<verse eid="2CH 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 18:14"/>When Micaiah arrived, the king <char style="add">of Israel</char> asked him, “Should we go to attack Ramoth, or not?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 18:14">Micaiah replied, “Sure, go! Yahweh will enable your army to defeat them!”<verse eid="2CH 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 18:15"/>But King Ahab <char style="add">realized that Micaiah was lying, so he</char> said to Micaiah, “I have told you many times that you must always tell only the truth when you say what Yahweh <char style="add">has revealed to you</char>!”<verse eid="2CH 18:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 18:16"/>Then Micaiah replied, “<char style="add">The truth is that in a vision</char> I saw all the troops of Israel scattered on the mountains. They seemed to be like sheep that did not have a shepherd. And Yahweh said, ‘Their master has been killed. So tell them all to go home peacefully.’”<verse eid="2CH 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 18:17"/>Ahab said to Jehoshaphat, “I told you that he never predicts that anything good will happen to me! He <char style="add">always</char> predicts that bad things will happen to me.”<verse eid="2CH 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 18:18"/>But Micaiah continued, saying, “Listen to what Yahweh showed to me! <char style="add">In a vision</char> I saw Yahweh sitting on his throne, with all the armies of heaven <char style="add">standing around him</char>, on his right side and on his left side. <verse eid="2CH 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 18:19"/>And Yahweh said, ‘Who can persuade Ahab, the king of Israel, to go to fight against the people of Ramoth, in order that he may be killed there?’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 18:19">“Some suggested one thing, and others suggested something else.<verse eid="2CH 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 18:20"/>“Finally one spirit, <char style="add">having received a message from Satan</char>, came to Yahweh and said, ‘I can do it!’</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 18:20">“Yahweh asked him, ‘How will you do it?’<verse eid="2CH 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 18:21"/>“The spirit replied, ‘I will go and inspire all of Ahab’s prophets to tell lies.’ Yahweh said, ‘You will be successful; go and do it!’<verse eid="2CH 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 18:22"/>“So now <char style="add">I tell you that</char> Yahweh has caused your prophets to lie to you. Yahweh has decided that something terrible will happen to you.”<verse eid="2CH 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 18:23"/>Then Zedekiah son of Kenaanah walked over to Micaiah and slapped him on his face. He said, “Do you think that Yahweh’s Spirit left me in order to speak to you?”<verse eid="2CH 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 18:24"/>Micaiah replied, “You will find out for yourself <char style="add">to which of us Yahweh’s Spirit has truly spoken</char> on the day when you go into a room of some house to hide <char style="add">from the Syrian soldiers</char>!”<verse eid="2CH 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 18:25"/>King Ahab commanded <char style="add">his soldiers</char>, “Seize Micaiah and take him to Amon, the governor of this city, and to my son Joash. <verse eid="2CH 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 18:26"/>Tell them that I have commanded that they should put this man in prison and give him only bread and water. Do not give him anything else to eat until I return safely <char style="add">from the battle</char>!”<verse eid="2CH 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 18:27"/>Micaiah replied, “If you return safely, <char style="add">it will be clear that</char> it was not Yahweh who told me what to say to you!” Then he said <char style="add">to all those who were standing there</char>, “Do not forget what I have said <char style="add">to King Ahab</char>!”<verse eid="2CH 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ahab died in the battle at Ramoth-Gilead</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 18:28"/>So the king of Israel and the king of Judah <char style="add">led their armies</char> to Ramoth, in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>. <verse eid="2CH 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 18:29"/>King Ahab said to Jehoshaphat, “I will put on different clothes, <char style="add">in order that no one will recognize that I am the king.</char> But you should wear your royal robe.” So the king of Israel disguised himself, and they both went into the battle.<verse eid="2CH 18:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 18:30"/>The King of Syria told his soldiers who were driving the chariots, “Attack only the king of Israel!” <verse eid="2CH 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 18:31"/>So when the soldiers who were driving the Syrian chariots saw Jehoshaphat <char style="add">wearing the royal robes</char>, they thought “He must be the king of Israel!” <verse eid="2CH 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 18:32"/>So they turned to attack him. But when Jehoshaphat cried out, Yahweh helped him, and they realized that he was not the king of Israel. And God caused them to stop pursuing him.<verse eid="2CH 18:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 18:33"/>But one <char style="add">Syrian</char> soldier shot an arrow at Ahab, without knowing that it was Ahab. The arrow struck Ahab between the places where the parts of his armor joined together. Ahab told the driver of his chariot, “Turn the chariot around and take me out of here! I have been <char style="add">severely</char> wounded!” <verse eid="2CH 18:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 18:34"/>The battle continued all that day. Ahab was sitting propped up in his chariot, facing the Syrian soldiers. And late in the afternoon, when the sun was setting, he died.<verse eid="2CH 18:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="2CH 19"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 19:1"/>When King Jehoshaphat was returning safely to his palace in Jerusalem, <verse eid="2CH 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 19:2"/>the prophet Jehu, the son of <char style="add">the prophet</char> Hanani, went out of the city to meet the king, and said to him, “It was not right for you to help a wicked man and to love those who hate Yahweh. Because of what you have done, Yahweh is angry with you. <verse eid="2CH 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 19:3"/>But you have done some good things; you got rid of the poles in this country for <char style="add">worshiping the goddess</char> Asherah, and you have strongly determined to do what pleases God.”<verse eid="2CH 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jehoshaphat appointed men to settle disputes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 19:4"/>Jehoshaphat lived in Jerusalem. But <char style="add">one time</char>, like he had done once previously, he went out among all the people in the country, from Beersheba <char style="add">city in the far south</char> to the hilly area of <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Ephraim <char style="add">in the far north</char>, and he convinced them to return to <char style="add">worshiping</char> Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>. <verse eid="2CH 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 19:5"/>He appointed judges throughout Judah, in each of the cities that had walls around them. <verse eid="2CH 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 19:6"/>He told them, “Make your decisions carefully, because you are judging cases not <char style="add">in order</char> to <char style="add">please</char> people but to <char style="add">please</char> Yahweh. And he will be watching you whenever you make a decision. <verse eid="2CH 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 19:7"/>So now revere Yahweh, and judge cases carefully, <char style="add">and do not forget that</char> Yahweh our God never acts unjustly, and he never does what people want because of their offering him money; he never accepts bribes.”<verse eid="2CH 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 19:8"/>In Jerusalem also, Jehoshaphat appointed some priests and other descendants of Levi and some leaders of Israeli families <char style="add">to be judges</char>. He told them to do what Yahweh’s laws said was right when they settled disputes. Those men lived in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 19:9"/>He told them this: “You must always do your work faithfully, revering Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 19:10"/>In every dispute that your fellow Israelis who live in the cities want you to settle, you must warn them to not sin against Yahweh <char style="add">by telling lies during the trial</char>. If you do not warn them, God will punish both you and your fellow Israelis. If you warn them, you will not be sinning. You must warn them whether <char style="add">someone has accused them</char> of murdering someone, or of disobeying some other law or command or decree <char style="add">of Yahweh</char>.<verse eid="2CH 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 19:11"/>Amariah the Supreme Priest will supervise you in any matter that Yahweh is concerned about, and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the leader of the tribe of Judah, will supervise you in any matter that I am responsible for. And the descendants of Levi will assist you. Act courageously, and I pray that Yahweh will help those who do their work well.”<verse eid="2CH 19:11"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="2CH 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Jehoshaphat’s army defeated armies from Moab and Ammon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 20:1"/>Later <char style="add">armies from</char> Moab and Ammon and some soldiers from <char style="add">the</char> Meun <char style="add">area in Edom</char> came <char style="add">to fight</char> against Jehoshaphat’s <char style="add">army</char>.<verse eid="2CH 20:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 20:2"/>Some men came and told Jehoshaphat, “A huge army is coming to attack your army. They are coming from <char style="add">the</char> Edom <char style="add">region</char>, from the eastern side of the <char style="add">Dead</char> Sea. They have already come to Hazazon-Tamar!” Another name for that place is En-Gedi. <verse eid="2CH 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 20:3"/>Jehoshaphat became very afraid, so he decided to ask Yahweh <char style="add">what he should do</char>. He also proclaimed that all <char style="add">the people of</char> Judah should fast. <verse eid="2CH 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 20:4"/>The people of Judah gathered together to request Yahweh to help them. They came <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> from every town in Judah to seek help from Yahweh.<verse eid="2CH 20:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 20:5"/>Then Jehoshaphat stood up in front of the people of Judah in front of the new courtyard of the temple, <verse eid="2CH 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 20:6"/>and he prayed this:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 20:6">“Yahweh, the God whom our ancestors belonged to, you are surely the God who <char style="add">rules from</char> heaven. You rule over all the kingdoms of the nations. You have great power, and no one can successfully oppose you. <verse eid="2CH 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 20:7"/>Our God, you expelled the people who lived in this land while your Israeli people advanced, and you certainly gave it to us who are descendants of your friend Abraham, to belong to us forever. <verse eid="2CH 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 20:8"/>We have lived here and have built a temple where we, your people, worship you. We said, <verse eid="2CH 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 20:9"/>'If we experience disasters, either from our enemies attacking us or from you punishing us, or if we experience a plague or a famine, we will stand in your presence in front of this temple that is built to honor you, and we will cry out to you when we are distressed/suffering, and you will hear us and will rescue us.'<verse eid="2CH 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 20:10"/>You would not allow our Israeli ancestors to enter the countries of Ammon and Moab and Edom when they were traveling from Egypt <char style="add">to Canaan</char>. So our ancestors turned away from those areas and did not attack the people there and did not destroy them. But now they are coming here <char style="add">to attack us</char>. <verse eid="2CH 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 20:11"/><char style="add">We did not destroy them. But now</char> look at how they are repaying us by trying to expel us from the land that you gave to our ancestors to belong to them <char style="add">and their descendants forever</char> <verse eid="2CH 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 20:12"/>So, our God, please punish them, because we do not have enough power to resist/defeat this huge army that is coming to attack us. We do not know what to do. But we are pleading for you to help us.”<verse eid="2CH 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 20:13"/>All the men of Judah and their wives and children and babies were standing there in the presence of Yahweh <char style="add">while Jehoshaphat prayed</char>.<verse eid="2CH 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 20:14"/>Then the Spirit of Yahweh came upon Jahaziel, who was the son of Zechariah, who was the son of Benaiah, who was the son of Jeiel, who was the son of Mattaniah. He was a descendant of Levi and a descendant of Asaph. He stood up in front of the whole group that was gathered there, <verse eid="2CH 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 20:15"/>and said, “King Jehoshaphat and all you who live in Jerusalem and in other places in Judah, listen! This is what Yahweh says to you: ‘Do not be afraid or discouraged because of this huge army <char style="add">that is coming to attack you</char>, because it is not you who <char style="add">will win</char> this battle. It is God <char style="add">who will win it</char>. <verse eid="2CH 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 20:16"/>Tomorrow march down toward them. They will be climbing up through Ziz Pass <char style="add">north of En-Gedi</char>. You will meet them at the end of the gorge near the Jeruel Desert. <verse eid="2CH 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 20:17"/>But you will not need to fight this battle. You soldiers from Jerusalem and other places in Judah, just take your positions, and then stand still and watch <char style="add">what will happen</char>. You will see Yahweh rescue you. Do not be afraid or discouraged. March toward them tomorrow, and Yahweh will be with you.’”<verse eid="2CH 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 20:18"/>Jehoshaphat prostrated himself with his face touching the ground, and all the people of Jerusalem and other places in Judah <char style="add">who were there</char> knelt down to worship Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 20:19"/>Then some descendants of Levi who were descendants of both Kohath and Korah stood up and loudly praised Yahweh, the God whom the Israelis <char style="add">belonged to</char>.<verse eid="2CH 20:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 20:20"/>Early the next morning the army left to go to the desert near Tekoa <char style="add">town</char>. While they were leaving, Jehoshaphat stood up and said to the people, “You people of Jerusalem and other places in Judah, listen to me! Trust in Yahweh our God; if you do that, you will be strong. Trust in <char style="add">what </char> his prophets <char style="add">have said</char>; if you do that, you will be successful.” <verse eid="2CH 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 20:21"/>Then, after consulting with some of the people, he appointed some men to go in front of the army, singing to Yahweh and praising him because of his being holy and wonderful. They were singing,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CH 20:21">“Thank Yahweh,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2CH 20:21">because he faithfully loves us forever.”<verse eid="2CH 20:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 20:22"/>When they began to sing and praise Yahweh, Yahweh caused the soldiers from Ammon and Moab and Edom who were invading Judah to panic, with the result that they were defeated. <verse eid="2CH 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 20:23"/>The soldiers from Ammon and Moab started to fight against the soldiers from Edom, and they completely annihilated the soldiers from Edom. After they finished slaughtering the men from Edom, they started to attack each other.<verse eid="2CH 20:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 20:24"/>When the soldiers from Judah came to the place where they could look down over the desert, they looked toward that huge army <char style="add">of their enemies</char>, and they saw only corpses lying on the ground. No one had survived.<verse eid="2CH 20:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 20:25"/>So Jehoshaphat and his soldiers went to take the possessions of their enemies, and they saw that there was a lot of equipment and clothing and other valuable things; there was more than they could carry away. There were very many things, with the result that it took three days for them to collect it all. <verse eid="2CH 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 20:26"/>The following day they gathered in Beracah Valley and praised Yahweh there. That is why that valley is still called Beracah, <char style="add">which means praise.</char><verse eid="2CH 20:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 20:27"/>Then while Jehoshaphat led them, all the soldiers who were from Jerusalem and other places in Judah returned to Jerusalem. They were happy because Yahweh had enabled them to defeat their enemies. <verse eid="2CH 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 20:28"/>When they arrived at Jerusalem, they went to the temple, <char style="add">playing</char> harps and lutes and trumpets.<verse eid="2CH 20:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 20:29"/>People in the kingdoms of the nearby countries became very afraid when they heard how Yahweh had fought against the enemies of the Israelis. <verse eid="2CH 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 20:30"/>Then there was peace in the kingdom that was ruled by Jehoshaphat, because God had caused the surrounding nations not to attack it.<verse eid="2CH 20:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The final years that Jehoshaphat ruled</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 20:31"/>Jehoshaphat continued to rule Judah. He was 35 years old when he became king of Judah, and he ruled in Jerusalem for 25 years. His mother’s name was Azubah, the daughter of Shilhi. <verse eid="2CH 20:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 20:32"/>He did things that were pleasing to Yahweh, like his father Asa had done, and he did not stop doing those things. <verse eid="2CH 20:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 20:33"/>But he did not get rid of the shrines on the hilltops, and many of the people still did not faithfully do what the God whom their ancestors belonged to wanted.<verse eid="2CH 20:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 20:34"/>A record of the other things that Jehoshaphat did while he ruled, from when he began to rule until he died, is in the scrolls written by <char style="add">the prophet</char> Jehu, the son of Hanani. They are also in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel.<verse eid="2CH 20:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 20:35"/>During his reign, Jehoshaphat made a treaty with Ahaziah, the king of Israel, who was a very wicked king. <verse eid="2CH 20:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 20:36"/>They agreed that their workers would build a fleet of ships to use to buy and sell <char style="add">things with other countries</char>. After those ships were built at Ezion-Geber <char style="add">on the Gulf of Aqaba</char>, <verse eid="2CH 20:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2CH 20:37"/>Eliezer the son of Dodavahu from Mareshah <char style="add">city</char> warned Jehoshaphat. He said, “You have made an alliance with Ahaziah, <char style="add">who is a wicked king</char>. Therefore, Yahweh will destroy the ships that your workers have made.” And the ships were wrecked, and were not able to sail to other countries.<verse eid="2CH 20:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="2CH 21"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 21:1"/>Then Jehoshaphat died, and was buried where his ancestors were buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. Then his son Jehoram became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>. <verse eid="2CH 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 21:2"/>His <char style="add">younger</char> brothers were Azariah, Jehiel, Zechariah, Azariah, Michael, and Shephatiah. <verse eid="2CH 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 21:3"/>Before Jehoshaphat died, he gave them gifts of silver and gold and other valuable things. He also appointed them to rule various cities in Judah that had walls around them. But he appointed Jehoram to be the king of Judah, because Jehoram was his oldest son.<verse eid="2CH 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Jehoram of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 21:4"/>After Jehoram was completely in control of his father’s kingdom, he had all of his <char style="add">younger</char> brothers executed, along with some of the leaders of the nation. <verse eid="2CH 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 21:5"/>Jehoram was 32 years old when he became the king, and he ruled in Jerusalem for eight years. <verse eid="2CH 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 21:6"/>But he did many of the <char style="add">evil</char> things that the kings of Israel had done. He did many things that Yahweh considers to be evil, things that the family of Ahab had done, because he married one of Ahab’s daughters. <verse eid="2CH 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 21:7"/>However, because of the agreement that Yahweh had made with King David, Yahweh did not want to get rid of the descendants of David. He had promised that David’s descendants would always be the ones who ruled Judah.<verse eid="2CH 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 21:8"/>While Jehoram was ruling, the people of <char style="add">the</char> Edom <char style="add">region</char> rebelled against <char style="add">the king of</char> Judah and appointed their own king. <verse eid="2CH 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 21:9"/>So Jehoram and his officers and his men in chariots went to Edom. There, the army of Edom surrounded them. Jehoram escaped during the night. <verse eid="2CH 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 21:10"/>But the king of Judah was never able to regain control of Edom, and Edom is still not controlled by Judah. <char style="add">The people in</char> Libnah <char style="add">city between Judah and Philistia</char> also rebelled against Judah. Those things happened because Jehoram turned away from <char style="add">obeying</char> Yahweh, the God whom his ancestors <char style="add">belonged to</char>.<verse eid="2CH 21:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 21:11"/>On the hilltops in Judah he had also built shrines <char style="add">to worship idols</char>, and had caused the people of Judah to stray away from Yahweh by worshiping foreign gods.<verse eid="2CH 21:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 21:12"/>One day, Jehoram received a letter from the prophet Elijah. Elijah had written this in the letter:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 21:12">“This is what Yahweh, the God whom your ancestor <char style="add">King</char> David <char style="add">worshiped</char>, says: 'You have not done things that please me like your father Jehoshaphat did or what King Asa did. <verse eid="2CH 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 21:13"/>Instead, you have continually done the <char style="add">evil things</char> that the kings of Israel have done. You have encouraged the people in Jerusalem and other places in Judah to stop worshiping Yahweh, like the descendants of Ahab did. You have also murdered your own brothers, who were more righteous men than you are.<verse eid="2CH 21:13"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 21:14"/>So now Yahweh is about to very severely punish the people in your kingdom and even your own children and your wives and everything that you own. <verse eid="2CH 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 21:15"/>And you yourself will have an intestinal disease that will continue to become worse, and you will suffer from it until you die.' ”<verse eid="2CH 21:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 21:16"/>Then Yahweh caused some men from the Philistia people-group and some Arabs who lived near the coast <char style="add">of the Mediterranean Sea</char>, where people from Ethiopia had settled, to become angry with Jehoram. <verse eid="2CH 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 21:17"/>Their army invaded Judah and took away <char style="add">from Jerusalem</char> all the valuable things that they found in the king’s palace, and even his sons and wives. His youngest son, Ahaziah, was the only one of his sons whom they did not take away.<verse eid="2CH 21:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 21:18"/>After that happened, Yahweh caused Jehoram to be afflicted with an intestinal disease that no one could cure. <verse eid="2CH 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 21:19"/>About two years later, while he was in great pain, he died because of that disease. The people of Judah had made bonfires to honor his ancestors when they died, but they did not make a bonfire for Jehoram.<verse eid="2CH 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 21:20"/>Jehoram was 32 years old when he became the king, and he ruled in Jerusalem for eight years. No one was sorry when he died. His corpse was buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’, but he was not buried where the other kings <char style="add">of Judah</char> had been buried.<verse eid="2CH 21:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="2CH 22"/>
  <para style="s1">King Ahaziah of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 22:1"/>The people of Jerusalem appointed Jehoram’s youngest son Ahaziah as their king, because the men <char style="add">from Philistia</char> who had invaded Judah with some Arabs had killed all of Jehoram’s other sons. So Ahaziah started to rule Judah.<verse eid="2CH 22:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 22:2"/>Ahaziah was 22 years old when he became king. He ruled in Jerusalem for one year. His mother’s name was Athaliah, a granddaughter of <char style="add">King</char> Omri <char style="add">of Israel</char>.<verse eid="2CH 22:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 22:3"/>King Ahaziah conducted his life just like the members of Ahab’s family had done, because his mother encouraged him to do things that are evil. <verse eid="2CH 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 22:4"/>He did things that Yahweh considers to be evil, like the descendants of Ahab had done, because after Ahaziah’s father died, they became his advisors. And Ahaziah died as a result of heeding their bad advice. <verse eid="2CH 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 22:5"/>He also did what they advised when he went with Joram, the son of King Ahab of Israel, to fight against the army of Hazael, the king of Syria, at Ramoth-Gilead.<verse eid="2CH 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 22:6"/>Then King Ahaziah went down to Jezreel <char style="add">city</char> to see Joram, the son of <char style="add">King</char> Ahab, because he had been wounded. <verse eid="2CH 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 22:7"/>It was during that visit that God caused Ahaziah to die. When Ahaziah arrived, he went with Joram to meet Jehu, the son of Nimshi, whom Yahweh had appointed to kill all the descendants of Ahab. <verse eid="2CH 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 22:8"/>While Jehu <char style="add">and the men who were with him</char> were killing the descendants of Ahab, they found the leaders of Judah and the sons of Ahaziah’s relatives who had been working for Ahaziah, and they killed all of them. <verse eid="2CH 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 22:9"/>Then Jehu went to find Ahaziah, and his soldiers found Ahaziah while he was hiding in Samaria <char style="add">city</char>. They brought him to Jehu and executed him. Then they buried his corpse, because they said, “<char style="add">He deserves to be buried, because</char> he was a descendant of Jehoshaphat, who tried hard to please Yahweh.” There were no descendants of Ahaziah who were powerful enough to become the kings of Judah.<verse eid="2CH 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Athaliah and Joash</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 22:10"/>When Athaliah, the mother of Ahaziah, saw that her son had been killed, she commanded that all the members of Ahaziah’s family <char style="add">who might become king</char> must be executed. <verse eid="2CH 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 22:11"/>But Jehosheba, the daughter of King Jehoram, took Joash, Ahaziah’s very young son, away from the other sons of the king who were about to be murdered, and she hid him and his nursemaid in a bedroom in the temple. Because Jehosheba, who was the daughter of King Jehoram and the wife of the Supreme Priest Jehoiada, was Ahaziah’s sister, she hid the child, with the result that Athaliah could not kill him. <verse eid="2CH 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 22:12"/>He remained hidden there for six years while Athaliah ruled <char style="add">Judah</char>.<verse eid="2CH 22:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="2CH 23"/>
  <para style="s1">The revolt against Athaliah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 23:1"/>After Joash had been hidden in the temple for six years, Jehoiada the priest decided that it was necessary to do something. So he made an agreement with the army commanders of groups of 100 soldiers: Azariah the son of Jeroham, Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, Azariah the son of Obed, Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zicri. <verse eid="2CH 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 23:2"/>They went throughout Judah and gathered the descendants of Levi and the leaders of Israeli families from all the towns. When they came to Jerusalem, <verse eid="2CH 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 23:3"/>the whole group went to the temple and made an agreement with the young king there. Jehoiada said to them, “This is the son of the previous king of Judah. So he is the one who must rule, like Yahweh promised that the descendants of King David must do.<verse eid="2CH 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 23:4"/>“So this is what you must do: One-third of you priests and other descendants of Levi who are starting their work on the Sabbath day must guard the doors <char style="add">of the temple</char>. <verse eid="2CH 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 23:5"/>One-third of you must guard the king’s palace, and one-third of you must guard the Foundation Gate. All the other people will be in the courtyards outside the temple. <verse eid="2CH 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 23:6"/>Only the priests and the descendants of Levi who work there will enter the temple. They will be allowed to enter the temple because they are set apart <char style="add">for that work</char>. All the others must remain in the courtyards, obeying what Yahweh has commanded. <verse eid="2CH 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 23:7"/>You descendants of Levi must stand around the young king, each of you with your weapon in your hand. Anyone else who tries to enter the temple you must kill. And stay close to the young king, wherever he goes.”<verse eid="2CH 23:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 23:8"/>So the descendants of Levi and all <char style="add">the men of</char> Judah did what Jehoiada had told them. He did not allow anyone to go home after having finished his work on that Sabbath day. Each commander took charge of his men, the ones who were finishing their work on that day and those who were starting their work on that day. <verse eid="2CH 23:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 23:9"/>Then Jehoiada gave each of the commanders the spears and the large and small shields that had been put there in the temple by King David. <verse eid="2CH 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 23:10"/>He commanded all the guards to stand in their positions, each with his sword in his hand, all around the king—around the altar and the temple, from the north side to the south side.<verse eid="2CH 23:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 23:11"/>Then Jehoiada and his sons brought Joash out. They put a crown on his head and gave him <char style="add">a scroll</char> on which were written the rules <char style="add">that the kings needed to obey</char>, and proclaimed that he was now the king. They anointed him with olive oil and shouted, “We hope that the king will live for many years!”<verse eid="2CH 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 23:12"/>When Athaliah heard the noise being made by the people running <char style="add">toward the king</char> and cheering, she ran to the temple. <verse eid="2CH 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 23:13"/>She saw the young king there, standing alongside the pillar at the entrance of the temple, <char style="add">which is the place at the temple</char> where the kings usually stood. The army commanders and trumpet players were standing beside the king, and all the people of Judah were rejoicing and blowing trumpets, and singers with their musical instruments were leading the people while they praised God. Then Athaliah tore her robes and started screaming, “You are committing treason!”<verse eid="2CH 23:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 23:14"/>Jehoiada the Supreme Priest said to the army commanders, “Kill her, but do not kill her at the temple of Yahweh!” Then he said to them, “Bring Athaliah out in front of the troops and kill anyone who tries to follow her!” <verse eid="2CH 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 23:15"/><char style="add">She tried to flee, but</char> they seized her as she reached the gate where horses enter the palace area, and they killed her there. <verse eid="2CH 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 23:16"/>Then Jehoiada made an agreement that he and the king and all the other people would be Yahweh’s people. <verse eid="2CH 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 23:17"/>Then all the people who were there went to the temple of Baal and tore it down. They smashed the altars <char style="add">of Baal</char>. They also killed Mattan, the priest of Baal, in front of those altars.<verse eid="2CH 23:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 23:18"/>Then Jehoiada appointed the priests, who were also descended from Levi, to work at the temple. They were part of the group to whom King David had given various jobs at the temple, to sacrifice the animals that were to be completely burned on the altar, doing what was written in the laws that Moses had given to them. He also told them to rejoice and sing, which was also what David had commanded. <verse eid="2CH 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 23:19"/>He also put guards at the gates of the temple in order that anyone who was unacceptable to God would not be allowed to enter.<verse eid="2CH 23:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 23:20"/>Jehoiada took with him the army commanders, the important men, the leaders and many others, and brought the king down from the temple. They went into the palace through the Upper Gate, and put the king on his throne. <verse eid="2CH 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 23:21"/>Then all the people of Judah rejoiced. And there was calm throughout the city, because Athaliah had been killed.<verse eid="2CH 23:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="2CH 24"/>
  <para style="s1">King Joash of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 24:1"/>Joash was seven years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>, and he ruled in Jerusalem for 40 years. His mother’s name was Zibiah; she was from Beersheba <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 24:2"/>Joash did what pleased Yahweh as long as Jehoiada was <char style="add">the Supreme</char> Priest. <verse eid="2CH 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 24:3"/>Jehoiada chose two women to be Joash’s wives. And they bore Joash sons and daughters.<verse eid="2CH 24:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 24:4"/>Some years later, Joash decided that the temple should be repaired. <verse eid="2CH 24:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 24:5"/>He summoned the priests and other descendants of Levi and said to them, “Go to the towns in Judah and collect from the people the tax money that they are required to pay each year, and use that money to pay for repairing the temple. Do it immediately.” But the descendants of Levi did not do it immediately.<verse eid="2CH 24:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 24:6"/>So the king summoned Jehoiada and said to him, “Why have you not required the descendants of Levi to bring to Jerusalem from various places in Judah the annual/yearly tax that Moses said that the people of Judah must pay, for taking care of the Sacred Tent?”<verse eid="2CH 24:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 24:7"/>
    <char style="add">The temple needed to be repaired</char> because the sons of that wicked woman Athaliah had entered into the temple <char style="add">and had wrecked some of the things</char>, and had also used some of the sacred items that were in it for <char style="add">the worship of</char> Baal.<verse eid="2CH 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 24:8"/>So, obeying what the king commanded, the descendants of Levi made a chest and placed it outside the temple, at one of the entrances. <verse eid="2CH 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 24:9"/>Then the king sent letters everywhere in Judah, requesting everyone to bring their tax money to the temple, like Moses had required the Israeli people to do <char style="add">when they were</char> in the desert. <verse eid="2CH 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 24:10"/>All the officials and the other people <char style="add">agreed, and they</char> brought their contributions gladly. They put the money into the chest until it was full. <verse eid="2CH 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 24:11"/>Whenever the descendants of Levi brought the chest to the king’s officials, and they saw that there was a lot of money in it, the king’s secretary and the assistant to the <char style="add">Supreme</char> Priest would take all the money from the chest, and then put the chest back in its place. They did this frequently, and they collected a huge amount of money. <verse eid="2CH 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 24:12"/>The king and Jehoiada gave the money to the men who were supervising the work of repairing the temple. Those men hired stoneworkers and carpenters to repair the temple. They also hired men who worked with iron and bronze to repair things in the temple <char style="add">that were broken</char>.<verse eid="2CH 24:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 24:13"/>The men who did the repair work worked hard, and the work of repairing the temple progressed. They rebuilt the temple so that it was like it was originally, and they even made it stronger. <verse eid="2CH 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 24:14"/>When they had finished the repair work, they brought to the king and to Jehoiada the money that they had not used for the repairs. That money was used to make things to use for offering the sacrifices that were completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and to make bowls and other gold and silver things for the temple. As long as Joash lived, the people continually brought to the temple sacrifices that were to be completely burned on the altar.<verse eid="2CH 24:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 24:15"/>Jehoiada lived to become very old. He died when he was 130 years old. <verse eid="2CH 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 24:16"/>He was buried where the kings had been buried, in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’. <char style="add">He was buried there</char> because of the good things that he had done in Judah for God and for God’s temple.<verse eid="2CH 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joash and the people of Judah turned away from Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 24:17"/>After Jehoiada died, the leaders of Judah went to Joash, bowed in front of him, and persuaded him to do what they wanted. <verse eid="2CH 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 24:18"/>So they and the other people stopped worshiping at the temple, and they started worshiping the poles dedicated to <char style="add">the goddess</char> Asherah and other idols. Because of their doing those sinful things, God was very angry with the people of Jerusalem and <char style="add">with the people in other places in</char> Judah. <verse eid="2CH 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 24:19"/>Although Yahweh sent prophets to persuade them to return to him, and although the prophets told them about the evil things that they had done, the people would not pay attention.<verse eid="2CH 24:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 24:20"/>Then God’s Spirit came upon Zechariah, the son of Jehoiada the <char style="add">Supreme</char> Priest. He stood up front of the people and said, “This is what God says: ‘Why are you disobeying what I, Yahweh, have commanded? You have abandoned me, so I will abandon you.’ ”<verse eid="2CH 24:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 24:21"/>But the people planned to kill Zechariah. And the king joined them in doing it. The people killed Zechariah by throwing stones at him in the temple courtyard. <verse eid="2CH 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 24:22"/>King Joash had forgotten about how Zechariah’s father Jehoiada had been kind to him. That’s why he gave orders for the people to kill Jehoiada’s son Zechariah, who said as he was dying, “I hope that Yahweh will see <char style="add">what you are doing to me</char> and punish <char style="add">you for doing it</char>.”<verse eid="2CH 24:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 24:23"/>Near the end of that year (OR, early in the following year), the army of Syria marched to attack <char style="add">the army of</char> Joash. They invaded Judah and attacked Jerusalem and killed all the leaders of the people. They <char style="add">seized many valuable things and</char> sent them to their king in Damascus, <char style="add">their capital city.</char> <verse eid="2CH 24:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 24:24"/>The army of Syria <char style="add">that came to Judah</char> was very small, but Yahweh allowed them to defeat the large army of Judah, because he was punishing Joash and the other people of Judah for having abandoned him, the God whom their ancestors worshiped. <verse eid="2CH 24:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 24:25"/>Before the battle ended, Joash was severely wounded. Then his officials decided to kill him for murdering Zechariah, the son of Jehoiada the <char style="add">Supreme</char> Priest. They killed him while he was in his bed. He was buried in <char style="add">the part of Jerusalem called</char> ‘The City of David’, but they did not bury him in the place where the other kings had been buried.<verse eid="2CH 24:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 24:26"/>Those who conspired to kill him were Zabad the son of Shimeath, who was a woman from the Ammon <char style="add">people-group</char>, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith, who was a woman from the Moab <char style="add">people-group</char>. <verse eid="2CH 24:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 24:27"/>An account of the things that were done by the sons of Joash and the many prophecies about Joash and what he did to repair the temple are written in the scroll called ‘the History of the Kings <char style="add">of Judah and Israel</char>’. Then after Joash died, Amaziah his son became the king.<verse eid="2CH 24:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="2CH 25"/>
  <para style="s1">King Amaziah of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 25:1"/>Amaziah was 25 years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>, and he ruled from Jerusalem for 29 years. His mother was Jehoaddin; she was from Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 25:2"/>Amaziah did many things that pleased Yahweh, but he did not do them enthusiastically. <verse eid="2CH 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 25:3"/>As soon as he was in complete control of his kingdom, he caused to be executed the officials who had murdered his father. <verse eid="2CH 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 25:4"/>But he did not command their sons to be executed; he obeyed what was in the laws that Moses had written. In those laws Yahweh had commanded, “People must not be executed because of <char style="add">what</char> their children <char style="add">have done</char>, and children must not be executed for <char style="add">what</char> their parents <char style="add">have done</char>. People must be executed only for the sins that they themselves have committed.”<verse eid="2CH 25:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 25:5"/>Amaziah summoned the men of <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Judah and Benjamin to come to Jerusalem, and there he put them in groups, each clan in a group by themselves. Then he appointed officers to command each group. Some officers commanded 100 men and some commanded 1,000 men. They counted the men who were at least 20 years old; altogether there were 300,000 men. They were all men who were prepared to be in the army, and able to <char style="add">fight well,</char> using spears and shields. <verse eid="2CH 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 25:6"/>Amaziah also hired 100,000 capable soldiers from Israel and paid almost four tons of silver for them.<verse eid="2CH 25:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 25:7"/>But a prophet came to him and said, “Your majesty, you must not allow those soldiers from Israel to march with your soldiers, because Yahweh does not help the people of the tribe of Ephraim or from <char style="add">anywhere else in</char> Israel. <verse eid="2CH 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 25:8"/>Even if your soldiers go and fight courageously in battles, God will cause your enemies to defeat you; do not forget that God has the power to help armies or to cause them to be defeated.”<verse eid="2CH 25:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 25:9"/>Amaziah asked that prophet, “If I do that, what about the huge amount of silver that I paid to hire those soldiers from Israel?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 25:9">The prophet replied, “Yahweh is able to pay you back more money than you paid <char style="add">to hire those soldiers</char>.”<verse eid="2CH 25:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 25:10"/>So Amaziah told those soldiers from Israel to return home. They left to go home, but they were very angry with the king of Judah <char style="add">for not allowing them to stay and fight</char>.<verse eid="2CH 25:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 25:11"/>Then Amaziah became brave, and he led his army to the Salt Valley. There they killed 10,000 men from the Edom people-group. <verse eid="2CH 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 25:12"/>The army of Judah also captured 10,000 others, and took them to the top of a cliff and threw them all down over the cliff, with the result that their corpses were all smashed to pieces.<verse eid="2CH 25:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 25:13"/>While that was happening, the soldiers from Israel whom Amaziah had sent home after not allowing them to fight along with his soldiers, raided cities and towns in Judea, from Samaria <char style="add">city</char> to Beth-Horon <char style="add">town</char>. They killed 3,000 people and took away a great amount of valuable things.<verse eid="2CH 25:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 25:14"/>When Amaziah returned <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> after his army had slaughtered the soldiers from Edom, he brought the idols that were worshiped by the people of Edom. He set them up to be his own gods. Then he bowed down to <char style="add">worship</char> them and offered sacrifices to them. <verse eid="2CH 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 25:15"/>Because of that, Yahweh was very angry with Amaziah. He sent a prophet to him, who said, “Why do you worship these foreign gods that were not even able to save their own people when your army attacked them?”<verse eid="2CH 25:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 25:16"/>While he was still speaking, the king said to him, “We certainly did not appoint you to be one of my advisors. So stop <char style="add">talking</char>! If you say anything more, <char style="add">I will tell my soldiers to</char> kill you!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 25:16">So the prophet said, “I know that God has determined to get rid of you, because you have <char style="add">begun to</char> worship idols, and have not heeded my advice.” Then the prophet said nothing more.<verse eid="2CH 25:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 25:17"/>Some time later Amaziah, the king of Judah, consulted his advisors. Then he sent a message to Jehoash, the king of Israel. He wrote, “Come here and let’s talk together.”<verse eid="2CH 25:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 25:18"/>But Jehoash replied to King Amaziah, “One time a thistle growing <char style="add">in the mountains</char> in Lebanon sent a message to a cedar tree saying, ‘Let your daughter marry my son.’ But a wild animal in Lebanon came along and trampled the thistle under its feet. <verse eid="2CH 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 25:19"/><char style="add">The meaning of what I am saying is that</char> you are saying to yourself that your army has defeated the army of Edom, so you have become very proud. But you should stay at your home. It would not be good for you to cause trouble, which would result in you and your kingdom of Judah being destroyed.”<verse eid="2CH 25:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 25:20"/>But Amaziah refused to heed Jehoash’s message. That happened because God wanted Jehoash’s army to defeat them, because they were worshiping the gods of Edom. <verse eid="2CH 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 25:21"/>So Jehoash’s army attacked. Their two armies faced each other at Beth-Shemesh <char style="add">city</char> in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 25:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 25:22"/>The army of Judah was badly defeated by the army of Israel, and all the soldiers of Judah fled to their homes. <verse eid="2CH 25:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 25:23"/>King Jehoash’s army also captured King Amaziah there. Then he brought Amaziah to Jerusalem, and his soldiers tore down the wall <char style="add">that was around the city</char>, from the Ephraim Gate to the Corner Gate. That was a section that was about 600 feet long. <verse eid="2CH 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 25:24"/>His soldiers also carried away the gold and silver and other valuable furnishings from the temple which the descendants of Obed-Edom had previously been guarding. They also took away the valuable things in the palace, and they took to Samaria some prisoners whom they had captured.<verse eid="2CH 25:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 25:25"/>King Jehoash of Israel died, and King Amaziah of Judah lived for 15 years after that. <verse eid="2CH 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 25:26"/>An account of all the other things that Amaziah did while he was the king <char style="add">of Judah</char> is written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Judah and Israel’. <verse eid="2CH 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 25:27"/>From the time that Amaziah started to disobey Yahweh, some men in Jerusalem planned to kill him. He was able to escape to Lachish <char style="add">city</char>, but those who wanted to kill him sent another group of people to Lachish and killed him there. <verse eid="2CH 25:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 25:28"/>They put his corpse on a horse and brought it back to Jerusalem and buried it where his ancestors <char style="add">had been buried</char> in the part of Jerusalem called ‘The City of David’.<verse eid="2CH 25:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="2CH 26"/>
  <para style="s1">King Uzziah of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-2" style="v" sid="2CH 26:1-2"/>After King Amaziah died, all the people of Judah appointed his son Uzziah, who then was 16 years old, as their king. <char style="add">One of the things that happened</char> while he was the king <char style="add">was that</char> his men captured Elath <char style="add">town on the Gulf of Aqaba</char> and rebuilt it.<verse eid="2CH 26:1-2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 26:3"/>Uzziah ruled in Jerusalem for 52 years. His mother was Jecoliah; she was from Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 26:4"/>Uzziah did things that Yahweh considered to be good, like his father Amaziah had done. <verse eid="2CH 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 26:5"/>He tried to please God while <char style="add">the priest</char> Zechariah was living, because Zechariah taught him to revere God. As long as Uzziah tried to please God, God enabled him to be successful.<verse eid="2CH 26:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 26:6"/>Uzziah and his army started to fight against the army of Philistia. They tore down the walls of Gath, Jabneh, and Ashdod <char style="add">cities</char>. Then they rebuilt the towns near Ashdod and in other places in Philistia. <verse eid="2CH 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 26:7"/>God helped them to fight the army of Philistia and the Arabs who lived in <char style="add">the town of</char> Gur-Baal and the descendants of Meun who had come to that area from Edom. <verse eid="2CH 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 26:8"/>Even the Ammon <char style="add">people-group</char> paid taxes to Uzziah each year. So Uzziah became famous as far as the border of Egypt, because he had become very powerful.<verse eid="2CH 26:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 26:9"/>Uzziah’s <char style="add">workers</char> built watchtowers in Jerusalem at the Corner Gate, at the Valley Gate, and at the place where the wall turns, and they placed weapons in them. <verse eid="2CH 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 26:10"/>They also built watchtowers in the desert and dug many wells. They did that <char style="add">to provide water</char> for a lot of the king’s cattle that were in the foothills and in the plains. Uzziah liked farming, so he also stationed workers <char style="add">to take care of</char> his fields and vineyards in the hills and in the fertile areas.<verse eid="2CH 26:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 26:11"/>Uzziah’s army was trained for fighting battles. They were in groups that were always ready to go into battle. Jeiel, the king’s secretary, and Maaseiah, one of the army officers, counted the men and placed them in groups. Hananiah, one of the king’s officials, was their commander. <verse eid="2CH 26:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 26:12"/>There were 2,600 leaders of those groups of soldiers. <verse eid="2CH 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 26:13"/>In the groups that those leaders commanded there were a total of 307,500 well-trained soldiers. It was a very powerful army which was ready to help the king fight against his enemies. <verse eid="2CH 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 26:14"/>Uzziah gave to each soldier a shield, a spear, a helmet, a vest made of iron plates, a bow <char style="add">and arrows</char>, and a slingshot. <verse eid="2CH 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 26:15"/>In Jerusalem his skilled workers made machines to put on the watchtowers and on the corners <char style="add">of the walls</char>, to shoot arrows and to hurl large stones. He became very famous even in distant places, because God helped him very much and enabled him to become very powerful.<verse eid="2CH 26:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 26:16"/>But because Uzziah was very powerful, he became very proud, and that led to his being punished. He disobeyed what Yahweh his God had commanded. He went into the temple to burn incense on the altar <char style="add">where God had said that only the priests should burn</char> incense. <verse eid="2CH 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 26:17"/>Azariah the <char style="add">Supreme</char> Priest and 80 other brave priests followed him into the temple. <verse eid="2CH 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 26:18"/>They rebuked him and said to him, “Uzziah, it is not right for you to burn incense to <char style="add">honor</char> Yahweh. That duty is only for the priests, those who are descendants of Aaron <char style="add">our first Supreme Priest</char>! You must leave <char style="add">immediately</char>, because you have disobeyed Yahweh our God, and he will not honor you <char style="add">for what you have done</char>!”<verse eid="2CH 26:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 26:19"/>Uzziah had in his hand a pan for burning incense. He became very angry with the priests, but suddenly there was leprosy on his forehead. <verse eid="2CH 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 26:20"/>When Azariah the <char style="add">Supreme</char> Priest and all the other priests <char style="add">who were there</char> looked at him, they saw the leprosy on his forehead, so they quickly took him outside. And truly the king was eager to leave the temple, because he knew that it was Yahweh who had caused him to have that leprosy, <char style="add">and he did not want it to become worse.</char><verse eid="2CH 26:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 26:21"/>King Uzziah had leprosy until he died. And because he had leprosy, he lived in a house that was not near other houses, and he was not allowed to enter <char style="add">the courtyard of</char> the temple. His son Jotham supervised the palace and ruled the people of Judah.<verse eid="2CH 26:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 26:22"/>A record of all the other things that Uzziah did while he was the king <char style="add">of Judah</char> was written by the prophet Isaiah, the son of Amoz. <verse eid="2CH 26:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 26:23"/>Because Uzziah was a leper, <char style="add">when he died,</char> they would not bury him in the tombs where the other kings were buried. Instead, he was buried in a nearby cemetery that the kings owned. Then his son Jotham became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>.<verse eid="2CH 26:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="2CH 27"/>
  <para style="s1">King Jotham of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 27:1"/>Jotham was 25 years old when he became the king of Judah. He ruled from Jerusalem for 16 years. His mother was Jerushah, the daughter of <char style="add">the priest</char> Zadok. <verse eid="2CH 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 27:2"/>Jotham did many things that pleased Yahweh like his father Uzziah did. He obeyed Yahweh and did things that are right. He did many things that his father Uzziah had done, but he did not burn incense in the temple, like his father had done. However, the people of Judah continued to sin against Yahweh.<verse eid="2CH 27:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 27:3"/>Jotham’s <char style="add">workers</char> rebuilt the Upper Gate of the temple, and they did a lot of work to repair the wall near Ophel <char style="add">Hill</char>. <verse eid="2CH 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 27:4"/>They built towns in the hills of Judah, and they built forts and defense towers in the forests.<verse eid="2CH 27:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 27:5"/>During the time that Jotham was the king of Judah, his army attacked and defeated the army of the Ammon people-group. Then, every year during the next three years, he required the Anmon people-group to pay to him four tons of silver, 60,000 bushels of wheat, and 60,000 bushels of barley.<verse eid="2CH 27:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 27:6"/>Jotham faithfully obeyed Yahweh his God, and as a result he became a very powerful king.<verse eid="2CH 27:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 27:7"/>A record of everything else that Jotham did during the time that he was the king, including the wars that his army fought, is written in the scroll called ‘<char style="add">the History of</char> the Kings of Israel and Judah’. <verse eid="2CH 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 27:8"/>After Jotham had ruled Judah for 16 years, he died when he was 41 years old. <verse eid="2CH 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 27:9"/>He was buried in Jerusalem, and his son Ahaz became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>.<verse eid="2CH 27:9"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="2CH 28"/>
  <para style="s1">King Ahaz of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 28:1"/>Ahaz was 20 years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>. He ruled from Jerusalem for 16 years. His ancestor King David was a good king, but Ahaz was not like David. He constantly disobeyed Yahweh <verse eid="2CH 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 28:2"/>and was as sinful as the kings of Israel had been. He made idols of the god Baal. <verse eid="2CH 28:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 28:3"/>He burned incense in Hinnom Valley. He even <char style="add">killed some of</char> his own sons <char style="add">and</char> offered <char style="add">them</char> as sacrifices to be completely burned. That imitated the disgusting customs of the people-groups who previously lived there, people whom Yahweh had expelled as the Israelis advanced through the land. <verse eid="2CH 28:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 28:4"/>Ahaz offered sacrifices <char style="add">to idols</char> at shrines on hilltops and under every big green tree.<verse eid="2CH 28:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 28:5"/>Therefore Yahweh his God allowed his army to be defeated by the army of the king of Syria. They captured many soldiers of Judah and took them as prisoners to Damascus.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 28:5">The army of the king of Israel also defeated the army of Judah and killed very many of their soldiers. <verse eid="2CH 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 28:6"/>In one day the army of Remaliah’s son, King Pekah <char style="add">of Israel</char>, killed 120,000 soldiers in Judah. That happened because <char style="add">the people of</char> Judah had abandoned Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>. <verse eid="2CH 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 28:7"/>Zicri, a warrior from the tribe of Ephraim, killed king Ahaz’s son Maaseiah, Azrikam the officer in charge of the palace, and Elkanah, the king’s assistant. <verse eid="2CH 28:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 28:8"/>The soldiers of Israel captured 200,000 of the people of Judah, including many wives and sons and daughters <char style="add">of the soldiers of Judah</char>. They also seized and took back to Samaria many valuable things.<verse eid="2CH 28:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 28:9"/>But a prophet of Yahweh whose name was Obed was there <char style="add">in Samaria</char>. He went out of the city to meet the army when it returned to Samaria. He said to them, “Because Yahweh, the God whom your ancestors <char style="add">belonged to</char>, was angry with <char style="add">the people of</char> Judah, he allowed you to defeat them. But God has seen the cruel way that you slaughtered them. <verse eid="2CH 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 28:10"/>And now you want to <char style="add">sin by</char> causing men and women from Judah to become your slaves, but you have certainly also sinned against Yahweh our God! <verse eid="2CH 28:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 28:11"/>So listen to me! Send back <char style="add">to Judah</char> your fellow-countrymen whom you have captured, because Yahweh is extremely angry with you <char style="add">for what you did to them</char>.”<verse eid="2CH 28:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 28:12"/>Then some of the leaders of <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Ephraim—Azariah the son of Jehohanan, Berekiah the son of Meshillemoth, Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai—rebuked those who were returning from the battle. <verse eid="2CH 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 28:13"/>They said to them, “You must not bring those prisoners here! If you do that, Yahweh will consider that we are guilty of sinning. We are already guilty of committing many sins; do you want to cause us to be even more guilty by committing another sin? God is already very angry with <char style="add">us people of</char> Israel!”<verse eid="2CH 28:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 28:14"/>So, while their leaders and others were watching, the soldiers released the prisoners, and also gave back to them the valuable things that they had captured. <verse eid="2CH 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 28:15"/>The leaders who were selected took some of the clothes that the soldiers had taken from the prisoners and gave those clothes back to the people who were naked. They also gave to the prisoners sandals and other clothes and things to eat and drink, and they gave them olive oil to rub on their wounds. They gave donkeys to those who were very weak, in order that they could ride on them. Then they led them all to Jericho, the city that had many palm trees. Then those leaders <char style="add">of Israel</char> returned to Samaria.<verse eid="2CH 28:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 28:16"/>About that time, King Ahaz sent <char style="add">a message</char> to the king of Assyria requesting help. <verse eid="2CH 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 28:17"/><char style="add">He did that because the army from</char> the Edom people-group had come again and attacked Judah and taken away many of the people of Judah as prisoners. <verse eid="2CH 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 28:18"/>At the same time, men from Philistia had raided/attacked towns in the foothills and in the southern desert of Judah. They had captured Beth-Shemesh, Aijalon, and Gederoth <char style="add">cities</char>, as well as Soco, Timnah and Gimzo <char style="add">towns</char> and the nearby villages. <verse eid="2CH 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 28:19"/>Yahweh <char style="add">allowed those things to happen in order to</char> humble king Ahaz, because he had encouraged the people of Judah to do wicked things and had disobeyed Yahweh very much. <verse eid="2CH 28:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 28:20"/>Tiglath-Pileser, the king of Assyria, sent <char style="add">his army saying that they would</char> help Ahaz, but instead of helping him, they caused him to experience trouble. <verse eid="2CH 28:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 28:21"/>Ahaz’s <char style="add">soldiers</char> took some of the <char style="add">valuable</char> things from the temple and from the king’s palace and from other leaders of Judah and sent them to the king of Assyria <char style="add">to pay him to help them</char>, but the king of Assyria refused to help Ahaz.<verse eid="2CH 28:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 28:22"/>While King Ahaz was experiencing those troubles, he disobeyed Yahweh even more. <verse eid="2CH 28:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 28:23"/>He offered sacrifices to the gods that were worshiped in Damascus, whose <char style="add">army</char> had defeated his <char style="add">army</char>. He thought, “The gods that are worshiped by the kings of Syria have helped them, so I will offer sacrifices to those gods in order that they will help me.” But worshiping those gods caused Ahaz and all of Israel to be ruined.<verse eid="2CH 28:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 28:24"/>Ahaz gathered all the furnishings <char style="add">that were used</char> in the temple and broke them into pieces. He locked the doors of the temple and set up altars <char style="add">for worshiping idols</char> at every street corner in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 28:25"/>In every town in Judah, his workers built shrines to burn sacrifices to other gods, and that caused Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, to be very angry.<verse eid="2CH 28:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 28:26"/>A record of the other things that Ahaz did while he was the king, from when he started to rule until he died, is written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Judah and Israel’. <verse eid="2CH 28:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 28:27"/>Ahaz died and was buried in Jerusalem, but he was not buried in the tombs where the other kings <char style="add">had been buried</char>. Then his son Hezekiah became the king.<verse eid="2CH 28:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="2CH 29"/>
  <para style="s1">King Hezekiah of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 29:1"/>Hezekiah was 25 years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>. He ruled from Jerusalem for 29 years. His mother was Abijah, the daughter of <char style="add">a man whose name was</char> Zechariah. <verse eid="2CH 29:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 29:2"/>Hezekiah did things that Yahweh considered to be right, like his ancestor King David had done.<verse eid="2CH 29:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hezekiah purified the temple</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 29:3"/>During March of the first year that Hezekiah was ruling Judah, he unlocked the doors of the temple, and his workers repaired them. <verse eid="2CH 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 29:4"/>Then he gathered the priests and other descendants of Levi in the area on the east side of the temple, <verse eid="2CH 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 29:5"/>and he said to them, “You descendants of Levi, listen to me! Consecrate yourselves. And then consecrate the temple of Yahweh, the God whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped/belonged to</char>. Remove from the temple all the things that are not pleasing to God. <verse eid="2CH 29:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 29:6"/>Our ancestors disobeyed God; they did many things that he considered to be evil, things that were not pleasing to him. They abandoned this place where Yahweh lives, and they have turned away from him. <verse eid="2CH 29:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 29:7"/>They locked the doors of the temple and extinguished the lamps. They did not burn any incense, and they did not offer any sacrifices that were to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 29:8"/>Therefore, Yahweh has become very angry with us people of Jerusalem and <char style="add">other places in</char> Judah, and he has caused other people to become frightened and horrified <char style="add">when they hear what Yahweh did to punish us</char>. And they ridicule us. You know this very well. <verse eid="2CH 29:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 29:9"/>That is why our fathers have been killed in battles, and our sons and daughters and our wives have been captured and taken <char style="add">to other countries</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 29:10"/>But now I intend to make an agreement with Yahweh, our God, in order that he will no longer be angry with us. <verse eid="2CH 29:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 29:11"/><char style="add">You who are like</char> my sons, do not waste any time. <char style="add">Do immediately what Yahweh wants you to do.</char> Yahweh has chosen you to stand in his presence and offer sacrifices and burn incense.”<verse eid="2CH 29:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 29:12"/>Then these descendants of Levi started to work <char style="add">in the temple</char>:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 29:12">From the descendants of Kohath there were Mahath the son of Amasai, and Joel the son of Azariah.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 29:12">From the descendants of Merari there were Kish the son of Abdi, and Azariah the son of Jehallelel.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 29:12">From the descendants of Gershon there were Joah the son of Zimmah, and Eden the son of Joah.<verse eid="2CH 29:12"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 29:13"/>From the descendants of Elizaphan there were Shimri and Jeiel.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 29:13">From the descendants of Asaph there were Zechariah and Mattaniah.<verse eid="2CH 29:13"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 29:14"/>From the descendants of Heman there were Jehiel and Shimei.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="2CH 29:14">From the descendants of Jeduthun there were Shemaiah and Uzziel.<verse eid="2CH 29:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 29:15"/>When those men had gathered their fellow descendants of Levi and had consecrated themselves, they entered the temple in order to consecrate it. That was what the king had commanded them to do, and they were also obeying what Yahweh had commanded. <verse eid="2CH 29:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 29:16"/>The priests entered the temple to consecrate it. They brought out into the courtyard of the temple everything that they had found in the temple that was not pleasing to Yahweh. Then the descendants of Levi took those things down to the Kidron Valley <char style="add">and burned them there</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 29:17"/>The priests and other descendants of Levi started this work on the first day of March and finished purifying the courtyard <char style="add">of the temple</char> on the eighth day of that month, and they finished purifying the temple one week later.<verse eid="2CH 29:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 29:18"/>Then they went to King Hezekiah and reported, “We have purified all parts of the temple, and the altar where sacrifices are completely burned, and all the items used at the altar, the table on which the priests place the sacred bread, and the things <char style="add">used at that table</char>. <verse eid="2CH 29:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 29:19"/>While Ahaz was our king, he disobeyed what Yahweh had commanded, and he removed from the temple many things <char style="add">that should be there</char>, but now we have brought them back and placed them in front of the sacred altar.”<verse eid="2CH 29:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 29:20"/>Early the next morning, King Hezekiah gathered together the city officials, and they went to the <char style="add">courtyard of the</char> temple. <verse eid="2CH 29:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 29:21"/>They took with them seven bulls, seven rams, seven male lambs, and seven male goats to be an offering in order that Yahweh would forgive the sins of all the people in the kingdom of Judah, and in order to purify the temple. The king commanded that the priests, who were descendants of Aaron, should offer those animals to be sacrificed to Yahweh on the altar. <verse eid="2CH 29:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 29:22"/>So first the priests slaughtered those bulls, and took their blood and sprinkled it on the altar. Then they slaughtered the rams and sprinkled their blood on the altar. Then they slaughtered the lambs and sprinkled their blood on the altar. <verse eid="2CH 29:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 29:23"/>The goats that were slaughtered to be an offering in order that Yahweh would forgive the sins of the people were brought to the king and the others who were there. Then the king and those who were present laid their hands on those goats. <verse eid="2CH 29:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 29:24"/>Then the priests slaughtered those goats and splashed their blood on the altar in order that Yahweh would forgive the sins that all the Israeli people had committed. The priests did that because the king had commanded that offerings that would be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> and other sacrifices should be made for all the people of Israel.<verse eid="2CH 29:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 29:25"/>The king then told the descendants of Levi to stand in the temple with their cymbals and harps and lyres, obeying what David and his prophets Gad and Nathan had commanded. Those were things that Yahweh had told his prophets that the descendants of Levi should do. <verse eid="2CH 29:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 29:26"/>So the descendants of Levi <char style="add">went and</char> stood in the temple, ready to play the musical instruments that King David had given to them. And the priests were ready to blow their trumpets.<verse eid="2CH 29:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 29:27"/>Then Hezekiah told some of the priests to burn the animals that would be sacrificed on the altar. When they started to burn the animals, the people started to sing to <char style="add">praise</char> Yahweh, while the other descendants of Levi were playing their instruments. <verse eid="2CH 29:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 29:28"/>All the people who were there bowed to worship Yahweh, while the singers sang and the trumpeters blew their trumpets. They continued to do this until they had finished slaughtering all the animals that would be completely burned.<verse eid="2CH 29:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 29:29"/>When they finished making those offerings, the king and all those who were there knelt down and worshiped Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 29:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 29:30"/>Then King Hezekiah and his officials commanded the descendants of Levi to praise Yahweh, singing the songs <char style="add">composed/written</char> by David and Asaph the prophet. So they sang songs joyfully and bowed their heads to worship.<verse eid="2CH 29:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 29:31"/>Then Hezekiah said, “You have now dedicated yourselves to Yahweh. So come close to the temple and bring animals to be sacrificed and other offerings to thank <char style="add">Yahweh for what he has done for you</char>.” And those who wanted to bring animals to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> brought them.<verse eid="2CH 29:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 29:32"/>Altogether they brought 70 bulls, 100 rams, and 200 male lambs to be completely burned on the altar. <verse eid="2CH 29:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 29:33"/>The other animals that they brought were 600 bulls and 3,000 sheep and goats that were set apart to be sacrifices. <verse eid="2CH 29:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2CH 29:34"/>But there were not enough priests to remove the skins from the animals that would be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. So their fellow descendants of Levi helped them until that work was finished, and until other priests had purified/consecrated themselves to do that work. It was necessary for them to do that because many of the priests had not yet performed the rituals to consecrate themselves for that work, like the descendants of Levi had done.<verse eid="2CH 29:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2CH 29:35"/>In addition to the all the offerings that were completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, the priests also burned the fat of the other animals that were sacrificed to maintain good fellowship with Yahweh, and the usual wine offerings.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 29:35">So the worship at the temple began again. <verse eid="2CH 29:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2CH 29:36"/>And Hezekiah and all the other people of Judah celebrated, because God had enabled them to do all those things very quickly.<verse eid="2CH 29:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="2CH 30"/>
  <para style="s1">Preparations to celebrate the Passover Festival</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-3" style="v" sid="2CH 30:1-3"/>The king and his officials and all the other people who had gathered in Jerusalem wanted to celebrate the Passover Festival. But they were not able to celebrate it at the usual time, because many of the priests had still not performed the rituals to purify themselves; therefore they were not allowed to do serve in the festival. Also, everyone had still not come to Jerusalem <char style="add">to celebrate the Passover</char>. So they decided to celebrate it one month later than usual. <verse eid="2CH 30:1-3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 30:4"/>The king and all the other people who had gathered thought that was a good plan. <verse eid="2CH 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 30:5"/>So they decided to send messages to all the towns in Judah and in Israel, from Beersheba <char style="add">in the far south</char> to Dan <char style="add">in the far north</char>, including towns in the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh, to invite people to come to the temple in Jerusalem to celebrate the Passover <char style="add">Festival</char> to <char style="add">honor</char> Yahweh, the God whom the Israeli people <char style="add">worshiped/belonged to</char>. Many of the people had not previously celebrated that festival, even though it had been written <char style="add">in the laws of Moses that they should do that</char>.<verse eid="2CH 30:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 30:6"/>Obeying what the king commanded, messengers went throughout Judah and Israel, taking messages that had been written by the king and his officials. This is what they wrote:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CH 30:6">“You Israeli people, you who survived after being slaves of the kings of Assyria, return to Yahweh, the God whom <char style="add">our great ancestors</char> Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob <char style="add">worshiped/belonged to</char>, in order that he may return to you. Your fathers and brothers did not faithfully obey Yahweh, the God whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>. <verse eid="2CH 30:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 30:7"/>Do not act like they did, because what they did caused other people to become disgusted with them. <verse eid="2CH 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 30:8"/>Do not be stubborn as our ancestors were. Do what Yahweh desires. Come <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> to the temple, which he has set apart forever. Do what pleases Yahweh our God, in order that he will no longer be angry with you. <verse eid="2CH 30:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 30:9"/>If you return to Yahweh, the people who have captured our brothers <char style="add">and sisters</char> and our children will be kind to them, and allow them to return to this land. Do not forget that Yahweh our God is kind and merciful. If you return to him, he will no longer reject you.”<verse eid="2CH 30:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 30:10"/>The messengers went to all the towns in the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh, as far <char style="add">north</char> as the tribe of Zebulun, <char style="add">and gave them this message,</char> but most of the people there scorned them and ridiculed them. <verse eid="2CH 30:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 30:11"/>But some of the people of <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Asher, Manasseh, and Zebulun humbled themselves and went to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 30:12"/>Also in Judah God motivated the people to be united in wanting to do what Yahweh wanted them to do, which is what the king and his officials had told them to do in the message that they sent.<verse eid="2CH 30:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">They celebrated the Passover Festival</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 30:13"/>So a huge crowd of people gathered in Jerusalem in May, to celebrate the Festival of Eating Unleavened Bread. <verse eid="2CH 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 30:14"/>They removed the altars <char style="add">of Baal</char> in Jerusalem and took away the altars for burning incense <char style="add">to honor other gods, and burned them</char> in Kidron Valley.<verse eid="2CH 30:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 30:15"/>They slaughtered the Passover lambs on the fourteenth day of that month. Some of the priests and the other descendants of Levi were ashamed <char style="add">because they had not performed the rituals to cause them to be acceptable to work for Yahweh</char>. So they performed those rituals, and brought to the temple animals to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>.<verse eid="2CH 30:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 30:16"/>Then they stood at the places where Moses had written in his laws that they should stand. Then the descendants of Levi gave to the priests <char style="add">bowls containing blood of the animals that were being sacrificed</char>, and the priests sprinkled <char style="add">the altar</char> with some of the blood. <verse eid="2CH 30:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 30:17"/>Many people in the crowd had not purified themselves, and therefore they were not able to kill the lambs <char style="add">and dedicate them</char> to Yahweh. So it was necessary for the descendants of Levi to kill the lambs for them. <verse eid="2CH 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 30:18"/>Although most of the people who had come from <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Ephraim, Manasseh, and Issachar had not purified themselves, they ate the food of the Passover Festival anyway, ignoring the rules written <char style="add">by Moses</char>. But Hezekiah prayed for them, saying “Yahweh, you always do what is good; I pray that you will forgive everyone <verse eid="2CH 30:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 30:19"/>who sincerely wants to honor you, the God whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, even if they have not purified themselves by obeying the sacred laws that you gave to us.” <verse eid="2CH 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 30:20"/>And Yahweh heard what Hezekiah prayed; he forgave the people, <char style="add">and did not punish them</char>.<verse eid="2CH 30:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 30:21"/>The Israeli people who were there in Jerusalem celebrated the Festival of Eating Unleavened Bread for seven days. They rejoiced greatly as they celebrated, while the priests and other descendants of Levi sang to Yahweh every day, and played musical instruments to <char style="add">praise</char> God.<verse eid="2CH 30:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 30:22"/>Hezekiah thanked all the descendants of Levi for doing this work for Yahweh, and for very skillfully leading the people who were worshiping. For those seven days the people ate the Passover food and brought offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh and praised Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">belonged to/had worshiped</char>.<verse eid="2CH 30:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 30:23"/>Then the whole group decided to celebrate for seven more days, so they did: They celebrated joyfully for seven more days. <verse eid="2CH 30:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 30:24"/>King Hezekiah provided 1,000 bulls and 7,000 sheep to be slaughtered for the people <char style="add">to eat during the festival</char>, and the officials also gave them 1,000 bulls and 10,000 sheep and goats. Many priests consecrated themselves. <verse eid="2CH 30:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 30:25"/>All the people of Judah rejoiced, including the priests and other descendants of Levi and all the people from Israel who had come, and including some from other countries who were living in Israel and some from other countries who were living in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 30:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 30:26"/>Everyone in Jerusalem was very joyful, because nothing like this had happened in Jerusalem since the time when David’s son Solomon was the king of Israel. <verse eid="2CH 30:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 30:27"/>The priests and the other descendants of Levi stood up to bless the people, and God heard them in heaven, the holy place where he lives.<verse eid="2CH 30:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="2CH 31"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 31:1"/>After the festival ended, the Israelis who were there went to all the towns in Judah and smashed the stones/pillars <char style="add">for worshiping idols</char>, and cut down the poles <char style="add">for worshiping the goddess</char> Asherah. They destroyed the shrines on the hilltops and the altars <char style="add">of Baal</char> throughout the areas where the tribes of Judah and Benjamin lived, and also in the areas of the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh. After destroying all of them, they returned to their own towns.<verse eid="2CH 31:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The offerings for the priests and Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 31:2"/>Hezekiah divided the priests and <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi into groups. He appointed some of the groups to offer sacrifices that would be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> and offerings to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>. He appointed some groups to do other work at the temple: some to lead the people in their worship, some to thank Yahweh, and some to sing songs to praise to Yahweh at the gates of the temple. <verse eid="2CH 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 31:3"/>The king contributed some of his own funds to buy animals that would be sacrificed in the morning and in the evening of each day, and on the Sabbath days, to celebrate the new moons, and during the other feasts, according to what was written in the laws <char style="add">that Yahweh gave to Moses</char>. <verse eid="2CH 31:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 31:4"/>Hezekiah told the people living in Jerusalem to give to the priests and the other descendants of Levi the portions <char style="add">of meat</char> that should be given to them, in order that they could devote all their time to obeying the laws of Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 31:5"/>As soon as he told that to the people, they generously gave the first part of their harvest of grain, and the first part of the new wine <char style="add">that they produced</char>, and <char style="add">olive</char> oil and honey, and of the crops that grew in their fields. They brought <char style="add">to the temple</char> a tenth of all their crops. <verse eid="2CH 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 31:6"/>The men of Israel and Judah who were living in various towns in Judah also brought a tenth of their cattle and sheep and goats, and a tenth of other things that they had dedicated to Yahweh their God, and they piled all those things in heaps. <verse eid="2CH 31:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 31:7"/>They started to do that in May and finished doing it in September. <verse eid="2CH 31:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 31:8"/>When Hezekiah and his officials saw the heaps, they praised Yahweh and <char style="add">requested God to</char> bless the people.<verse eid="2CH 31:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 31:9"/>But Hezekiah asked the priests and other descendants of Levi, “Why are these heaps of things here?” <verse eid="2CH 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 31:10"/>Then Azariah the <char style="add">Supreme</char> Priest, a descendant of Zadok, replied, “Since the time that the people started to bring their offerings to the temple, we have had even more food than we need. This has happened because Yahweh has greatly blessed our fellow Israelis, with the result that all this is left over <char style="add">after we priests and other descendants of Levi took all that we need</char>!”<verse eid="2CH 31:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 31:11"/>Then Hezekiah ordered that they should prepare storerooms in the temple. So they did that. <verse eid="2CH 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 31:12"/>Then they brought into the storerooms all the tithes and offerings and the things dedicated to Yahweh <char style="add">which the people had brought</char>. One of the descendants of Levi whose name was Conaniah was in charge of those things, and his <char style="add">younger</char> brother Shimei was his assistant. <verse eid="2CH 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 31:13"/>Those two men supervised Jehiel, Azaziah, Nahath, Asahel, Jerimoth, Jozabad, Eliel, Ismakiah, Mahath and Benaiah while they did the work. They were appointed by King Hezekiah; Azariah was in charge of <char style="add">everything that was done in</char> the temple.<verse eid="2CH 31:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 31:14"/>Kore the son of Imnah, another descendant of Levi, who guarded the east gate of the temple, was in charge of the offerings to God that were made voluntarily. He distributed to the priests and <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi the offerings and other things that were dedicated to Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 31:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 31:15"/>Eden, Miniamin, Jeshua, Shemaiah, Amariah and Shecaniah faithfully assisted him in the towns where the priests lived. They distributed those things to the groups of their fellow priests; they distributed them to everyone, from the youngest to the oldest.<verse eid="2CH 31:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 31:16"/>They also distributed things to the males who were at least 30 years old, those whose names were written on the scrolls where lists of family names were written. They were males who <char style="add">were allowed to</char> enter the temple to perform their tasks/work each day, the tasks that each group had been assigned to do. <verse eid="2CH 31:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 31:17"/>The names of the priests were on the scrolls where their clans’ names were written. They also distributed things to groups of <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi, those who were at least 20 years old. <verse eid="2CH 31:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 31:18"/>They included all their little children and wives and other sons and daughters whose names were on the scrolls where their clans’ names were written, because they also faithfully had dedicated themselves to Yahweh.<verse eid="2CH 31:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 31:19"/>
    <char style="add">Hezekiah</char> also appointed other men to distribute portions of those offerings to the priests and other descendants of Levi who were living in the pasturelands around the towns in Judah. But they gave things only to those who were descendants of Aaron <char style="add">the first Supreme Priest</char>, whose names were on the scrolls containing the names of their clans.<verse eid="2CH 31:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 31:20"/>That is what Hezekiah did throughout Judah. He always faithfully did things that Yahweh his God considered to be right and good. <verse eid="2CH 31:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 31:21"/>In everything that he did for the worship in the temple, and as he obeyed God’s laws and commands, he tried to find out what his God wanted, and he worked energetically. So he was successful.<verse eid="2CH 31:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 31"/>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="2CH 32"/>
  <para style="s1">The army of King Sennacherib of Assyria invaded Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 32:1"/>After King Hezekiah had obeyed Yahweh’s instructions and had done all those things, King Sennacherib of Assyria came <char style="add">with his army</char> and invaded Judah. He commanded his soldiers to surround the cities that had walls around them, thinking that they would <char style="add">break through those walls and</char> conquer those cities. <verse eid="2CH 32:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 32:2"/>When Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib had come <char style="add">with his army</char> and that they intended to attack Jerusalem, <verse eid="2CH 32:2"/><verse number="3-4" style="v" sid="2CH 32:3-4"/>he consulted with his officials and army leaders. They said among themselves, “Why should we allow the king of Assyria <char style="add">and his army</char> to come and find plenty of water to drink?” So they decided to stop the water from flowing outside the city. So a large group of men gathered together and blocked all the springs and the stream that flowed through that area. <verse eid="2CH 32:3-4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 32:5"/>Then they worked hard to repair all the sections of the city wall that had been broken, and they built watchtowers on the walls. They built another wall outside/around the wall that was already outside the city, and they strengthened the defenses on the sloping terraces <char style="add">on the east side of the area called ‘The City of David’</char>. They also made a large number of weapons and shields.<verse eid="2CH 32:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 32:6"/>Hezekiah appointed army commanders, and he gathered them in front of him in the square at one of the city gates, and he encouraged them by saying this to them: <verse eid="2CH 32:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 32:7"/>“Be strong and courageous. Do not be afraid or discouraged on account of the king of Assyria and the huge army that is with him, because <char style="add">Yahweh</char> is with us, and his <char style="add">power</char> is greater than their <char style="add">power</char>. <verse eid="2CH 32:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 32:8"/>They have to rely on the power of humans, but we have Yahweh our God to help us and to fight battles for us.” So the people became more confident because of what Hezekiah, the king of Judah, said.<verse eid="2CH 32:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 32:9"/>Later, when Sennacherib and all his soldiers were surrounding Lachish <char style="add">city</char>, he sent some officers to Jerusalem to give this message to King Hezekiah and to all the people of Judah who were there:<verse eid="2CH 32:9"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 32:10"/>“<char style="add">I am</char> Sennacherib, the <char style="add">great</char> king of Assyria, <char style="add">and</char> this is what I say: 'While you are staying in Jerusalem, my soldiers are surrounding the city. So why [RHQ] are you so confident? <verse eid="2CH 32:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 32:11"/>Hezekiah says to you, “Yahweh our God will save us from <char style="add">being defeated by the army of</char> the king of Assyria,” but he is misleading you. He wants you to die from having no food or water. <verse eid="2CH 32:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 32:12"/>Isn’t Hezekiah the one who told his men to get rid of your god Yahweh’s shrines and altars on the hilltops, saying to <char style="add">you people of</char> Jerusalem and other places in Judah, “You must worship at only one altar and burn sacrifices on only that altar”?<verse eid="2CH 32:12"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="13-14" style="v" sid="2CH 32:13-14"/>'Do you people not know what I and my ancestors have done to all the people-groups in other countries? <char style="add">We destroyed them all, and</char> none of the gods of those nations were ever able to prevent my <char style="add">troops</char> from conquering them! So how can your god prevent my soldiers from conquering you? <verse eid="2CH 32:13-14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 32:15"/>So do not allow Hezekiah to deceive you like this. Do not believe what he says, because no god of any nation or kingdom has ever been able to rescue his people from being conquered by my army and the armies of my ancestors. So certainly your god will not be able to rescue you from my power' .”<verse eid="2CH 32:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 32:16"/>Sennacherib’s officers said more things to belittle Yahweh the God of the Israelis and Hezekiah, who served God <char style="add">well</char>. <verse eid="2CH 32:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 32:17"/>King Sennacherib wrote more letters insulting Yahweh, the God whom the Israelis <char style="add">belonged to/worshiped</char>. He said things like this: “The gods <char style="add">worshiped by</char> the people-groups in other countries did not rescue their people from my power. Similarly, the god of Hezekiah will not rescue his people from my power.” <verse eid="2CH 32:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 32:18"/>Then King Sennachereb’s officers shouted in the Hebrew language to the people who were on the wall, in order to cause them to be terrified, thinking that as a result the army of Assyria could capture the city <char style="add">without a battle</char>. <verse eid="2CH 32:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 32:19"/>They belittled the God <char style="add">worshiped by the people</char> of Jerusalem as they belittled the gods of the other people-groups of the world—saying that they were only <char style="add">idols</char> made by humans.<verse eid="2CH 32:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 32:20"/>Then King Hezekiah and the prophet Isaiah cried out to God, praying about this. <verse eid="2CH 32:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 32:21"/>And <char style="add">that night</char> Yahweh sent an angel who killed all the soldiers of Assyria and their leaders and their officers in the place where the king of Assyria and his army had set up their tents. So the king of Assyria left and returned to his own country, very disgraced. And one day when he went into the temple of his god, some of his sons struck him with their swords and killed him.<verse eid="2CH 32:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 32:22"/>That is how Yahweh rescued Hezekiah and the people of Jerusalem from the power of Sennacherib, the king of Assyria, and from their other enemies. Yahweh took care of them (OR, gave them peace) everywhere in the country. <verse eid="2CH 32:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 32:23"/>Many people brought offerings for Yahweh to Jerusalem, and also brought valuable gifts for King Hezekiah. And from that time, Hezekiah was highly respected/honored by the people of all the other nations.<verse eid="2CH 32:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hezekiah became proud</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 32:24"/>About that time, Hezekiah became very ill. He was about to die. But he prayed to Yahweh, and Yahweh answered his prayer. He performed a miracle <char style="add">and healed Hezekiah</char>. <verse eid="2CH 32:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 32:25"/>But Hezekiah [SYN] was very proud, and he did not thank Yahweh for being kind to him. Therefore Yahweh was angry with him and <char style="add">and punished him</char> and <char style="add">the people of</char> Jerusalem and other places in Judah. <verse eid="2CH 32:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 32:26"/>Then Hezekiah said that he was sorry for being proud, and the people of Jerusalem also said that they were sorry <char style="add">for their sins</char>. So Yahweh did not punish them during the remaining years that Hezekiah <char style="add">was their king</char>.<verse eid="2CH 32:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hezekiah became very rich</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 32:27"/>Hezekiah became very rich and was greatly honored. His <char style="add">workers</char> made storerooms for his silver and gold, and for his very valuable stones, and for spices and shields and other valuable things. <verse eid="2CH 32:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 32:28"/><char style="add">His workers</char> also built buildings to store the grain and wine and <char style="add">olive</char> oil <char style="add">that people produced and brought to him</char>. They also made stalls for various kinds of cattle and pens for his flocks <char style="add">of sheep and goats</char>. <verse eid="2CH 32:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 32:29"/>They built towns and acquired for the king many flocks <char style="add">of sheep and goats</char> and herds <char style="add">of cattle</char>, because God had enabled him to become very rich.<verse eid="2CH 32:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 32:30"/>Hezekiah was the one who told his workers to block the place where the water flows out of the Gihon Spring, and to build a tunnel through which the water flowed to the west side of the area called ‘The City of David’. He was able to do everything that he wanted to do. <verse eid="2CH 32:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 32:31"/>But when messengers who were sent by the rulers of Babylon came and asked about the miracle that God had performed for him, God allowed Hezekiah to say what he himself wanted to say, in order to test <char style="add">whether or not Hezekiah would admit that God had performed a miracle</char>.<verse eid="2CH 32:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 32:32"/>A record of the other things that happened while Hezekiah was ruling, and the things that he did to please God, is on the scroll in which is written the vision that <char style="add">Yahweh gave to</char> the prophet Isaiah. It is also written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Judah and Israel’. <verse eid="2CH 32:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 32:33"/>When Hezekiah died, he was buried in the tombs where the most respected kings <char style="add">of Judah</char> were buried. Everyone in Jerusalem and other places in Judah honored him. Then his son Manasseh became the king.<verse eid="2CH 32:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 32"/>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="2CH 33"/>
  <para style="s1">King Manasseh of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 33:1"/>Manasseh was 12 years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>, and he ruled from Jerusalem for 55 years. <verse eid="2CH 33:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 33:2"/>He did many things that Yahweh considered to be evil. He imitated the disgusting things that were formerly done by the people-groups that Yahweh had expelled from Israel as his people advanced <char style="add">though the land</char>. <verse eid="2CH 33:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 33:3"/>He commanded his workers to rebuild the shrines <char style="add">for worshiping idols</char> that his father Hezekiah had destroyed. He told them to set up altars to <char style="add">honor</char> the statues of Baal, and to make altars to <char style="add">honor the goddess</char> Asherah. He bowed down to <char style="add">worship</char> all the stars. <verse eid="2CH 33:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 33:4"/>He directed his workers to build altars <char style="add">for foreign gods</char> in the temple, about which Yahweh had said, “It is here in Jerusalem that I want people to worship me, forever.” <verse eid="2CH 33:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 33:5"/>He directed that altars for <char style="add">worshiping</char> all the stars be built in both of the courtyards outside the temple. <verse eid="2CH 33:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 33:6"/>He even sacrificed <char style="add">some of</char> his own sons and burned them in a fire in Hinnom Valley. He performed rituals to practice sorcery. He asked fortune-tellers for advice. He performed witchcraft. He talked to people who consulted the spirits of people who had died to find out what would happen in the future. He did many things that Yahweh considered o be very evil, things that caused Yahweh to become very angry.<verse eid="2CH 33:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 33:7"/>Manasseh took a carved idol <char style="add">that his workers had made</char> and put it in the temple. That is the temple concerning which God had said to David and to his son Solomon, “My temple will be here in Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen <char style="add">where I want people to</char> worship me, forever. <verse eid="2CH 33:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 33:8"/>If they will obey all the laws and decrees and regulations that I told Moses to give to them, I will not again force the Israeli people to leave this land that I gave to their ancestors.” <verse eid="2CH 33:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 33:9"/>But Manasseh led the people of Jerusalem and other places in Judah to do things that are wrong, with the result that they did more evil than was done by the people in the people-groups that Yahweh had expelled as the Israeli people advanced <char style="add">through the land</char>.<verse eid="2CH 33:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 33:10"/>Yahweh spoke to Manasseh and the people of Judah, but they paid no attention. <verse eid="2CH 33:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 33:11"/>So Yahweh caused the army commanders of Assyria <char style="add">and their soldiers</char> to <char style="add">come to Jerusalem, and they</char> captured Manasseh. They put a hook in his nose and put bronze chains on his <char style="add">feet</char> and took him to Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 33:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 33:12"/>There, while he was suffering, he humbled himself greatly in the presence of Yahweh, the God whom his ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, and pleaded with Yahweh to help him. <verse eid="2CH 33:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 33:13"/>When he prayed, Yahweh heard him and pitied him. So he <char style="add">allowed him to</char> return to Jerusalem and <char style="add">to</char> rule his kingdom again. Then Manasseh realized that Yahweh is <char style="add">an all-powerful</char> God.<verse eid="2CH 33:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 33:14"/>Later, Manasseh’s <char style="add">workers</char> rebuilt the eastern section of the outer wall around Jerusalem, and <char style="add">they</char> made it higher. That section extended from Gihon Spring <char style="add">north</char> to the Fish Gate, and around the part of the city that they called Ophel <char style="add">Hill</char>. Manasseh also appointed army officers to guard each of the cities in Judah that had walls around them. <verse eid="2CH 33:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 33:15"/>Manasseh’s <char style="add">workers</char> removed from the temple the idols and the stone statues of gods of other nations. Manasseh also <char style="add">told them to</char> remove the altars that they had previously built on Zion Hill and in <char style="add">other places in</char> Jerusalem. He had all those things thrown out of the city. <verse eid="2CH 33:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 33:16"/>Then he <char style="add">told them to</char> repair the altar of Yahweh, and he offered sacrifices to restore fellowship with Yahweh and to thank him. And he told <char style="add">the people of</char> Judah that they must worship <char style="add">only</char> Yahweh. <verse eid="2CH 33:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 33:17"/>The people continued to offer sacrifices on the hilltops, but only to Yahweh their God.<verse eid="2CH 33:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 33:18"/>The other things that happened while Manasseh was ruling, including his prayer to God and the messages from Yahweh that the prophets gave to him, are written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel’. <verse eid="2CH 33:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 33:19"/>What Manasseh prayed and how God pitied him because he pleaded to God, and also his sins and ways in which he disobeyed God, and the <char style="add">list of</char> places where he built shrines and set up poles to <char style="add">honor the goddess</char> Asherah and other idols <char style="add">before he humbled himself</char>, are written in what the prophets wrote. <verse eid="2CH 33:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 33:20"/>Manasseh died and was buried in his palace. Then his son Amon became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>.<verse eid="2CH 33:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Amon of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 33:21"/>Amon was 22 years old when he became king, and he ruled in Jerusalem for two years. <verse eid="2CH 33:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 33:22"/>He did things that Yahweh considered to be evil, like his father Manasseh had done. Amon worshiped all the idols that Manasseh’s <char style="add">workers</char> had made. <verse eid="2CH 33:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 33:23"/>But he did not humble himself and turn to Yahweh like his father did. So he became more sinful than his father had been.<verse eid="2CH 33:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 33:24"/>Then Amon’s officials made plans to kill him. They assassinated him in his palace. <verse eid="2CH 33:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 33:25"/>But then the people of Judah killed all those who had assassinated Amon, and they appointed his son Josiah to be their king.<verse eid="2CH 33:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 33"/>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="2CH 34"/>
  <para style="s1">King Josiah of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 34:1"/>Josiah was eight years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>. He ruled from Jerusalem for 31 years. <verse eid="2CH 34:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 34:2"/>He did things that were pleasing to Yahweh and conducted his life like his ancestor King David had done. He fully obeyed [IDM] all the laws of God.<verse eid="2CH 34:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 34:3"/>When he had been ruling for almost eight years, while he was still a young man, he began to worship God like his ancestor <char style="add">King</char> David had done. Four years later, he began to get rid of all the pagan shrines on hilltops in Jerusalem and in <char style="add">other places in</char> Judah, and the poles to <char style="add">honor the goddess</char> Asherah, and the carved idols and statues of gods. <verse eid="2CH 34:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 34:4"/>While he directed them, his workers tore down the altars where people worshiped Baal. They smashed the altars that were near those altars, where people burned incense. They smashed the poles to<char style="add">honor the goddess</char> Asherah and the idols and statues. They smashed them to bits and scattered the bits over the graves of those who had offered sacrifices to them. <verse eid="2CH 34:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 34:5"/>They burned the bones of the priests <char style="add">who had offered sacrifices</char>; they burned them on their own altars. In that way Josiah caused Jerusalem and other places in Judah to be acceptable places to worship Yahweh again. <verse eid="2CH 34:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 34:6"/>In the towns in <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Manasseh, Ephraim, and Simeon, and as far <char style="add">north</char> as <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Naphtali and in the ruins around all those towns, <verse eid="2CH 34:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 34:7"/>Josiah’s <char style="add">workers</char> tore down the pagan altars and the poles to <char style="add">honor the goddess</char> Asherah, and crushed the idols to powder. They also smashed to pieces all the altars for burning incense throughout Israel. Then Josiah returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 34:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 34:8"/>When Josiah had been ruling for almost 18 years, he <char style="add">did something else to</char> cause the land and the temple to be acceptable places to worship Yahweh. He sent Shaphan the son of Azaliah and Maaseiah the governor of the city and Joah the son of Joahaz, who wrote on a scroll what happened in the city, to repair the temple of Yahweh.<verse eid="2CH 34:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 34:9"/>They went to Hilkiah the Supreme Priest and gave him the money that had been brought to the temple. That was the money that the descendants of Levi who guarded the doors of the temple had collected from the people of <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Manasseh and Ephraim and <char style="add">other places in northern</char> Israel, and also from all the people in Jerusalem and other places in the tribes of Judah and Benjamin.<verse eid="2CH 34:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 34:10"/>Then Hilkiah gave some of the money to the men who had been appointed to supervise the work of repairing the temple. The supervisors paid the men who did the repair work. <verse eid="2CH 34:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 34:11"/>They also gave some of the money to the carpenters and builders to buy the cut stones and the timber for the joists and the beams for the buildings that the kings of Judah had allowed to decay.<verse eid="2CH 34:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 34:12"/>The workers did their work faithfully. Their supervisors were Jahath and Obadiah, who were descendants of <char style="add">Levi’s son</char> Merari, and Zechariah and Meshullam, who were descendants of <char style="add">Levi’s son</char> Kohath. All the other descendants of Levi, those who played musical instruments well, <verse eid="2CH 34:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 34:13"/>supervised all the workers as they did their various jobs. Some of the descendants of Levi were secretaries and some kept records and some guarded the gates <char style="add">of the temple</char>.<verse eid="2CH 34:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The scroll containing God’s laws was found</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 34:14"/>While they were giving to the supervisors the money that had been taken to the temple, Hilkiah the <char style="add">Supreme</char> Priest found a scroll on which were written the laws that Yahweh had told Moses to give to the people. <verse eid="2CH 34:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 34:15"/>So Hilkiah said to Shaphan, “I have found in the temple a scroll on which are written the laws <char style="add">that God gave to Moses</char>!” Then Hilkiah gave the scroll to Shaphan.<verse eid="2CH 34:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 34:16"/>Shaphan <char style="add">took the scroll</char> to the king and said to him, “Your officials are doing everything that you told them to do. <verse eid="2CH 34:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 34:17"/>They have taken the money that was in the temple, and they have given it to the men who will supervise the workers who will repair the temple.” <verse eid="2CH 34:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 34:18"/>Then Shaphan said to the king, “<char style="add">I have brought to you</char> a scroll <char style="add">that </char> Hilkiah gave to me.” And Shaphan started to read it to the king.<verse eid="2CH 34:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 34:19"/>When the king heard the laws <char style="add">that were written in the scroll</char>, he tore his clothes <char style="add">because he was very dismayed/worried</char>. <verse eid="2CH 34:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 34:20"/>Then he gave these instructions to Hilkiah, to Shaphan’s son Ahikam, to Micah’s son Abdon, to Shaphan, and to Asaiah the king’s special advisor: <verse eid="2CH 34:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 34:21"/>“Go and ask Yahweh for me, and for all his people who are still alive in Judah and Israel, about what is written in this scroll that has been found. Because <char style="add">it is clear that</char> Yahweh is very angry with us because our ancestors disobeyed what Yahweh said; they did not obey the laws that are written on this scroll.”<verse eid="2CH 34:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 34:22"/>So Hilkiah and the others went to talk with a woman whose name was Huldah, who was a prophetess who lived in the newer part of Jerusalem. Her husband Shallum who was the son of Tikvah, took care of the robes that were worn <char style="add">in the temple</char>.<verse eid="2CH 34:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 34:23"/>
    <char style="add">When they told her what the king had said,</char> she said to them, “This is what Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, says: ‘Go back and tell the king who sent you <verse eid="2CH 34:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 34:24"/>that this is what Yahweh says: “Listen to this carefully. I am going to cause a disaster to strike Jerusalem and all the people who live here. I will cause them to experience the curses that were written in the scroll that was read to the king of Judah. <verse eid="2CH 34:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 34:25"/>I will do that because they have rejected me, and they burn incense to <char style="add">honor</char> other gods. They have caused me to become very angry because of all the idols that they have made (OR, because of all the wicked things that they have done), <char style="add">and my anger is like</char> a fire that will not be extinguished. <verse eid="2CH 34:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CH 34:26"/>The king of Judah sent you to ask what I, Yahweh, want. Go and tell him that this is what I, Yahweh, the God whom you Israelis worship, say about what you read: <verse eid="2CH 34:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CH 34:27"/>“Because you heeded <char style="add">what was written in the scroll</char>, and you humbled yourself when you heard what I said to warn <char style="add">about what would happen to</char> this city and the people who live here, and because you tore your robes and wept in my presence, I have heard you. <verse eid="2CH 34:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CH 34:28"/>So I will allow you to die and be buried peacefully. I will cause a great disaster to strike this place and the people who live here, but you will not <char style="add">be alive to</char> see it.” ’ ”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CH 34:28">So they reported her reply to the king. <verse eid="2CH 34:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CH 34:29"/>Then the king summoned all the elders of Jerusalem and <char style="add">other places in</char> Judea. <verse eid="2CH 34:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CH 34:30"/>They went up together to the temple with the leaders of Judah and many other people of Jerusalem and the priests and other descendants of Levi, from the least important to the most important ones. And while they listened, the king read to them everything that was in the scroll containing God’s laws that had been found in the temple.<verse eid="2CH 34:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CH 34:31"/>Then the king stood next to the pillar <char style="add">at the entrance to the temple, where kings stood when they announced something important</char>, and while Yahweh was listening, he repeated his promise to very sincerely and completely obey Yahweh and all his commands and regulations and decrees that were written on the scroll.<verse eid="2CH 34:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CH 34:32"/>Then the king said that everyone who lived in Jerusalem and from <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Benjamin should promise that they also would obey those laws. And they did that, agreeing that they would keep the agreement that God, whom their ancestors had worshiped, had made with them.<verse eid="2CH 34:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CH 34:33"/>Josiah <char style="add">instructed his workers to</char> remove all the detestable idols from everywhere in the land of the Israeli people, and he commanded that all the people from Israel who were there should worship <char style="add">only</char> Yahweh their God. And as long as Josiah was alive, the people did what was pleasing to Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>.<verse eid="2CH 34:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 34"/>
  <chapter number="35" style="c" sid="2CH 35"/>
  <para style="s1">Josiah led them in celebrating the Passover Festival</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 35:1"/>Josiah <char style="add">commanded that the people should</char> celebrate the Passover Festival to honor Yahweh in Jerusalem. So they slaughtered the lambs for the Passover <char style="add">Festival</char> at the end of March. <verse eid="2CH 35:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 35:2"/>Josiah assigned to the priests the tasks that they should perform at the temple and encouraged them to do their work well. <verse eid="2CH 35:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 35:3"/>The <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi were the ones who taught all the Israeli people; they had been dedicated to serve Yahweh. Josiah said to them, “Put the Sacred Chest in the temple that <char style="add">the workers of</char> David’s son <char style="add">King</char> Solomon of Israel built. But <char style="add">carry it on poles;</char> do not carry it on your shoulders. And do your your work well for Yahweh your God and for his Israeli people. <verse eid="2CH 35:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 35:4"/>Divide yourselves into clans, obeying the instructions that King David and his son Solomon wrote.<verse eid="2CH 35:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 35:5"/>Then stand in the temple, with one group of the descendants of Levi to help each clan of the people <char style="add">when they bring their offerings to the temple</char>. <verse eid="2CH 35:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 35:6"/>Slaughter the lambs for the Passover <char style="add">Festival</char>. Perform the rituals to cause yourselves to be acceptable to Yahweh for doing this work. Prepare the sacrifices, doing what Yahweh told Moses to tell you that you should do.”<verse eid="2CH 35:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 35:7"/>Josiah provided <char style="add">from his own flocks and herds</char> 30,000 sheep and goats for the Passover sacrifices.<verse eid="2CH 35:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 35:8"/>His officials also voluntarily contributed animals for the people and the priests and the <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi. Hilkiah, Zechariah, and Jehiel, the officials who were in charge of the temple, gave to the priests 2,600 lambs and 300 cattle to be sacrifices for the Passover. <verse eid="2CH 35:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 35:9"/>And Conaniah along with his <char style="add">younger</char> brothers Shemaiah and Nethanel, and Hashabiah, Jeiel, and Jozabad, the leaders of the <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi, provided 5,000 lambs and 500 cattle for the other descendants of Levi, to be sacrifices for the Passover.<verse eid="2CH 35:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 35:10"/>Everything <char style="add">for the Passover</char> was arranged: The priests and the other descendants of Levi stood in their places in their groups, like the king had commanded. <verse eid="2CH 35:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 35:11"/>Then they slaughtered the Passover lambs. The priests sprinkled the blood <char style="add">from the bowls</char> that were handed to them, while the <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi removed the skins from the animals. <verse eid="2CH 35:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 35:12"/>They set aside the animals to be completely burned on the altar, in order to give them to the various family groups to offer to Yahweh, obeying the instructions that were written in the laws God gave Moses. They did the same thing with the cattle. <verse eid="2CH 35:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 35:13"/>Obeying those regulations, they roasted the lambs for the Passover over the fire. And they boiled the <char style="add">meat of the</char> sacred offerings in pots and kettles and pans, and served the meat immediately to all the people <char style="add">who were there</char>. <verse eid="2CH 35:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 35:14"/>After that, they prepared meat for themselves and for the priests, because the priests were busy until nighttime, sacrificing the offerings to be completely burned and burning the fat parts of the offerings. So the <char style="add">other</char> descendants of Levi prepared meat for themselves and for the priests, who were descendants of Aaron, <char style="add">the first Supreme Priest</char>.<verse eid="2CH 35:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 35:15"/>The musicians, who were descendants of Asaph, stood in their places, as King David, Asaph, Heman, and Jeduthun the king’s prophet had commanded. The men who guarded the gates <char style="add">of the temple</char> did not need to leave their places, because their fellow descendants of Levi prepared food for them to eat.<verse eid="2CH 35:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 35:16"/>So on that day everything that needed to done for worshiping Yahweh was done. They celebrated the Passover <char style="add">Festival</char>, and they presented offerings to be completely burned on the altar, which was what Josiah had commanded. <verse eid="2CH 35:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 35:17"/>The Israelis who were there celebrated the Passover <char style="add">Festival</char> on that day, and for seven days they celebrated the Festival of <char style="add">Eating</char> Unleavened Bread. <verse eid="2CH 35:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 35:18"/>The Passover <char style="add">Festival</char> had not been celebrated like that in Israel since the time that the prophet Samuel lived. None of the other kings of Israel had ever celebrated the Passover like Josiah did, along with the priests, the other descendants of Levi, and all <char style="add">the other people of</char> Judah and Israel who were there with the people who lived in Jerusalem. <verse eid="2CH 35:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 35:19"/>They celebrated this Passover Festival when Josiah had been ruling for almost 18 years.<verse eid="2CH 35:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The end of Josiah’s life</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 35:20"/>After Josiah had done all those things to <char style="add">restore the worship at</char> the temple, King Neco of Egypt went <char style="add">with his army</char> to attack Carchemish <char style="add">city</char> alongside the Euphrates <char style="add">River</char>, and Josiah marched <char style="add">with his army</char> to fight against them. <verse eid="2CH 35:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 35:21"/>Neco sent some messengers to Josiah, to tell him, “You are the king of Judah, and there is certainly no quarrel between you and me. My army is not attacking you people; we are attacking another army, <char style="add">the army of Babylonia</char>. God has told me to hurry. So stop opposing God, who is for me. If you do not stop, God will get rid of you.”<verse eid="2CH 35:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 35:22"/>But Josiah would not pay attention to him. Instead, he disguised himself in order to be able to attack <char style="add">the army of Egypt without anyone recognizing him</char>. He did not pay any attention to what God had told Neco to say. Instead, he <char style="add">and his army</char> went to fight Neco’s army at the plain of Megiddo.<verse eid="2CH 35:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 35:23"/>Some Egyptian archers shot King Josiah. He told his officers, “Take me away from here because I am badly wounded.” <verse eid="2CH 35:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CH 35:24"/>So they took him out of his chariot and put him in another chariot that he had brought with him, and they took him to Jerusalem, where he died. He was buried in the tombs where his ancestors <char style="add">had been buried</char>, and all <char style="add">the people of</char> Jerusalem and <char style="add">other places in</char> Judah mourned for him.<verse eid="2CH 35:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CH 35:25"/>
    <char style="add">The prophet</char> Jeremiah composed a song to mourn for Josiah, and all the men and women singers in Israel still mourn for Josiah by singing that song. That became a custom in Israel; the words of that song are written in a scroll of funeral songs.<verse eid="2CH 35:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26-27" style="v" sid="2CH 35:26-27"/>A record of the other things that happened while Josiah ruled, from the time he started to rule until he died, including how he faithfully honored God by obeying everything that was written in the laws of Yahweh, is in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel and Judah’.<verse eid="2CH 35:26-27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 35"/>
  <chapter number="36" style="c" sid="2CH 36"/>
  <para style="s1">King Jehoahaz of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CH 36:1"/>Then the people of Judah chose Josiah’s son Jehoahaz and appointed him as the king in Jerusalem.<verse eid="2CH 36:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CH 36:2"/>Jehoahaz was 23 years old when he became the king, but he ruled from Jerusalem for <char style="add">only</char> three months. <verse eid="2CH 36:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CH 36:3"/>King Neco of Egypt <char style="add">captured him and</char> prevented him from ruling any longer. He also forced the people of Judah to pay him a tax of almost four tons of silver and about 75 pounds of gold. <verse eid="2CH 36:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CH 36:4"/>The king of Egypt appointed Jehoahaz’s <char style="add">younger</char> brother Eliakim to be the king of Judah. He changed Eliakim’s name to Jehoiakim. After Neco captured Jehoahaz, he took him to Egypt.<verse eid="2CH 36:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Jehoiakim of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CH 36:5"/>Jehoiakim was 25 years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>, and he ruled from Jerusalem for 11 years. He did things that Yahweh his God considers to be evil. <verse eid="2CH 36:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CH 36:6"/>Then the army of King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon attacked Jehoiakim’s army. They <char style="add">captured Jehoiakim and</char> bound him with bronze chains and took him to Babylon. <verse eid="2CH 36:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CH 36:7"/>Nebuchadnezzar’s soldiers also took valuable things from the temple; they took them to Babylon and put them in king <char style="add">Nebuchadnezzar’s</char> palace there.<verse eid="2CH 36:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CH 36:8"/>A record of the other things that happened while Jehoiakim was ruling, the detestable things that he did, including the evil things that people said that he did, is written in the scroll called ‘The History of the Kings of Israel and Judah’. After <char style="add">he was taken to Babylon</char>, his son Jehoiachin became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>.<verse eid="2CH 36:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Jehoiachin of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CH 36:9"/>Jehoiachin was 18 years old when he became the king <char style="add">of Judah</char>, and he ruled from Jerusalem for <char style="add">only</char> three months and ten days. He did things that Yahweh considers to be evil. <verse eid="2CH 36:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CH 36:10"/>During the spring of the next year, King Nebuchadnezzar sent <char style="add">soldiers</char> to bring him to Babylon. They also took to Babylon many valuable things from the temple of Yahweh. Then Nebuchadnezzar appointed Jehoiachin’s uncle, Zedekiah, to be the king of Judah.<verse eid="2CH 36:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Zedekiah of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CH 36:11"/>Zedekiah was 21 years old when he became the king, and he ruled in Jerusalem for 11 years. <verse eid="2CH 36:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CH 36:12"/>He did many things that Yahweh his God considered to be evil. And he did not humble himself when the prophet Jeremiah gave him a message from Yahweh <char style="add">to warn him</char>. <verse eid="2CH 36:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CH 36:13"/>He would not return to Yahweh, the God that the people of Israel <char style="add">said that they worshiped</char>. Zedekiah also rebelled against King Nebuchadnezzar, who had forced him to solemnly promise using God’s name <char style="add">to be loyal to him</char>. Zedekiah became very stubborn. <verse eid="2CH 36:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CH 36:14"/>Furthermore, all the leaders of the priests and also the people <char style="add">of Judah</char> became more wicked again, doing all the detestable things that the people of the other nations did, and causing the temple in Jerusalem that Yahweh had caused to be holy to become <char style="add">an</char> unacceptable <char style="add">place to worship him</char>.<verse eid="2CH 36:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jerusalem was ruined</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CH 36:15"/>Yahweh, the God whom the ancestors <char style="add">of the people of Judah belonged to/worshiped</char>, gave messages to his prophets many times, and the prophets told those messages to the people of Judah. Yahweh did that because he pitied his people and did not want his temple to be destroyed. <verse eid="2CH 36:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CH 36:16"/>But the people continually made fun of God’s messengers. They despised God’s messages. They ridiculed his prophets, until finally God became extremely angry with his people, with the result that nothing could stop him <char style="add">from destroying Judah</char>. <verse eid="2CH 36:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CH 36:17"/>He incited the king of Babylonia to attack <char style="add">Judah with his army</char>. They killed the young men with their swords, even in the temple. They did not spare/pity anyone, young men or young women or old people. God enabled the army of Nebuchadnezzar to kill all of them. <verse eid="2CH 36:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CH 36:18"/>His soldiers took to Babylon all the things that were used in God’s temple—big things and little things, all the valuable things, and the valuable things that belonged to the king and his officials. <verse eid="2CH 36:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CH 36:19"/>They burned the temple, and they broke down the wall surrounding Jerusalem. They burned all the palaces <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char> and destroyed all the remaining valuable things there.<verse eid="2CH 36:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CH 36:20"/>Nebuchadnezzar’s soldiers took to Babylon the remaining people who had not been killed with their swords. Then those people became the king’s slaves and his son’s slaves, until the <char style="add">army of the</char> king of Persia conquered <char style="add">the army of Babylonia</char>. <verse eid="2CH 36:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CH 36:21"/><char style="add">Moses had said that every seventh year the people must not plant their fields; they must allow the soil to rest. But the people had not done that. So after the army of Babylonia destroyed Judah,</char> the soil was allowed to rest. That continued for 70 years, fulfilling what Yahweh told Jeremiah and what Jeremiah had predicted/prophesied would happen.<verse eid="2CH 36:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CH 36:22"/>During the first year that Cyrus was the king of Persia, in order that what Yahweh told Jeremiah would happen would occur, Yahweh motivated Cyrus to write this and proclaim it throughout his kingdom:<verse eid="2CH 36:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CH 36:23"/>“I, Cyrus, the king of Persia, declare that Yahweh, the God <char style="add">who rules</char> in heaven, has enabled me to become the ruler of all the kingdoms of this world. And he wants me to <char style="add">command that my workers</char> build a temple {a temple be built} for him in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Any of his people living among you people of Persia are allowed to go to Jerusalem. And I will pray that Yahweh will be with them.”<verse eid="2CH 36:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CH 36"/>
</usx>
