<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2CO" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">2 CORINTHIANS</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Corinthians</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Co</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book is one of the letters that the Apostle Paul wrote to the Christians at Corinth. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 Corinthians</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2CO 1"/>
  <para style="s1">2 Corinthians 1:1-2</para>
  <para style="s1">Paul and Timothy greet the Christians who are in Corinth.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 1:1"/>
    <char style="add">I</char>, Paul, who <char style="add">write this letter to you</char>, became an apostle of Christ Jesus because God chose me for that. <char style="add">Timothy, our</char> fellow believer, <char style="add">is with me. I am sending this letter</char> to you who are God’s people in the congregations in Corinth <char style="add">city. I want</char> the believers who live in <char style="add">other places</char> in Achaia <char style="add">province to also read this letter</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 1:2"/><char style="add">We(exc) desire</char> that you will <char style="add">experience</char> God our Father and our Lord Jesus Christ <char style="add">acting</char> kindly toward you and causing you to have <char style="add">inner</char> peace.<verse eid="2CO 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We thank God that he encourages us in all our troubles so that we are able to encourage you when you suffer. We suffered so much in Asia province that we were sure that we were going to die, but we learned to trust in God. He saved us from death and he will continue to save us from death.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 1:3-11">2 Corinthians 1:3-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 1:3"/>
    <char style="add">We should</char> praise God, who is the father of our <char style="add">(inc)</char> Lord Jesus Christ. He always pities us and helps us <char style="add">because he is like</char> [MET] a father to us <char style="add">and we are like his children</char>. He always encourages us <char style="add">(inc)</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 1:4"/>He has encouraged us <char style="add">(exc)</char> whenever we suffered hardships. As a result, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> are able to encourage others whenever they suffer hardships, just as/just like God has encouraged us <char style="add">(exc)</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 1:5"/>It is true that just like Christ suffered, we <char style="add">who serve him</char> also continually suffer <char style="add">because we belong to him</char>. But also, because we <char style="add">belong to</char> Christ, God greatly strengthens us ◄just as/just like► <char style="add">God strengthened him</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 1:6"/>So, whenever we <char style="add">(exc)</char> experience sufferings, we <char style="add">learn how to encourage</char> you <char style="add">when you experience sufferings. As a result, you will become more and more the kind of people God</char> wants you to be. Whenever <char style="add">God</char> strengthens us <char style="add">(exc) when we are suffering, he</char> does that in order that you <char style="add">may see how he makes us strong when we are suffering. Then, as God</char> encourages <char style="add">you in that way</char>, you will learn to continue patiently <char style="add">trusting him</char> when you suffer as we do. <verse eid="2CO 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 1:7"/>As a result, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> strongly expect that because you suffer just as/just like we do, <char style="add">God</char> will encourage you ◄just as/just like► <char style="add">he</char> encourages us.<verse eid="2CO 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 1:8"/>
    <char style="add">Our</char> fellow believers, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> want you to know [LIT] about the trouble that we suffered in Asia <char style="add">province</char>. That trouble was so very great that it was much more than we were able to endure. As a result, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> thought that we would certainly die. <verse eid="2CO 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 1:9"/>Indeed, we felt <char style="add">like a person feels when he has heard a judge say</char>, “I condemn you to die/be executed [MET].” But <char style="add">God allowed us to think that we were going to die</char> so that we would not ◄rely on/trust in► our own <char style="add">strength. He wanted us</char> instead <char style="add">to rely</char> only on his <char style="add">strength, because he</char> is the one who <char style="add">has power even to make</char> those who have died live <char style="add">again</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 1:10"/>And <char style="add">even though</char> we <char style="add">(exc)</char> were <char style="add">in terrible danger and were</char> about to die, God rescued us. And he will continue to rescue us <char style="add">whenever we are in trouble</char>. We confidently expect that he will continue to rescue us <char style="add">time after time</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 1:11"/><char style="add">And we are also relying on</char> you to help us by praying for us <char style="add">(exc)</char>. <char style="add">If many people pray for us</char>, many people will also thank <char style="add">God</char> when <char style="add">he</char> kindly answers those many prayers <char style="add">and delivers us from danger</char>.<verse eid="2CO 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">You can trust what I tell you. I did not visit you, because I wanted to give you the opportunity to obey the instructions that I wrote to you. Now that you have punished enough the man who caused those problems, I urge you to forgive him and to encourage him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 1:12-2:11">2 Corinthians 1:12—2:11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 1:12"/>I am happy <char style="add">to say</char> that I have behaved toward all people [MTY] in an honest and sincere way. My conscience assures me <char style="add">that this is true</char>. Especially, I have behaved toward you <char style="add">honestly and sincerely because that is what</char> God wants us to do. As I have done that, <char style="add">my thoughts</char> have not been the thoughts that unbelieving people [MTY] <char style="add">think are</char> wise. Instead, <char style="add">I have behaved toward people only as God wants me to, depending on</char> God to help me in ways that I do not deserve. <verse eid="2CO 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 1:13"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because <char style="add">in all my letters to you</char> I have always written [LIT] clearly in a way that you can easily and completely understand <char style="add">when you</char> read them. <verse eid="2CO 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 1:14"/><char style="add">Previously some of</char> you, but not all of you, have completely understood <char style="add">that I am always honest and sincere with you</char>. But I confidently expect that <char style="add">soon</char> you will all be fully convinced <char style="add">about that</char>. Then when the Lord Jesus [MTY] <char style="add">returns, you will all be able to say that</char> you are pleased with me, just like I will <char style="add">be able to say that</char> I am pleased with you.<verse eid="2CO 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15-16" style="v" sid="2CO 1:15-16"/>It was because I felt sure <char style="add">that all of you were pleased with me</char> that I was planning to visit you on my way from <char style="add">here</char> to Macedonia <char style="add">province</char>. I also planned to visit you again on my way back from there, so that I could <char style="add">spend time with you</char> twice, and be able to help you more, and I was hoping that you would <char style="add">give me things that I needed</char> [EUP] for my journey to Judea <char style="add">province</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:15-16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 1:17"/>So then, even though I <char style="add">changed my mind later and did not do what</char> I <char style="add">first</char> planned to do, <char style="add">it was not because I did not have an important reason for changing my plans</char>. Surely you do not <char style="add">really think</char> that I decide what I am going to do like people who do not know God do! [RHQ] I am <char style="add">not like that</char>. I am not <char style="add">a person who</char> says <char style="add">to people</char>, “Yes, <char style="add">certainly I will do that</char>,” and then <char style="add">for no good reason changes his mind and says</char>, “No, <char style="add">I will not do it</char>.” <verse eid="2CO 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 1:18"/>Just as surely as God always does what he says <char style="add">he will do, it is true that I have never said</char>, “Yes, <char style="add">I will do this</char>” when I <char style="add">really meant</char> “No.” <verse eid="2CO 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 1:19"/><char style="add">I follow the example of</char> God’s Son, Jesus Christ. When I, along with Silas and Timothy, taught you <char style="add">about Christ</char>, we told you that he was not <char style="add">someone who said that he</char> would do <char style="add">something</char> and <char style="add">then</char> did not <char style="add">do it</char>. Jesus Christ never <char style="add">said to anyone</char>, “Yes, <char style="add">I will do what you desire</char>,” and <char style="add">then did</char> not <char style="add">do it</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 1:20"/><char style="add">We(inc) know that is true</char>, because everything that God promised to do <char style="add">for his people</char>, he has done completely by <char style="add">sending</char> Christ <char style="add">to save us</char>. That is why we say, “Yes, it is true! <char style="add">God has done everything that he promised to do</char>!” And we praise him for that! <verse eid="2CO 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 1:21"/>Now it is only God himself who causes us <char style="add">(exc)</char>, as well as you, to keep on <char style="add">believing</char> strongly in Christ. God is the one who chose us <char style="add">(inc) to belong to him and to have a close relationship</char> with Christ. <verse eid="2CO 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CO 1:22"/>He also sent his Holy Spirit into our <char style="add">(inc)</char> lives to mark us as belonging to himself [MET]. Also, since he has sent his Spirit to live in us <char style="add">(inc)</char>, <char style="add">he wants us to know by this that</char> he guarantees [MET] <char style="add">to give us every other</char> ◄<char style="add">blessing/good thing</char>► <char style="add">that he has promised</char>.<verse eid="2CO 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CO 1:23"/>So now <char style="add">I will tell you why I changed my mind and did not visit you as I intended to do</char>: God himself knows <char style="add">that what I am telling you is true</char>. The reason that I did not return to Corinth was so that I might not have to <char style="add">speak to you severely about the wrong that you had done</char>. <verse eid="2CO 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CO 1:24"/>It is not that Silas, Timothy and I want to boss you <char style="add">and tell you that you must</char> believe only what we say. <char style="add">Not at all</char>! On the contrary, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> are working as partners <char style="add">with you</char> in order to make you happy. <char style="add">We do not try to force you to believe everything that we believe, because we are sure that you are continuing to</char> trust <char style="add">the Lord Jesus Christ</char> and that you are remaining firmly committed to him.<verse eid="2CO 1:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2CO 2"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 2:1"/>Anyway, I definitely decided that I would not come to visit you again <char style="add">now. If I had come, I would have spoken severely to you again, and</char> I would have made you unhappy as I did the last time <char style="add">I visited you</char>. <verse eid="2CO 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 2:2"/><char style="add">And</char> if I make you unhappy, I will have made unhappy <char style="add">the only people who can cheer me up</char>, so ◄there will be none of you to cheer me up!/who would cheer me up?► [RHQ] <verse eid="2CO 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 2:3"/>So, <char style="add">instead of going to visit you at that time</char>, I wrote a letter <char style="add">and sent it to you</char>. I wrote it the way I did so that <char style="add">you would know what you should do. Then</char> when I come to visit you, you will not make me unhappy when you should be causing me to rejoice. I was quite sure that all of you <char style="add">would do what I told you to do in that letter, and because of that</char> I would be happy and you would be happy, too. <verse eid="2CO 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 2:4"/>I wrote to you <char style="add">the way I did</char> because I felt very troubled and distressed about you. I was even crying very much as I wrote. <char style="add">My purpose in writing was</char> not in order to make you feel bad, but, instead, in order that you might know how deeply/much I love you.<verse eid="2CO 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 2:5"/>
    <char style="add">Now I want to write about the man who</char> caused all this anguish. <char style="add">What he did was very wrong, but</char> I know that it has caused you much more sorrow than it has caused me, because <char style="add">what he did</char> has <char style="add">affected</char> all of you <char style="add">to some extent. I say</char>, “to some extent,” <char style="add">because I do not want to say that he has</char> done more harm <char style="add">than he really has done</char>. <verse eid="2CO 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 2:6"/><char style="add">Since he has now stopped sinning in that way</char>, the punishment that nearly all of you <char style="add">decided was right for him</char> has continued long enough. <verse eid="2CO 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 2:7"/>So now, instead <char style="add">of punishing him any longer</char>, you need to forgive him and deal kindly with him. <char style="add">If you do not forgive him</char>, he may become so sad that he will begin to <char style="add">think that you will never forgive him</char> (OR, will stop <char style="add">believing in Christ</char>).<verse eid="2CO 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 2:8"/>For those reasons, I beg you to <char style="add">forgive him and accept him into your group again, and by doing that</char> assure him that you truly love him. <verse eid="2CO 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 2:9"/><char style="add">I feel sure that you will do as I ask</char>, because when I wrote <char style="add">severely</char> to you <char style="add">before</char>, I did it to test you by finding out whether or not you really would do everything <char style="add">that I, as your apostle, asked you to do</char>. <verse eid="2CO 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 2:10"/>So <char style="add">since you obeyed what I told you before, I feel sure that now you will obey what I am writing in this letter</char> and forgive the man, as I have done, because I indeed have forgiven him for the wrong thing that he did. Anything he needed me to forgive him for, I have forgiven, and Christ knows <char style="add">that I have forgiven him sincerely. I have done that mainly</char> to help you <char style="add">so that you and I will again have fellowship with each other, and that you will accept him into your group again</char>. <verse eid="2CO 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 2:11"/><char style="add">I want you to forgive him</char> so that Satan will not be able to take advantage of <char style="add">the problems among</char> us <char style="add">and make the situation worse</char>. We know very well [LIT] that Satan is always planning to <char style="add">cause problems among us</char>.<verse eid="2CO 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I did not find Titus in Troas, so I went on to Macedonia province. Everywhere we go, God causes people to know Christ through our teaching. We do not teach in order to get money; we teach with sincere motives.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 2:12-17">2 Corinthians 2:12-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 2:12"/>
    <char style="add">I will continue by telling you what I did after I wrote to you from Ephesus city</char>. I went to Troas <char style="add">city</char> in order to <char style="add">tell people</char> the message <char style="add">about</char> Christ. <char style="add">When I arrived there</char>, I found <char style="add">many people</char> who had been prepared by the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> [MET] <char style="add">to listen to what I told them about him</char>. <verse eid="2CO 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 2:13"/>But because my fellow believer Titus had not <char style="add">arrived with a report from you</char>, I still felt very anxious and concerned <char style="add">about you</char>. So, <char style="add">after spending only a short time at Troas</char>, I said goodbye to <char style="add">the believers who were there</char> and came <char style="add">here</char> to Macedonia <char style="add">province to find Titus</char>. <verse eid="2CO 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 2:14"/>However, <char style="add">before I tell you any more about that</char>, I <char style="add">want to</char> thank God <char style="add">for what he is doing. As a great leader of fighting men causes all his prisoners to take part in his victory parade</char> [MET], God leads us <char style="add">who are his workers</char> to always be victorious <char style="add">over Satan because of our(exc) close relationship with Christ. God causes people to come to</char> know Jesus Christ as a result of our <char style="add">(exc) teaching his message. That message is like</char> [MET] the smell of perfume. <verse eid="2CO 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 2:15"/><char style="add">When we(exc) tell God’s message</char> about Christ, it <char style="add">spreads out among people</char> like the smell of perfume. <char style="add">Those who believe the message that we tell them</char> are saved {<char style="add">Jesus Christ</char> saves them} <char style="add">from the guilt of their sin. But those who reject that message</char> will be separated from God <char style="add">forever</char>. <verse eid="2CO 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 2:16"/>To those who <char style="add">are on the way to hell, our message is like</char> [MET] a foul smell <char style="add">because it is about dying</char> and being separated from God forever. But, to those <char style="add">on the way to heaven, the message that we teach is like</char> a pure fragrant smell, <char style="add">because we tell them</char> that they will live <char style="add">forever with God. As we think about that, we think</char> ◄no one is able <char style="add">to do</char> such important work <char style="add">for God!</char>/how can anyone be able <char style="add">to do</char> such important work <char style="add">for God</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="2CO 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 2:17"/><char style="add">But perhaps God considers us(exc) able</char>, because we do not work/act like so many <char style="add">others whom you know</char>. They teach God’s message in a way that <char style="add">they think people will like, and they think that</char> people will pay them for teaching that way. We <char style="add">(exc) certainly do not do that</char>. On the contrary, <char style="add">as servants of</char> Christ, and knowing that God is watching us <char style="add">(exc)</char>, we teach sincerely <char style="add">the message that</char> God sent us to proclaim.<verse eid="2CO 2:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2CO 3"/>
  <para style="s1">The way you now live proves that we teach the truth about Jesus Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 3:1-6">2 Corinthians 3:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 3:1"/>
    <char style="add">As I write these things about myself</char>, I am [RHQ] not <char style="add">doing it</char> to boast about how good I am, <char style="add">as some of you say I do</char>. Some people always carry letters with them that tell how well they work, <char style="add">that other people</char> have <char style="add">written</char>. But I do not [RHQ] need <char style="add">to bring</char> letters like that <char style="add">when I come to you</char>. Nor do I need to ask you <char style="add">to write</char> letters like that <char style="add">for me when I go to other congregations</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 3:2"/>You yourselves are [MET] <char style="add">like a</char> letter that recommends my work <char style="add">for God to everyone</char>. People see <char style="add">how Christ changed</char> your <char style="add">lives when you believed the message that I taught you</char>. Everyone <char style="add">who knows you</char> can see <char style="add">the result of my work for God</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 3:3"/>You are [MET] <char style="add">like</char> a letter that Christ himself <char style="add">has written</char> that says good things about <char style="add">my work for God in your lives</char>. You show <char style="add">people by the way you now conduct your lives that God has changed your lives</char> as a result of my work <char style="add">among you. People did</char> not <char style="add">find out about you by</char> reading <char style="add">a letter that was written to them on paper</char> with <char style="add">pen and</char> ink. Instead, <char style="add">they saw how</char> the Spirit of the all-powerful God <char style="add">has changed your lives</char>. Nor <char style="add">did people find out about you by reading</char> a letter that was carved on stone slabs <char style="add">like the stone slabs that God gave to Moses</char>. Instead, <char style="add">it was the change that God’s Spirit made in</char> your lives [MET] <char style="add">that they saw</char>.<verse eid="2CO 3:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 3:4"/>I <char style="add">can very</char> confidently <char style="add">write these things about the work that Silas, Timothy, and I did among you, because God knows that what I write is true. We(exc) are true workers</char> for God <char style="add">because of what</char> Christ <char style="add">has done for us</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 3:5"/>We <char style="add">(exc)</char>, by ourselves, do not have the ability <char style="add">to do this work</char>. None of us <char style="add">apostles</char> can say, “<char style="add">I have changed the lives of these people</char>.” God is the one <char style="add">who has given us this ability</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 3:6"/>He is the one who enables us <char style="add">(exc)</char> to be his messengers. <char style="add">He has enabled us to tell people the message</char> about the new agreement <char style="add">that he is making with them</char>. This is not a <char style="add">message about obeying all the</char> written laws <char style="add">of his old agreement that he made with the Jewish people</char>. Instead, <char style="add">it is a message about God giving us his</char> Spirit. <char style="add">Previously, God condemned people to be</char> separated from him forever <char style="add">if they did not obey his laws</char>. But by <char style="add">God’s new agreement</char> his Spirit enables people to live <char style="add">eternally</char>.<verse eid="2CO 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Our work of teaching people about God’s New Agreement is much greater than the work of teaching people about his Old Agreement.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 3:7-11">2 Corinthians 3:7-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 3:7"/>
    <char style="add">Moses</char> taught <char style="add">the people that if they did not obey God’s laws completely they would be</char> separated from God forever. <char style="add">God </char> wrote <char style="add">his laws</char> on stone <char style="add">slabs. Then he gave them to Moses to teach them to the people. Although God’s laws condemned the people </char> to die, <char style="add">when Moses brought those laws down from Sinai Mountain, God caused Moses’ face to shine</char> Moses’ face to shine radiantly <char style="add">to show the people that these laws were God’s laws. It shone</char>. so brightly that the people of Israel could not keep looking at Moses’ face. <char style="add">They had to look away</char>. But the brightness was slowly fading away. <verse eid="2CO 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 3:8"/><char style="add">So</char>, <char style="add">since God showed in such a wonderful way that those laws that condemned the people to die were from him</char>, surely when we <char style="add">(exc)</char> teach <char style="add">people about how God’s</char> Spirit will <char style="add">change their lives</char>, <char style="add">God will show</char> in an even more wonderful way <char style="add">that</char> it is <char style="add">his message.</char> [RHQ] <verse eid="2CO 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 3:9"/>The message <char style="add">that Moses taught them was wonderful, but when people heard</char> that message, <char style="add">they realized that they were sinners and that God</char> would punish them. But God’s message that we <char style="add">(exc) teach is a</char> much more wonderful message. We teach people that God will ◄erase the record of/declare people no longer guilty for► <char style="add">the sinful things that they have done</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 3:10"/><char style="add">The truth is that, although the work of teaching the people to obey God’s laws</char> was once important, it is not as important now, because <char style="add">the work of teaching people that God will forgive them and</char> enable them to live to please him is far more important. <verse eid="2CO 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 3:11"/>Furthermore, <char style="add">the message that Moses taught was not a lasting message, just like</char> the brightness on his face was not lasting and soon faded away. But <char style="add">when God gives his Spirit to people</char>, the wonderful work that <char style="add">God’s Spirit does in their lives</char> is much greater <char style="add">because</char> it lasts forever.<verse eid="2CO 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We teach a message that transforms people’s lives. So we teach it with great confidence.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 3:12-18">2 Corinthians 3:12-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 3:12"/>We <char style="add">(exc)</char> know that the message that we teach is a <char style="add">much more wonderful message than the message that Moses taught</char>. So we <char style="add">can preach</char> boldly. <verse eid="2CO 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 3:13"/>We do not <char style="add">need to put a veil over our faces when we teach people</char>, as Moses did. Moses put a veil over his face so that the Israelites would not see that the radiance <char style="add">on his face</char> soon faded away. <char style="add">Similarly, the glory of the old agreement has also faded away</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 3:14"/>But the Israelis stubbornly refused to <char style="add">understand that the old agreement would end</char>. Even now, when they read the old agreement, <char style="add">they still do not realize that it has ended. It is as if</char> [MET] that same veil <char style="add">that Moses put on his face</char> is now over their <char style="add">minds, keeping them from understanding God’s true message</char>. They will <char style="add">understand that message</char> only when <char style="add">they come to trust</char> in Christ. Then <char style="add">it will be as though God</char> has removed the veil. <verse eid="2CO 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 3:15"/><char style="add">Throughout all these years</char>, even until now, when <char style="add">the Israelis</char> read what Moses <char style="add">write, it is as though</char> a veil is covering their minds. <verse eid="2CO 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 3:16"/>But when any of them believes in the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char>, <char style="add">God</char> removes that veil from them. <verse eid="2CO 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 3:17"/><char style="add">It is by the power of his</char> Spirit that the Lord <char style="add">works in our lives</char>, and the Lord’s Spirit has set us free <char style="add">from trying to obey all the rules and rituals that God gave Moses</char>. <verse eid="2CO 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 3:18"/><char style="add">It is as though God</char> has removed the veil from our faces [MET]. We realize how awesome Jesus is. As we realize that, we are continually being changed {<char style="add">the Holy Spirit is</char> continually changing us} to become more and more like Jesus, <char style="add">so that people can see</char>, more and more, how awesome <char style="add">Jesus is</char>. It is the Spirit of the Lord who does <char style="add">this</char>.<verse eid="2CO 3:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2CO 4"/>
  <para style="s1">We are servants of Jesus. It is Jesus who has shown us how great God is.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 4:1-6">2 Corinthians 4:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 4:1"/>So, because God has acted so kindly <char style="add">toward me</char>, enabling <char style="add">me to teach</char> this great <char style="add">message to people</char>, I never get <char style="add">so</char> discouraged <char style="add">that I stop teaching it</char>. <verse eid="2CO 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 4:2"/>And I have determined that we <char style="add">(exc)</char> will be honest [LIT] in everything that we do. We will not <char style="add">do anything that would cause</char> us to be ashamed <char style="add">if people found out about it</char>. We never try to deceive <char style="add">you with clever arguments, as some other people do</char>. We never <char style="add">try to deceive you</char> by changing God’s message, <char style="add">as those same people do</char>. Instead, we always teach <char style="add">people only</char> the truth <char style="add">about Christ</char>, and we teach it clearly. Knowing that God is watching what we do, we <char style="add">teach his message in an honest way, with the result that</char> no one can <char style="add">accuse</char> us <char style="add">(exc) of being deceitful</char>. <verse eid="2CO 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 4:3"/>And if, <char style="add">as some of you say, some people are</char> not able to understand the message <char style="add">that we teach about Christ, it is not because we do not teach it clearly</char>. It is because those people <char style="add">do not want to believe it</char>. They are going to perish eternally. <verse eid="2CO 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 4:4"/><char style="add">Satan, who is</char> the one <char style="add">who rules</char> this world, controls the thoughts of those unbelievers. He prevents them from understanding the message about how wonderful Christ is. <char style="add">They are not able to understand that</char> Jesus is like God <char style="add">in every way</char>. <verse eid="2CO 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 4:5"/>That is why, <char style="add">when we(exc) teach people</char>, we do not boast about ourselves, <char style="add">as some people say that we do</char>. Instead, <char style="add">we teach you</char> that Jesus Christ is our Lord. We ourselves are <char style="add">only</char> your servants. <char style="add">We want to honor and obey</char> Jesus. <verse eid="2CO 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 4:6"/>When God <char style="add">created the world</char>, he commanded the light to shine <char style="add">where there was nothing but</char> darkness. He is the one who has <char style="add">made his message about Jesus to be like</char> [MET] a light shining into our <char style="add">(inc)</char> minds. <char style="add">God</char> has done that <char style="add">for all of us who believe in Jesus. He has done that so that we will understand that when people saw</char> Christ, they saw how awesome God himself was.<verse eid="2CO 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">As Jesus’ servants we suffer, but through our suffering many people will receive eternal life and thank and praise God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 4:7-15">2 Corinthians 4:7-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 4:7"/>
    <char style="add">This work that God has given to</char> us <char style="add">(exc)</char> is [MET] <char style="add">like</char> a very valuable treasure. But we who have that treasure <char style="add">are as weak as fragile</char> [MET] clay pots. <char style="add">God has planned it like that</char> in order that <char style="add">people</char> will know that the power <char style="add">that changes lives</char> is God’s power, and not any power of our own. <verse eid="2CO 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 4:8"/>We are continually oppressed {<char style="add">People</char> continually oppress us} in many ways, but <char style="add">we have</char> not been prevented {<char style="add">God has</char> not <char style="add">allowed them to</char> prevent us} <char style="add">from teaching the message about Jesus Christ</char>. We often do not know what to do <char style="add">in difficult situations</char>, but we never say, “God has abandoned us.” <verse eid="2CO 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 4:9"/><char style="add">We are frequently</char> persecuted {<char style="add">People frequently</char> cause us to suffer}, but <char style="add">God</char> never abandons us. <char style="add">Sometimes we are</char> badly wounded {<char style="add">people</char> badly wound us}, but <char style="add">God does</char> not <char style="add">allow</char> us <char style="add">to</char> be killed {<char style="add">them to</char> kill us}. <verse eid="2CO 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 4:10"/><char style="add">Wherever we(exc) go</char>, we continually <char style="add">realize that because people killed</char> Jesus, <char style="add">people may</char> kill us <char style="add">for teaching his message. But we are willing to go on living this way</char> in order that <char style="add">people</char> will know that Jesus is alive and <char style="add">that he is directing</char> us [SYN]. <verse eid="2CO 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 4:11"/><char style="add">So, although</char> we are <char style="add">still</char> alive, we always realize that we may be killed {that <char style="add">people some day</char> may kill us} because <char style="add">we teach about</char> Jesus. <char style="add">God allows us to suffer</char> in order that <char style="add">people</char> will see that Jesus is alive and that he is <char style="add">strengthening</char> our bodies that are some day going to die. <verse eid="2CO 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 4:12"/>So <char style="add">I conclude that although</char> we <char style="add">apostles</char> are constantly <char style="add">suffering and may soon</char> die, <char style="add">the result of that is that all of</char> you <char style="add">have now received eternal</char> life.<verse eid="2CO 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 4:13"/>We are not discouraged. We are like <char style="add">the person who</char> wrote <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>, “<char style="add">God</char>, I trusted <char style="add">in you</char> and so I continue speaking <char style="add">your message</char>.” We <char style="add">(exc)</char> also trust <char style="add">in God</char>, so we continue speaking <char style="add">his message</char>. <verse eid="2CO 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 4:14"/><char style="add">We do this</char> because we <char style="add">(exc)</char> know that <char style="add">although people might kill us, God</char>, who caused the Lord Jesus to live again after he died, will also cause us <char style="add">(exc)</char> to live again <char style="add">after we die. God will do this because we belong to</char> Jesus. <char style="add">And then God</char> will bring us <char style="add">(exc)</char>, together with you, to be with him. <verse eid="2CO 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 4:15"/><char style="add">So I say that</char> all these things <char style="add">that we(exc) suffer</char> happen in order to help you. <char style="add">We have suffered all this</char> in order that more and more people, <char style="add">as a result of hearing that God will</char> kindly/freely <char style="add">forgive their sins</char>, will thank <char style="add">him and praise him. Then</char> they will greatly honor him <char style="add">and worship him</char>.<verse eid="2CO 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">As our bodies get weaker, God continually makes our inner lives stronger. He will reward us for all that we have suffered.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 4:16-18">2 Corinthians 4:16-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 4:16"/>So, <char style="add">because we know that as a result of our suffering many people will honor God</char>, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> never get so discouraged <char style="add">that we stop teaching his message</char>. Although our bodies are getting weaker, <char style="add">God</char> encourages us every day and strengthens us spiritually. <verse eid="2CO 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 4:17"/><char style="add">I know that</char> all these troubles that <char style="add">happen to us in this life are</char> not significant and will not last forever. <char style="add">When we think of</char> the glorious things <char style="add">that God is preparing</char> for us <char style="add">to enjoy</char> forever <char style="add">in heaven</char>, all <char style="add">our suffering now</char> is not important. <verse eid="2CO 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 4:18"/>That is why we say, “We will not continue thinking about <char style="add">all the suffering that we</char> are experiencing now. Even though <char style="add">we</char> cannot see <char style="add">all the things that God has prepared for us in heaven</char>, those are what we should be thinking about.” <char style="add">That is how we should think</char>, because <char style="add">all these troubles</char> that <char style="add">we(exc)</char> have <char style="add">now</char> will last only a short time. But what <char style="add">we will have in heaven</char>, what <char style="add">we</char> cannot see <char style="add">now</char>, will last forever.<verse eid="2CO 4:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="2CO 5"/>
  <para style="s1">God will give all of us new heavenly bodies, and he will reward us according to what we did while we were living in our earthly bodies.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 5:1-10">2 Corinthians 5:1-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 5:1"/>We know that <char style="add">these bodies</char> we live in <char style="add">here in this world are like</char> [MET] tents. <char style="add">They are like temporary living/dwelling places</char>. <char style="add">So we should not be concerned about what happens to our bodies</char>. We know that if we are killed {if <char style="add">someone</char> kills us}, God will give us <char style="add">permanent living places. Those permanent living places</char> [MET] will not be houses that people have made. They <char style="add">will be new bodies in which we will live forever</char> in heaven. <verse eid="2CO 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 5:2"/><char style="add">While we are here on earth, we suffer</char>. We often groan because we desire <char style="add">to go</char> to heaven <char style="add">where God</char> will give us our new <char style="add">bodies</char> [MET]. <verse eid="2CO 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 5:3"/>When <char style="add">God gives us(inc) our new bodies</char> [MET], our <char style="add">spirits will have</char> [LIT, MET] bodies to live in <char style="add">that will last forever</char>.<verse eid="2CO 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 5:4"/>
    <char style="add">It is true that</char> while we are still living in these bodies [MET] <char style="add">that do not last forever</char>, we often groan [DOU] <char style="add">because we desire to be free from them</char>. We are not longing to be without a body. Instead, <char style="add">we groan because</char> we desire to receive our new bodies [MET] in heaven. We long for this to happen so that these bodies that are going to die some day will suddenly be changed <char style="add">into bodies</char> that will live <char style="add">forever</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 5:5"/>It is God himself who has prepared us to <char style="add">receive</char> these <char style="add">new bodies</char>. He is also the one who has guaranteed/assured us <char style="add">(inc)</char> that this will happen. He has guaranteed it by sending his Spirit <char style="add">to live inside us now</char>.<verse eid="2CO 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 5:6"/>So, <char style="add">because God’s Spirit lives in us</char>, we are always confident <char style="add">that God will give us new bodies</char>. We know that as long as we have bodies here on <char style="add">earth</char>, we are not yet <char style="add">living together</char> with the Lord <char style="add">Jesus in heaven</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 5:7"/>While we <char style="add">(exc)</char> live <char style="add">here, we</char> do not have our <char style="add">new bodies, but we are</char> trusting <char style="add">that God will give them to us</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 5:8"/><char style="add">As I said</char>, we <char style="add">(exc)</char> are confident <char style="add">that he will give us new bodies</char>. We <char style="add">(exc)</char> would much prefer to leave these bodies <char style="add">which we have now</char>, and be with the Lord <char style="add">Jesus in our</char> home in <char style="add">heaven</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 5:9"/>Because of all that, we always want to please <char style="add">Jesus in everything that we do</char>. Whether we <char style="add">(exc)</char> are <char style="add">still living</char> here <char style="add">in these</char> bodies or whether we have <char style="add">left</char> them and are living in our home <char style="add">in heaven</char>, we want to please him. <verse eid="2CO 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 5:10"/><char style="add">And we need to try hard to do that</char> because each one of us <char style="add">believers</char> must stand before Christ <char style="add">to be</char> judged <char style="add">by him</char> {<char style="add">when he will</char> judge <char style="add">his people</char>}. <char style="add">At that time</char> he will <char style="add">reward each one of</char> us according to what we have done <char style="add">while we lived in this world</char> in these bodies. <char style="add">He will reward us according to</char> whether we have done good things or whether we have done evil things.<verse eid="2CO 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ has shown me how much he loves people. That is why I teach his message with all the strength that I have. Therefore, I plead with you to believe that God will forgive you because of what Christ did for you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 5:11-6:2">2 Corinthians 5:11—6:2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 5:11"/>It makes me fearful <char style="add">to think that some day I will stand before the Lord for him to judge me</char>. So I <char style="add">do everything that I can to</char> convince people <char style="add">that they should believe</char> (OR, <char style="add">that I teach</char> sincerely) <char style="add">God’s message</char>. God knows very well <char style="add">how I conduct my life and what I teach</char>, and I really believe that you know it, too. <verse eid="2CO 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 5:12"/>Once again <char style="add">I say, as I write this</char>, I am not just <char style="add">trying to</char> make you think well/highly of me, <char style="add">as some people will probably say that I am</char>. Instead, I am <char style="add">telling you in this letter why you have</char> good reason <char style="add">to tell those who criticize me</char> that you think highly of me. <char style="add">I am telling you this</char> so that you will know what to say to those <char style="add">teachers of false doctrine among you</char>. They are proud <char style="add">of what they have done</char>, instead of <char style="add">making sure that</char> they <char style="add">are right with God and being pleased with that</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 5:13"/><char style="add">Some of them say that after God has enabled me to see visions</char>, I <char style="add">talk like</char> a crazy person. If <char style="add">that is so, I want you to realize that I talk that way in order to please</char> God. On the other hand, if <char style="add">you think that</char> I <char style="add">speak and act</char> wisely, <char style="add">that is good. I want you to know that I do</char> speak and act wisely in order to <char style="add">help</char> you. <verse eid="2CO 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 5:14"/><char style="add">I speak and act the way I do</char> because the love that Christ <char style="add">has for people</char> influences me <char style="add">in everything that I say and do</char>. When Christ died, <char style="add">he suffered the punishment</char> for <char style="add">the sins of</char> all people. So, we should all <char style="add">think of ourselves as having</char> died with him, <char style="add">being as unresponsive to sinful desires as</char> [MET] a corpse is. <verse eid="2CO 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 5:15"/>When <char style="add">Christ</char> died for the everyone, he died in order that <char style="add">we believers who are alive now</char> should not conduct our lives in a way that will just <char style="add">please ourselves</char>. Instead, <char style="add">we should conduct our lives in a way that will please</char> Christ, <char style="add">because</char> he is the one who died for us and was brought back to life {whom <char style="add">God</char> raised} again.<verse eid="2CO 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 5:16"/>So, <char style="add">because I realize how much Christ loves everyone</char>, I no longer think about people in the way that those who do not believe <char style="add">in Christ</char> think about <char style="add">them</char>. Before I <char style="add">was a believer</char>, I thought about Christ in the way that other non-believers did. But I do not think of him that way any more. <verse eid="2CO 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 5:17"/>The fact is that God makes every one <char style="add">of us</char> who <char style="add">trusts</char> in Christ to be completely different <char style="add">than we were before</char>. Our old <char style="add">way of conducting our lives</char> is gone. We now have a <char style="add">completely</char> new way of <char style="add">conducting our lives</char>. <verse eid="2CO 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 5:18"/>This <char style="add">complete change in our lives</char> is all something that God <char style="add">does</char>. It is God who made it possible for us to have a peaceful relationship with him. <char style="add">He was able to do that</char> because of what Christ <char style="add">did for us</char>. Now God <char style="add">has sent</char> me, and those <char style="add">who work</char> with me, to tell <char style="add">people that they</char> can have a peaceful relationship with him. <verse eid="2CO 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 5:19"/>That is, <char style="add">he sent us(exc) to tell them that</char> when Christ <char style="add">died</char>, God was <char style="add">making it possible for everyone</char> [MTY] in the world to have a peaceful relationship with him. He no longer keeps a record of the sinful things that <char style="add">we believers</char> have done. The message that <char style="add">God</char> has given to us <char style="add">to tell people is how we can have a</char> peaceful relationship with him. <verse eid="2CO 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 5:20"/>So, it is I and my companions who are Christ’s representatives <char style="add">in this world. When we tell people the message about Christ</char>, it is God himself who is pleading with them by means of what we <char style="add">say</char>. So, as true representatives of Christ, we plead with you: <char style="add">Believe God’s true message about Christ in order that you may</char> be reconciled to {have a peaceful relationship with} him. <verse eid="2CO 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 5:21"/><char style="add">You must believe that even though</char> Jesus never sinned, God <char style="add">punished him for all the</char> sinful things <char style="add">that people do, just</char> as <char style="add">if Jesus had done those sinful things himself</char>. And because of our close relationship with Christ, God has erased the record of our sins/declared us no longer guilty for our sins.<verse eid="2CO 5:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="2CO 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 6:1"/>
    <char style="add">Therefore</char>, because I am working together with God <char style="add">himself</char>, I say this to you very strongly: God has <char style="add">already</char> kindly <char style="add">forgiven you because Christ died for you</char>, so do not now <char style="add">say</char> “It does not matter <char style="add">if I live just to please myself</char>.” <verse eid="2CO 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 6:2"/>For God said <char style="add">long ago in the Scriptures</char>:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CO 6:2">When it is the right time <char style="add">for me</char> to help you, <char style="add">you will ask me to help you</char>, and I will hear you. Then I will <char style="add">send</char> a Savior to help you.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CO 6:2">
    <char style="add">So listen to what</char> I am telling you: God <char style="add">has sent</char> his Savior, so now is the time when <char style="add">God is ready to</char> save <char style="add">people from the guilt of their sins</char>.<verse eid="2CO 6:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">In spite of much suffering, we have lived as servants of God should live.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 6:3-10">2 Corinthians 6:3-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 6:3"/>Neither I nor the men <char style="add">working</char> with me do anything that would hinder people from trusting in Christ, and so we cannot be accused {no one can accuse <char style="add">us</char>} <char style="add">of not</char> serving <char style="add">God properly</char>. <verse eid="2CO 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 6:4"/>Instead, in everything <char style="add">that we(exc) say and do</char>, we show <char style="add">people</char> that we serve God faithfully. We patiently endure <char style="add">all the things that happen to us. People cause us</char> many troubles and, as a result, we are anxious <char style="add">and often do not know what to do</char>. <verse eid="2CO 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 6:5"/>Sometimes we have been beaten <char style="add">and bound</char> {People have beaten <char style="add">us and tied us</char>} <char style="add">with</char> chains in prison. <char style="add">Angry mobs</char> have attacked us, <char style="add">wanting to kill us</char>. We have continued working <char style="add">for God until we had no more strength to work</char>. We have had many sleepless nights, and we have <char style="add">often been without food</char>. <verse eid="2CO 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 6:6"/><char style="add">All that we think about and all that we do is</char> pure <char style="add">in God’s sight</char>. Knowing <char style="add">how God wants us to conduct our lives, we do what pleases him</char>. We are patient <char style="add">with those who oppose us</char>. We are kind <char style="add">to everyone. We depend on</char> the Holy Spirit <char style="add">to help us</char>. We love people sincerely <char style="add">as God wants us to love them</char>. <verse eid="2CO 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 6:7"/>We faithfully teach <char style="add">the true</char> message <char style="add">about Christ</char>, and God <char style="add">gives us</char> his power <char style="add">as we teach it. Like soldiers</char> using weapons [MET] <char style="add">in a battle</char>, we, by <char style="add">living</char> righteously, <char style="add">defend God’s message and refute those who attack it</char>. <verse eid="2CO 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 6:8"/><char style="add">We serve God faithfully</char>, whether <char style="add">people</char> praise us <char style="add">(exc)</char> or <char style="add">whether they</char> despise us, whether <char style="add">people say</char> bad things <char style="add">about us(exc)</char> or <char style="add">whether they say</char> good things <char style="add">about us. We keep teaching</char> the truth, <char style="add">even though some people say that</char> we are deceiving <char style="add">people</char>. <verse eid="2CO 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 6:9"/><char style="add">Some people</char> know <char style="add">well that we are true servants of God, and yet others</char>, who know us, refuse to <char style="add">believe that. People have often tried to</char> kill us <char style="add">(inc)</char>, yet we are still alive. We have <char style="add">often</char> been beaten, but we have not been killed {<char style="add">People have often</char> beaten us <char style="add">(exc)</char>, but <char style="add">they</char> have not killed us}. <verse eid="2CO 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 6:10"/>Although we <char style="add">(exc)</char> are often very sad <char style="add">because people have rejected our message</char>, we are always joyful <char style="add">because of all that God has done for us</char>. Even though we <char style="add">(exc)</char> are poor, we make <char style="add">it possible for</char> many people to be <char style="add">spiritually</char> rich. It is true that <char style="add">in this world</char> we <char style="add">(exc)</char> have nothing <char style="add">valuable</char> [HYP], but <char style="add">because we belong to God’s family</char>, all <char style="add">that God has</char> belongs to us.<verse eid="2CO 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I ask you to accept us and love us as we love you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 6:11-13">2 Corinthians 6:11-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 6:11"/>You <char style="add">fellow believers</char> in Corinth, <char style="add">I have been</char> completely honest with you. <char style="add">I have told you exactly how we(exc) feel about you, that</char> we love you very much [IDM]. <verse eid="2CO 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 6:12"/>We are not <char style="add">treating you as though we do not</char> love you, but you are <char style="add">treating us as though you do</char> not love us. <verse eid="2CO 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 6:13"/>In return <char style="add">for our loving you, will you not</char> love <char style="add">us</char> [IDM] just as <char style="add">much as we love you?</char> I am writing <char style="add">to you</char> as if you were my own children.<verse eid="2CO 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not get involved with people who do not honor God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 6:14-7:1">2 Corinthians 6:14—7:1</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 6:14"/>Do not ◄team up/have a close relationship► with anyone who does not trust <char style="add">in Christ. I say this</char> because we who <char style="add">trust in Christ and do</char> what is right should not [RHQ] <char style="add">want to do things</char> with wicked people. Or <char style="add">to say it in another way</char>, just like light and darkness never join together, so <char style="add">those who belong to Christ and those who belong to Satan should never join together</char> [RHQ]. <verse eid="2CO 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 6:15"/>There is no [RHQ] agreement of any kind between Christ and Satan. <char style="add">So</char>, believers have no [RHQ] common <char style="add">spiritual</char> interests with unbelievers. <verse eid="2CO 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 6:16"/><char style="add">Just</char> as no one would <char style="add">dare to bring</char> idols into the Temple <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>, believers should never [RHQ] join with those who worship idols. <char style="add">I say that</char> because [MET] <char style="add">the Holy Spirit is in us, and so</char> we are <char style="add">like</char> the Temple of the all-powerful God. <char style="add">It is</char> as God himself said <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:16">I will live in <char style="add">my people</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:16">I will always be with/helping them.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:16">
    <char style="add">They will say to me</char>, “You are our God,” and</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:16">
    <char style="add">I will say to them</char>, “You are my people.”<verse eid="2CO 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 6:17"/>
    <char style="add">In another place in the Scriptures we read that</char> the Lord said:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:17">Get away from those who do evil things;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:17">keep yourselves separated from them.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:17">Do <char style="add">nothing sinful that would make you</char> unacceptable to me.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:17">Then I will welcome you <char style="add">as members of my family</char>.<verse eid="2CO 6:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 6:18"/>
    <char style="add">The Lord also said</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:18">I will <char style="add">care for you</char> as [MET] a loving father <char style="add">cares for his children</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:18">and <char style="add">it will be as though</char> you are my own sons and daughters.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 6:18">I, the all-powerful Lord, am saying this <char style="add">to you</char>.<verse eid="2CO 6:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="2CO 7"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 7:1"/>My friends, whom I love, because <char style="add">God</char> has promised <char style="add">to accept us(inc) as his children</char>, we <char style="add">(inc)</char> must stop doing anything that is sinful. We must not do sinful things with our bodies, and we must not <char style="add">think</char> sinful thoughts. <char style="add">Because</char> we greatly revere God, we must strive to <char style="add">live</char> a completely pure life. By doing that we will become the kind of people that he wants us to be.<verse eid="2CO 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I love you all and I have great confidence in you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 7:2-4">2 Corinthians 7:2-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 7:2"/>So, as I just wrote, I want you to love me (OR, us [IDM] <char style="add">who are true apostles of Christ</char>). I/we <char style="add">(exc)</char> have never done anything wrong to any of you. I/we have not done anything to harm any one of you spiritually or financially. And I/we have not tried to get money from <char style="add">you</char> ◄for myself/for ourselves►. <verse eid="2CO 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 7:3"/><char style="add">It is true that some people among you have said that I have done such things. Nevertheless</char>, I am not trying to make you all feel ashamed because, as I wrote before, I will continue to love you all very much [IDM], whether I live with you or die with you. I am very confident about you. <verse eid="2CO 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 7:4"/>I am very pleased with you. You have greatly encouraged me, so that I am now very joyful in spite of all the hardships that I have endured.<verse eid="2CO 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Titus told me that my letter caused you to repent, and so now I am very happy.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 7:5-16">2 Corinthians 7:5-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 7:5"/>Now <char style="add">I will write more about what I was saying about Titus</char>. When I <char style="add">left Troas and</char> came <char style="add">here to</char> Macedonia <char style="add">province</char>, I still did not get any rest. Everywhere we <char style="add">(exc)</char> went, <char style="add">people were constantly</char> causing us trouble. <char style="add">And not only were</char> people <char style="add">constantly causing us</char> trouble, but I was greatly concerned <char style="add">about you all</char>. <verse eid="2CO 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 7:6"/>But God, who always encourages his people when they are discouraged, encouraged us by <char style="add">sending</char> Titus back to us. <verse eid="2CO 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 7:7"/>I was encouraged by <char style="add">seeing</char> Titus, <char style="add">but when I heard how</char> you had encouraged him, that encouraged me even more. He told me how much you wanted <char style="add">to see me. He told me</char> that you were very sorry <char style="add">that you had made me so unhappy. He also told me</char> that you are very eager for me <char style="add">to continue to serve as your apostle. When Titus told me those things</char>, I was very, very happy.<verse eid="2CO 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 7:8"/>Even though what <char style="add">I wrote</char> in my letter ◄distressed you/made you sad►, I am not sorry <char style="add">that I wrote it</char>. For a while I was sorry that I had written it, <char style="add">because I knew that it would distress you</char>. Now <char style="add">Titus has also told</char> me that it did distress you <char style="add">when you read it</char>, but you were distressed only for a short time. <verse eid="2CO 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 7:9"/><char style="add">So now</char> I am happy <char style="add">that I wrote it</char>. I am not happy that you were distressed {that <char style="add">I</char> distressed you}, but <char style="add">I am happy</char> because, when you became distressed, you felt sorry for what you had done and <char style="add">you asked God to forgive you. What I mean is that you felt sorry in the way that God wanted you to feel sorry, so my making</char> you feel sorry did not harm you at all. <verse eid="2CO 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 7:10"/><char style="add">The fact is that</char> when God causes <char style="add">us to feel</char> truly sorry for having sinned and we turn from our sinful behavior, then God saves us <char style="add">and will not punish us for the sinful things that we have done</char>. And no one is ever sorry about that. <char style="add">However</char>, the people who do not trust <char style="add">in God</char> [MTY] may be sorry <char style="add">for the sinful things that they have done</char>. But <char style="add">if they do not turn from their sinful behavior and ask God to forgive them</char>, they will remain separated from him forever. <verse eid="2CO 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 7:11"/>But <char style="add">think about what happened when you read my letter</char>: God caused you to be truly sorry <char style="add">for what you had done</char>. You eagerly <char style="add">wanted to do what was right</char>, and you wanted to show <char style="add">God</char> (OR, <char style="add">me</char>) that you had done the right thing. You were angry <char style="add">about what had happened</char>, and you were worried <char style="add">that God would punish you if the situation continued</char>. You also wanted me <char style="add">to visit you to encourage and help you</char>. You wanted me to know <char style="add">that you really do accept me as your apostle, and that you punished the man who had sinned, as I told you to do. By doing</char> all of those things, you have shown <char style="add">me</char> that you have done what is right in this matter. <verse eid="2CO 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 7:12"/>So, even though I wrote that <char style="add">severe</char> letter to you, I did not <char style="add">write it just</char> so that <char style="add">you would punish</char> the man who had done what was wrong. Also, I <char style="add">did not write it</char> for the benefit of the person whom <char style="add">he</char> had wronged. Instead, <char style="add">I wrote it</char> so that, when you <char style="add">read the letter</char>, God would enable you to realize how much you really do respect <char style="add">my authority</char>. <verse eid="2CO 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 7:13"/>So, <char style="add">because you listened to me and did what I asked you to do</char>, ◄I was/we <char style="add">(exc)</char> were all► encouraged. Not only ◄was I/were we► encouraged, but ◄I was/we <char style="add">(exc)</char> were► <char style="add">also</char> very happy to see how happy Titus was <char style="add">when he arrived here. He told me/us that</char> he did not need to worry any more, because <char style="add">he saw</char> that you all <char style="add">had a good attitude toward me</char>. <verse eid="2CO 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 7:14"/>I had told Titus that I was pleased about you. And I did not need to be ashamed <char style="add">for feeling that way about you, because you did what I knew that you would do</char>. Just like everything that I have taught you <char style="add">and written to you</char> has been the truth, the good things that I told Titus about you were also true. <verse eid="2CO 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 7:15"/>Now he happily remembers how you all <char style="add">were willing to</char> do <char style="add">what I asked you to do</char>. He is <char style="add">also happy about the way you</char> treated him with great respect. <char style="add">When he thinks about those things</char>, <char style="add">it makes</char> him love you even more <char style="add">than he did when he was with you</char>. <verse eid="2CO 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 7:16"/><char style="add">As for me</char>, I am very happy <char style="add">because now</char> I am certain that I can depend on you <char style="add">to do what you know God wants you to do</char>.<verse eid="2CO 7:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="2CO 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The believers in Macedonia have already collected the money that they are going to send to the believers in Jerusalem. You should also finish collecting the money that you are preparing to send, and have it ready to send to Jerusalem soon.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 8:1-15">2 Corinthians 8:1-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 8:1"/>Now, my fellow believers, I want to tell you <char style="add">what happened because of</char> God’s <char style="add">acting</char> kindly <char style="add">in the lives</char> of <char style="add">the believers in</char> the congregations <char style="add">here</char> in Macedonia <char style="add">province</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 8:2"/>Even though <char style="add">the non-believers here</char> have been causing the believers to suffer severely, the believers are always very joyful. <char style="add">Although they</char> are very poor, <char style="add">they gave</char> very generously <char style="add">to help other believers</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 8:3"/><char style="add">I know that this is true</char>, because I have seen for myself that they not only gave <char style="add">money</char> [EUP] that they were able <char style="add">to give</char>, they gave <char style="add">so much money that they did</char> not even keep enough <char style="add">to buy what they needed for themselves</char>. Without anyone telling them <char style="add">to share their possessions</char>, <verse eid="2CO 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 8:4"/>they themselves kept requesting us to let them participate in what <char style="add">other believers</char> are doing in <char style="add">sending a gift of money to</char> [EUP] God’s people <char style="add">in Judea province</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 8:5"/>I thought <char style="add">that they would give only a little of their money, but</char> they did much <char style="add">more than that</char>. First, they told the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> that they wanted to do <char style="add">what pleases him. After that, they told</char> me that they wanted to do <char style="add">whatever I thought was good for them to do, because they were sure that</char> would be what God <char style="add">wanted them to do</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 8:6"/>So, because Titus was the one who <char style="add">helped you to</char> begin <char style="add">gathering the money</char> [EUP, MTY] for your gift, I urged him to also <char style="add">help you</char> finish <char style="add">collecting the rest of</char> your generous and loving gift. <verse eid="2CO 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 8:7"/>You are doing very well in so many <char style="add">other</char> ways. <char style="add">God’s Spirit enables you to</char> believe that <char style="add">God</char> will <char style="add">do miracles. His Spirit has given you the ability to</char> tell <char style="add">God’s message to others. His Spirit makes you able to</char> know things that he reveals to you. You eagerly <char style="add">want to help people</char>, and you love us <char style="add">(exc)</char> very much. <char style="add">So now</char>, try to also do well in getting your generous <char style="add">gift of money</char> [EUP] <char style="add">ready to send to the believers in Judea province</char>.<verse eid="2CO 8:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 8:8"/>I am not commanding you <char style="add">to do this</char>. But <char style="add">because I have seen how believers in</char> other <char style="add">places</char> are eager <char style="add">to help other believers who do not have</char> ◄<char style="add">what they need/enough to live on</char>►, I want you similarly to show that you love others sincerely. <verse eid="2CO 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 8:9"/>You already know <char style="add">how much</char> our Lord Jesus <char style="add">did for you</char> that you did not deserve. Everything <char style="add">in heaven</char> belonged to him. But in order to benefit you, <char style="add">he left all of those things behind and became a human being. Here on earth he had</char> very few possessions <char style="add">of his own</char>. But because he became poor like that, he is <char style="add">able to cause</char> you <char style="add">(pl)</char> to become <char style="add">spiritually</char> rich. <verse eid="2CO 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 8:10"/>So, <char style="add">as you think of our Lord’s example, I will tell you</char> what I think that you should do in this matter <char style="add">of giving money. As you know</char>, last year, because you desired <char style="add">to give money to help God’s people in Judea province</char>, you began <char style="add">collecting money</char> [EUP]. <verse eid="2CO 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 8:11"/>So now you should finish <char style="add">collecting</char> the money [EUP] that you began <char style="add">to gather</char>. In that way, <char style="add">everyone will know that you are just</char> as ready to finish <char style="add">collecting this gift</char> as you were to begin collecting it. Give what you are able to give. <verse eid="2CO 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 8:12"/><char style="add">Keep in mind that</char> if you really want to <char style="add">give something to help others</char>, whatever any one of you is <char style="add">able to give</char> will be pleasing <char style="add">to God. God does not expect his people to give more</char> than they can afford to give. <verse eid="2CO 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 8:13"/>I do not mean that <char style="add">you should give so much to help others that</char> you yourselves do not have what you need. No, what I want is that <char style="add">both you and others</char> will have what <char style="add">you need</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 8:14"/>Right now, when you have ◄more <char style="add">than you need/</char>plenty► and <char style="add">the believers in Judea</char> do not have ◄enough/all that they need►, <char style="add">with your gift you will enable them to have enough. Maybe some day</char> when you do not have ◄enough/all that you need► and they have more than they need, they will <char style="add">be able to</char> help you. Then everyone will have enough (OR, In that way each will share alike). <verse eid="2CO 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 8:15"/><char style="add">If that happens, the result will be like it is written</char> {<char style="add">like someone/Moses</char> wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures about the time when God provided manna for his people</char>,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2CO 8:15">If someone gathered a lot <char style="add">of manna</char>, he still did not have more than he needed, <char style="add">because he gave some to someone who did not have enough</char>. And those who gathered only a little <char style="add">manna</char> still had all that they needed [LIT], <char style="add">because others who gathered more than they needed gave some manna to them</char>.<verse eid="2CO 8:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I am sending Titus to you, along with two other believers, to help you get your gift ready. They are all well respected and trustworthy men, so treat them well. It will be good if you have your gift ready to send to Judea province by the time I arrive in Corinth.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 8:16-9:5">2 Corinthians 8:16—9:5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 8:16"/>
    <char style="add">So now I am sending Titus to visit you again</char>. God has caused him to be just as eager <char style="add">to help you prepare your gift</char> as I am. I thank God for that. <verse eid="2CO 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 8:17"/><char style="add">He is going there</char>, not only because we urged him to go, but because he himself is very eager <char style="add">to visit you again</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 8:18"/>I am sending with Titus another believer <char style="add">whom you know well</char>. All the groups of believers <char style="add">in this area</char> think highly of him because he has <char style="add">faithfully taught</char> the good message <char style="add">about Christ</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 8:19"/>Not only that, but he was appointed by the congregations <char style="add">in this area</char> {the congregations <char style="add">in this area</char> appointed him} to <char style="add">go</char> to Jerusalem with us <char style="add">(exc)</char>. He <char style="add">will go</char> with us <char style="add">when we take</char> the generous gift of money [EUP] <char style="add">to the believers in Jerusalem. We are taking this</char> gift to honor the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> and to show them that we all <char style="add">very much</char> want to <char style="add">help them</char>.<verse eid="2CO 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 8:20"/>
    <char style="add">The believers have</char> given money [EUP] generously. So, <char style="add">by sending that fellow believer along with Titus</char> to take the money <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char>, we are trying to make sure that no one will be able to accuse us <char style="add">(exc) of taking some of the money for ourselves</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 8:21"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because we <char style="add">(exc)</char> want to make sure that the Lord <char style="add">God</char> will see that what we <char style="add">(exc)</char> do is right, and other people will see it, too. <verse eid="2CO 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CO 8:22"/>Furthermore, there is also another believer <char style="add">here</char> whom we are sending <char style="add">to you along with the two</char> men <char style="add">whom I have just mentioned</char>. Many times I have seen his good work <char style="add">for the Lord</char>, and I know that he is eager <char style="add">to serve the Lord</char>. Now, because he knows for sure that you <char style="add">want to give this gift the same as other believers do</char>, he is even more eager than he was before <char style="add">to go with the two other men</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CO 8:23"/>As for Titus, <char style="add">I have chosen him because</char> he is my partner, and he has worked faithfully with me <char style="add">to help you</char>. As for the other two men, the congregations <char style="add">in this area</char> are sending them as their messengers. These two men honor Christ <char style="add">by everything they do</char>. <verse eid="2CO 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CO 8:24"/>So then, show them that you truly love <char style="add">others</char>, and <char style="add">in that way</char> help other congregations to understand <char style="add">why</char> we <char style="add">(exc)</char> are always saying such good things about you.<verse eid="2CO 8:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="2CO 9"/>
  <para style="s1">You and I will be ashamed if your gift is not ready when I arrive.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 9:1-5">2 Corinthians 9:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 9:1"/>Now <char style="add">I want to write</char> more about the gift <char style="add">of money</char> [EUP] that <char style="add">you and other believers are preparing to send</char> to the believers <char style="add">in Judea province</char>. I do not <char style="add">really</char> need to <char style="add">continue writing to you about it</char>, <verse eid="2CO 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 9:2"/>because I already know that you really want to help them. In fact, I have been boasting <char style="add">about you</char>, telling the <char style="add">believers here in</char> Macedonia <char style="add">province</char> that <char style="add">you people in</char> Achaia <char style="add">province</char> have been ready to help, since last year. As a result, because you are very eager to help <char style="add">the believers in Judea province</char>, you have made most of <char style="add">the believers here in Macedonia province also want</char> to give <char style="add">a gift</char>. <verse eid="2CO 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 9:3"/>However, I am sending Titus and the other two believers in order that <char style="add">they will be able to help you finish collecting the money. Then when I and others arrive later, the people with me will see for themselves that</char> the things that I have been boasting about you are true [LIT]. <char style="add">I want</char> you <char style="add">to have your gift</char> ready <char style="add">for us(exc) to take to Jerusalem</char>, just like I have been telling others that you were ready. <verse eid="2CO 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 9:4"/>When I come, if any of <char style="add">the believers from</char> Macedonia come with me, <char style="add">I do not want them to find that your gift is</char> [MTY, EUP] not ready. If that were <char style="add">to happen</char>, I would be very ashamed, and you yourselves would be even more ashamed. <verse eid="2CO 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 9:5"/>So that is why I felt that it was necessary to urge these <char style="add">three</char> believers to go <char style="add">and visit</char> you before I <char style="add">come. In that way, they would be able to help you finish</char> collecting the generous gift [EUP] that had been promised by you {you had said you would give}. <char style="add">If you do that, not only will</char> the gift be ready <char style="add">by the time that we arrive, but everyone will see that you have given because you really want to give, and</char> not because anyone has forced you to give.<verse eid="2CO 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">If you give generously and willingly, God will always continue to bless you so that you will have enough to continue giving generously, and your generosity will cause many other people to praise and honor God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 9:6-15">2 Corinthians 9:6-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 9:6"/>Do not forget this: “<char style="add">A farmer</char> who sows only a few <char style="add">seeds</char> will not gather/reap a large <char style="add">harvest</char>, but the one who sows a lot <char style="add">of seeds</char> will gather/reap a large <char style="add">harvest</char> [MET].” <char style="add">Similarly, if you give just a little to help others, God will give you only a few blessings. But if you give willingly and cheerfully to help people, you will receive in return many blessings from God</char>. <verse eid="2CO 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 9:7"/>Each of you should decide how much you <char style="add">(sg)</char> should give, <char style="add">and then give that amount</char>. You <char style="add">(sg)</char> should not <char style="add">be thinking to yourself</char>, “<char style="add">I really</char> do not want to give this money.” <char style="add">And you(sg) should</char> not give <char style="add">just</char> because someone tells <char style="add">you to give. Instead, you should give willingly and cheerfully</char>, because God loves those who give cheerfully. <verse eid="2CO 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 9:8"/>Moreover, God can enable you to <char style="add">give to others cheerfully. If you give that way</char>, God will <char style="add">in return</char> give you many good blessings. He will do that so that at all times you will always have everything that you need. Indeed, you will have even more <char style="add">than you need. As a result, you will be able to do</char> many more good things <char style="add">to help others</char>. <verse eid="2CO 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 9:9"/><char style="add">Those who give willingly and cheerfully will be rewarded like the man about whom</char> it is written {<char style="add">about whom</char> ◄someone/the Psalmist► wrote} in the Scriptures,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 9:9">He generously <char style="add">helps others</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 9:9">
    <char style="add">he gives to those</char> who are poor.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 9:9">
    <char style="add">God will remember</char> the good things that he did,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 9:9">
    <char style="add">and reward him with</char> good things forever.<verse eid="2CO 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 9:10"/>
    <char style="add">God always</char> gives seeds to farmers to plant, and also gives them food to eat. <char style="add">So, similarly, God will</char> always make it possible for you to have enough money [MET], so that you will be able more and more to generously <char style="add">help those who are needy</char>. <verse eid="2CO 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 9:11"/><char style="add">God</char> will <char style="add">give you</char> many blessings in many different ways as a result of your generously <char style="add">helping others</char>. Furthermore, <char style="add">the</char> generous <char style="add">gift that you are getting ready for</char> us <char style="add">(exc) to take to the believers in Judea province</char> will cause <char style="add">many people</char> to thank God.<verse eid="2CO 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 9:12"/>
    <char style="add">Also remember that</char> when you give money to [EUP] help God’s people, you not only give them what they need, but also, <char style="add">because of that</char>, <char style="add">many people will</char> thank God very much <char style="add">for you and for what you have done</char>. <verse eid="2CO 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 9:13"/>As a result of your giving <char style="add">money to help others</char>, they will praise God, not only because you have believed the good message about Christ, but also because you have <char style="add">generously given some of your possessions</char> so that they and other <char style="add">believers will all have</char> ◄<char style="add">enough/their needs supplied</char>►. <verse eid="2CO 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 9:14"/>Also, when they pray for you, <char style="add">asking God to bless you, they will remember how grateful they are</char> [IDM] that God <char style="add">caused you to give</char> very willingly and cheerfully. <verse eid="2CO 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 9:15"/><char style="add">Finally, we should all</char> thank God <char style="add">because he gave us the greatest gift of all when he sent his Son to save/rescue us(inc)</char> ◄<char style="add">from the guilt of our sin/from being punished for our sin</char>►. That is a gift too wonderful for anyone to be able to tell about completely!<verse eid="2CO 9:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="2CO 10"/>
  <para style="s1">I Paul say to you, “Do not listen to those who say that I am afraid to rebuke you when I am with you and that I behave like people do who are not believers.”</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 10:1-6">2 Corinthians 10:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 10:1"/>Now I myself, Paul, appeal to you in a gentle and humble way, like Christ <char style="add">would. Certain people among you have falsely accused me by saying</char>, “When <char style="add">Paul</char> is with you, he is humble <char style="add">and speaks gently</char> to you, but when he is away from you, <char style="add">in the letters he writes to you</char> he threatens <char style="add">to punish</char> you.” <char style="add">Those people claim that I do not have authority over you as an apostle</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 10:2"/>I strongly plead with you, “<char style="add">Please do not listen to people who say things like that!</char>” <char style="add">I strongly plead with you not to listen to them</char>, so that when I am there <char style="add">with you</char> I will not <char style="add">need to</char> speak severely <char style="add">to you</char> in the same severe way as I <char style="add">plan to</char> speak to those people who think that I behave like people who are not believers. <verse eid="2CO 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 10:3"/><char style="add">Remember that</char> although I am <char style="add">human like everyone else</char> in the world, I do not fight <char style="add">against those who oppose me</char> in the way that people who are not believers fight those who oppose them. <verse eid="2CO 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 10:4"/><char style="add">I will tell you what I mean by that: Just like soldiers use</char> various weapons <char style="add">to fight their enemies</char> [MET], <char style="add">I</char> ◄<char style="add">fight against/oppose</char>► <char style="add">those who</char> oppose God’s message, but I do it in a different way. I do not <char style="add">use human arguments and clever/sweet talk</char>, like unbelievers do. Instead, <char style="add">I fight against my opponents</char> with the powerful means that God <char style="add">has given me</char>. With that power <char style="add">I destroy their arguments against God’s message and against me, just like soldiers destroy</char> [MET] the fortresses <char style="add">of their enemies</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 10:5"/><char style="add">Specifically</char>, I show that the <char style="add">human</char> arguments that they use to deceive <char style="add">people are completely wrong</char>. When they <char style="add">proudly say things that</char> keep other people from knowing God, <char style="add">I show them that they are completely wrong. I also enable people to</char> change their ways of thinking so that they think about everything as Christ <char style="add">wants them to think</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 10:6"/>I am also ready to discipline everyone <char style="add">among you</char> who has not obeyed <char style="add">the things that Christ taught. I will do this</char> as soon as you <char style="add">who truly want to obey Christ show me that</char> you are <char style="add">going to</char> obey him completely.<verse eid="2CO 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Those who teach what is false must come to realize that I also belong to Christ and that God has given me authority over you. I worry that they will deceive you and that you will stop being faithful to Christ alone.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 10:7-11:6">2 Corinthians 10:7—11:6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 10:7"/>
    <char style="add">I want you to understand what is</char> happening among you. There are certain <char style="add">people there who are telling you that</char> they know for sure that they are Christ’s <char style="add">representatives and that I am not</char>. Those people should realize that I <char style="add">represent</char> Christ as much as they do. <verse eid="2CO 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 10:8"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because the authority that the Lord gave me <char style="add">as his apostle</char> is to help you to become mature believers, not to cause you to stop <char style="add">trusting in Christ</char>. So even if I were to boast a little more than I have <char style="add">already done</char> (OR, proudly talk a little more than I have <char style="add">already talked</char> about the authority the Lord gave me <char style="add">as his apostle</char>), <char style="add">no one would be able to make me</char> ashamed <char style="add">by proving that Jesus has not given me that authority</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 10:9"/>I do not intend to make you afraid of me by the letters that I <char style="add">write to you</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 10:10"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because some people are saying, “<char style="add">When Paul writes</char> letters, he says severe things <char style="add">in order to make you obey him</char>, but when he is here with you, <char style="add">people look at him and say</char> he is weak, and he certainly is not a skillful speaker.” <verse eid="2CO 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 10:11"/>The <char style="add">people who say</char> such things should think carefully about this: The kind of <char style="add">severe</char> person that <char style="add">you think</char> me to be when you read my letters is exactly the kind of person I will be when I come. <char style="add">I will do what I wrote that I would do</char>.<verse eid="2CO 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 10:12"/>
    <char style="add">Those who oppose me</char> tell others how good they are. <char style="add">If they really were superior to me</char> [IRO], I would not be so bold as to say that I <char style="add">was equal to them, or</char> to compare myself with them. <char style="add">But they are not superior to me</char>. They make up their own standards <char style="add">about what God’s servants should be like</char>, and then they look at their own <char style="add">conduct</char> and decide <char style="add">whether or not they meet those standards. By doing that, they show that</char> they are foolish. <verse eid="2CO 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 10:13"/>But as for me, I will not boast about <char style="add">working among people living in</char> areas outside of the areas <char style="add">that God sent/assigned me to work in</char>. But <char style="add">it is right for</char> me to say that <char style="add">I have worked</char> in the areas that God assigned to me. <char style="add">And since those areas</char> include the one where you live, <verse eid="2CO 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 10:14"/><char style="add">when I talk about working among you</char>, I am not boasting <char style="add">about working in an area where God did not give me the right to work. What those who oppose me say about my not having authority as an apostle to you might be true</char> if I had not already come all the way to your area. <char style="add">But that is not true</char>, because I was the one who first brought the message about Christ to you. <char style="add">I came to Corinth before they did</char>!<verse eid="2CO 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 10:15"/>Also, <char style="add">my opponents</char> boast about work that others have done <char style="add">as if it were their own work</char>. It is improper for them to do that, but I do not do as they do. I confidently expect that as you trust more and more <char style="add">in the gospel that I preach</char>, you will more and more <char style="add">agree that God has given me the right to</char> work <char style="add">as Christ’s representative</char> among you. <verse eid="2CO 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 10:16"/>Then I will be able to go to places beyond where you <char style="add">are</char>. I will be able to tell the good message about Christ <char style="add">to people in areas where no one has yet gone to tell that message</char>. And <char style="add">I will be able to talk about the work I myself have done in that area</char>, instead of boasting about work that someone else has already done <char style="add">as if it were my work</char>. <verse eid="2CO 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 10:17"/><char style="add">I try to do according to what someone/Jeremiah wrote in the Scriptures</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2CO 10:17">If anyone wants to boast <char style="add">about something</char>, he should boast <char style="add">only</char> about what the Lord <char style="add">God has done</char>.<verse eid="2CO 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 10:18"/>
    <char style="add">You can realize, then, that</char> it is not those who ◄praise themselves/tell you what great things they have done►, <char style="add">as my opponents do</char>, whom you should accept <char style="add">as apostles</char>. Instead, you <char style="add">should accept as true apostles only</char> those whom the Lord commends.<verse eid="2CO 10:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="2CO 11"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 11:1"/>
    <char style="add">But now, because my opponents are saying that Christ sent them to you as his representatives and that he did not send me</char>, please be patient with me, too, <char style="add">while I say a</char> few things <char style="add">that may sound as if</char> [IRO] <char style="add">I am praising myself, like</char> a foolish person <char style="add">would do. You have been</char> ◄<char style="add">putting up with/tolerating</char>► <char style="add">those who teach what is false;</char> now then, ◄put up with/tolerate► me <char style="add">too</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 11:2"/>I really do care about <char style="add">what happens to</char> you, just as God cares about <char style="add">what happens to you. Just like a father wants his daughter to be sexually pure when he presents her to the man she will marry</char> [MET], I <char style="add">want you to belong</char> to Christ <char style="add">alone and to no other</char>. I want to present you <char style="add">to him</char> as people who remain faithful to him <char style="add">only, and who have not believed the deceitful message of those who are teaching what is false</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 11:3"/>However, just like <char style="add">Satan, when he</char> cunningly <char style="add">appeared as a</char> snake, deceived Eve <char style="add">and caused her to disobey the Lord God</char>, I am concerned that <char style="add">those teachers</char> will cause you to think wrongly so that you will no longer <char style="add">be faithful to</char> Christ alone. <verse eid="2CO 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 11:4"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because some people have come among you who are teaching <char style="add">their own thoughts about</char> Jesus. They <char style="add">are saying about him</char> things that are <char style="add">entirely</char> different from what I taught you. <char style="add">They are urging</char> you to receive a <char style="add">powerful</char> spirit who <char style="add">would come to live in you</char>, but it is not the same <char style="add">Spirit</char> that you received <char style="add">from God when you believed in Christ</char>. They preach <char style="add">what they call</char> a good message, and you accept <char style="add">their message, even though it is not the same as the good message about Christ that you heard from me. And</char> you have gladly accepted them and their message! <verse eid="2CO 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 11:5"/>I consider that [LIT] none of those <char style="add">men, even though they think of themselves as being</char> [IRO] extra-special apostles, are in any way greater than I am. <verse eid="2CO 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 11:6"/><char style="add">I admit that</char> I am not an eloquent speaker, but I do know <char style="add">God’s message</char>. I have made that clear to you by everything <char style="add">that I have done among you and by everything that I have taught you</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">You are mistaken if you think that I do not love you because I refused to accept money from you for my teaching. I will go on doing that to prevent those false apostles among you from boasting that they work just as I do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 11:7-15">2 Corinthians 11:7-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 11:7"/>
    <char style="add">I refused to accept money</char> from you as pay for teaching you God’s message about Christ. ◄It is ridiculous for you to think that what I did was wrong!/Was that wrong?► [RHQ] <char style="add">I know that by teaching you without pay</char>, I made myself seem [IRO] unimportant to you. <char style="add">But I did it</char> to honor you. <verse eid="2CO 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 11:8"/><char style="add">Some people might say that it was as though</char> [IRO] I was robbing other congregations because I accepted money from them in order that I might work among you. <verse eid="2CO 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 11:9"/>Furthermore, when I was <char style="add">there</char> with you and had no <char style="add">money to buy the things that I needed</char>, I did not cause any <char style="add">of you</char> ◄<char style="add">to have difficulties by my depending on you/by asking you for money/support</char>►, because our <char style="add">(inc)</char> fellow believers who came from <char style="add">here in</char> Macedonia <char style="add">province</char> brought enough <char style="add">money for me to buy everything</char> that I needed. So I have not caused you any difficulty at all <char style="add">by asking you for money</char>, and I never will <char style="add">ask you for money</char> [EUP]. <verse eid="2CO 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 11:10"/><char style="add">And</char> as <char style="add">sure as you know that</char> everything that Christ says is true, <char style="add">you can be sure that what</char> I say <char style="add">to you now is true. Wherever I go</char> there in Achaia <char style="add">province</char>, <char style="add">I do not let you believers pay me for doing God’s work among you</char>. And no one will be able to prevent me from boasting <char style="add">about that</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 11:11"/>No one should wrongly [RHQ] think that it is because I do not love you that <char style="add">I do not take pay from you</char>. God knows <char style="add">that you truly/really are very dear to me</char>.<verse eid="2CO 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 11:12"/>There are <char style="add">some men there among you</char> who would like to be able to say boastfully that they <char style="add">work among you</char> just as I do. So, in order to make it impossible [IDM] <char style="add">for them to say that</char>, I have <char style="add">refused to accept pay from you</char>, and I will continue doing that. <verse eid="2CO 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 11:13"/>Those men are lying <char style="add">when they say that they are</char> apostles. They work deceitfully. <char style="add">Even though they say that they work for God, they are working only for themselves</char>. They try to make people think that Christ <char style="add">sent them</char> as his apostles, <char style="add">but they do not truly represent him</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 11:14"/>I am not surprised <char style="add">that they act like that</char>, because Satan himself causes people to think <char style="add">that he has come</char> as a shining messenger <char style="add">from God</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 11:15"/>So it should not surprise <char style="add">you</char> if these men, who <char style="add">really</char> serve <char style="add">Satan, do good things in order</char> to make you think they <char style="add">serve God</char>. Some day God will <char style="add">punish them</char> according to what they deserve because of the <char style="add">evil</char> things that they do.<verse eid="2CO 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">You seem to listen to those who boast, so I too will boast. I will boast about being a Jew (as those others do), and I will boast about having suffered greatly for Christ, and about an extraordinary vision that God gave me. Although God caused me to suffer an affliction, he promised that he would help me and strengthen me.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 11:16-12:10">2 Corinthians 11:16—12:10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 11:16"/>I say again: I do not want any of you to think that my <char style="add">boasting about myself</char> is like foolish <char style="add">people</char> boast. But even if anyone <char style="add">thinks that I am boasting about myself like a foolish person boasts, listen to</char> what I <char style="add">have to say anyway, just like you listen to those false apostles</char>. They really <char style="add">speak</char> foolishly! Listen to me while I also boast a little. <verse eid="2CO 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 11:17"/>About the things that I am <char style="add">going to tell you</char>, boasting confidently <char style="add">about myself, surely you know that they are not the kind of things</char> that the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> would say. Instead, <char style="add">I will speak</char> as a foolish <char style="add">person would speak</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 11:18"/>Because many among you are boasting <char style="add">about their own work</char>, as unbelievers do, I will also boast <char style="add">about myself and my work</char> [MTY, IRO]. <verse eid="2CO 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 11:19"/><char style="add">I am sure that you, who think that you are so wise, will accept what I say</char> because you gladly <char style="add">accept the</char> false teachers and the foolish things <char style="add">that they say</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 11:20"/>When people <char style="add">treat</char> you as if they were your bosses, you gladly submit <char style="add">to them. You think that it is all right when others</char> force you to provide for their needs. You think that it is all right <char style="add">when people</char> take control over you, when they boast about themselves, <char style="add">or when they insult you by</char> slapping you in the face. <verse eid="2CO 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 11:21"/>I agree that I was not bold enough to treat you in such ways. <char style="add">Ha! Do you think that</char> [IRO] I should feel ashamed <char style="add">because I did not do that?</char></para>
  <para style="p" vid="2CO 11:21">So now, talking like a person who does not have any sense, I will boldly tell you <char style="add">some things about myself, just like those false apostles tell you things about themselves</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2CO 11:22"/>Do <char style="add">they tell you</char> that they are Hebrews <char style="add">and can speak the Hebrew language?</char> Well, I can say the same thing <char style="add">about myself</char>. Do they <char style="add">tell you that they</char> belong <char style="add">to God’s people</char>, the nation of Israel? Well, I can say the same thing <char style="add">about myself</char>. <char style="add">Do they tell you that</char> they are descendants of <char style="add">our great</char> ancestor Abraham? Well, he is my ancestor, too. <verse eid="2CO 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2CO 11:23"/><char style="add">Do they tell you how much</char> work they have done for Christ? Now I am talking like a crazy person talks [EUP]. Well, I work for Christ much more <char style="add">than they do. I have been</char> in prison many more times <char style="add">than they have. Many times I</char> have been beaten {<char style="add">people</char> have beaten me} very severely <char style="add">because I believe in and obey Christ</char>. Many times I almost died <char style="add">because of serving Christ</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2CO 11:24"/>On five occasions Jewish <char style="add">religious leaders</char> beat me 39 times with a whip. <verse eid="2CO 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2CO 11:25"/>On three occasions I was beaten {<char style="add">Roman</char> officials beat me} with wooden sticks. On one occasion <char style="add">a large crowd of people</char> threw stones at me <char style="add">to kill me</char>. On three occasions the ship <char style="add">that I was traveling on</char> was wrecked <char style="add">and sank. On one of those occasions</char> I was <char style="add">floating</char> in the water a night and a day <char style="add">before I was rescued</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2CO 11:26"/>As I have often traveled to other places, <char style="add">I have often risked losing my life. For example</char>, sometimes I have been in danger <char style="add">crossing</char> rivers. <char style="add">I have been</char> in danger <char style="add">traveling in places</char> where there were bandits. <char style="add">At times I have been in</char> danger among people of my own nation, <char style="add">the Jews</char>, and <char style="add">at other times I been in</char> danger among those who are not Jews. <char style="add">I have been</char> in danger in cities, and I have been in dangerous situations in barren areas. I have been in dangerous situations <char style="add">when I was traveling in ships</char>. <char style="add">I have been in</char> danger among people who falsely <char style="add">claim to be</char> fellow believers. <verse eid="2CO 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2CO 11:27"/>I have worked very hard [DOU] <char style="add">to earn</char> ◄<char style="add">a living/what I need</char>►, and often I did not sleep. At times I was hungry and thirsty, and at times I did not have enough time to eat. Sometimes I was cold <char style="add">because</char> I did not have enough clothes <char style="add">to wear</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2CO 11:28"/>In addition to all that, I am constantly and deeply concerned about all the congregations <char style="add">that I have helped to begin</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2CO 11:29"/><char style="add">Every time that I hear about fellow believers</char> [RHQ] who are not strong <char style="add">spiritually</char>, I sympathize with them <char style="add">and try to help them. Every time that I learn about a fellow believer</char> [RHQ] who causes <char style="add">another believer</char> to do something wrong, that makes me very angry.<verse eid="2CO 11:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2CO 11:30"/>Because <char style="add">it seems that</char> it is necessary for me to <char style="add">continue</char> boasting <char style="add">about myself</char>, I will boast about things that <char style="add">caused some people to think of me</char> as being weak. <verse eid="2CO 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2CO 11:31"/>God, who is the Father of our <char style="add">(inc)</char> Lord Jesus, and who is the one <char style="add">whom we should</char> praise forever, knows that I am not lying <char style="add">about this</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2CO 11:32"/><char style="add">One time when I was</char> in Damascus <char style="add">city</char>, the governor whom King Aretas <char style="add">had appointed</char> to rule <char style="add">part of his area, told his soldiers</char> to guard <char style="add">the gates of</char> the city so that they could seize me <char style="add">if I tried to leave the city</char>. <verse eid="2CO 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2CO 11:33"/>But <char style="add">my friends</char> helped me to escape <char style="add">by</char> putting me in a large basket and lowering me <char style="add">to the ground by a rope</char> through an opening in the <char style="add">city</char> wall. <char style="add">That was really humiliating</char>!<verse eid="2CO 11:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="2CO 12"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 12:1"/>
    <char style="add">It seems that</char> I must go on boasting <char style="add">about myself</char>. Although <char style="add">I do</char> not <char style="add">think that my telling you about</char> this will help <char style="add">you to accept me as Christ’s representative to you</char>, I <char style="add">will say this anyway</char>. I will tell you about visions that the Lord <char style="add">gave a certain man</char> and about things that he <char style="add">supernaturally</char> revealed <char style="add">to that man. I will tell you this because some of the people among you boast that it was in visions that they received the things that they teach</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 12:2"/>The man that I will tell you about is one <char style="add">who believes</char> in Christ. Fourteen years ago he was taken {<char style="add">Christ</char> took him} up into the third heaven, <char style="add">the highest heaven, the place where God is</char>. I do not know whether he went there <char style="add">in his physical body</char> or whether he was outside of his body <char style="add">at that time and only his spirit went</char>. Only God really knows. <verse eid="2CO 12:2"/><verse number="3-4" style="v" sid="2CO 12:3-4"/>But he was <char style="add">suddenly</char> taken {<char style="add">Christ suddenly</char> took him} up to <char style="add">a place called</char> Paradise, <char style="add">that wonderful place where God lives. I repeat that</char> I do not know whether his body <char style="add">went there</char> or only his spirit. Only God knows <char style="add">that. While he was there, God</char> told him some things that he does not allow <char style="add">human beings</char> to tell <char style="add">others about</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:3-4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 12:5"/>I will proudly talk about that man. However, I will not be boasting <char style="add">as</char> I say that I <char style="add">am the one who saw and heard those wonderful things</char>. I will talk only about the things that <char style="add">cause others to think of</char> me as a weak <char style="add">human being like everyone else</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 12:6"/>But even if I should choose to boast <char style="add">to you about such wonderful things that happened to me</char>, I would not be <char style="add">speaking like</char> a fool, because I would be telling you the truth. But I will not <char style="add">talk proudly about such things</char>, because I do not want any of you to think highly of me <char style="add">because of the things that have happened to me</char>. Instead, <char style="add">I want you to decide what kind of person I am by the way you see</char> me <char style="add">acting</char> and by what you hear me teach. <verse eid="2CO 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 12:7"/>In order that I might not become proud because of those many wonderful things <char style="add">that Christ</char> revealed to me, <char style="add">God permitted</char> Satan to send a messenger <char style="add">to humble me</char> (OR, to <char style="add">make me sick</char>). <char style="add">What that messenger did to me was painful, like</char> [MET] a thorn pricking my body. <verse eid="2CO 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 12:8"/>Three times I prayed to the Lord about it, begging him to take this away from me. <verse eid="2CO 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 12:9"/>But he said to me, “<char style="add">No, I will not take this away from you. Instead</char>, I will kindly help you, and that will be all that you need, because it is <char style="add">when you are</char> weak that I <char style="add">can</char> best <char style="add">work</char> powerfully <char style="add">to help you</char>.” So, because of <char style="add">what the Lord said to me</char>, I will very gladly boast about <char style="add">the things that make</char> me <char style="add">seem</char> weak, so that <char style="add">people may realize</char> that it is Christ who gives me power <char style="add">to serve him</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 12:10"/>For that reason, <char style="add">whenever I am</char> weak, or <char style="add">when people</char> insult me, <char style="add">or when I have to endure</char> hardships, or <char style="add">when I am persecuted</char> {<char style="add">people</char> cause me to suffer}, or <char style="add">when I am in situations that</char> distress me, I am content because <char style="add">I am serving</char> Christ. <char style="add">I can say that</char> because at any time when I myself am weak, that is the <char style="add">very</char> time when <char style="add">Christ</char> powerfully <char style="add">helps me</char>.<verse eid="2CO 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When I was with you, I did things that showed you that I am truly Christ’s representative. But I still will not take pay from you when I come to visit you again. And those people are wrong who say that I tricked you by sending Titus to get money for myself from you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 12:11-18">2 Corinthians 12:11-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 12:11"/>It has been foolish for me <char style="add">to talk about myself like this</char>, but it is you who forced me to do it. Truly <char style="add">if the Lord would not help me</char>, I would be worthless, <char style="add">as my opponents say that I am</char>. But none of the men whom you <char style="add">wrongfully think</char> [IRO] are great apostles are greater in any way than I am. So it would have been right/proper for you to say good things about me. <verse eid="2CO 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 12:12"/><char style="add">You should have done that, because</char> when I was with you <char style="add">I</char> repeatedly did the things that showed you that <char style="add">I am truly</char> an apostle, such as performing many [DOU] miracles. <verse eid="2CO 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 12:13"/>And I have <char style="add">certainly treated</char> you as well as <char style="add">I treated</char> the other congregations <char style="add">that I helped to start. Or do you think that</char> by not asking you <char style="add">to pay me for my work</char>, I was not treating you as well as I treated the other congregations? ◄It is foolish for you to <char style="add">think that</char> [IRO] <char style="add">it</char> was wrong for me not <char style="add">to ask for pay from you for my work, and therefore I should ask</char> you to forgive me for that!/Do you <char style="add">think that it</char> was wrong for me not <char style="add">to ask for pay from you for my work, and therefore I should ask</char> you to forgive me for that?► [RHQ]<verse eid="2CO 12:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 12:14"/>Now listen to me! It is time for me to come to you for a third <char style="add">visit. When I come</char>, I <char style="add">still</char> will not insist that you <char style="add">pay me for my work</char>, because I do not want <char style="add">any of</char> your <char style="add">money</char> [EUP]! What I want is for you [MTY] <char style="add">to love and appreciate me</char>. It is not <char style="add">normally the duty of</char> children to save <char style="add">money to provide for the needs of</char> their parents. Instead, it <char style="add">is the duty of</char> parents to <char style="add">provide</char> for their children [MET]. In the same way, <char style="add">it is not your duty to provide for me. Instead, it is my duty to provide spiritual help for you because you are my spiritual children</char>. <verse eid="2CO 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2CO 12:15"/>So, for my part, <char style="add">as a good parent would do</char>, I will be very happy to use everything that I have, and do everything that I possibly can, <char style="add">in order to help you</char>. And because I love you very much, ◄I will be very disappointed if <char style="add">you</char> do not love me a little bit, too./will <char style="add">you</char> not love me a little bit, too?► [RHQ]<verse eid="2CO 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2CO 12:16"/>
    <char style="add">You all</char> know that I did not depend on you <char style="add">to provide for my needs</char>. However, <char style="add">there are some who accuse me, saying that</char> [IRO] I was very clever and got money from you by tricking you. <verse eid="2CO 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2CO 12:17"/>But did I ever do that? No! I never [RHQ] asked any of the men whom I sent to you <char style="add">to get money</char> from you <char style="add">and bring it to me</char> <verse eid="2CO 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2CO 12:18"/>Titus went <char style="add">and visited you because</char> I urged him to do so. I also sent the other believer, <char style="add">whom you know</char>, to go with Titus. <char style="add">You know that</char> Titus did not [RHQ] trick <char style="add">you in order to get money from you. And you certainly know that</char> he and I have always [RHQ] acted in exactly the same <char style="add">honest</char> way <char style="add">towards you</char>.<verse eid="2CO 12:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I am worried that when I visit you I will find that many of you are still sinning. I pray that God will help you turn from your sinful behavior, so that I will not have to discipline you when I come.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 12:19-13:10">2 Corinthians 12:19—13:10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2CO 12:19"/>While <char style="add">you have been reading this letter, if</char> you have been thinking that I have <char style="add">just</char> been <char style="add">saying these things to</char> defend myself <char style="add">against those who accuse me, you are wrong</char>. I have been saying <char style="add">these things honestly, knowing</char> that God is listening <char style="add">to me. I also speak as one who has a close relationship</char> with Christ. Everything that I do and <char style="add">everything that I say is</char> to <char style="add">help you</char> whom I love ◄to grow <char style="add">spiritually/</char> to become <char style="add">spiritually</char> mature►. <verse eid="2CO 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2CO 12:20"/><char style="add">I have written this way to you</char> because I worry that when I come <char style="add">to visit you</char>, I will see that <char style="add">some of</char> you are <char style="add">not conducting your lives the way</char> that I want you <char style="add">to</char>. If that is so, <char style="add">when I get there</char> you will see that I will have <char style="add">to act</char> in a <char style="add">very severe way toward you, and I am sure</char> that you do not want that. Specifically, I am afraid that <char style="add">some of you</char> may be quarreling, or that you are being jealous <char style="add">of each other</char>, or that you quickly get very angry <char style="add">with them</char>, or that you are acting selfishly, or that <char style="add">some of</char> you are saying bad things about others, or that you are ◄spreading false rumors/saying false things► about each other, or that you are acting proudly, or that you are <char style="add">doing things</char> in a disorderly manner. <verse eid="2CO 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2CO 12:21"/><char style="add">I</char> ◄<char style="add">feel anxious/am concerned</char>► <char style="add">about you. I worry that</char> when I visit you again, God, the one whom I <char style="add">serve</char>, will make me feel ashamed of you <char style="add">when I see that</char> you <char style="add">still are not conducting your lives as believers should</char>. Then I will feel very sad about <char style="add">some of</char> you who were sinning previously and have not stopped your sinful behavior. <char style="add">Some of you</char> may still have impure <char style="add">thoughts. Some of you</char> may be having sexual intercourse with those to whom you are not married. <char style="add">And some of you</char> may be doing other shameful things.<verse eid="2CO 12:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="2CO 13"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2CO 13:1"/>
    <char style="add">In the Scriptures it is stated that when one person</char> accuses <char style="add">another of wrongdoing, you must not believe his</char> accusation <char style="add">right away</char>. <char style="add">First, you must listen to at least</char> two or three people who actually saw what happened. <char style="add">So keep in mind that</char> this will be the third time that I will visit you! <verse eid="2CO 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2CO 13:2"/>When I visited you the second time, I warned you <char style="add">that I was going to punish all the wrongdoers among you</char>. <char style="add">And now</char> I am <char style="add">warning you</char> again while I am still away <char style="add">from you</char>. When I visit you this third time, I will punish those who were sinning <char style="add">at the time when I visited you</char> before <char style="add">and who are still sinning</char>, and I will <char style="add">punish</char> the others <char style="add">who have been sinning since then, if they have not stopped their sinful behavior</char>. <verse eid="2CO 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2CO 13:3"/>Because you have demanded that I prove to you that Christ is speaking <char style="add">to you when</char> I <char style="add">speak to you, I will show you that I speak to you as his apostle. Christ</char> does not approve of your sinful behavior. On the contrary, he will powerfully <char style="add">discipline you</char>. <verse eid="2CO 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2CO 13:4"/><char style="add">It is true that</char> Christ <char style="add">seemed to be</char> weak when he was crucified {when <char style="add">people</char> killed him by nailing him to the cross}. But <char style="add">it is also true that</char> he <char style="add">now</char> lives because God <char style="add">worked</char> powerfully <char style="add">to bring him back to life. Similarly</char>, as I <char style="add">serve</char> God, I also am a weak human <char style="add">being as Christ was</char>. But I also <char style="add">have a close relationship with</char> Christ <char style="add">who is now alive again</char>. And with his <char style="add">authority</char> I will use God’s power <char style="add">to discipline</char> you.<verse eid="2CO 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2CO 13:5"/>Each of you should ask yourself: “<char style="add">Do I</char> believe <char style="add">God’s message about Christ?</char>” Each of you should <char style="add">examine yourselves to</char> make sure that you truly do <char style="add">believe</char> in Christ <char style="add">and so truly belong to him</char>, and that <char style="add">his Spirit lives</char> in you <char style="add">(pl)</char>. When you examine yourselves <char style="add">in that way</char>, I am sure that you will [RHQ] say <char style="add">to me</char>, “Yes, of course we <char style="add">belong to</char> Christ.” <verse eid="2CO 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2CO 13:6"/>I am <char style="add">also</char> certain that you will know that I <char style="add">belong to Christ, just like you do</char>. <verse eid="2CO 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2CO 13:7"/>But <char style="add">because I do not want to have to punish you</char>, I am praying to God that he will help you not to do anything evil <char style="add">that would cause me to have to punish you. I pray this</char>, not in order that when people <char style="add">who say that I am not your apostle</char> realize <char style="add">that my ministry among you has been very successful, they will have to agree</char> that I do have authority from Christ. Instead, <char style="add">I pray this because I want</char> you to do what is right, even though that might mean that <char style="add">my opponents would think</char> that I do not have authority from Christ, <char style="add">since I would not have an opportunity to show my authority to discipline you</char>. <verse eid="2CO 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2CO 13:8"/><char style="add">If you do what is right, I will not discipline you</char>, <char style="add">because it would</char> not <char style="add">be right for me to do that if you are conducting your lives the way you should, like</char> God’s true <char style="add">message says that you should. What God asks me to do is to help people to know and obey his</char> true <char style="add">message</char>. <verse eid="2CO 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2CO 13:9"/>I am happy <char style="add">whenever</char> you are strongly <char style="add">trusting and obeying Christ, and because of that I do not have to use my authority to discipline you. It does not matter to me if that makes people think that I do not have any authority</char>. Truly, what I am praying for is that <char style="add">God</char> will <char style="add">help</char> you to completely change your conduct. <verse eid="2CO 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2CO 13:10"/>That is why I am writing these things while I am still away from you. <char style="add">What I want is that</char> when I visit you, <char style="add">you will already be conducting your lives as God wants you to</char>, and so I will not have to <char style="add">discipline you</char> severely, as the <char style="add">Lord Jesus Christ gave me</char> the authority to do. The authority that I have from the Lord is to help you to become <char style="add">spiritually</char> mature believers, not to cause you to stop <char style="add">trusting in him</char>.<verse eid="2CO 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I finish my letter with some advice. All of us here send you our greetings, and I pray that God will bless you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2CO 13:11-14">2 Corinthians 13:11-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2CO 13:11"/>Finally, my fellow believers, <char style="add">I say to you</char>, be joyful. Completely <char style="add">change how you conduct your lives</char>, and do what I have urged you <char style="add">to do</char>. Be united in what you think <char style="add">about the matters about which I have written to you</char>. Live peacefully <char style="add">with each other. If you do those things</char>, God, who <char style="add">enables you to</char> love <char style="add">each other</char> and be peaceful, will bless [MTY] you. <verse eid="2CO 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2CO 13:12"/>Greet each other affectionately as <char style="add">fellow members</char> of God’s family <char style="add">should</char>. <verse eid="2CO 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2CO 13:13"/>All God’s people <char style="add">here</char> send you greetings. <verse eid="2CO 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2CO 13:14"/><char style="add">I pray that</char> the Lord Jesus Christ will act kindly <char style="add">toward</char> all of you, in ways that you do not deserve, that God will <char style="add">show all of you how much he</char> loves you, and that the Holy Spirit <char style="add">will cause you to have good</char> fellowship <char style="add">with him and with each other</char>.<verse eid="2CO 13:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2CO 13"/>
</usx>
