<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2SA" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">2 SAMUEL</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 Samuel</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Samuel</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Sa</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of King David reigning over all of Israel. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 Samuel</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2SA 1"/>
  <para style="s1">David found out about Saul’s death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 1:1"/>After Saul died, David <char style="add">and the men who were with him</char> returned to Ziklag <char style="add">town</char> after defeating the descendants of Amalek. They stayed in Ziklag for two days. <verse eid="2SA 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 1:2"/>On the third day, unexpectedly a man arrived there who had come from where Saul’s army was camped. He had torn his clothes and put dust on his head <char style="add">to show that he was grieving</char>. He came to David, and prostrated himself on the ground <char style="add">in front of David to show respect for him</char>.<verse eid="2SA 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 1:3"/>David asked him, “Where have you come from?” The man replied, “I escaped from where the Israeli army had been camped.”<verse eid="2SA 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 1:4"/>David asked him, “What happened? Tell me <char style="add">about the battle</char>!” The man replied, “The Israeli soldiers ran away from the battle. Many of them were killed. And Saul and his son Jonathan ◄are dead/were also killed►.”<verse eid="2SA 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 1:5"/>David said to the young man, “How do you know that Saul and his son Jonathan are dead?”<verse eid="2SA 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 1:6"/>The young man replied, “It happened that I was on Gilboa Mountain <char style="add">where the battle occurred</char>, and I saw Saul, leaning on his spear. The <char style="add">enemy</char> chariots and their drivers had come very close to Saul. <verse eid="2SA 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 1:7"/>Saul turned around and saw me, and he called out to me. I answered him and said, ‘What do you want me to do?’<verse eid="2SA 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 1:8"/>He replied, ‘Who are you?’ I replied, ‘I am a descendant of Amalek.’<verse eid="2SA 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 1:9"/>Then he said to me, ‘Come over here and kill me. I am still alive, but I am enduring a lot of pain.’<verse eid="2SA 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 1:10"/>So I went to him and killed him, because I knew that he was wounded very badly and would ◄not continue to live/soon die►. I took the crown that was on his head and the band/bracelet that was on his arm, and I have brought them to you.”<verse eid="2SA 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 1:11"/>Then David and all the men who were with him tore their clothes <char style="add">to show that they were very sad</char>. <verse eid="2SA 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 1:12"/>They mourned for Saul and his son Jonathan, and they cried and ◄fasted/abstained from eating food► until it was evening. They also mourned for all the army of Yahweh, and for all the Israeli people, because many of their soldiers had been killed in the battle [MTY].<verse eid="2SA 1:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 1:13"/>Then David asked the young man who had told him <char style="add">about the battle</char>, “Where are you from?” He replied, “My father is a descendant of Amalek, but we live in Israel.”<verse eid="2SA 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 1:14"/>David asked him, “◄Why were you not afraid <char style="add">that you would be punished if you</char> killed Saul, whom Yahweh had appointed [MTY] <char style="add">to be the king</char>?/You should have been afraid <char style="add">that you would be punished if you</char> killed Saul, whom Yahweh had appointed [MTY] <char style="add">to be the king</char>.► [RHQ] <verse eid="2SA 1:14"/><verse number="15-16" style="v" sid="2SA 1:15-16"/>You yourself said, ‘I killed the man whom Yahweh appointed to be the king.’ So you have caused yourself to be guilty [MTY] of causing your own death!” Then David summoned one of his soldiers and said to him, “Kill him!” So the soldier killed him by striking him <char style="add">with a sword</char>.<verse eid="2SA 1:15-16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David’s song about Saul and Jonathan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 1:17"/>Then David composed/wrote this sad song about Saul and Jonathan, <verse eid="2SA 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 1:18"/>and he commanded that it be taught to the people of Judah. <char style="add">The song is called</char> ‘The Bow <char style="add">and Arrow</char>’ and it has been written in the Book of Jashar:<verse eid="2SA 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 1:19"/>“You Israeli people, your glorious [MTY] leaders have been killed on the mountains!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:19">
    <char style="add">It is very sad that</char> those mighty men have died!<verse eid="2SA 1:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 1:20"/>“Do not tell it <char style="add">to our enemies in the Philistia area</char>;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 1:20">do not tell to the people who live in Gath <char style="add">city</char> what happened;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:20">do not proclaim it in the streets of Ashkelon <char style="add">city</char>, because if you tell them, <char style="add">even</char> the women in that area will be happy;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:20">do not allow those ◄pagan women/women who do not know God► to rejoice.<verse eid="2SA 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 1:21"/>I hope/desire that there will be no rain or dew on the mountains of <char style="add">the</char> Gilboa <char style="add">area</char> [APO],</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 1:21">and that no grain will grow in the fields there,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:21">because there the shield of Saul, the mighty <char style="add">king</char>, fell on the ground.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 1:21">No one rubbed <char style="add">olive</char> oil on Saul’s shield;<verse eid="2SA 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 1:22"/>instead, it was stained with the blood of those whom he had killed,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:22">and the fat of mighty enemy soldiers was smeared on it.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 1:22">Jonathan [PRS] did not retreat carrying his bow <char style="add">and arrows</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:22">and Saul always <char style="add">defeated his enemies when he fought them</char> with his sword. [PRS, LIT]<verse eid="2SA 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 1:23"/>“Saul and Jonathan were loved and they pleased many people.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:23">They were together [LIT] while they lived and when they died.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 1:23">
    <char style="add">In battles</char> they were swifter than eagles and they were stronger than lions.<verse eid="2SA 1:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 1:24"/>“You Israeli women, cry about Saul;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 1:24">He provided beautiful scarlet/red clothes for you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:24">and he gave you gold ornaments/jewelry to fasten on those clothes.<verse eid="2SA 1:24"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 1:25"/>“<char style="add">It is very sad that</char> this mighty soldier has died!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:25">Jonathan has been killed on the mountains/hills.<verse eid="2SA 1:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 1:26"/>Jonathan, my dear friend, I grieve for you;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:26">you were very dear to me.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 1:26">You loved me in a wonderful manner;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:26">it was better than the way that a woman loves <char style="add">her husband and her children</char>.<verse eid="2SA 1:26"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 1:27"/>“It is very sad that those mighty men have died,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 1:27">and their weapons are now abandoned!<verse eid="2SA 1:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2SA 2"/>
  <para style="s1">David was appointed to be the king of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 2:1"/>Some time after that, David asked Yahweh, “Should I go back to <char style="add">live in</char> one of the towns in Judah?” Yahweh replied, “Yes, go up there.” Then David asked, “To which town should I go?” Yahweh replied, “To Hebron.”<verse eid="2SA 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 2:2"/>So David went up there, taking his two wives, Ahinoam who was from Jezreel <char style="add">city</char>, and Abigail, the widow of Nabal from Carmel <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="2SA 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 2:3"/>He also took the men who had been with him, and their families. They all started to live in villages near Hebron. <verse eid="2SA 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 2:4"/>Then the men of Judah came to Hebron, and <char style="add">one of</char> them poured olive oil on David’s head <char style="add">to show they were appointing him to be</char> [MTY] the king of the tribe [MTY] of Judah.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 2:4">When David found out that the people of Jabesh <char style="add">town</char> in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> had buried Saul’s body, <verse eid="2SA 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 2:5"/>he sent messengers to the men of Jabesh to tell them this: “I desire/hope that Yahweh will bless you for having shown, by burying the body of Saul your king, that you were loyal to him. <verse eid="2SA 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 2:6"/>Now I also desire/hope that Yahweh will faithfully love you and be loyal to you. And I will do good things for you because of what you have done <char style="add">for Saul</char>. <verse eid="2SA 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 2:7"/>Now, although Saul your king is dead, be strong and courageous, like the people of Judah, who have appointed me to be their king.”<verse eid="2SA 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ishbosheth was appointed to be the king of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 2:8"/>
    <char style="add">While this was happening</char>, Ner’s son Abner, the commander of Saul’s army, took Saul’s son Ishbosheth and went across <char style="add">the Jordan River</char> to Mahanaim <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="2SA 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 2:9"/>There Abner proclaimed that Ishbosheth was now the king of <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> and of the tribe of Asher and the region of Jezreel and the tribes of Ephraim and Benjamin. That meant that he was the king of all of the people of Israel.<verse eid="2SA 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 2:10"/>Ishbosheth was 40 years old when he started to rule over the people of Israel. He ruled them for two years. But the tribe of Judah ◄was loyal to David/wanted David to be their king►, <verse eid="2SA 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 2:11"/>and he ruled them for seven and a half years while he was living in Hebron.<verse eid="2SA 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The war between the armies of Judah and Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 2:12"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> Abner and the officials of Isbosheth went from Mahanaim <char style="add">across the Jordan River</char> to Gibeon <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="2SA 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 2:13"/>Joab, whose mother was Zeruiah, and some of David’s officials <char style="add">went from Hebron to Gibeon, and</char> met at the pool there. They all sat down, the one group on one side of the pool and the other group on the other side.<verse eid="2SA 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 2:14"/>Abner said to Joab, “Let’s tell some of our young men to fight each other!” Joab replied, “Okay!”<verse eid="2SA 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 2:15"/>So twelve men from the tribe of Benjamin fought for Ishbosheth, against twelve of David’s soldiers. <verse eid="2SA 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 2:16"/>Each of them grabbed the head of the man against whom he was fighting, and thrust his sword into that man’s side. The result was that all 24 of them fell down dead. So that area in Gibeon is now called ‘Field of Swords’.<verse eid="2SA 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 2:17"/>Then <char style="add">the others started to fight</char>. It was a very fierce battle. Abner and the men of Israel were defeated by David’s soldiers.<verse eid="2SA 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joab’s brother Asahel was killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 2:18"/>Zeruiah’s three sons were there <char style="add">on that day</char>: Joab, Abishai, and Asahel. Asahel was able to run very fast; he could run as fast as a wild gazelle/antelope. <verse eid="2SA 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 2:19"/>Asahel started to pursue Abner. He ran straight toward Abner, without stopping. <verse eid="2SA 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 2:20"/>Abner looked behind him, and said “Is that you, Asahel?” Asahel replied, “Yes!”<verse eid="2SA 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 2:21"/>Abner yelled at him, “Turn to one side or the other, <char style="add">and pursue someone else</char>!” But Asahel would not stop pursuing Abner.<verse eid="2SA 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 2:22"/>So Abner yelled at him again, “Stop ◄chasing after/pursuing► me! ◄Why should I kill you?/It would not be good for me to kill you!► [RHQ] If I did that, ◄how could I &lt;face/be reconciled with&gt; your brother Joab?/it would be very difficult for me to &lt;face/be reconciled with&gt; your brother Joab.► [RHQ]”<verse eid="2SA 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 2:23"/>But Asahel refused to stop pursuing Abner. So Abner <char style="add">suddenly turned and</char> thrust the butt end of his spear into Asahel’s stomach. Because he thrust it very strongly, that end of the spear <char style="add">went though Asahel’s body and</char> came out at his back, and he fell to the ground, dead. All the other soldiers who came to the place where his body was lying stopped and stood there, <char style="add">stunned</char>.<verse eid="2SA 2:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 2:24"/>But Joab and Abishai continued to pursue Abner. At sunset they came to Ammah Hill, which is east of Giah, along the road to the desert near Gibeon. <verse eid="2SA 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 2:25"/>The men from the tribe of Benjamin gathered around Abner in one group, and stood at the top of a hill.<verse eid="2SA 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 2:26"/>Then Abner called out to Joab, saying “Are we going to continue to fight forever [RHQ]? Do you not realize that <char style="add">if we continue fighting</char>, the result will be very bad [RHQ]? We are all descendants of Jacob. <char style="add">So we should stop fighting each other</char> ◄How long will it be until you tell your soldiers to stop pursuing us?/Tell your soldiers to stop pursuing us.►” [RHQ]<verse eid="2SA 2:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 2:27"/>Joab replied, “Just as surely as God lives, if you had not said that, my soldiers would have continued pursuing your men until tomorrow morning!”<verse eid="2SA 2:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 2:28"/>So Joab blew a trumpet <char style="add">to signal that they should stop fighting</char>. So all his men did that. They did not pursue the soldiers of Israel any more, and they stopped fighting.<verse eid="2SA 2:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 2:29"/>That night Abner and his soldiers went through the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley. They crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and marched all the next morning, and they finally arrived at Mahanaim.<verse eid="2SA 2:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 2:30"/>Joab <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> stopped pursuing Abner. And when he gathered all his soldiers together, he found out that in addition to Asahel, only 19 of them had been killed in the battle. <verse eid="2SA 2:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 2:31"/>But David’s soldiers had killed 360 of Abner’s men, all from the tribe of Benjamin. <verse eid="2SA 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 2:32"/><char style="add">Some of Joab’s soldiers</char> took Asahel’s body and buried it in the tomb where his father had been buried, in Bethlehem. Then they marched all during the night, and at dawn they arrived <char style="add">back home</char> at Hebron.<verse eid="2SA 2:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2SA 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 3:1"/>There was a long war between those who wanted Saul’s son to be their king and those who wanted David to be their king. But more and more people began to want David to be the king, while the number of people who wanted Saul’s son to be the king continued to become smaller.<verse eid="2SA 3:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David’s sons born at Hebron</para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 3:2"/>David’s wives gave birth to six sons at Hebron. The oldest was Amnon, whose mother was Ahinoam, from Jezreel <char style="add">city</char>.<verse eid="2SA 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 3:3"/>The next one was Kileab, whose mother was Abigail, the widow of Nabal, from Carmel <char style="add">city</char>.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="2SA 3:3">The next one was Absalom, whose mother was Maacah, the daughter of Talmai, the king of <char style="add">the</char> Geshur <char style="add">region</char>.<verse eid="2SA 3:3"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 3:4"/>The next one was Adonijah, whose mother was Haggith.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="2SA 3:4">The next one was Shephatiah, whose mother was Abital.<verse eid="2SA 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 3:5"/>The youngest one was Ithream, whose mother was Eglah, <char style="add">another one of</char> David’s wives.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="2SA 3:5">Those sons of David were all born in Hebron.<verse eid="2SA 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Abner decided that David would be king of all of them</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 3:6"/>While those who wanted Saul’s son to rule over them and those who wanted David to rule over them continued to fight against each other, Abner was becoming more influential among those who wanted Saul’s son to be the king. <verse eid="2SA 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 3:7"/>When Saul was alive, he had as one of his wives a slave woman named Rizpah, the daughter of Aiah. <char style="add">But one day Abner had sexual relations with her</char>. So Ishbosheth said to Abner, “Why have you had sexual relations with [EUP] my father’s slave wife?”<verse eid="2SA 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 3:8"/>Abner became very angry about what Ishbosheth said to him. He said to Ishbosheth, “◄Do you think that I am a <char style="add">worthless</char> dog [MET] from Judah?/You are treating me as though I am a <char style="add">worthless</char> dog [MET] from Judah.► [RHQ] From the beginning, I have been loyal to Saul your father, to his brothers, and to his friends. And I have prevented you from being defeated by David’s army. So now ◄why are you criticizing me about <char style="add">what I have done with</char> some woman?/you should not be criticizing me about <char style="add">what I have done with</char> some woman.► [RHQ] <verse eid="2SA 3:8"/><verse number="9-10" style="v" sid="2SA 3:9-10"/>Yahweh solemnly promised that he would not allow Saul and his descendants to continue to rule. He promised that he would cause David to rule over all the tribes of Israel and Judah, from Dan <char style="add">city</char> far in the north to Beersheba <char style="add">city</char> far in the south. So I hope/desire that God will punish me severely [HYP] if I do not enable that to happen!” <verse eid="2SA 3:9-10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 3:11"/>Ishbosheth was very afraid of Abner, so he did not say anything in reply to Abner.<verse eid="2SA 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 3:12"/>Then Abner sent messengers to David <char style="add">when he was at Hebron</char>, to say to him, “<char style="add">Either you or I</char> should be [RHQ] the ruler of this entire nation, <char style="add">but not Isbosheth. However,</char> if you make an agreement with me, I will help you by encouraging all the people of Israel to ◄be want you to be their king/start to support► you.” <verse eid="2SA 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 3:13"/>David sent back this reply: “Good! I am willing to make an agreement with you. But before that happens, there is one thing that you must do. When you come to see me, you must bring my wife Michal, Saul’s daughter.” <verse eid="2SA 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 3:14"/>Then David sent messengers to Ishbosheth, to say to him, “I <char style="add">had to kill</char> 100 men from Philistia <char style="add">and cut off</char> their foreskins to give to Saul to pay for Michal <char style="add">to be my wife</char>. So now give her back to me!”<verse eid="2SA 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 3:15"/>So Ishbosheth sent some men to take Michal from her husband Palti. But <char style="add">when they took her,</char> her husband followed them all the way to Bahurim <char style="add">town</char>, crying as he went. <verse eid="2SA 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 3:16"/>Then Abner <char style="add">turned and</char> said to him, “Go back <char style="add">home</char>!”, so he did.<verse eid="2SA 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 3:17"/>Abner went to the Israeli leaders and talked with them. He said, “For a long time you have wanted David to be your king. <verse eid="2SA 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 3:18"/>So now you have an opportunity to do that. Keep in mind that Yahweh promised this: ‘With the help of David, who serves me <char style="add">well</char>, I will rescue my people from the people of Philistia, and from the power [MTY] of all their other enemies’.” <verse eid="2SA 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 3:19"/>Abner also spoke to the people of the tribe of Benjamin. Then he went to Hebron, to tell David what all the people of Israel and the people of the tribe of Benjamin had agreed to do.<verse eid="2SA 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 3:20"/>When Abner came with 20 of his soldiers to see David at Hebron, David made a feast for all of them. <verse eid="2SA 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 3:21"/>Afterwards, Abner said to David, “Sir/Your majesty, I will now go and encourage all the people of Israel to accept you to be their king, as you have desired.” Then Abner left, peacefully.<verse eid="2SA 3:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joab murdered Abner</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 3:22"/>Soon after that, Joab and some of David’s other soldiers returned <char style="add">to Hebron</char> after raiding <char style="add">one of their enemies’ villages</char>, bringing with them a lot of things that they had captured. But Abner was not there at Hebron, because David had sent him safely home. <verse eid="2SA 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 3:23"/>When Joab and the soldiers who were with him arrived, someone told him that Abner had come there and talked with the king, and that the king allowed to go home safely.<verse eid="2SA 3:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 3:24"/>So Joab went to the king and said, “Why have you done that? Listen to me! Abner <char style="add">is your enemy, but</char> when he came to you, you allowed him [RHQ] to leave! <verse eid="2SA 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 3:25"/>Do you not know that he came to you to deceive you and to find out everything that you are doing, and all the places that you go to?”<verse eid="2SA 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 3:26"/>After Joab left David, he sent some messengers to get Abner. They found him at Sirah Well, and brought him back to Hebron, but David did not know that they had done that. <verse eid="2SA 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 3:27"/>So when Abner returned to Hebron, Joab met him at the city gate, and took him aside as though he wanted to speak with him privately. Then he stabbed Abner in the stomach <char style="add">with his knife/sword</char>. In that way he murdered Abner because Abner had killed [MTY] Joab’s brother Asahel.<verse eid="2SA 3:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 3:28"/>Later, after David heard what had happened, he said, “Yahweh knows that I and the people of my kingdom are not at all ◄responsible for/guilty of► murdering [MTY] Abner. <verse eid="2SA 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 3:29"/>I hope/desire that Joab and all his family will be punished [MTY] for doing that! I hope/desire that there will always be someone in his family who has sores, or someone who is a leper, or some man who is forced to do women’s work, or someone who is killed in a battle, or someone who does not have enough food to eat!”<verse eid="2SA 3:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 3:30"/>That is how Joab and his brother Abishai murdered Abner, because he had killed their brother Asahel in the battle at Gibeon.<verse eid="2SA 3:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 3:31"/>Then David said to Joab and to all Joab’s soldiers, “Tear your clothes and put on coarse cloth <char style="add">to show that you are sad</char>, and mourn for Abner!” And <char style="add">at the funeral</char>, King David walked behind <char style="add">the men who were carrying</char> the coffin. <verse eid="2SA 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 3:32"/>They buried Abner’s body at Hebron. And at the grave, the king cried loudly, and all the other people also cried.<verse eid="2SA 3:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 3:33"/>David sang this sad song to lament for Abner:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 3:33">“It is not right that [RHQ] Abner died like outlaws die!<verse eid="2SA 3:33"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2SA 3:34"/>No one tied his hands or put chains on his feet, <char style="add">like they do to criminals</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 3:34">No, he was murdered by wicked men!”<verse eid="2SA 3:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2SA 3:35"/>Then many [HYP] people came to David to tell him to eat some food before sunset, but David refused. He said, “I hope/desire that God will punish me severely [HYP] if I eat any food before the sun goes down!” <verse eid="2SA 3:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2SA 3:36"/>All the people saw what David did, and they were pleased. Truly, everything that the king did pleased the people.<verse eid="2SA 3:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="2SA 3:37"/>So all the people realized that the king had not wanted Abner to be killed. <verse eid="2SA 3:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="2SA 3:38"/>The king said to his officials, “◄Do you not realize that a leader and a great man has died today in Israel?/You should realize that a leader and a great man has died today in Israel.► [RHQ] <verse eid="2SA 3:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="2SA 3:39"/>Even though Yahweh appointed me to be the king, today I feel weak. These two sons of Zeruiah, <char style="add">Joab and Abishai</char>, are very violent; I cannot control them. So I hope/desire that Yahweh will punish them severely in return for this wicked thing that they have done!”<verse eid="2SA 3:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2SA 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Ishbosheth was murdered</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 4:1"/>When Saul’s son Ishbosheth heard that Abner had been killed at Hebron, <char style="add">he realized that he might also be killed</char>. He became discouraged, and all the Israeli people ◄trembled/became afraid►. <verse eid="2SA 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 4:2"/>Ishbosheth had two officers who were leaders of groups that raided other villages. <char style="add">They were brothers;</char> their names were Baanah and Rechab, sons of Rimmon from Beeroth <char style="add">town</char> in the tribe of Benjamin. Beeroth is in the area that had <char style="add">been assigned to</char> the tribe of Benjamin. <verse eid="2SA 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 4:3"/>But the people of Beeroth had fled to Gittaim <char style="add">town</char>, and they still live there.<verse eid="2SA 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 4:4"/>Saul’s son Jonathan had a son named Mephibosheth. When Mephibosheth was five years old, Saul and Jonathan died in the battle. When people brought that news from Jezreel, Mephibosheth’s nursemaid picked him up and ran away. She ran very fast, with the result that she dropped him, and his legs became crippled.<verse eid="2SA 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 4:5"/>One day, Rechab and Baanah left <char style="add">their home</char> to go to Ishbosheth’s house. They arrived there about noontime, when Ishbosheth was taking his midday nap. <verse eid="2SA 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 4:6"/>The woman who was the doorkeeper was sifting wheat. While doing that, she became sleepy, and fell asleep. So Rechab and his brother Baanah were able to creep in quietly.<verse eid="2SA 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 4:7"/>They entered Ishbosheth’s bedroom, where he was sleeping. They killed him <char style="add">with their swords</char> and cut off his head. They carried his head and walked all night through the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley. <verse eid="2SA 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 4:8"/>They took the head of Ishbosheth to David at Hebron. They said to him, “Here is the head of Ishbosheth, the son of your enemy Saul, who tried to kill you. Your majesty, today Yahweh has allowed you to get revenge on Saul and his descendants!”<verse eid="2SA 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 4:9"/>But David replied to them, “Yahweh is the one who has rescued me from all my troubles. And just as surely as Yahweh lives, what I am now saying is also true. <verse eid="2SA 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 4:10"/>When a messenger came to Ziklag and told me ‘Saul is dead!’ and he thought that the news that he was bringing to me was good news, I seized him and <char style="add">commanded one of my soldiers to</char> kill him. That was the reward I gave to him for his news! <verse eid="2SA 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 4:11"/>So because you two evil men murdered a man who is ◄innocent/has done nothing wrong► when he was sleeping on his bed in his own house, I will do something worse to you. I will surely [RHQ] get revenge on you two for murdering [MTY] him, and ◄wipe you/cause you to disappear► from the earth!”<verse eid="2SA 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 4:12"/>Then, following David’s orders, his soldiers killed the two men, and cut off their hands and their feet, and hung their bodies (OR, their hands and feet) <char style="add">on a pole</char> near the pool at Hebron. But they took the head of Ishbosheth and buried it <char style="add">respectfully</char> in the tomb of Abner, there at Hebron.<verse eid="2SA 4:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="2SA 5"/>
  <para style="s1">David became the king of all the Israeli tribes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 5:1"/>Then <char style="add">the leaders of</char> all the tribes of Israel came to David at Hebron, and said to him, “Listen, we have the same ancestors [IDM] that you do. <verse eid="2SA 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 5:2"/>In the past, when Saul was our king, it was you who led our Israeli soldiers <char style="add">in our battles</char>. You are the one to whom Yahweh promised, ‘You will be the leader [MET] of my people; you will be their king.’ ”<verse eid="2SA 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 5:3"/>So while Yahweh was listening, all those leaders of the people of Israel declared there at Hebron <char style="add">that David would be their king</char>. And David made a sacred agreement with them. They anointed him <char style="add">with olive oil to set him apart</char> to be the king of the Israeli people. <verse eid="2SA 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 5:4"/>David was 30 years old when he became their king. He ruled them for 40 years. <verse eid="2SA 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 5:5"/>In Hebron he ruled over the tribe of Judah for seven and a half years, and in Jerusalem he ruled over all the people of Judah and Israel for 33 years.<verse eid="2SA 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David’s army captured Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 5:6"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> King David and his soldiers went to Jerusalem to fight against the Jebus people-group who lived there. The people there thought that David’s army would not be able to capture the city, so they sent a message to David, saying “Your army will never be able to get inside our city! Even the blind and crippled people will be able to chase you away!” <verse eid="2SA 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 5:7"/>But David’s army captured the fortress on Zion <char style="add">Hill</char>, <char style="add">and later it was known as</char> David’s City. <verse eid="2SA 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 5:8"/>On that day, David said <char style="add">to his soldiers</char>, “Those who want to get rid of the Jebus people-group should go through the water tunnel <char style="add">to enter the city</char>. Then they can attack those people whom I [SYN] detest—<char style="add">and we will find out if any</char> blind and crippled people <char style="add">will be able to stop them</char>!” That is why people say, “Blind and crippled people cannot enter Yahweh’s temple.”<verse eid="2SA 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 5:9"/>
    <char style="add">After </char> David <char style="add">and his soldiers captured</char> the city with its strong walls around it, he lived there, and they named it ‘David’s City’. David <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> built the city around the fortress, starting where the <char style="add">land was ◄filled in/terraces► on the east side of the hill</char>. <verse eid="2SA 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 5:10"/>David continued to become more and more powerful/influential, because the Almighty Commander of the armies of angels was with/helping him.<verse eid="2SA 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 5:11"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> Hiram, the king of Tyre <char style="add">city</char>, sent ambassadors/messengers to David <char style="add">to talk about making agreements between their countries</char>. Hiram agreed to provide cedar trees <char style="add">to make lumber</char>, and also that he would send carpenters and masons, to build a palace for David. <verse eid="2SA 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 5:12"/>His doing that caused David to realize that Yahweh truly had appointed him to be the king of Israel, and that Yahweh was going to cause his kingdom to prosper, because Yahweh loved the Israeli people, whom <char style="add">he had chosen to</char> belong to him.<verse eid="2SA 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 5:13"/>After David moved from Hebron to Jerusalem, he took more slave women to be his second-class wives, and he also married other women. <char style="add">All of those women</char> gave birth to more sons and daughters. <verse eid="2SA 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 5:14"/>The names of the sons who were born in Jerusalem were Shammua, Shobab, Nathan, Solomon, <verse eid="2SA 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 5:15"/>Ibhar, Elishua, Nepheg, Japhia, <verse eid="2SA 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 5:16"/>Elishama, Eliada, and Eliphelet.<verse eid="2SA 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David’s army defeated the Philistines</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 5:17"/>When the Philistia people heard that David had been appointed to be the king of Israel, their army went up <char style="add">toward Jerusalem</char> to try to capture David. But David heard that they were coming, so he went down to another fortified place. <verse eid="2SA 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 5:18"/>The <char style="add">army of</char> Philistia arrived at Rephaim Valley <char style="add">southwest of Jerusalem</char> and spread all over the valley. <verse eid="2SA 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 5:19"/>David asked Yahweh, “Should <char style="add">my men and</char> I attack the Philistia army? Will you enable us to defeat them [IDM]?” Yahweh replied, “Yes, attack them, because I will certainly enable your army to defeat them. [IDM]”<verse eid="2SA 5:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 5:20"/>So David <char style="add">and his army</char> went to <char style="add">where the Philistia army was</char>, and there they defeated them. Then David said, “Yahweh has burst through my enemies like a flood.” [SIM] So that place is called ‘Lord of Bursting-through’. <verse eid="2SA 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 5:21"/>The Philistia men left their idols there; so David and his soldiers took them away.<verse eid="2SA 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 5:22"/>Then the Philistia <char style="add">army</char> returned to Rephaim Valley and spread all over the valley. <verse eid="2SA 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 5:23"/>So again David asked Yahweh <char style="add">if his army should attack them</char>. But Yahweh replied, “Do not attack them <char style="add">from here</char>. Tell your men to go around them and attack them from the other side, near the balsam trees. <verse eid="2SA 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 5:24"/>When you hear something in the tops of the balsam trees that sounds like <char style="add">an army</char> marching, attack them, because I will have gone ahead of you <char style="add">to enable your army</char> to defeat their army.” <verse eid="2SA 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 5:25"/>So David did what Yahweh told him to do, and his <char style="add">army</char> defeated the Philistia army from Geba <char style="add">city</char> all the way <char style="add">west</char> to Gezer <char style="add">city</char>.<verse eid="2SA 5:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="2SA 6"/>
  <para style="s1">They moved the sacred chest to Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 6:1"/>Then David chose 30,000 Israeli men and gathered them together. <verse eid="2SA 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 6:2"/>He led them to the place in Judah <char style="add">formerly</char> called Baalah, <char style="add">now called Kiriath-Jearim</char>. They went in order to bring from there <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> the sacred chest, which had the name of Yahweh, the leader of the armies of <char style="add">the angels in</char> heaven, written on it, and which had the <char style="add">statues of the</char> winged creatures on top of it. Between those statues was where Yahweh spoke messages about ruling his people [MTY]. <verse eid="2SA 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 6:3"/>The sacred chest was in the house of Abinadab, on top of a hill. They went there, and they put the chest on a new cart. Uzzah and Ahio, the two sons of Abinadab, were guiding <char style="add">the oxen that were pulling the cart</char>. <verse eid="2SA 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 6:4"/>Uzzah walked alongside the cart, and Ahio walked in front of it. <verse eid="2SA 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 6:5"/>David and all the Israeli men were celebrating in God’s presence, singing with all their strength and <char style="add">playing</char> lyres and harps, and beating tambourines, and clashing castanets and cymbals.<verse eid="2SA 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 6:6"/>But when they came to the place where Nacon threshed grain, the oxen stumbled. So Uzzah put his hand on the sacred chest to ◄steady it/prevent it from falling <char style="add">off the cart</char>►. <verse eid="2SA 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 6:7"/>Yahweh immediately became very angry with Uzzah, and he killed him right there alongside the sacred chest, because he had touched the chest, <char style="add">and Yahweh had commanded that only the descendants of Levi who help the priests should touch the sacred chest</char>.<verse eid="2SA 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 6:8"/>David was angry because Yahweh had punished Uzzah. So ever since that time, that place has been called ‘The Punishment of Uzzah’.<verse eid="2SA 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 6:9"/>David was <char style="add">also</char> afraid of <char style="add">what else</char> Yahweh <char style="add">would do to punish them</char>, so he said, “◄How can I take the sacred chest with me <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char>?/I am afraid to take the sacred chest with me <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char>.►” [RHQ] <verse eid="2SA 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 6:10"/>So he did not want to take the sacred chest to Jerusalem. Instead, they took it to another place; they took it to the house of Obed-Edom, from Gath <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="2SA 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 6:11"/>They left the sacred chest in the house of Obed-Edom for three months, and <char style="add">during that time</char> Yahweh blessed Obed-Edom and his family.<verse eid="2SA 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 6:12"/>Later, people told David, “Yahweh has blessed Obed-Edom and his family because <char style="add">he is taking care</char> of the sacred chest!” When David heard that, he <char style="add">and some other men</char> went to Obed-Edom’s house, and very joyfully brought the sacred chest from there to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2SA 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 6:13"/><char style="add">This time, descendants of Levi</char> were carrying the sacred chest, but when they had walked only six steps, they stopped, and there David killed a bull and a fat calf, and offered them to Yahweh for a sacrifice. <verse eid="2SA 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 6:14"/>David was wearing <char style="add">only</char> a linen cloth wrapped around his waist, and was dancing very energetically to honor Yahweh. <verse eid="2SA 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 6:15"/>David and the Israeli men took the sacred chest up <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char>, shouting <char style="add">loudly</char> and blowing trumpets.<verse eid="2SA 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 6:16"/>While they were carrying the sacred chest into the city, <char style="add">David’s wife</char> Michal, who was Saul’s daughter, looked out the window <char style="add">of her house</char>. She saw King David leaping and dancing to honor Yahweh. So she was disgusted with him.<verse eid="2SA 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 6:17"/>They brought the sacred chest into the tent that David had erected for it. Then David gave to Yahweh offerings to be completely burned <char style="add">on an altar</char>, and other offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. <verse eid="2SA 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 6:18"/>When David had finished offering those sacrifices, he asked Yahweh, the Commander of the armies <char style="add">of the angels</char>, to bless the people. <verse eid="2SA 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 6:19"/>He also distributed food to all the people. To each Israeli man and woman he gave a loaf of bread, some meat, and a raisin cake. Then all the people returned to their homes.<verse eid="2SA 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 6:20"/>When David went home to <char style="add">ask Yahweh to</char> bless his family, his wife Michal came out to meet him. She said to him, “Maybe you, the king of Israel, <char style="add">think that you</char> [IRO] were honoring yourself today, but really, you acted like a fool, uncovering yourself while the female servants of your officials were watching!”<verse eid="2SA 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 6:21"/>David replied to Michal, “<char style="add">I was doing that</char> to honor Yahweh, who chose me instead of your father and other members of his family, to be the king of the Israeli people, the people who belong to Yahweh. And I will <char style="add">continue to</char> dance to honor Yahweh! <verse eid="2SA 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 6:22"/><char style="add">Even though you think that what I did</char> was disgraceful, I will continue to do it even more. You may despise me <char style="add">because of what I did</char>, but the women whom you were talking about will honor me!”<verse eid="2SA 6:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 6:23"/>
    <char style="add">As a result,</char> Saul’s daughter Michal never gave birth to any children.<verse eid="2SA 6:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="2SA 7"/>
  <para style="s1">What God promised David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 7:1"/>After <char style="add">King</char> David began to live in his palace, Yahweh protected him from all his enemies. <verse eid="2SA 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 7:2"/>One day he said to the prophet Nathan, “<char style="add">It is not right that</char> I am here, living in a <char style="add">beautiful</char> house made of cedar <char style="add">wood</char>, but the chest that contains God’s Ten Commandments is kept in a tent!”<verse eid="2SA 7:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 7:3"/>Then Nathan said to the king, “Yahweh is helping/directing you, so do <char style="add">regarding that chest</char> whatever you are thinking.”<verse eid="2SA 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 7:4"/>But that night, Yahweh said to Nathan,<verse eid="2SA 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 7:5"/>“Go and tell my servant, David, that this is what <char style="add">I</char>, Yahweh, am saying to him: ‘You are not the one [RHQ] who should build a temple for me to live in. <verse eid="2SA 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 7:6"/>I have not lived in any building from the day that I brought the Israeli people up from Egypt until now. Instead, I have been living in a tent, moving from one place to another <char style="add">when the Israelis</char> moved to other places. <verse eid="2SA 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 7:7"/>Wherever I went with all the Israelis <char style="add">as they traveled</char>, I never said [RHQ] to any of their leaders whom I appointed to lead them, “Why have you not built me a temple made of cedar <char style="add">wood</char>?”’<verse eid="2SA 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 7:8"/>So this is what you should say to my servant David: ‘The Almighty Commander of the armies of angels says that he took you from a pasture where you were taking care of sheep, <char style="add">and appointed you</char> to become the ruler of my Israeli people. <verse eid="2SA 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 7:9"/>I have ◄been with/helped► you wherever you have gone. I have gotten rid of all your enemies as you advanced. I will enable you to become very famous, as well-known as the names of all the greatest men <char style="add">who have ever lived</char> on the earth. <verse eid="2SA 7:9"/><verse number="10-11" style="v" sid="2SA 7:10-11"/>Formerly, during the time that I appointed leaders for my Israeli people, many violent groups oppressed the Israelis. But this will not happen any more. I have chosen a place where my Israeli people can live <char style="add">peacefully</char> and no one will disturb them any more. I will give them rest from <char style="add">being attacked by</char> their enemies. And I will defeat all your enemies.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2SA 7:10-11">I declare to you that I, Yahweh, will enable your descendants to rule after you <char style="add">die</char>. <verse eid="2SA 7:10-11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 7:12"/>When your life ends [EUP] and you go to be with your ancestors, I will appoint one of your sons to be king, and I will enable his kingdom to ◄be strong/resist all their enemies►. <verse eid="2SA 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 7:13"/>He is the one who will arrange for a temple to be built for me [MTY], and I will cause his <char style="add">descendants</char> to be kings [MTY] <char style="add">of Israel</char> forever. <verse eid="2SA 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 7:14"/>I will be <char style="add">like</char> a father to him, and <char style="add">it will be as though</char> he <char style="add">is </char> a son to me [MET]. When he does something that is wrong, I will punish him as fathers punish their sons. <verse eid="2SA 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 7:15"/>But I will not stop faithfully loving him as I stopped loving Saul, whom I removed from being king before you became king. <verse eid="2SA 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 7:16"/>Your descendants will rule the kingdom <char style="add">of Israel</char> forever. Their rule will never end. [DOU]’ ”<verse eid="2SA 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 7:17"/>So Nathan told David everything that Yahweh had told him.<verse eid="2SA 7:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David gave thanks to God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 7:18"/>Then David went into <char style="add">the Sacred Tent</char> and sat in the presence of Yahweh, and prayed this:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="2SA 7:18">“Yahweh, my God, I am not worthy [RHQ] <char style="add">for you to have done all these things</char> for me, and my family is not worthy, either.<verse eid="2SA 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 7:19"/>“And now, O Yahweh my God, in addition to everything else, you have spoken about what will happen to my descendants in the future for many generations.<verse eid="2SA 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 7:20"/>“ Yahweh God, what more can I, David, say to you <char style="add">for honoring me</char>? Although you know very well <char style="add">what I am like</char>, Yahweh my God, you have done things for me as though I was the most important man <char style="add">on the earth</char>! <verse eid="2SA 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 7:21"/>For my sake and because it is what you wanted to do, you have done all these great things for me.<verse eid="2SA 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 7:22"/>“ Yahweh my God, you are great. There is no one like you. Only you are God, just as we have always heard. <verse eid="2SA 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 7:23"/>And there is no other nation in the world like Israel. Israel is the only nation on the earth whose people you went out to rescue [RHQ]. By the great and awesome things that you did, you have become famous/well-known throughout the world. As your people advanced <char style="add">through this land</char>, you expelled other people-groups <char style="add">who were here in Canaan</char>, who worshiped other gods. <verse eid="2SA 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 7:24"/>And you caused us Israeli people to be your people forever, and you, Yahweh, have become our God!<verse eid="2SA 7:24"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 7:25"/>“And now, Yahweh my God, <char style="add">I pray that you will</char> cause the things that you promised to me about my descendants to be fulfilled forever, and <char style="add">that you will</char> do the things that you said <char style="add">that you would do</char>. <verse eid="2SA 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 7:26"/>When that happens, you will become famous forever, and people will exclaim, ‘The Almighty Commander of the armies of angels is the God who rules Israel.’ And you will cause that forever there will be descendants of mine who will rule.<verse eid="2SA 7:26"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 7:27"/>“Yahweh Almighty, the God whom we Israeli people <char style="add">worship</char>, you have revealed to me that you will make some of my descendants kings. For that reason, I have been brave enough to pray like this to you. <verse eid="2SA 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 7:28"/>So now, O Yahweh Almighty, because you are God, we can trust that you will do what you promise. You have promised these good things to me. <verse eid="2SA 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 7:29"/>So now I ask you that if it pleases you, you will bless my descendants, in order that they may continue <char style="add">to rule</char> forever. Yahweh God, you have promised these things, and <char style="add">so I know that</char> you will keep blessing my descendants forever.”<verse eid="2SA 7:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="2SA 8"/>
  <para style="s1">David’s army won many victories</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 8:1"/>Some time later, David’s army attacked the Philistia <char style="add">army</char> and defeated them. They took control over the entire Philistia area.<verse eid="2SA 8:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 8:2"/>David’s army also defeated the army of the Moab people-group. David forced their soldiers to lie down on the ground <char style="add">close to each other</char>. His men killed two out of every three of them. The <char style="add">other</char> Moab people <char style="add">were forced to</char> accept David as their ruler, and they were forced to give to him <char style="add">every year the</char> payment/tax <char style="add">that he demanded</char>.<verse eid="2SA 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 8:3"/>David’s army also defeated <char style="add">the army of</char> Hadadezer, the son of Rehob, who ruled <char style="add">the state of</char> Zobah <char style="add">in Syria</char>. That happened when David went to rule again over the area at <char style="add">the upper part of</char> the Euphrates River. <verse eid="2SA 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 8:4"/>David’s army captured 1,700 of Hadadezer’s soldiers who rode on horses, and 20,000 of his other soldiers. They also crippled/hamstrung most of the horses that pulled the chariots, but they left/spared enough horses to <char style="add">pull</char> 100 chariots.<verse eid="2SA 8:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 8:5"/>When <char style="add">the army of</char> Syria came from Damascus <char style="add">city</char> to help King Hadadezer’s <char style="add">army</char>, David’s soldiers killed 22,000 of them. <verse eid="2SA 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 8:6"/>Then David stationed ◄groups of his soldiers/army camps► in their area, and the people of Syria were forced to accept David as their ruler, and to give to David’s government <char style="add">every year</char> the payment/tax that he demanded. And Yahweh enabled David’s <char style="add">army</char> to win victories wherever they went.<verse eid="2SA 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 8:7"/>David’s soldiers took the gold shields that were carried by Hadadezer’s officials, and brought them to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2SA 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 8:8"/>They also brought <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> a lot of bronze <char style="add">that they found</char> in Betah and Berothai, two cities that King Hadadezer <char style="add">had previously</char> ruled.<verse eid="2SA 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 8:9"/>When Toi, the king of the Hamath <char style="add">city in Syria</char>, heard that David’s <char style="add">army</char> had defeated the entire army of King Hadadezer, <verse eid="2SA 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 8:10"/>he sent his son Joram to greet King David and to ◄congratulate him/say that he was happy► about his army defeating Hadadezer’s army, which Toi’s <char style="add">army</char> had fought many times. Joram brought to David many items/gifts made from gold, silver, and bronze.<verse eid="2SA 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 8:11"/>King David dedicated all those items to Yahweh. He also dedicated the silver and gold which his army had taken from the nations that they had conquered. <verse eid="2SA 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 8:12"/>They had taken items from the Edom people-group and the Moab people-group, from the Ammon people-group, from the Philistia people, and from <char style="add">the descendants of </char> Amalek, as well as from the people that Hadadezer <char style="add">previously</char> ruled.<verse eid="2SA 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 8:13"/>When David returned <char style="add">after defeating the armies of Syria</char>, he became more famous because his army killed 18,000 soldiers from the Edom people-group in the Salt Valley <char style="add">near the Dead Sea</char>.<verse eid="2SA 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 8:14"/>David stationed ◄groups of his soldiers/army camps► throughout the Edom area, and forced the people there to accept him as their king. Yahweh enabled David’s <char style="add">army</char> to win battles wherever they went.<verse eid="2SA 8:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 8:15"/>David ruled over all the Israeli people, and he always did for them what was fair and just. <verse eid="2SA 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 8:16"/>Joab was the army commander; Jehoshaphat, the son of Ahilud, was the man who reported to the people everything that David decided that they should do; <verse eid="2SA 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 8:17"/>Zadok the son of Ahitub and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar were the priests; Seraiah was the official secretary; <verse eid="2SA 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 8:18"/>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was the commander of ◄David’s bodyguards/the men who protected the king►; and David’s sons were priests (OR, his administrators/advisors).<verse eid="2SA 8:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="2SA 9"/>
  <para style="s1">David was kind to Mephibosheth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 9:1"/>One day David asked, “Is there anyone who is a descendant of Saul to whom I can be kind?” He asked this because he wanted to honor Jonathan.<verse eid="2SA 9:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 9:2"/>
    <char style="add">They told him that</char> there was <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char> a man named Ziba who had been a servant of Saul’s family. So <char style="add">David sent messengers to summon Ziba. When he arrived</char>, the king asked him, “Are you Ziba?” He replied, “Yes, your majesty, I am.”<verse eid="2SA 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 9:3"/>The king asked him, “Is there anyone in Saul’s family to whom I can be kind, <char style="add">as I promised Jonathan that I would do</char>?” Ziba replied, “Yes, there is one son of Jonathan who is still <char style="add">alive</char>. His feet are crippled.”<verse eid="2SA 9:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 9:4"/>The king asked him, “Where is he?” Ziba replied, “He is <char style="add">living</char> in the house of Machir, son of Ammiel, in Lo-Debar <char style="add">city east of the Jordan River</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 9:5"/>So King David sent <char style="add">messengers</char> to bring Mephibosheth <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char>.<verse eid="2SA 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 9:6"/>When Mephibosheth came to David, he knelt down with his face on the ground, to show respect. Then David said, “Mephibosheth!” He replied, “Yes, your majesty, how may I serve you?”<verse eid="2SA 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 9:7"/>David said to him, “Do not be afraid; I will be kind to you because Jonathan your father <char style="add">was my loyal friend</char>. I will give back to you all the land that belonged to your grandfather Saul. And <char style="add">I want</char> you to always eat with me at my house [MTY].”<verse eid="2SA 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 9:8"/>Mephibosheth bowed <char style="add">in front of David again</char> and said, “Sir, I am <char style="add">as worthless as</char> [MET] a dead dog; I do not deserve [RHQ] that you be kind to me!”<verse eid="2SA 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 9:9"/>Then the king summoned Saul’s servant Ziba and said to him, “Saul was your master; now I am giving to Mephibosheth everything that belonged to Saul and his family. <verse eid="2SA 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 9:10"/>You and your 15 sons and your 20 servants must till/plow the land for Mephibosheth’s <char style="add">family</char>, and <char style="add">plant crops</char> and harvest them, in order that they will have food to eat. But Mephibosheth will eat food with me at my house.”<verse eid="2SA 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 9:11"/>Ziba replied to the king, “Your majesty, I will do everything that you have commanded me to do.” So <char style="add">after that</char>, Mephibosheth always ate at the king’s table, as though he were one of the king’s sons.<verse eid="2SA 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 9:12"/>Mephibosheth had a young son named Mica. All of Ziba’s family became servants of Mephibosheth. <verse eid="2SA 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 9:13"/>And Mephibosheth, who was still crippled in both of his feet, started to live in Jerusalem, and he always ate ◄at the king’s table/with the king►.<verse eid="2SA 9:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="2SA 10"/>
  <para style="s1">David’s army defeated the Ammon people-group</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 10:1"/>Some time later, the king of the Ammon people-group died, and his son Hanun became their king. <verse eid="2SA 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 10:2"/>David thought, “Nahash was kind to me, so I will be kind to his son.” So David sent some officials there, to tell Hanun that David was sorry that Hanun’s father <char style="add">had died</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 10:2">When those messengers arrived in the land where the Ammon people-group lived, <verse eid="2SA 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 10:3"/>the leaders of the Ammon people-group said to Hanun, “Do you think that it is to honor your father that King David has sent these men to say that he is sorry that your father died [RHQ]? <char style="add">We think that</char> he has sent them here to look around the city to determine how his <char style="add">army</char> can conquer us!” <verse eid="2SA 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 10:4"/>Hanun <char style="add">believed what they said; so he commanded some soldiers to</char> seize David’s officials and <char style="add">insult them by</char> shaving off one side of each man’s beard, and <char style="add">by</char> cutting off the lower part of their robes, <char style="add">with the result that their buttocks could be seen</char>, and then they sent them away.<verse eid="2SA 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 10:5"/>The men were very humiliated/ashamed, <char style="add">so they did not want to return home</char>. When David found out about what had happened to his officials, he sent someone to tell them, “Stay at Jericho until your beards have grown again, and then return home.”<verse eid="2SA 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 10:6"/>Then <char style="add">the leaders of</char> the Ammon people-group realized that they had greatly insulted [IDM] David [IDM]. So they sent some men to hire/pay some soldiers <char style="add">from other nearby areas to help defend them</char>. They hired 20,000 soldiers from <char style="add">the </char> Beth-Rehob and Zobah <char style="add">regions northeast of Israel</char>, and 12,000 soldiers from <char style="add">the </char> Tob <char style="add">region</char>, and 1,000 soldiers from <char style="add">the army of</char> the king of Maacah <char style="add">region</char>.<verse eid="2SA 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 10:7"/>When David heard about that, he sent Joab with all of the army <char style="add">that Joab commanded</char>, to fight against them. <verse eid="2SA 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 10:8"/>The soldiers of the Ammon people-group marched out and ◄stood in their positions/arranged themselves for battle► at the entrance <char style="add">to their capital city, Rabbah</char>. The other soldiers from Syria and Tob and Maacah stood by themselves ◄in their positions/arranged themselves for battle► in the nearby fields.<verse eid="2SA 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 10:9"/>Joab saw that there were groups of enemy soldiers in front of his troops and behind his troops. So he chose some of the best Israeli soldiers, and put them in positions to fight against the soldiers of Syria. <verse eid="2SA 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 10:10"/>He appointed his <char style="add">older</char> brother Abishai to be the commander of all the other soldiers, and he told them to ◄stand in their positions/arrange themselves► in front of <char style="add">the army of</char> the Ammon people-group. <verse eid="2SA 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 10:11"/>Then Joab said, “If the soldiers from Syria are too strong for us to defeat them, your men must come and help us. But if the soldiers from the Ammon people-group are too strong for you to defeat, we will come and help your men. <verse eid="2SA 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 10:12"/>We must be strong, and fight hard [IDM] to <char style="add">defend</char> our people and the cities <char style="add">◄that belong to/where we worship►</char> our God. I will pray/request that Yahweh do what he considers to be good.”<verse eid="2SA 10:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 10:13"/>So Joab and his army <char style="add">advanced to</char> attack the army of Syria, and the soldiers from Syria ran away from them. <verse eid="2SA 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 10:14"/>And when <char style="add">the soldiers of</char> the Ammon people-group saw that the soldiers from Syria were running away, they also started to run away from Abishai and his army, and they retreated back inside the city. So Joab’s <char style="add">army</char> stopped fighting against <char style="add">the army of</char> the Ammon people-group, and Joab <char style="add">and his army</char> returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2SA 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 10:15"/>After <char style="add">the leaders of</char> the army of Syria saw that the Israeli army had defeated them, they gathered all their troops together. <verse eid="2SA 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 10:16"/><char style="add">Their king,</char> Hadadezer, summoned the soldiers of Syria who lived on the east side of the <char style="add">Euphrates</char> River. They gathered at Helam <char style="add">city</char>. Their commander was Shobach.<verse eid="2SA 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 10:17"/>When David heard about that, he gathered all the Israeli soldiers, and they crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and marched to Helam. There, the army of Syria ◄took their positions/arranged themselves for battle►, and the battle started. <verse eid="2SA 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 10:18"/>But the soldiers of Syria ran away from the Israeli soldiers. David <char style="add">and his army</char> killed 700 of their chariot-drivers and 40,000 other soldiers. They also wounded Shobach, their commander, and he died there. <verse eid="2SA 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 10:19"/>When all the kings who had been ruled by Hadadezer realized that they had been defeated by the Israeli <char style="add">army</char>, they made peace with the Israelis and agreed to accept David as their king. So <char style="add">the army of</char> Syria was afraid to help <char style="add">the army of</char> the Ammon people-group any more.<verse eid="2SA 10:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="2SA 11"/>
  <para style="s1">David sinned with Bathsheba</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 11:1"/>
    <char style="add">In that region</char>, kings usually went <char style="add">with their armies</char> to fight <char style="add">their enemies</char> in the springtime. But the following year, in the springtime, David <char style="add">did not do that. Instead, he</char> stayed in Jerusalem, and he sent <char style="add">his commander</char> Joab <char style="add">to lead the army</char>. So Joab went with the other officers and the rest of the Israeli army. They <char style="add">crossed the Jordan River and</char> defeated the army of the Ammon people-group. Then they surrounded <char style="add">their capital city,</char> Rabbah.<verse eid="2SA 11:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 11:2"/>Late one afternoon, after David got up from taking a nap, he walked around on the <char style="add">flat</char> roof of his palace. He saw a woman who was bathing <char style="add">in the courtyard of her house</char>. The woman was very beautiful. <verse eid="2SA 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 11:3"/>David sent a messenger to find out who she was. <char style="add">The messenger returned</char> and said, “She is [RHQ] Bathsheba. She is the daughter of Eliam, and her husband is Uriah, from the Heth people-group.”<verse eid="2SA 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 11:4"/>Then David sent more messengers to get her. They brought her to David, and he ◄slept/had sex► [EUP] with her. (She had just finished performing the rituals to make herself pure <char style="add">after her monthly menstrual period</char>.) Then Bathsheba went back home. <verse eid="2SA 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 11:5"/><char style="add">After some time</char>, she realized that she was pregnant. So she sent a messenger to tell David <char style="add">that she was pregnant</char>.<verse eid="2SA 11:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 11:6"/>Then David sent a message to Joab. He said, “Send Uriah, from the Heth people-group, to me.” So Joab did that. He sent Uriah to David. <verse eid="2SA 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 11:7"/>When he arrived, David asked if Joab was well, and if other soldiers were well, and how the war was progressing. <verse eid="2SA 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 11:8"/>Then David, <char style="add">hoping that Uriah would go home and sleep with his wife,</char> said to Uriah, “Okay, go home and relax for a while. [IDM]” So Uriah left, and David gave someone a gift <char style="add">of some food</char> to take to Uriah’s house. <verse eid="2SA 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 11:9"/>But Uriah did not go home. Instead, he slept at the palace entrance with the king’s palace guards.<verse eid="2SA 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 11:10"/>When someone told David that Uriah did not go to his house <char style="add">that night</char>, David <char style="add">summoned him again and</char> said to him, “Why didn’t you go home <char style="add">to be with your wife last night</char>, after having been away for a long time?” [RHQ]<verse eid="2SA 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 11:11"/>Uriah replied, “The soldiers of Judah and Israel are camping in the open fields, and even our commander Joab is sleeping in a tent, and the sacred chest is with them. ◄How could I/It would not be right for me to► go home, eat and drink, and sleep with my wife [RHQ]. I solemnly declare [IDM] that I will never do such a thing!”<verse eid="2SA 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 11:12"/>Then David said to Uriah, “Stay here today. I will let you return <char style="add">to the battle</char> tomorrow.” So Uriah stayed in Jerusalem that day and that night. <verse eid="2SA 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 11:13"/>The next day, David invited him <char style="add">to a meal</char>. So Uriah had a meal with David, and David made him drink a lot of wine so that he would get drunk, <char style="add">hoping that if he was drunk, he would sleep with his wife</char>. But that night, Uriah again did not go home. Instead, he slept on his cot with the king’s servants.<verse eid="2SA 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 11:14"/>
    <char style="add">Someone reported that to </char> David, <char style="add">so</char> the next morning he wrote a letter to Joab, and gave it to Uriah to take to Joab. <verse eid="2SA 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 11:15"/>In the letter, he wrote, “Put Uriah in the front line, where the fighting is the ◄worst/most severe►. Then command the soldiers to pull back from him, in order that he will be killed <char style="add">by our enemies</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 11:16"/>
    <char style="add">So after</char> Joab <char style="add">got the letter</char>, as his army was surrounding the city, he sent Uriah to a place where he knew that their enemies’ strongest and best soldiers would be fighting. <verse eid="2SA 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 11:17"/>The men from the city came out and fought with Joab’s soldiers. They killed some of David’s officers, including Uriah.<verse eid="2SA 11:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 11:18"/>Then Joab sent a messenger to David to tell him about the fighting. <verse eid="2SA 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 11:19"/>He said to the messenger, “Tell David the news about the battle. After you finish telling that to him, <verse eid="2SA 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 11:20"/>if David is angry <char style="add">because so many officers were killed</char>, he may ask you, ‘Why did your soldiers go so close to the city to fight [RHQ]? Did you not know that they would shoot <char style="add">arrows at you while they were standing on top</char> of the city wall [RHQ]? <verse eid="2SA 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 11:21"/>Do you not remember how Abimelech, the son of Gideon, was killed? A woman <char style="add">who lived</char> in Thebez threw a huge ◄millstone/stone for grinding grain► on him from <char style="add">the top of </char>a tower, and he died. So why did your troops go near to the city wall?’ If the king asks this, then tell him, ‘Your officer Uriah also was killed.’ ”<verse eid="2SA 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 11:22"/>So the messenger went and told David everything that Joab told him to say. <verse eid="2SA 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 11:23"/>The messenger said to David, “Our enemies were very brave, and came out of the city to fight us in the fields. <char style="add">They were defeating us</char> but we forced them back to the city gate. <verse eid="2SA 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 11:24"/>Then their archers shot arrows at us from <char style="add">the top of</char> the city wall. They killed some of your officers. They killed your officer Uriah, too.”<verse eid="2SA 11:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 11:25"/>David said to the messenger, “Go back to Joab and say to him, ‘Do not be distressed <char style="add">about what happened</char>, because no one ever knows who will be killed in a battle.’ Tell him that the next time his troops should attack the city more strongly, and capture it.”<verse eid="2SA 11:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 11:26"/>When Uriah’s wife <char style="add">Bathsheba</char> heard that her husband had died, she mourned for him. <verse eid="2SA 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 11:27"/>When her time of mourning was ended, David sent messengers to bring her to the palace. Thus, she became David’s wife. She later gave birth to a son. But Yahweh was very displeased with what David had done.<verse eid="2SA 11:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="2SA 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Nathan rebuked David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 12:1"/>Yahweh <char style="add">told the prophet Nathan what David had done, and he</char> sent Nathan to tell <char style="add">this story to</char> David: “<char style="add">I heard about</char> two men <char style="add">who</char> were living in a certain city. One was rich and the other was poor. <verse eid="2SA 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 12:2"/>The rich man owned a lot of cattle and sheep. <verse eid="2SA 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 12:3"/>But the poor man had only one little female lamb, which he had bought. He raised the lamb, and it grew up with his children. He would give the lamb some of his own food and let it drink from his cup. He let the lamb sleep in his arms. The lamb was like a daughter to him.<verse eid="2SA 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 12:4"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> a visitor came to <char style="add">visit</char> the rich man. The rich man did not want to take one of his own animals <char style="add">and kill it</char> to prepare a meal for the visitor. So instead, he stole the poor man’s lamb <char style="add">and killed it</char> and prepared a meal for his visitor.”<verse eid="2SA 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 12:5"/>
    <char style="add">When</char> David <char style="add">heard that, he</char> was very angry about <char style="add">what</char> the rich man <char style="add">had done</char>. He said to Nathan, “I solemnly declare that the man who did that should be executed! <verse eid="2SA 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 12:6"/>But before he is executed, he should pay back to the poor man four lambs for doing this, and for not having pity <char style="add">on the poor man</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 12:7"/>Nathan said to David, “You are the man <char style="add">I have been talking about</char>! And this is what Yahweh, the God we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, says to you: ‘I appointed you to be king of Israel, after having rescued you from Saul. <verse eid="2SA 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 12:8"/>I gave you his palace and his wives. I caused you to become the king to rule Israel and Judah. If <char style="add">you had told me that</char> you were not content with what I gave you, I would have given you twice as much! <verse eid="2SA 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 12:9"/>So why have you despised my commandment <char style="add">about not committing adultery</char>? You have done what I consider to be very evil! You have arranged for Uriah to be killed in a battle by the Ammon people-group’s soldiers, and you have taken his wife to be your wife! <verse eid="2SA 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 12:10"/>You have despised me, and have taken Uriah’s wife to be your wife. So for many generations some of your descendants will die violently. [MTY, PRS] <verse eid="2SA 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 12:11"/>I solemnly declare to you that I will cause someone from your own family to bring trouble to you. I will take your wives and give them to him, and he will have sexual relations with them in the daytime, where everyone can see it, and you will know all about it. <verse eid="2SA 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 12:12"/>What you did, you did secretly, but what I will cause to happen, everyone in Israel will be able to see it <char style="add">or know about it</char>. [IDM]’”<verse eid="2SA 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 12:13"/>David replied, “I have sinned against Yahweh.” Nathan said to David, “Yahweh has forgiven you for your sin: You will not die <char style="add">because of this sin</char>. <verse eid="2SA 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 12:14"/>But, you have shown contempt for Yahweh by doing this. So, your baby will die.”<verse eid="2SA 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 12:15"/>Then Nathan went home.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="2SA 12:15">David’s baby died</para>
  <para style="m" vid="2SA 12:15">Then Yahweh caused the baby t o become very sick, the one that Uriah’s wife had given birth to. <verse eid="2SA 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 12:16"/>So David prayed to God that the child <char style="add">would not die</char>. He ◄fasted/abstained from food►, and he went into <char style="add">the room where he slept</char> and lay all night on the floor. <verse eid="2SA 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 12:17"/><char style="add">The next morning</char> his advisors stood around him and urged him to get up. But he would not get up, and he would not eat any food with them.<verse eid="2SA 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 12:18"/>One week later the baby died. David’s servants were afraid to tell that to David. They said <char style="add">to each other</char>, “Hey, while the baby was still alive, we talked to him, but he would not answer us. Now, if we tell him that the baby is dead [RHQ], he may do something to harm himself!”<verse eid="2SA 12:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 12:19"/>But when David saw that his servants were whispering something to each other, he realized that the baby must be dead. So he asked them, “Is the baby dead?” They replied, “Yes, he is dead.”<verse eid="2SA 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 12:20"/>Then David got up from the floor. He bathed himself, put lotions on his body, and put on other clothes, Then he went into Yahweh’s Sacred Tent and worshiped Yahweh. Then he went home. He asked his servants for some food. They gave him some, and he ate it.<verse eid="2SA 12:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 12:21"/>Then his servants said to him, “We do not understand [RHQ] why you have done this! While the baby was still alive, you cried for him and refused to eat anything. But now that the baby has died, <char style="add">you are not crying any more!</char> You got up and ate some food!”<verse eid="2SA 12:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 12:22"/>David replied, “While the baby was still alive, I fasted and cried. I thought, ‘Who knows? Yahweh may be merciful to me and not allow the baby to die’. <verse eid="2SA 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 12:23"/>But now the baby is dead. So ◄there is no reason for me to &lt;fast/abstain from eating food&gt; any more./why should I &lt;fast/abstain from eating food&gt; any more?► [RHQ] ◄Can I bring him back to me?/I certainly cannot bring him back to me!► [RHQ] <char style="add">Some day</char> I will go to where he is, but he will not return to me.”<verse eid="2SA 12:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 12:24"/>Then David comforted his wife, Bathsheba. Then he ◄slept/had sexual relations► with her, and she <char style="add">became pregnant again and</char> gave birth to another son. David named that son Solomon. Yahweh loved that little boy. <verse eid="2SA 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 12:25"/>He told the prophet Nathan to tell David to name the baby boy Jedediah <char style="add">which means ‘loved by Yahweh’,</char> because Yahweh loved him.<verse eid="2SA 12:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David’s army captured Rabbah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 12:26"/>◄Meanwhile/While all that was happening►, Joab’s <char style="add">soldiers</char> attacked Rabbah, <char style="add">the capital city</char> of the Ammon people-group; and they captured the king’s fortress. <verse eid="2SA 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 12:27"/>Then Joab sent messengers to David, to tell him this: “My troops are attacking Rabbah, and we have captured the city’s water supply. <verse eid="2SA 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 12:28"/>Now gather your troops and come and surround the city and capture it. If you do not do that, my troops will capture the city and it will then be named ‘the City of Joab’.”<verse eid="2SA 12:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 12:29"/>So David gathered all his troops. They went <char style="add">with David</char> to Rabbah and attacked it and captured it. <verse eid="2SA 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 12:30"/>Then David took the crown from the head of the king of Rabbah (OR, from the head of <char style="add">Milcom</char> the god of Rabbah) and put it on his own head. It <char style="add">was very heavy; it</char> weighed ◄75 pounds/34 kg.►, and it had many very valuable stones fastened to it. His soldiers also took many other valuable things from the city. <verse eid="2SA 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 12:31"/>Then they brought the people of Rabbah out of the city and forced them to <char style="add">work for them</char> using saws and iron picks and axes. David’s troops also forced them to make bricks. David’s soldiers did this in all the towns of the Ammon people-group. Then David and all of his army returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2SA 12:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="2SA 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Amnon raped Absalom’s sister</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 13:1"/>David’s son Absalom had a beautiful sister named Tamar. Another of David’s sons, Amnon, was attracted to Tamar. <verse eid="2SA 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 13:2"/>He wanted <char style="add">to have sex with</char> [EUP] his half-sister very much, with the result that he made himself sick <char style="add">thinking about her all the time</char>. But it was not possible for Amnon to get her, because she was a virgin, <char style="add">so they kept men away from her</char>.<verse eid="2SA 13:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 13:3"/>But Amnon had a friend named Jonadab, who was the son of David’s brother Shimeah. Jonadab was a very crafty/shrewd man.<verse eid="2SA 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 13:4"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> Jonadab said to Amnon, “You are the king’s son, but every day I see that [RHQ] you seem very depressed/sad. What is your problem?” Amnon replied, “I ◄am in love/want to sleep► [EUP] with Tamar, my half-brother Absalom’s sister.”<verse eid="2SA 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 13:5"/>Jonadab said to him, “Lie down on your bed, and pretend that you are sick. When your father comes to see you, say to him, ‘Allow my half-sister Tamar to come and give me some food to eat. She can prepare the food while I am watching her. Then she can serve it to me herself.’”<verse eid="2SA 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 13:6"/>So Amnon lay down, and pretended that he was sick. When the king came to see him, Amnon said to him, “<char style="add">I am sick;</char> please allow my half-sister Tamar to come and make a couple scones/dumplings for me while I am watching, and then she can serve them to me.”<verse eid="2SA 13:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 13:7"/>So David sent a message to Tamar in the palace, saying “Amnon <char style="add">is sick and he wants you to</char> go to his house and prepare some food for him.” <verse eid="2SA 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 13:8"/>So Tamar went to Amnon’s house, where he was lying in bed. She took some dough and kneaded it, and formed it into some scones/dumplings while he was watching her. Then she baked them. <verse eid="2SA 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 13:9"/>She took them out of the pan and put them <char style="add">on a plate</char> in front of him, but he refused to eat them. Then he said to everyone else in the room, “All the rest of you, leave me now!” So all the others left his <char style="add">room</char>.<verse eid="2SA 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 13:10"/>Then Amnon said to Tamar, “Bring the food into my room and serve it to me.” So Tamar took into his room the scones/dumplings that she had made. <verse eid="2SA 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 13:11"/>But when she brought them close for him to eat them, he grabbed her and said to her, “Come to bed with me!”<verse eid="2SA 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 13:12"/>She replied, “No, do not force me to do such a disgraceful thing! We never do things like that in Israel! That would be awful/terrible! <verse eid="2SA 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 13:13"/>As for me, if I did that, I would not be able to [RHQ] endure being disgraced by having done that. And as for you, everyone in Israel would condemn you for having done such a disgraceful deed. So I plead with you, talk to the king. I am sure that he will allow me to marry you.” <verse eid="2SA 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 13:14"/>But he would not listen to her. He was stronger than she was, so he forced her to have sex with him.<verse eid="2SA 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 13:15"/>Then Amnon hated her very much. He hated her much more than he had desired her. He said to her, “Get up and get out of here!”<verse eid="2SA 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 13:16"/>But she said to him, “No! It would be very wrong for you to send me away. It would be worse than what you just did to me!” But he would not listen to her.<verse eid="2SA 13:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 13:17"/>He summoned his personal servant and said to him, “Take this woman outside, away from me, and lock the door <char style="add">so that she cannot come in again</char>!” <verse eid="2SA 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 13:18"/>So the servant put her outside and locked the door.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 13:18">Tamar was wearing a long robe with long sleeves, which was the clothing that was usually worn by the unmarried daughters of the king at that time. <verse eid="2SA 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 13:19"/>But Tamar tore the long robe that she was wearing, and put ashes on her head <char style="add">to show that she was very sad</char>. Then she put her hands on her head <char style="add">to show that she was grieving</char>, and she went away, crying.<verse eid="2SA 13:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 13:20"/>Her brother Absalom <char style="add">saw her and</char> said to her, “Has your half-brother Amnon [DOU] forced you to have sex with him [EUP]? Please, my sister, do not tell anyone, and do not become depressed/sad.” So Tamar went to live in Absalom’s house, and she was very sad and lonely.<verse eid="2SA 13:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 13:21"/>When King David heard about all that, he became very angry. <verse eid="2SA 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 13:22"/>And Absalom hated Amnon, because he had raped his sister, so he would not speak to Amnon about anything.<verse eid="2SA 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 13:23"/>Two years later, Absalom’s servants were shearing sheep at Baal-Hazor, which is near <char style="add">a town named</char> Ephraim. <char style="add">When they finished shearing the sheep, they celebrated</char>, and Absalom invited all the king’s sons <char style="add">to come and celebrate</char>. <verse eid="2SA 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 13:24"/>Absalom went to the king and said to him, “Sir, my servants have been shearing my sheep. Please come with your officials <char style="add">to celebrate</char> with us!”<verse eid="2SA 13:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 13:25"/>But the king replied, “No, my son, it would not be good for all of us to go, because it would cause you to do a lot of work and spend a lot of money for food.” Absalom continued urging him, but the king would not go. Instead, he said that he hoped/desired that God would bless them <char style="add">while they celebrated</char>.<verse eid="2SA 13:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 13:26"/>Then Absalom said, “If you will not go, please allow my half-brother Amnon to go with us.” But the king replied, “Why <char style="add">do you want</char> him to go with you?”<verse eid="2SA 13:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 13:27"/>But Absalom continued to insist, so finally the king permitted Amnon and all David’s other sons to go with Absalom.<verse eid="2SA 13:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 13:28"/>
    <char style="add">So they all went. And at the celebration</char>, Absalom commanded his servants, “Notice when Amnon has become a bit drunk from the wine. Then when I signal to you, kill him. Do not be afraid; you will be doing this <char style="add">only</char> because I told you [RHQ] to do it. So be courageous and do it!” <verse eid="2SA 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 13:29"/>So Absalom’s servants did what Absalom told them to do. <char style="add">They killed Amnon</char>. All the rest of David’s sons <char style="add">saw what happened and</char> fled, riding on their mules.<verse eid="2SA 13:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 13:30"/>While they were on their way home, someone <char style="add">went quickly and</char> reported to David, “Absalom has killed all of your other sons; none of them is still alive!” <verse eid="2SA 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 13:31"/>The king stood up, tore his clothes <char style="add">because he was extremely sad</char>, and then he threw himself down on the ground. All the servants who were there also tore their clothes.<verse eid="2SA 13:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 13:32"/>But Jonadab, the son of David’s brother Shimeah, said, “Your Majesty, <char style="add">I am sure that</char> they have not killed all your sons. <char style="add">I am sure that</char> only Amnon is dead, because Absalom has determined to do this ever since the day that Amnon raped [EUP] his half-sister Tamar. <verse eid="2SA 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 13:33"/>So, your majesty, do not believe the report that all your sons are dead. <char style="add">I am sure that</char> only Amnon is dead.”<verse eid="2SA 13:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2SA 13:34"/>In the meantime, Absalom ran away.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 13:34">Just then, the soldier/sentry <char style="add">who was standing on the city wall</char> saw a large crowd of people coming down the hill along the road from Horonaim. <char style="add">He ran and told the king what he had seen</char>. <verse eid="2SA 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2SA 13:35"/>Jonadab said to the king, “Aha! What I told you is true. Your other sons <char style="add">are alive and</char> have come!”<verse eid="2SA 13:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2SA 13:36"/>And as soon as he said that, David’s sons came in. They all started crying, and David and all his officials also cried very much.<verse eid="2SA 13:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37-38" style="v" sid="2SA 13:37-38"/>But Absalom had fled. He went to stay with the king of <char style="add">the</char> Geshur <char style="add">region</char>, who was Talmai the son of Ammihud. Absalom stayed there for three years.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 13:37-38">David mourned for his son Amnon for a long time, <verse eid="2SA 13:37-38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="2SA 13:39"/>but after that, he desired very much to see Absalom, because he was no longer grieving about Amnon being dead.<verse eid="2SA 13:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="2SA 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Joab cleverly arranged for Absalom to return</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 14:1"/>Joab realized that the king yearned [IDM] to see Absalom. <verse eid="2SA 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 14:2"/>So Joab sent someone to Tekoa <char style="add">town</char> to bring back a woman who was very clever. <char style="add">When she arrived,</char> Joab said to her, “Pretend that you are grieving because someone has died. Put on clothes that show that you are mourning. Do not put any lotion/ointment on your body. Act as if you are a woman who has been mourning for a long time. <verse eid="2SA 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 14:3"/>And go to the king, and tell him what I tell you to say.” Then Joab told her what to say [MTY] <char style="add">to the king</char>.<verse eid="2SA 14:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 14:4"/>So the woman from Tekoa went to the king. She prostrated herself in front of him and then bowed down to him, and said, “Your Majesty, help me!”<verse eid="2SA 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 14:5"/>The king replied, “What is your problem?” She replied, “Please, sir, I am a widow. My husband died <char style="add">some time ago</char>. <verse eid="2SA 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 14:6"/>I had two sons. But one day they quarreled with each other out in the fields. There was no one to separate them, and one of them struck the other one and killed him. <verse eid="2SA 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 14:7"/>Now, all my family oppose me. They are insisting that I allow them to kill my son who is still alive [MTY], in order that they may get revenge for his killing his brother. But if they do that, I will not have any son to inherit <char style="add">my husband’s possessions</char>. That would be like [MET] extinguishing the last coals of a fire, and my husband would not have a son to preserve our family’s name. [DOU]”<verse eid="2SA 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 14:8"/>Then the king said to the woman, “Go back home; I will take care of this matter for you.”<verse eid="2SA 14:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 14:9"/>The woman from Tekoa replied to the king, “Your Majesty, if you are criticized <char style="add">for helping me</char>, my family and I will accept the blame. You and the royal family will ◄be innocent/not have done what is wrong►.”<verse eid="2SA 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 14:10"/>The king said to her, “If anyone says anything <char style="add">to threaten you/cause you trouble</char> you, bring that person to me, and <char style="add">I will make sure that</char> he will never cause you trouble again.”<verse eid="2SA 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 14:11"/>Then the woman said, “Your Majesty, please pray that Yahweh your God will not allow my relative, who <char style="add">wants to get</char> revenge on my son for killing [MTY] his brother, to be able to do that.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 14:11">David replied, “As surely as Yahweh lives, your son will not be harmed at all. [IDM]” <verse eid="2SA 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 14:12"/>Then the woman said, “Your Majesty, please allow me to say one more thing to you.” He replied, “Speak!”<verse eid="2SA 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 14:13"/>The woman said, “Why have you done this bad thing to God’s people? You have not allowed your son Absalom to return home. By saying what you have just said, you have certainly declared [RHQ] that what you have done is wrong. <verse eid="2SA 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 14:14"/>We all die; we are like [SIM] water that cannot be picked up after it is spilled on the ground. But God does not just cause us to die; he creates ways to bring us back when we become separated from him.<verse eid="2SA 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 14:15"/>“Now, Your Majesty, I have come to you because others have threatened me. So I said to myself, ‘I will go and talk to the king, and perhaps he will do what I request him to do. <verse eid="2SA 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 14:16"/>Perhaps he will listen to me, and save me from the man who is trying to kill my son. If my son is killed, it would result in us disappearing from the land that God gave to us.’<verse eid="2SA 14:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 14:17"/>“And I thought, ‘What the king says will comfort/encourage me, because the king is like [SIM] an angel of God. He knows what is good and what is evil.’ I pray/desire that Yahweh our God will ◄be with/direct► you.”<verse eid="2SA 14:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 14:18"/>Then the king said to the woman, “I will now ask you a question. Answer it, and tell me the truth. [LIT]” The woman replied, “Your majesty, ask your question.”<verse eid="2SA 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 14:19"/>The king said, “Was Joab the one who told you to do this?” She replied, “Yes, Your Majesty, as surely as you live, I cannot avoid telling you what is true. Yes, indeed, it was Joab who told me to come here, and who told me what to say. <verse eid="2SA 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 14:20"/>He did it in order to cause you to think differently about this matter. Your Majesty, you are as wise as God’s angels, and <char style="add">it seems that</char> you know everything <char style="add">that happens</char> on the earth, <char style="add">so you know why Joab sent me here</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 14:21"/>Then the king <char style="add">summoned</char> Joab <char style="add">and</char> said to him, “Listen! I have decided to do <char style="add">what you want</char>. So go and get that young man Absalom and bring him back <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 14:22"/>Joab prostrated himself on the ground, and then he bowed down before the king, and <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless him. Then Joab said, “Your Majesty, today I know that you are pleased with me, because you have agreed to do what I requested.”<verse eid="2SA 14:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 14:23"/>Then Joab got up and went to Geshur, and got Absalom and brought him back to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2SA 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 14:24"/>But the king said/commanded that Absalom would not be permitted to live in the palace. He said, “I do not want him to come to see me.” So Absalom lived in his own house, and did not go to <char style="add">talk to</char> the king.<verse eid="2SA 14:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 14:25"/>Absalom was very handsome. He looked perfect, from the bottom of his feet to the top of his head. In all of Israel there was no one whom people admired more than Absalom. <verse eid="2SA 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 14:26"/>His hair was very thick, and he cut it only once each year, when it became too heavy for him. Using the standard weights, he would weigh the hair <char style="add">that he cut off</char>, and it always weighed about five pounds. <verse eid="2SA 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 14:27"/>Absalom had three sons and one daughter named Tamar. She was a very beautiful woman.<verse eid="2SA 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 14:28"/>
    <char style="add">After</char> Absalom <char style="add">returned to</char> Jerusalem, he lived there two years, and during that time he never <char style="add">was allowed to</char> see the king. <verse eid="2SA 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 14:29"/>So he sent <char style="add">a messenger</char> to Joab to ask him to come <char style="add">and talk to him</char>, but Joab refused to come. So Absalom sent <char style="add">a message to him</char> a second time, but he still would not come.<verse eid="2SA 14:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 14:30"/>Then Absalom said to his servants, “You know that Joab’s field is next to mine, and that he has barley <char style="add">growing</char> there. Go and light a fire there <char style="add">to burn his barley</char>.” So Absalom’s servants <char style="add">went there and</char> lit a fire, <char style="add">and all his barley burned</char>.<verse eid="2SA 14:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 14:31"/>Joab <char style="add">knew who had done it, so he</char> went to Absalom’s house and said to him, “Why have your servants burned <char style="add">the barley in</char> my field?” <verse eid="2SA 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 14:32"/>Absalom replied, “Because <char style="add">you did not come to me when</char> I sent messages to you <char style="add">requesting that you come</char>. I wanted to request that you go to the king to say to him, ‘Absalom ◄wants to know what good it did/says that is was useless► [RHQ] for him [RHQ] to leave Geshur and come here. <char style="add">He thinks that</char> it would have been better for him to have stayed there. <char style="add">He wants you to</char> allow him to talk to you. And if you think that he has done something that is wrong, you can <char style="add">command that</char> he be executed.’” <verse eid="2SA 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 14:33"/>So Joab went to the king, and told him <char style="add">what Absalom had said</char>. Then the king <char style="add">summoned Absalom</char>, and he came to the king and knelt down in front of him with his face touching the ground. Then the king kissed Absalom <char style="add">to show that he was pleased to see him</char>.<verse eid="2SA 14:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="2SA 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Absalom rebelled against David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 15:1"/>Some time later, Absalom acquired a chariot and horses <char style="add">to pull it</char>. He <char style="add">hired</char> 50 men to run in front of him <char style="add">to honor him while he was riding around Jerusalem in the chariot</char>. <verse eid="2SA 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 15:2"/>Furthermore, he always rose early <char style="add">each morning</char> and stood by the city gate. Whenever someone came there with a dispute/quarrel that he wanted the king to decide, Absalom would call out to him, asking “What city are you from?” When the person told him what <char style="add">city and</char> tribe he was from, <verse eid="2SA 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 15:3"/>Absalom would say to him, “Listen, <char style="add">I am sure that</char> what you are saying/claiming is right. But there is no one whom the king has appointed/authorized to listen to <char style="add">people like</char> you.” <verse eid="2SA 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 15:4"/>Absalom would then add, “I wish that I were a judge in this land. If I were a judge, anyone who had a dispute could come to me, and I would decide it fairly/justly.”<verse eid="2SA 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 15:5"/>And whenever anyone came near to Absalom to bow respectfully in front of him, Absalom would reach out and embrace him and kiss him. <verse eid="2SA 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 15:6"/>Absalom did this to everyone in Israel who came to the king because of having a dispute with someone. In that way, Absalom persuaded all the Israeli people to be more pleased with him [IDM] <char style="add">than they were pleased with David</char>.<verse eid="2SA 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 15:7"/>Four years later, Absalom <char style="add">went to</char> the king and said, “Please allow me to go to Hebron <char style="add">city</char>, in order that I can do what I promised Yahweh that I would do. <verse eid="2SA 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 15:8"/>When I was living in Geshur, in Syria, I promised Yahweh that if he brought me back to Jerusalem, I would worship him <char style="add">in Hebron</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 15:9"/>The king replied, “You may go.” So Absalom went to Hebron.<verse eid="2SA 15:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 15:10"/>But <char style="add">while he was there,</char> he secretly sent messengers to all the tribes in Israel, to tell them, “When you hear the sound of the trumpets <char style="add">being blown</char>, shout ‘Absalom has become the king at Hebron!’ ” <verse eid="2SA 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 15:11"/>Absalom had taken with him to Hebron 200 men from Jerusalem, but they did not know <char style="add">what Absalom was planning to do</char>. <verse eid="2SA 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 15:12"/>While Absalom was offering sacrifices <char style="add">at Hebron</char>, he sent a message to Ahithophel, from Giloh <char style="add">town</char>, requesting him to come. Ahithophel was one of the king’s advisors. So the number of people who joined Absalom and who were ready to rebel <char style="add">against David</char> became larger.<verse eid="2SA 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David escaped from Jerusalem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 15:13"/>Soon a messenger came to David and said to him, “All [HYP] the Israeli people [SYN] are joining Absalom to rebel against you!”<verse eid="2SA 15:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 15:14"/>So David said to all his officials, “We must leave immediately if we want to escape from Absalom! We must go quickly, before he <char style="add">and his men</char> arrive. If we do not do that, they will kill us and everyone else in the city!”<verse eid="2SA 15:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 15:15"/>The king’s officials said, “Okay, your majesty, we are ready to do whatever you decide.”<verse eid="2SA 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 15:16"/>So the king left ten of his slave wives there to take care of the palace, but all the other people in his palace went with him. <verse eid="2SA 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 15:17"/>When they all were leaving <char style="add">the city</char>, they stopped at the last house. <verse eid="2SA 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 15:18"/>The king and his officials stood there while his bodyguards went by in front of him. 600 soldiers from Gath <char style="add">city</char> also walked by in front of him.<verse eid="2SA 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 15:19"/>Then David said to Ittai, <char style="add">the leader of the soldiers</char> from Gath, “◄Why are you going with us?/You should not be going with us.► [RHQ] Go back and stay with <char style="add">Absalom</char> the <char style="add">new</char> king. You are not an Israeli; you are living away from your own land. <verse eid="2SA 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 15:20"/>You have lived here <char style="add">in Israel</char> for only a short time [HYP]. And we do not even know where we will be going. So it is not right [RHQ] for me to force you to wander around with us. And take your troops with you. And I hope/wish that Yahweh will faithfully love and be loyal to you.”<verse eid="2SA 15:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 15:21"/>But Ittai replied, “Your Majesty, as surely as you live, wherever you go, I will go; I will stay with you, whether they kill me or allow me to live.”<verse eid="2SA 15:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 15:22"/>David replied to Ittai, “Okay, march with us!” So Ittai and all his troops and their families went <char style="add">with David</char>.<verse eid="2SA 15:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 15:23"/>All the people <char style="add">along the road</char> cried when they saw them walking by. The king and all the others crossed the Kidron Valley and then they all went <char style="add">up the hill</char> toward the desert.<verse eid="2SA 15:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 15:24"/>Abiathar and Zadok, <char style="add">the priests,</char> were walking with them. The descendants of Levi <char style="add">who helped the priests</char> also went with them, carrying the sacred chest that contained the Ten Commandments. But they set it on the ground until all the others had left the city.<verse eid="2SA 15:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 15:25"/>Then the king said to Zadok, “You and Abiathar take the sacred chest back into the city. If Yahweh is pleased with me, he will some day allow me to return to see it and the place where it is kept. <verse eid="2SA 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 15:26"/>But if he says that he is not pleased with me, then I am willing for him to do to me whatever he thinks is good.”<verse eid="2SA 15:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 15:27"/>He also said to Zadok, “Listen <char style="add">to what I suggest</char>. You and Abiathar return to the city peacefully/safely, and take your son Ahimaaz and Abiathar’s son Jonathan with you. <verse eid="2SA 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 15:28"/>I will wait in the desert at the place where people can walk across the river, until you send a message to me.” <verse eid="2SA 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 15:29"/>So Zadok and Abiathar carried the sacred chest back to Jerusalem, and they stayed there.<verse eid="2SA 15:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 15:30"/>David <char style="add">and those with him</char> went up Olive <char style="add">Tree </char> Hill. David was crying while he walked. He was walking barefoot and had something covering his head <char style="add">to show that he was sorrowful</char>. All those who were going with him also covered their heads and were crying while they walked. <verse eid="2SA 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 15:31"/>Someone told David that Ahithophel had joined with those who were rebelling against David. So David prayed, “Yahweh, cause whatever Ahithophel suggests to Absalom <char style="add">that he should do to be considered</char> to be foolish!”<verse eid="2SA 15:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 15:32"/>When they arrived at the top of the hill, where there was a place where the people worshiped <char style="add">God</char>, suddenly Hushai, from the Arki people-group, met David. He had torn his clothes and put dirt on his head <char style="add">to show that he was very sad</char>. <verse eid="2SA 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 15:33"/>David said to him, “If you go with me, you will not be able to help me. <verse eid="2SA 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="2SA 15:34"/>But if you return to the city, <char style="add">you can help me by</char> saying to Absalom, ‘Your Majesty, I will serve you as faithfully as I served your father.’ If you do that <char style="add">and stay near Absalom</char>, you will be able to oppose any advice that Ahithophel gives to Absalom. <verse eid="2SA 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2SA 15:35"/>Zadok and Abiathar the priests are already there [RHQ]. Whatever you hear people say in the king’s palace, tell it to Zadok and Abiathar. <verse eid="2SA 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2SA 15:36"/>Keep in mind that Zadok’s son Ahimaaz and Abiathar’s son Jonathan are also there. You can tell them whatever you find out, and send them to report it to me.”<verse eid="2SA 15:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="2SA 15:37"/>So David’s friend Hushai returned to the city, at the same time that Absalom was entering Jerusalem.<verse eid="2SA 15:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="2SA 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Ziba gave food to David and the others</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 16:1"/>When David <char style="add">and the others</char> had gone a little way past the top of the hill, Mephibosheth’s servant Ziba met him. He had with him two donkeys that were carrying 200 loaves of bread, 100 bunches/clusters of raisins, 100 bunches of fresh fruit, and a leather bag full of wine.<verse eid="2SA 16:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 16:2"/>The king said to Ziba, “What are these for?” Ziba replied, “The donkeys are for your family to ride on, the bread and the fruit are for your soldiers to eat, and the wine is for them to drink when they become exhausted in the desert.”<verse eid="2SA 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 16:3"/>The king said, “Where is Mephibosheth, the grandson of your <char style="add">former</char> master <char style="add">Saul</char>?” Ziba <char style="add">deceived David by</char> saying, “He stayed in Jerusalem, because he thinks that now the Israeli people will allow him to rule the kingdom that his grandfather Saul ruled.”<verse eid="2SA 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 16:4"/>The king said to Ziba, “Okay, everything that belonged to Mephibosheth is now yours.” Ziba replied, “Your Majesty, I will humbly serve you; and I desire/hope that you will always be pleased with me.”<verse eid="2SA 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Shimei cursed David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 16:5"/>When King David <char style="add">and those with him</char> arrived at Bahurim <char style="add">town</char>, a man named Shimei met him. Shimei, whose father was Gera, was one of Saul’s relatives. Shimei was cursing David as he approached. <verse eid="2SA 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 16:6"/>Then he threw stones at David and his officials, even though the officials and David’s bodyguards surrounded David. <verse eid="2SA 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 16:7"/>Shimei cursed David and said to him, “Get out of here, you murderer, you scoundrel! <verse eid="2SA 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 16:8"/>Yahweh is ◄getting revenge on/punishing► you all for murdering [MTY] many people in Saul’s family. And now he is giving Saul’s kingdom to your son Absalom. You murderer, you are being paid back for the many people that you have killed/murdered [MTY]!”<verse eid="2SA 16:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 16:9"/>Then Abishai said to the king, “Your Majesty, this man is <char style="add">as worthless as</char> [MET] a dead dog! ◄Why should he be allowed to curse you?/He should not be allowed to curse you.► [RHQ] Allow me to go over there and cut off his head!”<verse eid="2SA 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 16:10"/>But the king replied, “You two sons of Zeruiah, ◄do not tell me what to do/this does not concern you► [RHQ]. If he is cursing me because Yahweh told him to do that, certainly no one should say ‘◄Why are you doing that?/You should not be doing that.► [RHQ]’”<verse eid="2SA 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 16:11"/>Then David said to Abishai and to all his officials, “You know that my own son is trying to kill me. So <char style="add">it is not surprising that</char> this man from the tribe of Benjamin is also trying to kill me. So ignore him, and allow him to curse me, because <char style="add">perhaps he thinks that</char> Yahweh told him to do that. <verse eid="2SA 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 16:12"/>Perhaps Yahweh will see that I am having all this trouble, and <char style="add">some day he will repay me by</char> ◄blessing/doing good things for► me in return for this man cursing me today.” <verse eid="2SA 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 16:13"/>Then David and those who were with him walked along the road, and Shimei continued walking along the hillside near him. While he walked along, he cursed David and threw stones and dirt at him. <verse eid="2SA 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 16:14"/>When David and those who were with him arrived at the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, they were very tired. So they rested there.<verse eid="2SA 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ahithophel gave advice to Absalom</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 16:15"/>While that was happening, Absalom and all the Israeli people who were with him had arrived in Jerusalem. Ahithophel had also arrived there. <verse eid="2SA 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 16:16"/>When David’s friend Hushai came to Absalom, he said to Absalom, “I desire/hope that the king will live a long time! May you live for many years!”<verse eid="2SA 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 16:17"/>Absalom said to Hushai, “You have been loyal [RHQ] to your friend <char style="add">David for a long time</char>. So why did you not go with him <char style="add">instead of coming to me</char>?”<verse eid="2SA 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 16:18"/>Hushai replied, “I will serve the one whom Yahweh and these people and all the other people of Israel have chosen <char style="add">to be their king</char>. So I will stay with you. <verse eid="2SA 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 16:19"/>You are my master <char style="add">King David’s</char> son; if I do not serve you, what other man should I serve [RHQ]? I will serve you as I served your father.”<verse eid="2SA 16:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 16:20"/>Then Absalom said to Ahithophel, “What do you advise that we should do?”<verse eid="2SA 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 16:21"/>Ahithophel replied, “Your father left some of his slave wives in the palace to take care of it. Have sex [EUP] with them. When everyone in Israel hears that you have done that, they will realize that you are acting very contemptuously toward your father. Then all those who are with you will be very encouraged.” <verse eid="2SA 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 16:22"/>So they set up a tent for Absalom on the roof <char style="add">of the palace</char>. And Absalom went into the tent and had sex [EUP] with his father’s slave wives, <char style="add">one by one,</char> and everyone [HYP] could see <char style="add">him going into the tent</char>.<verse eid="2SA 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 16:23"/>In those days, people accepted what Ahithophel recommended as though he were speaking the words of God. So just as David had always accepted what Ahithophel said, now Absalom did also.<verse eid="2SA 16:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="2SA 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 17:1"/>Then Ahithophel said to Absalom, “Allow me to choose 12,000 men, and I will leave <char style="add">with them</char> tonight to pursue David. <verse eid="2SA 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 17:2"/>We will attack him while he is tired and discouraged, and cause him to be very frightened. All the soldiers who are with him will run away. We will kill only the king. <verse eid="2SA 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 17:3"/>Then we will bring back all his soldiers to you, like [SIM] a ◄bride/woman comes to her husband when she is married►. You are wanting to kill only one man; so the other people will not be harmed.” <verse eid="2SA 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 17:4"/>Absalom and all the Israeli leaders <char style="add">who were with him</char> thought that what Ahithophel said would be good to do.<verse eid="2SA 17:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 17:5"/>But Absalom said, “Summon Hushai also, and we will hear what he suggests.” <verse eid="2SA 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 17:6"/>So when Hushai arrived, Absalom told him what Ahithophel had suggested. Then he asked Hushai, “What do you think we should do? If you do not think that we should do what Ahithophel suggests, tell us <char style="add">what you think that we should do</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 17:7"/>Hushai replied, “This time what Ahithophel has suggested is not good advice. <verse eid="2SA 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 17:8"/>You know that your father and the men who are with him are strong soldiers, and that now they are very angry, like [SIM] a mother bear whose cubs have been stolen from her. Furthermore, your father knows how to fight because he has fought in many battles. He will not stay with his troops during the night. <verse eid="2SA 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 17:9"/>Right now he is probably already hiding in one of the pits, or in some other place. <char style="add">If his soldiers start to attack your soldiers, and</char> if they kill some of them, whoever hears about that will say ‘Many of the soldiers with Absalom have been killed!’ <verse eid="2SA 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 17:10"/>Then your other soldiers, even if they are as fearless [SIM, IDM] as lions, they will become very afraid. Do not forget that everyone in Israel knows that your father is a great/strong soldier, and that the soldiers who are with him are also very brave/courageous.<verse eid="2SA 17:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 17:11"/>“So what I suggest is that you summon all the Israeli soldiers, from Dan <char style="add">in the far north</char> to Beersheba <char style="add">in the far south</char>. They will be as many as the grains of sand on the seashore [HYP]. And then you yourself lead us into the battle. <verse eid="2SA 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 17:12"/>We will find <char style="add">your father</char>, wherever he is, and we will attack him <char style="add">from all sides</char>, like [SIM] dew covers all the ground. And neither he nor any of the soldiers who are with him will survive. <verse eid="2SA 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 17:13"/>If he escapes into some city, all our soldiers will bring ropes and pull that city down into the valley. As a result, not one stone will be left there <char style="add">on top of the hill where that city was</char>!”<verse eid="2SA 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 17:14"/>Absalom and all the other Israeli men <char style="add">who were with him</char> said, “What Hushai suggests is better than what Ahithophel suggested.” The reason that happened was that Yahweh had determined that if they would accept the good advice that Ahithophel had given them, <char style="add">they would have been able to defeat/kill David</char>. But <char style="add">as a result of their doing what Hushai suggested</char>, Yahweh would cause a disaster to happen to Absalom.<verse eid="2SA 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Hushai arranged for a report to be sent to David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 17:15"/>Then Hushai told the two priests, Zadok and Abiathar, what both he and Ahithophel had suggested to Absalom and the Israeli leaders. <verse eid="2SA 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 17:16"/>Then he said to them, “Send <char style="add">a message</char> quickly to David. Tell him to not stay at the place where people walk across the river, near the desert. Instead, he and his soldiers must cross <char style="add">the Jordan River</char> immediately, in order that they will not be killed/wiped out.”<verse eid="2SA 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 17:17"/>
    <char style="add">The priest’s two sons,</char> Jonathan and Ahimaaz, were waiting at En-Rogel <char style="add">Spring</char>, outside Jerusalem. They did not <char style="add">dare to</char> enter the city, because if someone saw them, <char style="add">he would report it to Absalom</char>. <char style="add">While they were at En-Rogel,</char> a female servant <char style="add">of the two priests</char> would frequently go to them and report to them <char style="add">what was happening</char>, and then they would go and report it to King David. <verse eid="2SA 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 17:18"/>But a young man saw them, and went and reported it to Absalom. <char style="add">They found out what the young man had done,</char> so both of them left quickly and went to stay in the house of a man in Bahurim. That man had a well in his courtyard; so the two men went down into the well <char style="add">to hide</char>. <verse eid="2SA 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 17:19"/>The man’s wife took a cloth/mat and covered the well, and scattered grain on top of it in order that no one would know <char style="add">that two men were hiding inside it</char>.<verse eid="2SA 17:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 17:20"/>Some of Absalom’s soldiers <char style="add">found out where the two men had gone. So they</char> went to the house, and asked the woman, “Where are Ahimaaz and Jonathan?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 17:20">She replied, “They crossed the river.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 17:20">So the soldiers <char style="add">crossed the river and</char> searched for them. But they could not find them, so they returned to Jerusalem. <verse eid="2SA 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 17:21"/>After they had gone, the two men came out of the well and went and reported to King David <char style="add">what had happened and</char> what Ahithophel had suggested. Then they said to him, “Cross the river quickly!” <verse eid="2SA 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 17:22"/>So David and all his soldiers quickly started to cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, and by dawn they had all crossed to the other side.<verse eid="2SA 17:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 17:23"/>When Ahithophel realized that Absalom was not going to do what he suggested, he put a saddle on his donkey and returned to his own town. He gave <char style="add">to his family</char> instructions about his possessions, and then he hanged himself <char style="add">because he knew that Absalom would be defeated and that he would be considered a traitor and be killed</char>. His body was buried in the tomb where his ancestors <char style="add">had been buried</char>.<verse eid="2SA 17:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 17:24"/>David <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> arrived at Mahanaim. And Absalom <char style="add">and all his Israeli soldiers</char> also crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="2SA 17:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 17:25"/>Absalom had appointed <char style="add">his cousin</char> Amasa to be the commander of his army, instead of Joab. Amasa was the son of a man named Jether, a descendant of Ishmael. Amasa’s mother was Abigail, the daughter of Nahash and the sister of Joab’s mother Zeruiah. <verse eid="2SA 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 17:26"/>Absalom and his Israeli soldiers set up their tents in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>.<verse eid="2SA 17:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 17:27"/>When David <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> arrived at Mahanaim, Shobi the son of Nahash from Rabbah <char style="add">city</char> in the Ammon area, and Machir the son of Ammiel from Lo-Debar <char style="add">city</char>, and Barzillai from Rogelim <char style="add">town</char> in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> <verse eid="2SA 17:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 17:28"/>brought sleeping mats, bowls, clay pots, barley, wheat flour, parched grain, beans, and lentils to them. <verse eid="2SA 17:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 17:29"/>They brought honey and curds, sheep, and some cream/cheese for David and his soldiers to eat. They knew that David and his soldiers would be hungry and tired and thirsty <char style="add">from marching</char> in the desert.<verse eid="2SA 17:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="2SA 18"/>
  <para style="s1">David’s men prepared for the battle</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 18:1"/>David arranged his soldiers for the battle. He divided them into groups, and appointed a commander for each 100 soldiers and a commander for each 1,000 soldiers. <verse eid="2SA 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 18:2"/>He sent them out in three groups. Joab commanded one group, Joab’s brother Abishai commanded a second group, and Ittai from Gath commanded the third group. David said to them, “I myself will go with you <char style="add">to the battle</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 18:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 18:3"/>But his soldiers said, “No, we will not allow you to go with us. If they force us all to run away, they will not be concerned about that happening. Or if they kill half of us, that will also not be what they want. To them, <char style="add">killing</char> you is more important than <char style="add">killing</char> 10,000 of us. So it will be better that you <char style="add">stay here</char> in the city and send help to us.”<verse eid="2SA 18:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 18:4"/>The king replied, “Okay, I will do whatever seems best to you.” So he stood at the gate <char style="add">and watched</char> while his soldiers marched out, group by group.<verse eid="2SA 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 18:5"/>
    <char style="add">While they were leaving,</char> the king commanded Joab, Abishai, and Ittai, “For my sake, do not harm my son Absalom!” And all the troops heard it when David gave that order about Absalom to those three commanders.<verse eid="2SA 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joab killed Absalom</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 18:6"/>So the army went out to fight against the Israeli soldiers <char style="add">who were with Absalom</char>. They fought the battle in the forest <char style="add">where people from the tribe</char> of Ephraim <char style="add">lived</char>. <verse eid="2SA 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 18:7"/>David’s soldiers defeated Absalom’s soldiers. They killed 20,000 of them! <verse eid="2SA 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 18:8"/>The battle was fought {They fought the battle} all over that area, and the number of men who died because of <char style="add">dangerous things in</char> the forest [PRS] was greater than the number of men who were killed ◄in the battle/by swords►.<verse eid="2SA 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 18:9"/>During the battle, Absalom suddenly came near <char style="add">some of</char> David’s soldiers. Absalom was riding on his mule; and when the mule went under the thick branches of a large oak tree, Absalom’s head/hair was caught in the branches. The mule kept going, but Absalom was left dangling in the air.<verse eid="2SA 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 18:10"/>One of David’s soldiers saw what happened, and went and told Joab, “I saw Absalom hanging in an oak tree!”<verse eid="2SA 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 18:11"/>Joab said to the man, “What? You say that you saw him hanging there, so why did you not kill him immediately [RHQ]? <char style="add">If you had killed him,</char> I would have given you ten pieces of silver and a belt!”<verse eid="2SA 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 18:12"/>The man replied to Joab, “Even if you gave me 1,000 pieces of silver, I would not have done anything to harm [IDM] the king’s son. We all heard the king command you and Abishai and Ittai, ‘For my sake, do not harm my son Absalom!’ <verse eid="2SA 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 18:13"/>If I had disobeyed the king and killed Absalom, the king would have heard about it, because the king hears about everything, and even you would not have defended me!”<verse eid="2SA 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 18:14"/>Joab said, “I am not going to waste time talking to you!” Then he took three spears <char style="add">and went to where Absalom was</char>, and thrust them into Absalom’s chest/heart while he was still alive, dangling from the oak tree. <verse eid="2SA 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 18:15"/>Then ten young men who carried weapons for Joab surrounded Absalom and <char style="add">finished</char> killing him.<verse eid="2SA 18:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 18:16"/>Then Joab blew his trumpet <char style="add">to signal that they should not fight any more</char>, and his soldiers returned from pursuing those Israeli soldiers. <verse eid="2SA 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 18:17"/>They took Absalom’s body and threw it into a huge pit in the forest, and covered it with a huge pile of stones. Then all the remaining Israeli soldiers <char style="add">who had been with Absalom</char> fled to their own towns.<verse eid="2SA 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 18:18"/>Absalom had no sons to preserve his <char style="add">family</char> name. So, while Absalom was alive, he built a monument to himself in the King’s Valley <char style="add">near Jerusalem, in order that people would remember him</char>. He put his name on the monument, and people still call it Absalom’s monument.<verse eid="2SA 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The report of Absalom’s death reached David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 18:19"/>
    <char style="add">After Absalom had been killed,</char> Zadok’s son Ahimaaz said to Joab, “Allow me to run to the king to tell him the good news that Yahweh has rescued him from the power of his enemies!”<verse eid="2SA 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 18:20"/>But Joab said to him, “No, I will not allow you to take news to the king today. Some other day I will allow you to take some news, but not today. <char style="add">If you took news today it would not be good news for the king,</char> because his son is dead.”<verse eid="2SA 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 18:21"/>Then Joab said to David’s servant who was from Ethiopia, “You go and tell the king what you have seen.” So the man from Ethiopia bowed in front of Joab, and started to run.<verse eid="2SA 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 18:22"/>Then Ahimaaz said again to Joab, “Even though <char style="add">that man from Ethiopia is running</char>, allow me to run behind him.” Joab replied, “My boy/son, why do you want to do that? You will not receive any reward for your news!”<verse eid="2SA 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 18:23"/>But Ahimaaz replied, “That does not matter, I want to go.” So Joab said, “Okay, go.” So Ahimaaz ran along <char style="add">another</char> road through the Jordan Valley and arrived <char style="add">where David was</char> before the man from Ethiopia arrived.<verse eid="2SA 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 18:24"/>David was sitting between the outer gate and the inner gate <char style="add">of the city</char>. The watchman/lookout went up on top of the city wall and stood on the roof over the gates. He looked out and saw one man running alone. <verse eid="2SA 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 18:25"/>The watchman called down and reported it to the king. The king said, “If he is alone, <char style="add">that indicates/means that</char> he is bringing <char style="add">good</char> news.” The man who was running continued to come closer.<verse eid="2SA 18:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 18:26"/>Then the watchman saw another man running. So he called down to the gatekeeper, “Look! There is another man running!” And the king said, “He also is bringing <char style="add">some good</char> news.”<verse eid="2SA 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 18:27"/>The watchman said, “I think the first man <char style="add">must be Ahimaaz, because he</char> is running like Ahimaaz runs.” The king said, “He is a good man, and <char style="add">I am sure</char> he is coming with good news.”<verse eid="2SA 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 18:28"/>
    <char style="add">When</char> Ahimaaz <char style="add">reached the king, he</char> called out “I hope/desire that things will go well with you!” Then he prostrated himself on the ground in front of the king and said, “Your Majesty, praise Yahweh our God, who has rescued you from the men who were rebelling against you!”<verse eid="2SA 18:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 18:29"/>The king said, “Is the young man Absalom safe/all right?” Ahimaaz <char style="add">did not want to answer that question, so he</char> replied, “When Joab sent me, I saw that there was a lot of confusion, but I do not know what it was about.”<verse eid="2SA 18:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 18:30"/>Then the king said, “Stand aside.” So Ahimaaz stepped aside and stood there.<verse eid="2SA 18:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 18:31"/>Suddenly the man from Ethiopia arrived, and said, “Your Majesty, I have good news for you! Yahweh has enabled your soldiers to defeat all those who rebelled against you!”<verse eid="2SA 18:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 18:32"/>The king said to him, “Is the young man Absalom safe/all right?” And the man from Ethiopia replied, “Sir, I wish/desire that what happened to him would happen to all of your enemies and to all those who rebel against you!”<verse eid="2SA 18:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 18:33"/>The king <char style="add">realized that he meant that Absalom was dead, so he</char> became ◄extremely distressed/overcome with grief►, and he went up to the room above the gateway and cried. While he was going up, he kept crying out, “O, my son Absalom! My son! O, my son Absalom, I desire/wish that I had died instead of you!”<verse eid="2SA 18:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="2SA 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Joab rebuked the king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 19:1"/>Someone told Joab that the king was crying and mourning because Absalom had died. <verse eid="2SA 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 19:2"/>All of David’s soldiers became sad. Instead of rejoicing about defeating <char style="add">the soldiers who had fought with Absalom</char>, they were sad because they heard that the king was mourning because Absalom <char style="add">was dead</char>. <verse eid="2SA 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 19:3"/>The soldiers returned to the city quietly, like [SIM] soldiers do when they are ashamed because they ran away from battle. <verse eid="2SA 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 19:4"/>The king covered his face <char style="add">with his hands</char> and kept crying loudly, “O, my son Absalom! O, Absalom, my son! My son!”<verse eid="2SA 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 19:5"/>Then Joab entered the room where the king was, and said to the king, “Today you have caused your soldiers to be ashamed! You have humiliated the men who saved your life and the lives of your sons and daughters and your ordinary wives and your slave wives! <verse eid="2SA 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 19:6"/><char style="add">It seems that</char> you love those who hate you and <char style="add">that</char> you hate those who love you. You have caused it to be clear today that your commanders and your officers are not at all important to you. I think that if Absalom were still alive and we were all dead today, you would be happy. <verse eid="2SA 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 19:7"/>So, now go and thank your soldiers <char style="add">for what they did</char>. Because I solemnly declare that if you do not do that, none of them will still be with you by tomorrow morning and that would be worse <char style="add">for you</char> than all the disasters/troubles that you have experienced since you were a boy.”<verse eid="2SA 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 19:8"/>So the king got up and went and sat near the city gate. And all the people were told, “Hey, the king is sitting at the gate!” So they all came and gathered around him.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="2SA 19:8">The people of Israel and Judah wanted David to be their king again</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 19:8">Meanwhile, all the Israeli troops <char style="add">who had been with Absalom</char> had returned to their homes.<verse eid="2SA 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 19:9"/>Then all the people throughout the tribes of Israel started to quarrel among themselves. They said to each other, “King David rescued us from the people of Philistia and from our other enemies. But now he has fled from Absalom and left Israel! <verse eid="2SA 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 19:10"/>We appointed [MTY] Absalom to be our king, but he died in the battle <char style="add">against David’s soldiers</char>. So ◄why does someone not try to bring King David back?/surely someone should try to bring King David back.►” [RHQ]<verse eid="2SA 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 19:11"/>King David <char style="add">found out what the people were saying. So he</char> sent the two priests, Zadok and Abiathar, to say to the leaders of Judah, “The king says that he has heard that all the Israeli people <char style="add">want him to be king again</char>. And he says, ‘◄Why should you be the last ones to bring me back to my palace?/It is not right that you be the last ones to bring me back to my palace.► [RHQ] <verse eid="2SA 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 19:12"/>You are my relatives; we have the same ancestor [IDM]. So ◄why should you be the last ones to bring me back?/you should certainly not be the last ones to bring me back.► [RHQ]’” <verse eid="2SA 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 19:13"/>And say to Amasa, “You are one of my relatives. I hope/desire that God strike me dead [IDM] if I do not appoint you to be, from now on, the commander of my army instead of Joab.”<verse eid="2SA 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 19:14"/>
    <char style="add">By sending that message to them,</char> David convinced all the people of Judah [IDM] <char style="add">that they should ◄be loyal to him/accept him as their king</char>►. So they sent a message to the king, saying “We want you and all your officials to return here.” <verse eid="2SA 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 19:15"/>So the king <char style="add">and his officials started back toward Jerusalem</char>. When they reached the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, the people of Judah came there to Gilgal to meet the king, and to bring him across the river.<verse eid="2SA 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 19:16"/>Shimei, the man from the tribe of Benjamin, also came down quickly <char style="add">to the river</char> with the people of Judah to meet King David. <verse eid="2SA 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 19:17"/>There were 1,000 men from the tribe of Benjamin who came with him. And Ziba, who had been the servant of Saul, also hurried down to the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, bringing 20 of his servants with him. They all came to the king, <verse eid="2SA 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 19:18"/>and then they all <char style="add">prepared to</char> take the king and all his family across the river, at the place where they could walk across it. They wanted to do whatever the king wanted them to do. As the king was about to cross the river, Shimei came to him and prostrated himself in front of the king.<verse eid="2SA 19:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 19:19"/>He said to the king, “Your Majesty, please forgive me. Please do not keep thinking about the terrible thing that I did on the day that you left Jerusalem. Do not think about it any more. <verse eid="2SA 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 19:20"/>Because I know that I have sinned. Look, I have come today, the first one from the northern tribes to come here to greet you today, Your Majesty.”<verse eid="2SA 19:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 19:21"/>But Abishai, the son of Zeruiah, said, “He cursed the one that Yahweh appointed [MTY] to be the king! So ◄should he not be executed for doing that?/he certainly should be executed for doing that.►” [RHQ]<verse eid="2SA 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 19:22"/>But David said, “You sons of Zeruiah, what am I going to do with you? (OR, you are not the ones who should decide <char style="add">what to do to him</char>). <char style="add">It is as though</char> you have become my enemies today. I know that I am the one who has now become the king of Israel, <char style="add">so I say that</char> certainly no one [RHQ] in Israel should be executed today.” <verse eid="2SA 19:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 19:23"/>Then the king said to Shimei, “I solemnly promise that I will not execute you.”<verse eid="2SA 19:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 19:24"/>Then Miphibosheth, Saul’s grandson, came down <char style="add">to the river</char> to greet the king. He had not washed his feet or trimmed his beard or washed his clothes, from the time that the king left Jerusalem until the day that he returned. <verse eid="2SA 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 19:25"/>When he arrived from Jerusalem to greet the king, the king said to him, “Mephibosheth, why did you not go with me?”<verse eid="2SA 19:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 19:26"/>He replied, “Your Majesty, <char style="add">you know that</char> I am crippled. <char style="add">When I heard that you were leaving Jerusalem,</char> I said to my servant <char style="add">Ziba</char>, ‘Put a saddle on my donkey in order that I can ride on it and go with the king.’ But he deceived me <char style="add">and left without me</char>. <verse eid="2SA 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 19:27"/>And he lied to you about me. But, Your Majesty, you are <char style="add">as wise</char> as God’s angel. So do whatever seems right to you. <verse eid="2SA 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 19:28"/>All of my grandfather’s family expected/deserved that we would be executed. But <char style="add">you did not execute me;</char> you allowed me to eat food with you at your table! So I certainly do not have [RHQ] the right to request you for anything more.”<verse eid="2SA 19:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 19:29"/>The king replied, “You certainly do not need to say any more. I have decided that you and Ziba will divide <char style="add">equally</char> the land <char style="add">that belonged to your grandfather Saul</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 19:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 19:30"/>Mephibosheth replied to the king, “Your Majesty, <char style="add">I am content that</char> you have returned safely. So allow him to take all the land.”<verse eid="2SA 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 19:31"/>Barzillai, the man from <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, had come down to the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> from <char style="add">his town of</char> Rogelim, to escort the king across the river. <verse eid="2SA 19:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 19:32"/>Barzillai was a very old man, 80 years old. He was a very wealthy man, and he had provided food for the king <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> while they were at Mahanaim. <verse eid="2SA 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 19:33"/>The king said to Barzillai, “Come with me to Jerusalem, and I will take care of you.”<verse eid="2SA 19:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2SA 19:34"/>But Barzillai replied, “I certainly do not have [RHQ] many more years to live. So ◄why should I go with you to Jerusalem?/there is certainly no reason for me to go with you to Jerusalem.► [RHQ] <verse eid="2SA 19:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="2SA 19:35"/>I am now 80 years old. I do not [RHQ] know what is enjoyable and what is not enjoyable. I cannot [RHQ] enjoy what I eat and what I drink. I cannot [RHQ] hear the voices of men and women as they sing. So ◄why should I be another burden to you?/I do not want to be another burden to you.► [RHQ] <verse eid="2SA 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="2SA 19:36"/>I will cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> with you and go a little further, and that will be all the reward that I need <char style="add">for helping you</char>. <verse eid="2SA 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="2SA 19:37"/>Then please allow me to return to my home, because that is where I want to die, near my parents’ grave. But here is <char style="add">my son</char> Chimham. Your Majesty, allow him to go with you <char style="add">and serve you</char>, and do for him whatever seems good to you!”<verse eid="2SA 19:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="2SA 19:38"/>The king replied, “Okay, he will cross <char style="add">the river</char> with me, and I will do for him whatever seems good to you. And I will do for you whatever you want me to do.”<verse eid="2SA 19:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="2SA 19:39"/>Then King David and all the others crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. He kissed Barzillai and <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless him. Then Barzillai returned to his home.<verse eid="2SA 19:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="2SA 19:40"/>
    <char style="add">After they crossed the river,</char> Chimham went with the king, and all the army of Judah and half the army of the other Israeli tribes escorted/accompanied the king to Gilgal.<verse eid="2SA 19:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The troops from Judah and Israel argued</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="2SA 19:41"/>Then all the soldiers from the other Israeli tribes came to the king and said, “◄Why is it that our relatives, the men from Judah, took you away from us and wanted to be the only ones to escort you and your family across the river, along with all your men?/It is not right that our relatives, the men from Judah, took you away from us and wanted to be the only ones to escort you and your family across the river, along with all your men.► [RHQ] <char style="add">Why did you not request us to do that</char>?” [RHQ]<verse eid="2SA 19:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="2SA 19:42"/>The soldiers from Judah replied, “We did it because the king is from Judah. So ◄why are you angry about that?/you should not be angry about that.► [RHQ] The king has never paid for our food, and he has never given us any gifts.”<verse eid="2SA 19:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="2SA 19:43"/>The men of the other Israeli tribes replied, “<char style="add">There are ten tribes in Israel, and only one in Judah. So</char> it is ten times more right for us to say that David <char style="add">is our king</char> than it is for you to say that. So why are you despising us [RHQ]? We were certainly [RHQ] the first ones to talk about bringing David back <char style="add">to Jerusalem to be our king again</char>.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 19:43">But the men of Judah spoke more harshly than the men from the other tribes of Israel did.<verse eid="2SA 19:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="2SA 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Sheba rebelled against David</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 20:1"/>There was a man there <char style="add">at Gilgal</char> named Sheba. He was a man who always caused trouble. He was from the tribe of Benjamin and was the son of Bichri. He blew a trumpet and called out, “We have nothing to do with [DOU] David, that son of Jesse! So, men of Israel, let’s go to our homes!”<verse eid="2SA 20:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 20:2"/>So all the men from the other Israeli tribes deserted David and went with Sheba, but the men of Judah stayed with David. They wanted him to be their king, and went with him from near the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> up to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2SA 20:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 20:3"/>When David arrived at the palace in Jerusalem, he took the ten slave wives whom he had left there to take care of the palace and put them in another house. He put a guard at that house, and he provided for them what they needed, but he never had sexual relations [EUP] with them again. So they remained shut up in their house until they died. It was as though they were widows.<verse eid="2SA 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 20:4"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> the king said to Amasa, “Summon the soldiers of Judah to come here within three days, and you be here also.” <verse eid="2SA 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 20:5"/>So Amasa went to summon them, but he did not return within the time that David told him to.<verse eid="2SA 20:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 20:6"/>So David said to Abishai, “Now Sheba will harm us more than Absalom did. So you take my soldiers and pursue him. If you do not do that, he and his soldiers may occupy/capture some of the ◄fortified towns/towns that have walls around them►, and escape from us. [IDM]” <verse eid="2SA 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 20:7"/>So Abishai <char style="add">and Joab</char> and the king’s bodyguards and the other soldiers left Jerusalem, to pursue Sheba.<verse eid="2SA 20:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 20:8"/>When they arrived at the huge rock in <char style="add">the</char> Gibeah <char style="add">region</char>, Amasa met them. Joab was wearing a soldier’s uniform. He had a dagger/long knife fastened to his belt. When he came close <char style="add">to Amasa, he allowed</char> the dagger <char style="add">to</char> fall on the ground.<verse eid="2SA 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 20:9"/>Joab said to Amasa, “Are things going well with you, my friend?” Then Joab grabbed Amasa’s beard with his right hand, in order to kiss him. <verse eid="2SA 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 20:10"/>But Amasa did not see that Joab was holding <char style="add">another</char> dagger in his <char style="add">other</char> hand. And Joab stabbed it into Amasa’s belly, and his insides spilled out onto the ground. Amasa died <char style="add">immediately</char>; Joab did not need to stab him again. Then Joab and his brother Abishai continued to pursue Sheba.<verse eid="2SA 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 20:11"/>One of Joab’s soldiers stood alongside Amasa’s body and called out, “Everyone who wants Joab <char style="add">to be our commander</char> and who wants David <char style="add">to be our king</char>, go with Joab!” <verse eid="2SA 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 20:12"/>Amasa’s body was lying on the road. It was covered with blood. The soldier of Joab <char style="add">who had called out</char> saw that many others of Joab’s soldiers were stopping <char style="add">to see it</char>, so he dragged Amasa’s body off the road into a field, and threw a cloth/blanket over the body. <verse eid="2SA 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 20:13"/>After the body had been taken off the road, all the soldiers went with Joab to pursue Sheba.<verse eid="2SA 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 20:14"/>Sheba went through all the tribes of Israel, and arrived at Abel-Beth-Maacah <char style="add">town in the northern part of Israel</char>. There, all the members of <char style="add">his father</char> Bichri’s clan gathered, and went with Sheba into the town. <verse eid="2SA 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 20:15"/>The soldiers who were with Joab <char style="add">found out that Sheba had gone there, so they</char> went there and surrounded the town. They built a dirt ramp up against the town wall. They also pounded against the wall <char style="add">with heavy poles</char>, to cause it to collapse. <verse eid="2SA 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 20:16"/>Then a wise woman who was in that town <char style="add">stood on the top of the wall and</char> shouted down, “Listen to me! Tell Joab to come here, because I want to talk to him!” <verse eid="2SA 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 20:17"/>So <char style="add">after they told Joab</char>, he came there, and the woman said, “Are you Joab?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 20:17">He replied, “Yes, I am.” She said to him, “Listen to what I say.” He replied, “I am listening.” <verse eid="2SA 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 20:18"/>She said, “Long ago people used to say, ‘Go to Abel <char style="add">town</char> to get good advice about your problems.’ And that is what people did. <verse eid="2SA 20:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 20:19"/>We are peaceful and loyal Israelis. Our people here are important and respected [IDM]. So ◄why are you trying to destroy a town that belongs to Yahweh?/you should not be trying to destroy a town that belongs to Yahweh.►” [RHQ]<verse eid="2SA 20:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 20:20"/>Job replied, “I would certainly never want to ruin or destroy your town! <verse eid="2SA 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 20:21"/>That is not what we want to do. But Bichri’s son Sheba, a man from the hilly area in the tribe of Ephraim, is rebelling against King David. Put this man into our hands, and then we will ◄go away from/not attack► this town.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 20:21">The woman replied to Joab, “Okay, what we will do is, we will <char style="add">cut off</char> his head <char style="add">and</char> throw it over the wall to you.”<verse eid="2SA 20:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 20:22"/>Then this wise woman went to the elders of the town and told them what she had said to Joab. So they cut off Sheba’s head and threw it over the wall to Joab. Then Joab blew his trumpet <char style="add">to signal that the battle was ended</char>, and all his soldiers left the town and returned to their homes. And Joab returned to Jerusalem and told the king <char style="add">what had happened</char>.<verse eid="2SA 20:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 20:23"/>Joab was the commander of the entire Israeli army. Jehoiada’s son Benaiah was the commander of David’s bodyguards; <verse eid="2SA 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 20:24"/>Adoram supervised the men who were forced to work <char style="add">for the king</char>; Ahilud’s son Jehoshaphat was the man who reported <char style="add">to the people everything that David decided</char>; <verse eid="2SA 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 20:25"/>Sheva was the official secretary; Zadok and Abiathar were the priests; <verse eid="2SA 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 20:26"/>and Ira from Jair <char style="add">town</char> was also one of David’s priests.<verse eid="2SA 20:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="2SA 21"/>
  <para style="s1">The people of Gibeon got revenge for what Saul did</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 21:1"/>During the time that David <char style="add">ruled</char>, there was a famine <char style="add">in Israel</char> for three years. David prayed to Yahweh about it. And Yahweh said, “<char style="add">In order for the famine to end</char>, Saul’s family needs to be punished [MTY] because Saul killed many people from Gibeon <char style="add">city</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 21:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 21:2"/>The people of Gibeon were not Israelis; they were a small group of the Amor people-group whom the Israelis had solemnly promised to protect. But Saul had tried to kill all of them because he ◄was very zealous/wanted very much► to enable the people of Judah and Israel <char style="add">to be the only ones living in that land</char>. So the king summoned the leaders of Gibeon <verse eid="2SA 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 21:3"/>and said to them, “What shall I do for you? How can I make amends/up for what was done to your people, in order that you will bless us who belong to Yahweh?”<verse eid="2SA 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 21:4"/>They replied, “You cannot settle our quarrel with Saul and his family by giving us silver or gold. And we do not have the right to kill any Israelis.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 21:4">So David asked, “Then/So what do you say that I should do for you?” <verse eid="2SA 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 21:5"/>They replied, “Saul <char style="add">wanted to</char> get rid of us. He wanted to annihilate/kill all of us, in order that none of us would live anywhere in Israel. <verse eid="2SA 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 21:6"/>Hand over to us seven of Saul’s descendants. We will hang them where Yahweh is worshiped in Gibeon, our town, the town where Saul, whom Yahweh previously chose to be king, lived.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 21:6">The king replied, “Okay, I will hand them over to you.” <verse eid="2SA 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 21:7"/>The king did not hand over to them Saul’s grandson Mephibosheth, because of what he and <char style="add">Mephibosheth’s father</char> Jonathan had solemnly promised to each other. <verse eid="2SA 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 21:8"/>Instead, he took Armoni and another man named Mephibosheth, the two sons that Saul’s slave wife Rizpah, the daughter of Aiah, had given birth to, and the five sons that Saul’s daughter Merab had given birth to. Merab’s husband was Adriel, the son of a man named Barzillai from Meholah <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="2SA 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 21:9"/>David handed those men over to the men from Gibeon. Then they hanged those seven men on a hill where they worshiped Yahweh. They were all killed during the time of the year that the people started to harvest the barley.<verse eid="2SA 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 21:10"/>Then Rizpah took coarse cloth made from goats’ hair, and spread it on the rock <char style="add">where the corpses lay</char>. She stayed there from the time that people started to harvest the barley until the rains started. She did not allow any birds to come near the corpses during the day, and she did not allow any animals to come near during the night. <verse eid="2SA 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 21:11"/>When someone told David what Rizpah had done, <verse eid="2SA 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 21:12"/>he went with some of his servants to Jabesh in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> and got the bones of Saul and his son Jonathan. The people of Jabesh had stolen their bones from the ◄plaza/public square► in Beth-Shan <char style="add">city</char>, where the men from Philistia had hanged them previously, on the day that they had killed Saul and Jonathan on Gilboa <char style="add">Mountain</char>. <verse eid="2SA 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 21:13"/>David and his men took the bones of Saul and Jonathan, and they also took the bones of the seven men <char style="add">from Gibeon</char> whom the men from Philistia had hanged.<verse eid="2SA 21:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 21:14"/>They buried the bones of Saul and Jonathan in Zela <char style="add">town</char> in the land of <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Benjamin. Doing all that the king commanded, they buried their bones in the tomb where Saul’s father Kish <char style="add">was buried</char>. After that, <char style="add">because</char> God <char style="add">saw that Saul’s family had been punished to pay for Saul’s murder of many people from Gibeon, he</char> answered the Israelis’ prayers for their land, and caused the famine to end.<verse eid="2SA 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The battles against the giants of Philistia</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 21:15"/>The army of Philistia again started to fight against the army of Israel. And David and his soldiers went to fight the Philistines. During the battle, David became weary. <verse eid="2SA 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 21:16"/>One of the Philistia men thought that he could kill David. His name was Ishbi-Benob. He was a descendant of <char style="add">a group of</char> giants. He carried a bronze spear that weighed about ◄7-1/2 pounds/3-1/2 kg.►, and he also had a new sword. <verse eid="2SA 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 21:17"/>But Abishai came to help David, and attacked the giant and killed him. Then David’s soldiers forced him to promise that he would not go with them into a battle again. They said to him, “<char style="add">If you die, and none of your descendants become king, that would be like</char> [MET] extinguishing the last light in Israel.”<verse eid="2SA 21:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 21:18"/>Some time after that, there was a battle with the army of Philistia near Gob <char style="add">village</char>. During the battle, Sibbecai, from <char style="add">the</char> Hushah <char style="add">clan</char>, killed Saph, one of the descendants of the Rapha giants.<verse eid="2SA 21:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 21:19"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char> there was another battle with the army of Philistia at Gob. During that battle, Elhanan, the son of Jaare-Oregim from Bethlehem, killed <char style="add">the brother of</char> Goliath from Gath <char style="add">city</char>; Goliath’s spear shaft/handle was ◄very thick, like the bar on a weaver’s loom/over two inches thick►.<verse eid="2SA 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 21:20"/>Later there was another battle near Gath. There was a ◄huge man/giant► there who liked to fight <char style="add">in battles</char>. He had six fingers on each hand and six toes on each foot. He was descended from <char style="add">the</char> Rapha <char style="add">giants</char>. <verse eid="2SA 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 21:21"/>But when he ◄made fun of/ridiculed► the men in the Israeli <char style="add">army</char>, Jonathan, the son of David’s <char style="add">older</char> brother Shimeah, killed him.<verse eid="2SA 21:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 21:22"/>Those four men were some of the descendants of the Rapha giants who had lived in Gath, who were killed [MTY] by David and his soldiers.<verse eid="2SA 21:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="2SA 22"/>
  <para style="s1">David’s song to praise Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 22:1"/>After Yahweh had rescued David from Saul and his other enemies, David sang a song to Yahweh. <verse eid="2SA 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 22:2"/><char style="add">This is what</char> he sang:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:2">Yahweh, you are like a <char style="add">huge overhanging</char> rock <char style="add">under which I can hide</char> [MET];</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:2">you are like my fortress, and you rescue me.<verse eid="2SA 22:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 22:3"/>Yahweh, you protect me; you are like a shield;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:3">you are the powerful one [MET] who saves me;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:3">you are like a place where I ◄find refuge/am safe►.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:3">You save me from those who act violently toward me.<verse eid="2SA 22:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 22:4"/>I call out to you, Yahweh;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:4">you deserve to be praised,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:4">and you rescue me from my enemies.<verse eid="2SA 22:4"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 22:5"/>“ almost died [PRS]; it was like [MET] a huge wave had crashed over me,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:5">and almost destroyed me like a flood.<verse eid="2SA 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 22:6"/>I thought that I would die; it was as though death wrapped ropes around me;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:6">it was as though I was in a trap where I would surely die. [PRS, MET]<verse eid="2SA 22:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 22:7"/>But when I was ◄very distressed/in great trouble►, I called out to you, Yahweh;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:7">I cried out to you, my God.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:7">And from your temple you heard me;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:7">you listened when I called to you to help me.<verse eid="2SA 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 22:8"/>“Then <char style="add">it was as though</char> the earth quaked and shook;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:8">
    <char style="add">it was as though</char> the foundations that ◄<char style="add">held up/supported</char>► the sky trembled,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:8">because you were angry.<verse eid="2SA 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 22:9"/>
    <char style="add">It was as though</char> smoke poured out of your nostrils</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:9">and burning coals and fire that burns everything came out of your mouth.<verse eid="2SA 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 22:10"/>You tore open the sky and came down;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:10">there was a thick dark <char style="add">cloud</char> under your feet.<verse eid="2SA 22:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 22:11"/>You rode <char style="add">through the sky</char> on a winged creature;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:11">the wind enabled you to travel <char style="add">swiftly</char> [MET], like a bird.<verse eid="2SA 22:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 22:12"/>The darkness surrounded you, like a blanket;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:12">thick clouds that were full of water also surrounded you.<verse eid="2SA 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 22:13"/>Out of the lightning in front of you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:13">fire from burning coals flamed.<verse eid="2SA 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 22:14"/>Then, Yahweh, you spoke like thunder from the sky;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:14">it was your voice, God, you who are greater than all other gods, that was heard.<verse eid="2SA 22:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 22:15"/>When you sent flashes of lightning,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:15">
    <char style="add">it was as though</char> [MET] you shot your arrows and scattered your enemies.<verse eid="2SA 22:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 22:16"/>Then the bottom of the ocean was uncovered;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:16">the foundations of the world could be seen</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:16">when you rebuked <char style="add">your enemies</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:16">with a snort from your nostrils.<verse eid="2SA 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 22:17"/>“Yahweh, you reached down from heaven and lifted me up;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:17">you pulled me up from the deep water.<verse eid="2SA 22:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 22:18"/>You rescued me from my strong enemies,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:18">from those who hated me;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:18">
    <char style="add">I could not defeat them because</char> they were very strong.<verse eid="2SA 22:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 22:19"/>They attacked me when I was experiencing troubles/difficulties,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:19">but Yahweh, you protected me.<verse eid="2SA 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 22:20"/>You brought me to a place where I was safe;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:20">you rescued me because you were pleased with me.<verse eid="2SA 22:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 22:21"/>“Yahweh, you rewarded me because I do what is right;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:21">you did good things for me because I ◄was innocent/had not done things that are wrong►.<verse eid="2SA 22:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 22:22"/>Yahweh, I have obeyed your laws;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:22">I have not turned away from you, my God.<verse eid="2SA 22:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 22:23"/>All of your regulations were in my mind,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:23">and I did not turn away from <char style="add">obeying</char> all your statutes.<verse eid="2SA 22:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 22:24"/>You know that I have not done anything that is evil;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:24">I have kept myself from doing things for which I should be punished.<verse eid="2SA 22:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 22:25"/>So you have rewarded me in return for my doing what is right,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:25">because <char style="add">you know that</char> I ◄am innocent of doing/have not done► wrong things.<verse eid="2SA 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 22:26"/>“Yahweh, you are faithful/loyal to those who always trust in you;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:26">you always do what is good to those whose behavior is always good.<verse eid="2SA 22:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 22:27"/>You act sincerely toward those whose inner beings are pure,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:27">but you are hostile to those who are perverse/wicked.<verse eid="2SA 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 22:28"/>You rescue those who are humble,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:28">but you watch [MTY] those who are proud and humiliate them.<verse eid="2SA 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 22:29"/>Yahweh, you are <char style="add">like</char> [MET] a lamp</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:29">that causes it to become light when I am in the dark.<verse eid="2SA 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 22:30"/>With your strength/help I can run through a line of enemy soldiers</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:30">and I can climb over the wall <char style="add">that surrounds their city</char>.<verse eid="2SA 22:30"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 22:31"/>“My God whom I worship, everything that you do is perfect;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:31">you always do what you promise that you will do.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:31">You are like a shield [MET] to all those who request you to protect them.<verse eid="2SA 22:31"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 22:32"/>Yahweh, you are [RHQ] the only one who is God;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:32">only you are like a huge rock [MET] <char style="add">under which we are protected/safe</char>.<verse eid="2SA 22:32"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 22:33"/>God, you <char style="add">whom I worship</char> are a strong refuge for me;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:33">you keep me safe on the roads that I <char style="add">walk on</char>.<verse eid="2SA 22:33"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2SA 22:34"/>
    <char style="add">When I walk</char> in the mountains,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:34">you enable me to walk safely, without stumbling [MET]</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:34">like a deer runs.<verse eid="2SA 22:34"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2SA 22:35"/>You teach me <char style="add">how to fight</char> in a battle</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:35">in order that I can shoot arrows well from a very strong bow.<verse eid="2SA 22:35"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2SA 22:36"/>
    <char style="add">It is as though</char> [MET] you have given me a shield</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:36">by which you have saved/rescued me,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:36">and you have answered my prayers and caused me to become famous/great.<verse eid="2SA 22:36"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="2SA 22:37"/>You have not allowed <char style="add">my enemies</char> to capture me [IDM],</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:37">and I have not fallen down <char style="add">during battles</char>.<verse eid="2SA 22:37"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="2SA 22:38"/>“ pursued my enemies and defeated them;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:38">I did not stop <char style="add">fighting them</char> until they were all killed.<verse eid="2SA 22:38"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="2SA 22:39"/>I struck them down; I stabbed them with my sword;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:39">they fell down at my feet and did not stand up again.<verse eid="2SA 22:39"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="2SA 22:40"/>You have given me strength for fighting battles</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:40">and caused those who were attacking me to fall down, and I trampled on them.<verse eid="2SA 22:40"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="2SA 22:41"/>You caused my enemies to turn and run away from me;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:41">I destroyed those who hated me.<verse eid="2SA 22:41"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="2SA 22:42"/>They ◄looked for/wanted► someone to rescue them, but no one did.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:42">They cried out to you, Yahweh, <char style="add">for help,</char> but you did not answer them.<verse eid="2SA 22:42"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="2SA 22:43"/>I crushed them, and as a result they became like [SIM] tiny particles of dust.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:43">I trampled them, and they became like [SIM] mud in the streets.<verse eid="2SA 22:43"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="2SA 22:44"/>“You rescued me from those who tried to rebel <char style="add">against me</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:44">and you appointed me to rule many nations;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:44">people whom I did not know previously are now ◄under my authority/my slaves►.<verse eid="2SA 22:44"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="2SA 22:45"/>Foreigners humbly bowed down in front of me;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:45">as soon as they heard about me, they obeyed me.<verse eid="2SA 22:45"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="2SA 22:46"/>They became afraid,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:46">and they came to me, trembling, from the places where they were hiding.<verse eid="2SA 22:46"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="2SA 22:47"/>“Yahweh, you are alive! I praise you! You are like [MET] a <char style="add">huge overhanging</char> rock under which I am safe/protected!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:47">You are the one who rescues me [MET].</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:47">Everyone should exalt/honor/praise you.<verse eid="2SA 22:47"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="2SA 22:48"/>You enable me to conquer my enemies;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:48">you cause people of <char style="add">other</char> nations to be ◄under my authority/my slaves►.<verse eid="2SA 22:48"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="2SA 22:49"/>You delivered me from my enemies;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 22:49">you caused me to be honored more than they were;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:49">you rescued me from men who <char style="add">always</char> acted violently.<verse eid="2SA 22:49"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="2SA 22:50"/>Because of all that, I exalt you among many people-groups</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:50">and I sing to praise you.<verse eid="2SA 22:50"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="2SA 22:51"/>You enable me, whom you appointed to be king, to powerfully conquer <char style="add">my enemies</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 22:51">you faithfully love me, David, and you will love my descendants forever.<verse eid="2SA 22:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="2SA 23"/>
  <para style="s1">David’s final message</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 23:1"/>David, the son of Jesse, was a man whom <char style="add">God caused to</char> become great.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:1">He was appointed to become king by the God whom Jacob <char style="add">worshiped</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:1">He wrote beautiful songs for the Israeli people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:1">This is the last song that he wrote:<verse eid="2SA 23:1"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 23:2"/>“The Spirit of Yahweh tells me what to say;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:2">the message that I speak [MTY] comes from him.<verse eid="2SA 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 23:3"/>God, the one whom we Israeli <char style="add">people worship</char>, has spoken;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:3">the one who protects us Israeli people said to me,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:3">‘Kings who rule people justly</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:3">have an awesome respect for me, God.<verse eid="2SA 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 23:4"/>They are like the sun that shines at dawn</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:4">and causes the grass to <char style="add">sprout/sparkle</char> after the rain ends.’<verse eid="2SA 23:4"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 23:5"/>And truly, that is how God will surely bless my family [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:5">because he made an agreement with me that will endure forever,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:5">an agreement in which he promises that no part of it will ever be changed.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:5">He will surely cause me to prosper [RHQ],</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:5">and he will always help me,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2SA 23:5">and that is all that I desire.<verse eid="2SA 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 23:6"/>But <char style="add">he will get rid of</char> godless/evil people like [SIM] people throw away thorns</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:6">that <char style="add">injure people if they try to</char> pick them up with their hands.<verse eid="2SA 23:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 23:7"/>Someone <char style="add">who wants to get rid of thornbushes</char> does not grab them;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:7">he uses an iron <char style="add">shovel</char> or a spear <char style="add">to dig them out</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="2SA 23:7">and then he burns them completely.<verse eid="2SA 23:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">David’s three greatest warriors</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 23:8"/>These are the names of David’s three greatest warriors.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 23:8">The first was Esh-Baal, <char style="add">whose other name was Jashobeam</char>, from the Hachmon clan (OR, the son of Hachmon). He was the leader of the three men. One time he fought against 800 enemies and killed them all with his spear.<verse eid="2SA 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 23:9"/>The second/next one of the three greatest warriors was Eleazar, who was the son of Dodo from the clan of Ahoh. One day he was with David when they defied/challenged the soldiers of Philistia who had gathered for the battle. The <char style="add">other</char> Israeli soldiers retreated, <verse eid="2SA 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 23:10"/>but Eleazar stood there and fought the soldiers of Philistia until his arm became very tired, with the result that <char style="add">his hand cramped and</char> he could not stop gripping his sword. Yahweh won a great victory on that day. And afterwards the <char style="add">other</char> Israeli soldiers returned <char style="add">to where Eleazar was</char>, and stripped off the <char style="add">armor from the men whom he had</char> killed.<verse eid="2SA 23:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 23:11"/>The third one of the greatest warriors was Shammah, the son of Agee from <char style="add">the clan/town of</char> Harar. One time the Philistia soldiers gathered at Lehi <char style="add">town</char>, where there was a field full of lentils/peas <char style="add">that they wanted to steal</char>. The other Israeli soldiers ran away from the Philistia troops, <verse eid="2SA 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 23:12"/>but Shammah stood there in the field and did not let the Philistia soldiers <char style="add">steal the crops</char>, and killed them. Yahweh won a great victory on that day.<verse eid="2SA 23:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The 30 great warriors</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 23:13"/>Altogether there were 30 special warriors among David’s soldiers. Once, when it was almost time to harvest <char style="add">the crops</char>, three of those 30 men went down to Adullam Cave, where David was <char style="add">staying</char>. A group of men from the Philistia army had set up their tents in Rephaim Valley <char style="add">near Jerusalem</char>. <verse eid="2SA 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 23:14"/>David <char style="add">and his soldiers</char> were in the cave <char style="add">because it was safe there</char>, and <char style="add">another</char> group of Philistia soldiers was occupying Bethlehem. <verse eid="2SA 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 23:15"/><char style="add">One day</char> David very much wanted <char style="add">some water</char> to drink, and said “I wish that someone would bring me some water from the well near the gate at Bethlehem!” <verse eid="2SA 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 23:16"/>So his three greatest warriors forced their way through the camp of Philistia soldiers and drew some water from the well, and brought it to David. But he would not drink it. Instead, he poured it out <char style="add">on the ground</char> as an offering to Yahweh. <verse eid="2SA 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 23:17"/>He said, “Yahweh, it would certainly not be right for me to drink this water! That would be like [RHQ] drinking the blood of these men who were willing/ready to die for me!” So he refused to drink it.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="2SA 23:17">That was one of the things that those three great warriors did.<verse eid="2SA 23:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The list of the great warriors</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 23:18"/>Abishai, Joab’s <char style="add">younger</char> brother, was the leader of the 30 <char style="add">greatest warriors</char>. <char style="add">One day</char> he fought against 300 men and killed them all with his spear. As a result, he also became famous. <verse eid="2SA 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 23:19"/>He was the most famous of the thirty greatest warriors, and he became their leader/commander, but he was not one of the three greatest warriors.<verse eid="2SA 23:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 23:20"/>Jehoiada’s son Benaiah, from Kabzeel <char style="add">town</char>, also did great deeds. He killed two of the best warriors from the Moab people-group. Also, he went down into a pit on a day when snow was falling, and killed a lion there. <verse eid="2SA 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 23:21"/>He also killed a huge soldier from Egypt who carried a spear. Benaiah <char style="add">had only</char> his club, but he attacked the giant with it. Then he snatched the spear from the man’s hand and killed him with his own spear. <verse eid="2SA 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 23:22"/>Those are <char style="add">some of</char> the things that Benaiah did. As a result, he became famous, like the three greatest warriors were. <verse eid="2SA 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 23:23"/>He was more honored than the other members of the group of thirty great warriors, but not as famous as the three greatest warriors. David appointed him to be the commander of his bodyguards.<verse eid="2SA 23:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 23:24"/>
    <char style="add">These are the names of the great warriors</char>:</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:24">Asahel, the brother of Joab;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:24">Elhanan, the son of Dodo, from Bethlehem;<verse eid="2SA 23:24"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 23:25"/>Shammah and Elika, from <char style="add">the</char> Harod <char style="add">clan</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="2SA 23:26"/>Helez, from Pelet <char style="add">city</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:26">Ira, the son of Ikkesh, from Tekoa <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:26"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="2SA 23:27"/>Abiezer, from Anathoth <char style="add">city</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:27">Mebunnai <char style="add">whose other name was Sibbecai</char>, from Hushah’s <char style="add">clan</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:27"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="2SA 23:28"/>Zalmon <char style="add">whose other name was Ilai</char>, from Ahoh’s <char style="add">clan</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:28">Maharai, from Netophah <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:28"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="2SA 23:29"/>Heleb, the son of Baanah, also from Netophah <char style="add">town</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:29">Ittai, the son of Ribai, from Gibeah <char style="add">town</char> in <char style="add">the land that belonged to</char> the tribe of Benjamin;<verse eid="2SA 23:29"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="2SA 23:30"/>Benaiah, from Pirathon <char style="add">town</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:30">Hiddai, from the valleys near Gaash <char style="add">Mountain</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:30"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="2SA 23:31"/>Abi-Albon, from the clan of Arabah;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:31">Azmaveth, from Bahurim <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:31"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="2SA 23:32"/>Eliahba, from Shaalbon <char style="add">town</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:32">The sons of Jashen;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:32">Jonathan;<verse eid="2SA 23:32"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="2SA 23:33"/>Shammah, from Harar <char style="add">town/clan</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:33">Ahiam the son of Sharar, from Harar <char style="add">town/clan</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:33"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="2SA 23:34"/>Eliphelet, the son of Ahasbai, from Maacah <char style="add">town</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:34">Eliam, the son of Ahithophel, from Gilo <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:34"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="2SA 23:35"/>Hezro, from Carmel <char style="add">city</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:35">Paarai, from Arba <char style="add">city</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:35"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="2SA 23:36"/>Igal, the son of Nathan, from Zobah <char style="add">city</char>;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:36">Bani, from the tribe of Gad;<verse eid="2SA 23:36"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="2SA 23:37"/>Zelek, from the Ammon people-group;</para>
  <para style="li3" vid="2SA 23:37">Naharai, the man who carried Joab’s weapons, from Beeroth <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:37"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="2SA 23:38"/>Ira and Gareb, from Jattir <char style="add">town</char>;<verse eid="2SA 23:38"/></para>
  <para style="li3">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="2SA 23:39"/>Uriah, <char style="add">Bathsheba’s husband</char>, from the Heth people-group.</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="2SA 23:39">Altogether, there were 37 famous soldiers, <char style="add">but some of them had died and their names were not included</char>.<verse eid="2SA 23:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="2SA 24"/>
  <para style="s1">David ordered a census to be taken</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2SA 24:1"/>Yahweh was angry with the Israeli people again, so he incited David to cause trouble for them. He said to David, “Send <char style="add">some men</char> to count the people of Israel and Judah.”<verse eid="2SA 24:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="2SA 24:2"/>So the king said to Joab, the commander of his army, “Go <char style="add">with your officers</char> through all the tribes of Israel, from Dan <char style="add">city in the far north</char> to Beersheba <char style="add">town in the far south</char>, and count the people, in order that I may know how many people <char style="add">there are who are able to be soldiers in the army</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 24:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2SA 24:3"/>But Joab replied to the king, “Your Majesty, I wish/desire that Yahweh our God will cause there to be 100 times as many people <char style="add">in Israel</char> as there are now, and I wish/desire that you would see that happen <char style="add">before you die</char>. But why do you want us to do this?”<verse eid="2SA 24:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="2SA 24:4"/>But the king commanded Joab and his officers to do it. So they left the king and went out to count the people of Israel.<verse eid="2SA 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="2SA 24:5"/>They crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and set up their tents south of Aroer <char style="add">town</char>, in the middle of the valley, in the territory <char style="add">that was given to the tribe</char> of Gad. From there they went <char style="add">north</char> to Jazer <char style="add">city</char> <verse eid="2SA 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2SA 24:6"/>Then they went <char style="add">north</char> to <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> and to Kadesh <char style="add">city</char>, in the land where the Heth people-group lived. Then they went to Dan <char style="add">city in the far north of Israel</char>, and then further west, to Sidon <char style="add">city near the Mediterranean Sea</char>. <verse eid="2SA 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2SA 24:7"/>Then they went <char style="add">south</char> to Tyre, a city with high walls around it, and to all the cities where the Hiv and Canaan people-groups live. Then they went <char style="add">east</char> to Beersheba, in the southern part of Judah.<verse eid="2SA 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2SA 24:8"/>After nine months and 20 days, when they had finished going throughout the land <char style="add">and counting the people</char>, they returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="2SA 24:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2SA 24:9"/>They reported to the king the number of people that they had counted. There were 800,000 men in Israel and 500,000 men in Judah who were able to become soldiers in the army [MTY].<verse eid="2SA 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2SA 24:10"/>But after David’s men had counted the people, David regretted [IDM] that he had told them to do that. <char style="add">One night</char> he said to Yahweh, “I have committed a very big sin. Please forgive me, because what I have done is very foolish.”<verse eid="2SA 24:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="2SA 24:11"/>When David got up the next morning, Yahweh gave a message to the prophet Gad. He said to him, <verse eid="2SA 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2SA 24:12"/>“Go and tell this to David: ‘I am allowing you to choose one of three things <char style="add">to punish you</char>. I will do whichever one you choose.’ ”<verse eid="2SA 24:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2SA 24:13"/>So Gad went to David and told him <char style="add">what Yahweh had said</char>. He said to David, “You can choose whether there will be three years of famine in your land, or three months of your <char style="add">army</char> running away from your enemies, or three days when there will be a ◄plague/very severe illness► in your land. You think about it and choose <char style="add">which one you want, and tell me</char>, and I will return to Yahweh and tell him what your answer is.”<verse eid="2SA 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2SA 24:14"/>David said to Gad, “All those are very terrible things for me to choose between! But allow Yahweh to punish [MTY] me, because he is very merciful. Do not allow humans to punish me, <char style="add">because they will not be merciful</char>.”<verse eid="2SA 24:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2SA 24:15"/>So Yahweh sent a plague on the Israeli people. It started that morning and did not stop until the time that he had chosen/set. All over the land, from Dan to Beersheba, there were 70,000 Israelis who died <char style="add">because of the plague</char>. <verse eid="2SA 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2SA 24:16"/>When <char style="add">Yahweh’s</char> angel stretched out his hand toward Jerusalem to destroy <char style="add">the people by this plague</char>, Yahweh changed his mind about punishing <char style="add">any more</char> people. He said to the angel who was killing them <char style="add">with the plague</char>, “Stop what you are doing [IDM]! That is enough!” <char style="add">When he said that,</char> the angel was standing at the ground where Araunah, from the Jebus people-group, threshed grain.<verse eid="2SA 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="2SA 24:17"/>When David saw the angel who was causing the people to become sick and die, he said to Yahweh, “Truly, I am the one who has committed the sin. I have done a very wicked thing, but these people are <char style="add">as innocent as</char> sheep [MET]. They have certainly not [RHQ] done anything <char style="add">that is wrong</char>. So you should punish [IDM] me and my family, <char style="add">not these people</char>!”<verse eid="2SA 24:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="2SA 24:18"/>That day Gad came to David and said to him, “Go up to the place where Araunah threshes grain, and build an altar to <char style="add">worship</char> Yahweh there.” <verse eid="2SA 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2SA 24:19"/>So David did what Gad told him to do, which was what Yahweh had commanded, <char style="add">and he went up there</char>. <verse eid="2SA 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2SA 24:20"/>When Araunah looked down and saw the king and his officials coming toward him, he prostrated himself on the ground in front of the king, with his face touching the ground.<verse eid="2SA 24:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="2SA 24:21"/>Araunah said, “Your Majesty, why have you come to me?” David replied, “<char style="add">I have come</char> to buy this ground where you thresh grain, in order to build an altar to Yahweh <char style="add">and offer sacrifices on it</char>, in order that he will stop the plague.”<verse eid="2SA 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="2SA 24:22"/>Araunah replied to David, “Your Majesty, offer to Yahweh whatever you wish/want. Here, take my oxen to use for the offering that will be completely burned on the altar. And here, take their yokes and the boards <char style="add">that I use</char> for the threshing, <char style="add">and use them</char> for the wood that you will burn. <verse eid="2SA 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="2SA 24:23"/>I, Araunah, am giving all this to you, the king.” Then he said, “I desire/hope that Yahweh our God will accept your offering.”<verse eid="2SA 24:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="2SA 24:24"/>But the king said to Araunah, “No, <char style="add">I will not take these things as a gift.</char> I will pay you for it. I will not take sacrifices that have cost me nothing, and offer them to Yahweh to be completely burned on the altar.” So he paid 50 pieces of silver to Araunah for the oxen and the ground.<verse eid="2SA 24:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="2SA 24:25"/>Then David built an altar to Yahweh, and he offered <char style="add">the oxen</char> to be completely burned on the altar, and he also offered sacrifices to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. Then, Yahweh answered David’s prayers, and he caused the plague in Israel to end.<verse eid="2SA 24:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2SA 24"/>
</usx>
