<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="2TI" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">2 TIMOTHY</para>
  <para style="toc1">2 Timothy</para>
  <para style="toc2">2 Timothy</para>
  <para style="toc3">2Ti</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book is one of the letters that the Apostle Paul wrote to his assistant Timothy. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">2 Timothy</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="2TI 1"/>
  <para style="s1">2 Timothy 1:1-2</para>
  <para style="s1">This letter is from me, Paul, to you, Timothy.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2TI 1:1"/>
    <char style="add">I</char>, Paul, <char style="add">am writing this letter. I am</char> an apostle whom Christ Jesus chose so that I would do what God wanted. He chose me <char style="add">to tell people that God</char> has promised <char style="add">that they will</char> live <char style="add">eternally</char> as a result of their having a close relationship with Christ Jesus. <verse eid="2TI 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2TI 1:2"/><char style="add">I am writing to you</char>, Timothy, whom I love <char style="add">as if you were</char> my own son. <char style="add">I pray that</char> God our Father and Christ Jesus our Lord will <char style="add">continue to act</char> kindly to you, be merciful to you, and <char style="add">cause you to have</char> inner peace,<verse eid="2TI 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I thank God that you sincerely believe in Christ Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 1:3-5">2 Timothy 1:3-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2TI 1:3"/>I thank God <char style="add">for all that he has done for you</char>. I serve him, and my ancestors <char style="add">served him, too. I serve him</char> in a manner that I know to be right. <char style="add">I thank him</char> while repeatedly I <char style="add">pray for you</char> at night and during the day. <verse eid="2TI 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2TI 1:4"/><char style="add">While I am thanking God for you</char>, I very much want to see you because I remember how you cried [MTY] <char style="add">when we separated. I want to see you</char> in order that I may be ◄filled with joy/very happy►. <verse eid="2TI 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2TI 1:5"/><char style="add">I thank God because</char> I remember that you sincerely believe <char style="add">in Christ Jesus</char>. First, your grandmother, Lois, and your mother, Eunice, <char style="add">believed in him and</char>, I am ◄convinced/very sure► that you also believe in him.<verse eid="2TI 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">So I remind you to do fervently what God has enabled and assigned you to do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 1:6-7">2 Timothy 1:6-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2TI 1:6"/>Because <char style="add">I am sure that you believe in him</char>, I remind you to do fervently/wholeheartedly [MET] what God has ◄assigned for/appointed► you to do and what he has enabled you to do. <char style="add">God</char> ◄<char style="add">assigned for/appointed</char>► you to do it as a result of my putting my hands <char style="add">on you to show/indicate that he had chosen you to do his work</char>. <verse eid="2TI 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2TI 1:7"/>Remember that God has put <char style="add">his Spirit</char> within us. <char style="add">His Spirit does not cause us to be</char> afraid. Instead, <char style="add">he causes us to be</char> powerful <char style="add">to work for God</char>, and he helps us to love <char style="add">others</char> and <char style="add">to</char> control what we say and do.<verse eid="2TI 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Never be ashamed either of the message or of me, but be willing to endure with me whatever we suffer because we tell the good news.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 1:8-14">2 Timothy 1:8-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="2TI 1:8"/>So never be ashamed/reluctant to tell others the message about our Lord. And do not <char style="add">be ashamed</char> of me, <char style="add">even though I am</char> a prisoner <char style="add">because I preach about</char> him. Instead, <char style="add">be willing to</char> suffer as I do as you proclaim the message about Christ. <char style="add">Endure what you will suffer</char> by letting God empower <char style="add">you to endure it</char>. <verse eid="2TI 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2TI 1:9"/><char style="add">God</char> saved us and chose us to conduct our lives in a pure way. It was not our doing good deeds/actions <char style="add">that caused him to do this for us—something</char> that we did not deserve. Instead, before ◄time began/he created the world► he purposed/planned to <char style="add">be kind to us</char> as a result of what Christ Jesus <char style="add">would do for us</char>. <verse eid="2TI 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2TI 1:10"/>Now, as a result of our Savior Christ Jesus having come, it has been revealed {he has shown} <char style="add">that he acts kindly toward us. Specifically, Christ Jesus</char> has declared that we <char style="add">will not remain dead after we</char> die! He has also revealed that, as a result of <char style="add">our hearing and accepting</char> the message <char style="add">about Christ, we</char> will live <char style="add">forever in bodies that will</char> not decay! <verse eid="2TI 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2TI 1:11"/>I was chosen {Christ chose me} to go as an apostle to many places and proclaim that message to people. <verse eid="2TI 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2TI 1:12"/>So, even though I suffer <char style="add">here in this prison</char>, I am not ashamed <char style="add">of being here</char> (OR, I am very confident), because I know <char style="add">Christ Jesus</char>, the one whom I have trusted, and I am convinced/sure that he is able to keep safe the good message that he has entrusted to me (OR, the things that I have entrusted <char style="add">to him</char>), and that he will reward me at the time [MTY] <char style="add">when he comes again</char>.<verse eid="2TI 1:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2TI 1:13"/>Be sure that you tell others the same correct message that you heard from me. <char style="add">And as you tell it</char>, keep trusting <char style="add">in Christ Jesus</char> and keep loving <char style="add">others</char> as Christ Jesus <char style="add">enables you to do</char>. <verse eid="2TI 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2TI 1:14"/>Do not let anyone persuade you to change the <char style="add">good message that</char> God has entrusted/given to you. Allow the Holy Spirit who lives in us to <char style="add">direct what you say</char>.<verse eid="2TI 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Many people have turned away from me, but Onesiphorus often cheered me up and was not ashamed of me.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 1:15-18">2 Timothy 1:15-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2TI 1:15"/>You know that <char style="add">almost</char> all <char style="add">the believers</char> in Asia <char style="add">province</char> have ◄turned away from/abandoned► me, including Phygelus and Hermogenes. <verse eid="2TI 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2TI 1:16"/><char style="add">But I pray that</char> the Lord will be kind to the family of Onesiphorus for the following reasons: Often he cheered me up and, <char style="add">even though</char> I was a prisoner [MTY], he was not ashamed ◄of me/<char style="add">to admit he was</char> my <char style="add">friend</char>►. <verse eid="2TI 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2TI 1:17"/>On the contrary, when he came here to Rome, he diligently searched for me until he found me. <verse eid="2TI 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2TI 1:18"/><char style="add">I pray that</char> the Lord will be kind to him on that day [MTY] <char style="add">when he, the Lord, will judge people</char>. And how much Onesiphorus served <char style="add">me</char> in Ephesus <char style="add">city</char>, you know very well.<verse eid="2TI 1:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2TI 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="2TI 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Let God empower you; and entrust the message to loyal/trustworthy people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 2:1-2">2 Timothy 2:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2TI 2:1"/>You <char style="add">are like a</char> son to me. So I urge also that you <char style="add">let God</char> empower you <char style="add">spiritually</char> as a result of Christ Jesus acting kindly toward you. <verse eid="2TI 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2TI 2:2"/><char style="add">As you do that</char>, remembering that <char style="add">the message</char> that you heard from me is the same message that other people have affirmed/declared to you, you must entrust/give that message to people whom you can trust, people who will be competent/able/qualified to teach others.<verse eid="2TI 2:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Endure with me what we suffer for Christ Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 2:3-13">2 Timothy 2:3-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="2TI 2:3"/>Endure as I do what we suffer for Christ Jesus, like a good soldier <char style="add">endures what he suffers</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2TI 2:4"/><char style="add">You know that</char> soldiers, in order to please their captain, do not ◄become involved in civilian affairs/spend time doing other kinds of work► [MET]. <char style="add">So, like soldiers, do not let other matters ◄distract you as you serve/hinder you from serving</char>► <char style="add">Christ Jesus</char>! <verse eid="2TI 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2TI 2:5"/><char style="add">Similarly, you know that</char> athletes who do not obey the rules of the contest will not be given {not win} the prize [MET]. <char style="add">So, like athletes, do all that Christ Jesus has commanded so that God will reward you</char>! <verse eid="2TI 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2TI 2:6"/><char style="add">You also know that</char> a hard-working farmer should be the first to receive some of the harvest [MET]. <char style="add">So, like farmers, work hard for Christ Jesus and expect that God will reward you</char>! <verse eid="2TI 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2TI 2:7"/>Think about what I have just written, because, <char style="add">if you do</char>, the Lord will enable you to understand everything <char style="add">that you need to understand</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2TI 2:8"/><char style="add">Endure everything by</char> remembering how Jesus Christ <char style="add">endured it when he suffered</char>. Remember that he came back to life {God raised him from the dead} and <char style="add">God affirmed/declared him to be king as</char> his ancestor <char style="add">King</char> David was. Those are things that I tell to people when I tell them the message <char style="add">about Christ</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2TI 2:9"/>I am suffering <char style="add">here in prison</char> because <char style="add">some people oppose</char> the good message <char style="add">that I tell</char>. They have even put me in chains as if I were a criminal. Nevertheless, the message from God is not chained {nothing is preventing [MET] <char style="add">others from proclaiming</char> the message from God}. <verse eid="2TI 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2TI 2:10"/>Therefore I <char style="add">willingly</char> endure all <char style="add">that I am suffering</char> for the sake of those <char style="add">whom God has</char> chosen. <char style="add">I do this</char> in order that Christ Jesus will save them, too, and that they will be forever with <char style="add">him in the</char> glorious <char style="add">place where he is</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2TI 2:11"/><char style="add">Endure everything as you remember</char> that these words <char style="add">that we all say/sing</char> (OR, <char style="add">that we teach people</char>) <char style="add">are trustworthy</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2TI 2:11">Since we have stopped behaving as we did in the past, as though we died when he died,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2TI 2:11">we shall also live with him.<verse eid="2TI 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="2TI 2:12"/>Since we are also patiently enduring what we suffer,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2TI 2:12">we shall also rule with him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2TI 2:12">But if we say that we do not know him,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2TI 2:12">he also will say that he does not know us.<verse eid="2TI 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="2TI 2:13"/>If we ◄are unfaithful/stop doing what he tells us to do►,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2TI 2:13">he will treat us just like he promised to do,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="2TI 2:13">because he ◄can never be untrue to himself/always does what he says that he will do►.<verse eid="2TI 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Remind teachers about the things that I have told you and command them not to quarrel; and be sure that you yourself are the kind of person that God will approve of.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 2:14-15">2 Timothy 2:14-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2TI 2:14"/>
    <char style="add">Those whom you appointed to teach others</char> God’s truth, keep reminding them about these things that <char style="add">I have told you</char>. Tell them strongly that, since God knows what they are doing (OR, that God <char style="add">will judge them for everything that is wrong that they do, and therefore</char>) they must not quarrel ◄about words/about matters that are not important►, <char style="add">because, when teachers quarrel, it helps</char> no one, <char style="add">and because, when they quarrel, they spiritually</char> destroy those who hear them (OR, they cause those who hear <char style="add">them to</char> quit ◄being committed <char style="add">to Christ</char>/believing <char style="add">in Christ</char>►.)<verse eid="2TI 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="2TI 2:15"/>◄Do your best/Try hard► to be the kind of person that God will approve of. <char style="add">Be like a</char> good worker as you teach the true message accurately. If a worker works well, he will not need to be ashamed of (OR, will be pleased about) <char style="add">what he does</char>.<verse eid="2TI 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Have nothing to do with godless and foolish talk.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 2:16-19">2 Timothy 2:16-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2TI 2:16"/>◄Stay away from/Do not talk with► <char style="add">those who talk foolishly and</char> ◄<char style="add">godlessly/say things that displease God</char>►, because <char style="add">those who talk foolishly</char> will become even more ◄ungodly/displeasing to God►, <verse eid="2TI 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2TI 2:17"/>and <char style="add">because</char> their message will <char style="add">harm people</char> [SIM] <char style="add">like</char> gangrene/cancer does. <char style="add">You know</char> Hymenaeus and Philetus. They are <char style="add">two</char> such people <char style="add">who talk in this manner</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2TI 2:18"/><char style="add">Specifically</char>, they teach a wrong message; <char style="add">that is</char>, they say <char style="add">wrongly that God will not cause dead people to live again because</char> he has already given us <char style="add">spiritual</char> life. <char style="add">They claim that our spiritual life is the only new life that we will receive. By saying that</char>, they cause some people <verse eid="2TI 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="2TI 2:19"/>not to continue to believe <char style="add">in Christ</char>. However, <char style="add">the congregations of</char> God are strong [MET]. <char style="add">They are like</char> a strong foundation on which is written: “The Lord knows the people who really belong to him,” and “Every person who calls Jesus [MTY] ‘Lord’ must stop doing wicked things”.<verse eid="2TI 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Avoid the bad things that some young people desire to do. Do good instead.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 2:20-22">2 Timothy 2:20-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="2TI 2:20"/>In a wealthy person’s house there are not only utensils made of gold and of silver, but also utensils made of wood and of clay. The gold and silver <char style="add">utensils are used</char> at special <char style="add">occasions/events</char>, and the others are used at ordinary <char style="add">occasions. Similarly, in a congregation there are those who</char> ◄<char style="add">are ready/desire</char>► <char style="add">to do great things for the Lord Jesus, and there are those like the teachers of false doctrines/teachings who are not</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2TI 2:21"/>Therefore, those who rid themselves of <char style="add">what is evil in their lives</char> will be able to <char style="add">work well for the Lord. They will be like</char> utensils [MET] used at special <char style="add">occasions</char>, set apart for and especially useful to the owner <char style="add">of the big house. They will be like fine utensils</char> that have been prepared {are ready} to do any kind of good work. <verse eid="2TI 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2TI 2:22"/><char style="add">Because of that</char>, you <char style="add">(sg)</char> must avoid doing the wrong actions that <char style="add">many</char> young people desire to do. Instead, you must earnestly do right actions, believe <char style="add">the true teaching</char>, love <char style="add">God and others, and you must continually be at</char> peace with those who ask the Lord <char style="add">to help them and who are</char> pure in every way (OR, who serve <char style="add">Jesus</char> faithfully).<verse eid="2TI 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not discuss foolish questions but gently instruct those who oppose the true message.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 2:23-26">2 Timothy 2:23-26</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="2TI 2:23"/>Do not talk <char style="add">with anyone who</char> foolishly <char style="add">wants</char> to argue about matters that are not important. <char style="add">Do not talk with them</char>, because you know that <char style="add">when people talk about foolish things</char>, they begin to quarrel. <verse eid="2TI 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="2TI 2:24"/>But those who serve the Lord must not quarrel. Instead, they should be kind to all people, they should be able to teach <char style="add">God’s truth well</char>, and they should be patient <char style="add">with people</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="2TI 2:25"/><char style="add">That is, they should</char> gently instruct/teach people who oppose <char style="add">the true message. They should do that</char> in order that perhaps God will cause others to completely change what they think, so that they may acknowledge/believe the true <char style="add">message</char>. <verse eid="2TI 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="2TI 2:26"/>In that way they may get free from <char style="add">what is like</char> [MET] a trap <char style="add">set by</char> the devil. The devil has deceived them in order that <char style="add">they might do</char> what he wants <char style="add">them to do</char>.<verse eid="2TI 2:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2TI 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="2TI 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Realize that evil people will cause the last days to be difficult. Avoid such people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 3:1-9">2 Timothy 3:1-9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2TI 3:1"/>
    <char style="add">You need to</char> realize that during the last days [MTY] <char style="add">before Christ returns, evil people will make</char> it difficult <char style="add">for believers to behave as they should</char>. <verse eid="2TI 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2TI 3:2"/>This is because <char style="add">such evil</char> people will be habitually loving themselves and loving money. They will habitually boast <char style="add">about themselves</char>, they will be proud, and will often say bad things <char style="add">about others. They</char> will disobey <char style="add">their</char> parents. They will not be thankful, nor will they respect <char style="add">anything that is good</char>. <verse eid="2TI 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2TI 3:3"/>They will not <char style="add">even</char> love their own family, nor agree with <char style="add">anybody</char> (OR, <char style="add">they never forgive anyone</char>). They will tell lies about people. They will not control what they say and do, nor allow anyone to control them. They will not love <char style="add">anything that is</char> good. <verse eid="2TI 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2TI 3:4"/>They will ◄betray others/hand others over to their enemies► and act foolishly. They will be overly/very proud of themselves, and they will love to please themselves instead of loving God. <verse eid="2TI 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2TI 3:5"/><char style="add">And, although they will</char> pretend that they worship God, they will not let <char style="add">God’s Spirit</char> work powerfully <char style="add">in their lives</char>. Do not associate with such people (OR, Do not let such people join <char style="add">your congregation</char>), <verse eid="2TI 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="2TI 3:6"/>because some such <char style="add">people, even now</char>, subtly/deceivingly persuade foolish women to let them come into their houses, and then they deceive those women <char style="add">so that they control what those women think. These women</char> have been burdened with sins {have sinned very much} and they have been led to do {they do} the many <char style="add">evil</char> things that they strongly desire to do. <verse eid="2TI 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2TI 3:7"/><char style="add">Even though</char> they are always <char style="add">wanting to</char> learn new things, they are never able to recognize what is true. <verse eid="2TI 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2TI 3:8"/>Just like Jannes and Jambres <char style="add">long ago</char> very much opposed Moses, so also some <char style="add">people</char> now oppose the true <char style="add">message. Those</char> people think only what is evil. God rejects them <char style="add">because they do not</char> believe <char style="add">what is true</char>. <verse eid="2TI 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="2TI 3:9"/>Nevertheless, they will not continue to succeed, because most [HYP] people will understand clearly that such people are foolish, just like people also realized <char style="add">clearly that Jannes and Jambres were foolish</char>.<verse eid="2TI 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Continue to believe what you have learned and been assured of.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 3:10-17">2 Timothy 3:10-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="2TI 3:10"/>But as for yourself, you have fully known what I have taught. You have known <char style="add">and imitated</char> the way in which I conducted my life, <char style="add">and</char> what I have been trying to do. <char style="add">You have</char> trusted <char style="add">God as</char> I have. You have been patient as I have been. <char style="add">You have</char> loved people <char style="add">as</char> I have, and <char style="add">you have</char> endured <char style="add">as you suffered like</char> I have <char style="add">suffered</char>. <verse eid="2TI 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2TI 3:11"/><char style="add">You know how I endured many times when people</char> harmed me. <char style="add">They</char> caused me to suffer at Antioch, Iconium, and Lystra <char style="add">cities</char>. <char style="add">But although they caused me to suffer</char>, I endured it; and every time <char style="add">they</char> did those things to me, the Lord rescued me. <verse eid="2TI 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2TI 3:12"/>◄Indeed/You know that►, for us <char style="add">(inc)</char> who want to live ◄in a <char style="add">godly manner/</char>in a <char style="add">manner that pleases God</char>►, we will always be persecuted {there will always be people who will cause us to suffer} because we <char style="add">have a close relationship with</char> Christ Jesus. <verse eid="2TI 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2TI 3:13"/>Evil people (OR, And those) who deceive other people will ◄get worse/teach things that are more and more wrong►. <char style="add">Specifically, they will</char> deceive other people, and <char style="add">those who hear them will</char> deceive others. <verse eid="2TI 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="2TI 3:14"/>But you, in contrast, must continue <char style="add">to believe</char> what you have learned and ◄been assured of/firmly believe►. <char style="add">I know that you are confident/sure that it is true because</char> you know that you have learned it from all <char style="add">of us who taught you</char> ◄<char style="add">God’s truth/what is right</char>►. <verse eid="2TI 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2TI 3:15"/>From <char style="add">the time when you were</char> a child you have known the holy writings/Scriptures. <char style="add">You now know that</char> they enabled you to become wise so that God saved you because of your believing in Christ Jesus. <verse eid="2TI 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="2TI 3:16"/>God ◄inspired/put into men’s minds► everything <char style="add">that is written</char> in the Scriptures {they <char style="add">wrote</char> in the holy writings}, and those writings are all useful to teach <char style="add">us what is true</char>, to cause us to know <char style="add">when we are</char> wrong and then ◄to correct us/to show us what we have done that is wrong►, and to train/teach us to do what is right. <verse eid="2TI 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2TI 3:17"/>What <char style="add">is written</char> {they wrote} is useful to help us who <char style="add">serve</char> God to be ready/prepared to do all that we should do. By means of it, we are equipped {God gives us what we need} in order to do every <char style="add">kind of</char> good deeds.<verse eid="2TI 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2TI 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="2TI 4"/>
  <para style="s1">I solemnly command you to preach the true message and do everything that you ought to do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 4:1-8">2 Timothy 4:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="2TI 4:1"/>Christ Jesus <char style="add">is going to come back and</char> judge those who are living <char style="add">when he comes</char> and those who will have died. He will judge them <char style="add">concerning what rewards they deserve, and</char> he will rule everyone. So, <char style="add">knowing that</char> he and God are watching <char style="add">everything that we do</char>, I solemnly/earnestly command you <verse eid="2TI 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="2TI 4:2"/>that you proclaim the <char style="add">true</char> message to people. Always be ready/prepared <char style="add">to proclaim it</char>, whether people want to hear it or not. <char style="add">Some people are saying things that are not correct</char>; ◄refute their teaching/show why their teaching is wrong►. Rebuke them when they are doing wrong. Tell them what they ought to do. Be very patient while you teach them. <verse eid="2TI 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="2TI 4:3"/><char style="add">Do these things</char> because there will be a time when people will not listen to good teaching. Instead, they will bring in many teachers for themselves who will tell them just what they want to hear [IDM]. <char style="add">The reason that they will bring in such teachers is</char> that they want to do the evil things that they desire. <verse eid="2TI 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="2TI 4:4"/>That is, they will not listen to [MTY] what is true, but will listen instead to <char style="add">strange</char> stories from our ancestors. <verse eid="2TI 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="2TI 4:5"/><char style="add">Furthermore, I command that</char> you always control what you think and do. <char style="add">Be willing</char> to endure hardships/suffering. Your work should be telling people the message <char style="add">about Christ Jesus</char>. As you serve <char style="add">the Lord</char>, do everything that <char style="add">God has told</char> you to do.<verse eid="2TI 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="2TI 4:6"/>
    <char style="add">Timothy, I say these things to</char> you because as for me, <char style="add">it is as though</char> [MET] <char style="add">they are now about to kill me. It is as though my blood will</char> be poured out {they will kill me} <char style="add">as a sacrifice on the altar</char>; that is, <char style="add">I know</char> that it is the time for me to die [EUP]. <verse eid="2TI 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="2TI 4:7"/><char style="add">And as to telling people the</char> good <char style="add">message and defending it</char>, I have ◄exerted myself thoroughly/done it with all my energy► [MET], <char style="add">like a boxer does. As to doing</char> the work that God gave me to do, I have completed it, <char style="add">like a runner who finishes</char> [MET] the race. <char style="add">As to</char> what we believe, I ◄have been loyal to it/continue to believe it►. <verse eid="2TI 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="2TI 4:8"/><char style="add">So, like people award</char> a prize [MET] <char style="add">to the winner of a race</char>, the Lord, who judges rightly, will give me a reward <char style="add">because I have lived</char> righteously. He will give me that reward when [MTY] <char style="add">he judges people</char>. And not only <char style="add">will he reward</char> me, but he will also reward all those who very much want him to come back.<verse eid="2TI 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do your best to come to me soon.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 4:9-15">2 Timothy 4:9-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="2TI 4:9"/>◄Do your best/Try hard► to come to me soon. <verse eid="2TI 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="2TI 4:10"/><char style="add">I say that</char> because Demas has left me. He wanted very much <char style="add">the good things that he might enjoy</char> [MTY] in this world <char style="add">right now</char>, and so he went to Thessalonica <char style="add">city</char>. Crescens <char style="add">went to serve the Lord</char> in Galatia <char style="add">province</char>, and Titus went to Dalmatia <char style="add">district</char>. <verse eid="2TI 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="2TI 4:11"/>Luke is the only one who is still with me <char style="add">of those who were helping me. And when you come</char>, bring Mark with you, because he is useful to help me in my work. <verse eid="2TI 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="2TI 4:12"/>Tychicus <char style="add">cannot help me because</char> I sent him to Ephesus <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="2TI 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="2TI 4:13"/>And when you come, bring the coat that I left with Carpus in Troas <char style="add">city</char>. Also, bring the books, but ◄most of all/especially► <char style="add">I want</char> ◄the parchments/the animal skins► <char style="add">on which important things are written</char>.<verse eid="2TI 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="2TI 4:14"/>Alexander, the man who makes things from metal, did many evil/harmful things to me. The Lord will punish him for what he did. <verse eid="2TI 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="2TI 4:15"/>So you, too, must beware of him. <char style="add">He will try to destroy your work if he can</char>, because he very much opposes the message that we <char style="add">proclaim</char>.<verse eid="2TI 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Lord will rescue me from everything that is evil and bring me safely to heaven.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 4:16-18">2 Timothy 4:16-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="2TI 4:16"/>When I first defended myself <char style="add">in court here</char>, no one came along <char style="add">to help defend</char> me. Instead, they all left me. <char style="add">I pray</char> that it will not be counted against {<char style="add">God</char> will forgive} them [LIT] <char style="add">for leaving me</char>. <verse eid="2TI 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="2TI 4:17"/>Nevertheless, the Lord was with me and strengthened me. He enabled me to fully preach the message, and all the non-Jewish people <char style="add">in the court</char> (OR, people from many nations) heard it. And I was rescued <char style="add">by the Lord</char> {<char style="add">the Lord</char> rescued me} <char style="add">from great danger, as if I were taken</char> [MET] out of a lion’s (OR, wild animal’s) mouth. <verse eid="2TI 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="2TI 4:18"/><char style="add">Therefore, I am sure that</char> the Lord will rescue me from everything that is truly evil and will bring me safely to heaven, where he rules. Praise him forever! ◄Amen!/May it be so!►<verse eid="2TI 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Greet my friends there. Your friends here greet you. May the Lord bless you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="2TI 4:19-22">2 Timothy 4:19-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="2TI 4:19"/>Greet <char style="add">for me</char> Priscilla and <char style="add">her husband</char> Aquila and the family of Onesiphorus. <verse eid="2TI 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="2TI 4:20"/>Erastus stayed in Corinth <char style="add">city</char>. Trophimus, I left in Miletus <char style="add">city</char> because he was sick. <verse eid="2TI 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="2TI 4:21"/>◄Do your best/Try hard► to come to me before ◄the stormy season/winter►. Eubulus, Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and many other fellow believers <char style="add">in this city</char> ◄send their greetings to/say that they are thinking affectionately about► you. <verse eid="2TI 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="2TI 4:22"/><char style="add">I pray that</char> the Lord will <char style="add">help you in</char> your spirit, <char style="add">Timothy, and</char> that <char style="add">he</char> will act kindly toward all of you <char style="add">believers who are there</char>.<verse eid="2TI 4:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="2TI 4"/>
</usx>
