<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="DAN" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8) o</para>
  <para style="h">DANIEL</para>
  <para style="toc1">Daniel</para>
  <para style="toc2">Daniel</para>
  <para style="toc3">Dan</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of Daniel foretelling about God controlling all nations of the world and about the coming one. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Daniel</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="DAN 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Daniel was taken to Babylon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 1:1"/>After King Jehoiakim had been ruling in Judah for almost three years, King Nebuchadnezzar of Babylon came to Jerusalem <char style="add">with his army</char> and surrounded the city. <verse eid="DAN 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 1:2"/><char style="add">After two years,</char> Yahweh allowed Nebuchadnezzar’s <char style="add">soldiers </char> to capture Jehoiakim, <char style="add">who was the</char> King of Judah. They also took some of the things that were in the temple of God, and took them to Babylonia. There Nebuchadnezzar put them in the temple of his god.<verse eid="DAN 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 1:3"/>Then Nebuchadnezzar commanded Ashpenaz, the chief official in his palace, to bring <char style="add">to him</char> some of the Israeli men <char style="add">whom they had brought to Babylon. He wanted men </char> who belonged to important families, including the family of the King of Judah. <verse eid="DAN 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 1:4"/><char style="add">King Nebuchadnezzar wanted only</char> men who were very healthy, handsome/good-looking, wise, well-educated, capable of learning many things, and suitable for working in the palace. He also wanted to teach them the Babylonian language and have them read things that had been written in the Babylonian language. <verse eid="DAN 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 1:5"/>The king commanded <char style="add">his servants</char>, “Give them the same kind of food and wine that is given to me. Train them for three years. Then they will become my servants.”<verse eid="DAN 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 1:6"/>Among the young Israeli men <char style="add">who were chosen</char> were <char style="add">me</char>, Daniel, and Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, who all came from Judah. <verse eid="DAN 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 1:7"/>But Ashpenaz gave us <char style="add">Babylonian</char> names. The name he gave to me was Belteshazzar, the name he gave to Hananiah was Shadrach, the name he gave to Mishael was Meshach, and the name he gave to Azariah was Abednego.<verse eid="DAN 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 1:8"/>But I decided that I would not eat the kind of food that the king ate, or drink the wine that he drank, because that would make me ◄ritually defiled/unacceptable to God►. So I asked Ashpenaz to allow me to eat and drink other things. <verse eid="DAN 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 1:9"/>God had caused Ashpenaz to greatly respect me, <verse eid="DAN 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 1:10"/>but he was worried about what I suggested. He said, “My master, the king, has commanded that you eat the kinds of food and drink that he does. If <char style="add">you eat other things and as a result</char> you become more thin and pale than the other young men who are your age, he will <char style="add">order his soldiers to</char> cut off my head because of what you have done!”<verse eid="DAN 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 1:11"/>Ashpenaz had ordered a guard to watch me, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah. <verse eid="DAN 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 1:12"/>So I said to this guard: “<char style="add">Please</char> test us for ten days. <char style="add">During that time</char> give us <char style="add">only</char> vegetables to eat and water to drink. <verse eid="DAN 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 1:13"/>After ten days, see how we look, and see how the other young men look, the ones who are eating the kind of food that the king eats. Then you can decide about <char style="add">what food you will let us eat</char>.” <verse eid="DAN 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 1:14"/>The guard agreed to do what I suggested, and he tested us like that for ten days.<verse eid="DAN 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 1:15"/>After ten days, <char style="add">he saw that</char> my three friends and I looked healthier [DOU] than the young men who had been eating the food that the king wanted them to eat. <verse eid="DAN 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 1:16"/>So after that, the guard gave us <char style="add">only</char> vegetables to eat; he did not give us the king’s special food and wine.<verse eid="DAN 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 1:17"/>And God gave to us four young men wisdom and the ability to study many things that Babylonians had written and studied. And <char style="add">he also gave to</char> me the ability to understand the meaning of visions and dreams.<verse eid="DAN 1:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 1:18"/>When those three years that the king had set for training us young men from Judah were ended, Ashpenaz brought all of us to King Nebuchadnezzar. <verse eid="DAN 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 1:19"/>The king talked with <char style="add">each of</char> us, and realized that none of the other young men were as capable as Hananiah, Mishael, Azariah and I were. So we four became the king’s special advisors/servants. <verse eid="DAN 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 1:20"/>In all important matters, the king found that what we <char style="add">four men</char> advised was ten times as good as what all the magicians and sorcerers/fortune-tellers in his kingdom advised.<verse eid="DAN 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 1:21"/>I remained <char style="add">there serving the king more than 60 years</char>, until the first year that Cyrus became king.<verse eid="DAN 1:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="DAN 2"/>
  <para style="s1">What Nebuchadnezzar dreamed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 2:1"/>
    <char style="add">One night</char> during the second year that Nebuchadnezzar ruled, he had a dream. The dream worried him very much; and <char style="add">as a result</char> he could not sleep. <verse eid="DAN 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 2:2"/><char style="add">The next morning </char> he summoned his men who worked magic, fortune-tellers, those who worked sorcery, and those who studied the stars. <char style="add">Because he had forgotten what he had dreamed,</char> he insisted that they tell him what he had dreamed. As they stood there in front of the king, <verse eid="DAN 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 2:3"/>he said, “I had a dream <char style="add">last night </char> that worries me. <char style="add">Tell me what I dreamed, because</char> I want to know what the dream <char style="add">means</char>.”<verse eid="DAN 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 2:4"/>The men who studied the stars replied to the king, speaking in the Aramaic <char style="add">language</char>. They said, “King Nebuchadnezzar, we hope that you will live a long time! Tell us what you dreamed, and <char style="add">then</char> we will tell you what it means!”<verse eid="DAN 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 2:5"/>But the king replied, “I have firmly decided that you must tell me the dream, and <char style="add">also tell me</char> what it means. If you do not do that, I will <char style="add">order my soldiers to</char> cut you into pieces, and to cause your houses to become only piles of stones! <verse eid="DAN 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 2:6"/>But if you tell me what I dreamed and what it means, I will reward you. I will give you wonderful gifts and greatly honor you. So tell me what I dreamed and what it means!”<verse eid="DAN 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 2:7"/>But again they said, “Tell us what you dreamed, and <char style="add">then</char> we will tell you what it means.”<verse eid="DAN 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 2:8"/>The king replied, “I know that you are just trying to get more time, because you know that I will do to you what I said that I would do. <verse eid="DAN 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 2:9"/>If you do not tell me what I dreamed, you will be punished. <char style="add">I think that</char> you have all agreed to tell me lies and <char style="add">other</char> wicked things, because you hope that I will change ◄<char style="add">my mind/what I am thinking</char>►. But tell me the dream, and <char style="add">then</char> I will know that you can <char style="add">also</char> tell me what it means.”<verse eid="DAN 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 2:10"/>The men who studied the stars replied, “There is no one on the earth who can do what you ask! There is no king, <char style="add">even</char> a great and mighty king, who has <char style="add">ever</char> asked his men who work magic or his fortune-tellers or men who study the stars to do something like that! <verse eid="DAN 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 2:11"/>What you are asking <char style="add">us to do</char> is impossible. Only the gods can tell you what you dreamed, and they do not live among us!”<verse eid="DAN 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 2:12"/>The king was very angry when he heard that, so he commanded <char style="add">his soldiers</char> that they execute all such wise men in Babylon. <verse eid="DAN 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 2:13"/>And because of what the king commanded, they sent some men to find me and my <char style="add">three</char> friends, to execute us <char style="add">also</char>.<verse eid="DAN 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 2:14"/>Arioch, the commander of the king’s guards, came to kill us. But I spoke to him very wisely and tactfully/skillfully. <verse eid="DAN 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 2:15"/>I asked Arioch, “Why has the king made such a harsh/terrible decree?” So Arioch told me all that had happened <char style="add">because of the king’s dream</char>. <verse eid="DAN 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 2:16"/>I <char style="add">immediately</char> went to talk to the king and requested that the king give me some time, so that I could find out <char style="add">what the dream was and </char> what the dream meant.<verse eid="DAN 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 2:17"/>Then I went home, and I told my friends, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, what had happened. <verse eid="DAN 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 2:18"/>I urged them to ask God, who lives/rules in heaven, to have mercy on us by telling us the secret <char style="add">meaning of what the king dreamed</char>, in order that we and the other wise men in Babylon would not be executed. <verse eid="DAN 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 2:19"/>And that night <char style="add">God</char> gave to me a vision in which he revealed the secret. Then I praised God, <verse eid="DAN 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 2:20"/>saying,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 2:20">“We should praise God [MTY] forever,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 2:20">because <char style="add">only</char> he truly is wise and powerful.<verse eid="DAN 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 2:21"/>He determines what events will happen through the years.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 2:21">He removes <char style="add">some</char> kings and gives their authority to <char style="add">new</char> kings.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 2:21">He is the one who causes people to become wise</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 2:21">and enables those who study to understand <char style="add">many</char> things.<verse eid="DAN 2:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 2:22"/>He reveals things that are very mysterious;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 2:22">he is surrounded by light,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 2:22">but he knows things that are hidden <char style="add">as though they were</char> in the darkness.<verse eid="DAN 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 2:23"/>God, whom my ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 2:23">I thank you and I praise you,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 2:23">because you have caused me to be wise and made me strong.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 2:23">You have told me what my friends and I asked you to tell us;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 2:23">and you have revealed to us what the king demanded to know.”<verse eid="DAN 2:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Daniel told the meaning of the dream</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 2:24"/>Then I went to Arioch, the man whom the king had appointed to execute the wise men in Babylon. I said to him, “Do not kill those wise men. Take me to the king, and I will tell him what his dream means.”<verse eid="DAN 2:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 2:25"/>So Arioch quickly took me to the king. He said to the king, “I have found <char style="add">this man</char>, one of the men whom we brought from Judah who <char style="add">says he can</char> can tell you what your dream means!”<verse eid="DAN 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 2:26"/>The king said to me, whose <char style="add">new</char> name was Belteshazzar, “<char style="add">Is this true</char>? Can you tell me what I dreamed and what it means?”<verse eid="DAN 2:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 2:27"/>I replied, “There are no wise men or fortune-tellers or men who work magic or men who work sorcery who can tell such things to you. <verse eid="DAN 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DAN 2:28"/>But there is a God in heaven who reveals secrets. And he has shown in <char style="add">your dream</char> what will happen in the future. Now I will tell you what you dreamed, the vision you saw <char style="add">as you were lying</char> on your bed.<verse eid="DAN 2:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DAN 2:29"/>O King, while you were sleeping, you dreamed about events that will happen in the future. The one who reveals mysteries has shown you what is going to happen. <verse eid="DAN 2:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DAN 2:30"/>And it is not because I am wiser than anyone else on earth that I know the meaning of this mysterious dream. It is because God wanted you to understand what you were thinking.<verse eid="DAN 2:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="DAN 2:31"/>O King, <char style="add">in your vision</char> you saw in front of you a huge and terrifying statue <char style="add">of a man. It was</char> shining very brightly, and it was frightening and awesome. <verse eid="DAN 2:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DAN 2:32"/>The head of the statue was <char style="add">made</char> of pure gold. Its chest and arms <char style="add">were made of</char> silver. Its belly and thighs <char style="add">were made of </char> bronze. <verse eid="DAN 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DAN 2:33"/>Its legs <char style="add">were made of</char> iron, and its feet were a mixture of clay and iron. <verse eid="DAN 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DAN 2:34"/>As you watched, something cut a rock <char style="add">from a mountain, but it was</char> not a human <char style="add">who cut it</char>. The rock <char style="add">tumbled down and </char> smashed the feet of the statue, feet <char style="add">that were made of</char> iron and clay. It smashed them to bits. <verse eid="DAN 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DAN 2:35"/>Then the rest of the statue collapsed into a big heap of iron, clay, bronze, silver, and gold. The pieces of the statue were as small as bits of chaff on the ground where it is threshed, and the wind blew away all the tiny pieces. There was nothing left. But the rock that smashed the statue became a large mountain that covered the whole earth.<verse eid="DAN 2:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="DAN 2:36"/>That was what you dreamed. Now I will tell you what it means. <verse eid="DAN 2:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DAN 2:37"/>You are a king <char style="add">who rules</char> over <char style="add">many other</char> kings. The God who rules in heaven has caused you to rule over them and has given you great power [DOU] and has honored you. <verse eid="DAN 2:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DAN 2:38"/>He has caused you to be the ruler over all people, and <char style="add">even</char> the animals and birds are controlled by you. <char style="add">So</char> the head <char style="add">of the statue</char> represents you.<verse eid="DAN 2:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DAN 2:39"/>But after your <char style="add">kingdom/rule</char> ends, there will be another <char style="add">great</char> kingdom, <char style="add">but it</char> will not be as great as yours. <char style="add">The silver parts of the statue represent that kingdom</char>. Then there will be a third <char style="add">great</char> kingdom <char style="add">whose king </char> will rule over the whole earth. The bronze parts <char style="add">of the statue represent </char> that kingdom. <verse eid="DAN 2:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DAN 2:40"/>After that kingdom ends, there will be a fourth <char style="add">great</char> kingdom. The iron <char style="add">parts of the statue represent that kingdom</char>. <char style="add">The army of </char> that kingdom will smash the previous kingdoms, just like iron smashes everything that it strikes. <verse eid="DAN 2:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DAN 2:41"/>The feet and toes of the statue that you saw, that were a mixture of iron and clay, indicate that the kingdom they represent will <char style="add">later</char> be divided. <verse eid="DAN 2:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DAN 2:42"/>Some parts of that kingdom will be as strong as iron, but some parts will not remain together, just as iron and clay do not stick together. <verse eid="DAN 2:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DAN 2:43"/>The mixture of iron and clay <char style="add">in the statue</char> shows also that the rulers of those kingdoms that separate from each other will try to form alliances with each other as a result of members of the royal families of those kingdoms marrying each other. But that will not succeed, just as iron and clay do not stick together.<verse eid="DAN 2:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DAN 2:44"/>But while those kings are ruling, God who rules in heaven will establish a kingdom that will never end. No one will ever defeat its king. He will completely destroy all those kingdoms, but his kingdom will remain forever. <verse eid="DAN 2:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DAN 2:45"/>That is the meaning of the rock that something cut from the mountain, the rock that will crush to tiny bits the statue that is made of iron, bronze, silver, and gold.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DAN 2:45">O king, the great God has shown you what will truly happen in the future. And you can trust <char style="add">what I told you about</char> the meaning of the dream.”<verse eid="DAN 2:45"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Daniel was made the chief advisor</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="DAN 2:46"/>Then King Nebuchadnezzar prostrated himself in front of me <char style="add">in great respect</char>. He commanded <char style="add">his people</char> that they burn incense and burn an offering of grain to honor me. <verse eid="DAN 2:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DAN 2:47"/>The king said to me, “<char style="add">Your God has enabled </char> you to tell me the meaning of this dream/mystery, so now I truly know that your God is greater than all the other gods and all other kings. He reveals <char style="add">to people</char> things that they cannot know.”<verse eid="DAN 2:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="DAN 2:48"/>Then the king gave many gifts to me, and he <char style="add">also</char> appointed me to rule over the entire province of Babylon, and <char style="add">also</char> to be the boss of all his wise men. <verse eid="DAN 2:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DAN 2:49"/>I asked the king to appoint Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego to <char style="add">also</char> have important positions in Babylon province, and the king did what I asked him to do. But <char style="add">I did my work while</char> I stayed at the king’s palace.<verse eid="DAN 2:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="DAN 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Nebuchadnezzar had a gold statue made</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 3:1"/>King Nebuchadnezzar ordered his men to make a gold statue. It was ◄90 feet/27 meters► high and ◄9 feet/2.7 meters► wide. They set it up in the Dura plain in Babylon province. <verse eid="DAN 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 3:2"/>Then he sent messages to all the provincial governors, the district governors, the chief advisors, the counselors, the various judges, and all the other officials in the province. He told them to come to the dedication of the statue that he had set up. <verse eid="DAN 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 3:3"/>When they all arrived, they all stood in front of that statue. <verse eid="DAN 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 3:4"/>Then an announcer shouted, “You people who come from many countries and many people-groups and <char style="add">who speak many</char> languages, listen to what the king has commanded! <verse eid="DAN 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 3:5"/>When you hear the sounds made by the trumpets, the flutes, the guitars, the harps, the wind instruments, and all the other musical instruments, bow down to worship King Nebuchadnezzar’s gold statue. <verse eid="DAN 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 3:6"/>Anyone who refuses to do that will be thrown into a blazing furnace!”<verse eid="DAN 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 3:7"/>So when all those people who had gathered heard the sounds made by the musical instruments, they all bowed down to worship the statue.<verse eid="DAN 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 3:8"/>But some of the men who studied the stars went to the king. <verse eid="DAN 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 3:9"/>They reported to him, “We hope that you, O king, will live a long time! <verse eid="DAN 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 3:10"/>You decreed that all the officials <char style="add">whom you had gathered</char> should bow down and worship the gold statue when they heard the sounds made by the musical instruments. <verse eid="DAN 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 3:11"/>You also decreed that those who refused to do that would be thrown into a blazing furnace. <verse eid="DAN 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 3:12"/>Sir, there are some men from Judah whom you have appointed to be officials in Babylon province who have not obeyed your decree. Their names are Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. They have refused to worship your god and the gold statue that you have set up.”<verse eid="DAN 3:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 3:13"/>Nebuchadnezzar became very angry. He commanded <char style="add">his soldiers</char> to bring in Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego. When they were brought to him, <verse eid="DAN 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 3:14"/>Nebuchadnezzar said to them, “Is it true that you three men have refused to worship my gods or the gold statue that I have set up? <verse eid="DAN 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 3:15"/><char style="add">If that is true,</char> I will give you one more chance. If you bow down to worship the statue that I have set up when you hear the sounds of the musical instruments, fine. But if you refuse, you will be thrown immediately into the blazing furnace. Then ◄what god will be able to rescue you from my power?/no god will be able to rescue you from my power!►” [RHQ]<verse eid="DAN 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 3:16"/>Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego replied, “Nebuchadnezzar, we do not need to defend our <char style="add">actions</char> to you in this matter. <verse eid="DAN 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 3:17"/>If we are thrown into the blazing furnace, the God whom we worship is able to rescue us. Sir, he will rescue us from your power. <verse eid="DAN 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 3:18"/>But <char style="add">even</char> if he does not <char style="add">rescue us</char>, you need to know that we will never worship your gods or the gold statue that you have set up.”<verse eid="DAN 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 3:19"/>Nebuchadnezzar was extremely angry. <char style="add">His being very angry even</char> showed on his face. He commanded that the furnace should be made seven times as hot as usual. <verse eid="DAN 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 3:20"/><char style="add">After that was done,</char> he commanded some of the <char style="add">very</char> strong men of his army to tie Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego, and <char style="add">then</char> to throw them into the blazing furnace. <verse eid="DAN 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 3:21"/>So <char style="add">the soldiers</char> tied them up and threw them into the furnace, while they were wearing their clothes. <verse eid="DAN 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 3:22"/>Because the fire had been made very hot because the king had very strongly ordered them to do that, the flames <char style="add">leaped out and</char> killed the soldiers as they were throwing the men into the fire! <verse eid="DAN 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 3:23"/>So Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego fell into the roaring flames.<verse eid="DAN 3:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 3:24"/>But as Nebuchadnezzar was watching, he was amazed. He suddenly jumped up and shouted to his advisors, “Did we tie up three men and throw them into the flames, or not?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DAN 3:24">They replied, “Yes, O king, <char style="add">we did</char>.”<verse eid="DAN 3:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 3:25"/>Nebuchadnezzar shouted, “<char style="add">Look</char>! I see four men in the fire! They have no ropes on them, they are walking around, and <char style="add">the flames</char> are not hurting them! And the fourth man looks like a divine being!”<verse eid="DAN 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 3:26"/>Nebuchadnezzar came closer to the opening of the flaming furnace, and he shouted, “Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, you who worship the Supreme God, come out of there! Come here!” So they stepped out of the fire.<verse eid="DAN 3:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 3:27"/>Then all the king’s officials crowded around them. They saw that the flames had not harmed them. The flames had not <char style="add">even</char> singed any of the hair on their heads or scorched any of their clothes! There was not <char style="add">even</char> any smell of smoke on them!<verse eid="DAN 3:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DAN 3:28"/>
    <char style="add">Then</char> Nebuchadnezzar said, “Praise the God whom Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego <char style="add">worship</char>! He sent one of his angels to rescue these <char style="add">three</char> men who worship him and trust in him. They ignored my command; they insisted that they would worship only their God, and were willing to die instead of worshiping any other god. <verse eid="DAN 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DAN 3:29"/>Therefore, I am <char style="add">now</char> making this decree: ‘If any people, from any country or people-group or any language group, criticize the God whom Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego worship, they will be cut in pieces and their houses <char style="add">will be torn down and</char> made into a pile of rubble. There is no other god who can rescue people like this!’ ”<verse eid="DAN 3:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DAN 3:30"/>Then the king gave Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego more important positions in Babylon province than they had before.<verse eid="DAN 3:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="DAN 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Nebuchadnezzar dreamed about a tree</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 4:1"/>
    <char style="add">Several years after </char> Nebuchadnezzar <char style="add">started to rule, he sent this message </char> to <char style="add">the people of </char> every nation and people-group and all language groups in his empire. <char style="add">He wrote,</char></para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DAN 4:1">“I wish/hope that everything is going very well with you!<verse eid="DAN 4:1"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 4:2"/>I want you to know about <char style="add">all</char> the wonderful miracles [DOU] that the Supreme God has performed for me.<verse eid="DAN 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 4:3"/>He performs great miracles,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 4:3">and does wonderful things.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 4:3">His kingdom will last forever;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 4:3">his rule <char style="add">over people</char> will never end.<verse eid="DAN 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 4:4"/>I, Nebuchadnezzar, was living in my palace. I was living luxuriantly, and everything was going very well for me. <verse eid="DAN 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 4:5"/>But one night I had a dream that caused me to be very afraid. I saw visions that terrified me as I lay on my bed. <verse eid="DAN 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 4:6"/>So I summoned all the wise men in Babylon, in order that they would come and tell me what it meant. <verse eid="DAN 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 4:7"/>All the men who worked magic, the fortune-tellers, the men who worked sorcery, and men who studied the stars came to me. I told them what I had dreamed, but they could not tell me what it meant. <verse eid="DAN 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 4:8"/>Finally, Daniel came to me, and I <char style="add">decided to</char> tell him what I had dreamed. One of my officials had given him a new name, Belteshazzar, to honor my own god. I knew that the spirit of the holy gods was in him.<verse eid="DAN 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 4:9"/>So, <char style="add">using the name that had been given to him</char>, I said, ‘Belteshazzar, you are the most important of all my fortune-tellers. I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in you, and that you can reveal all mysteries. There is none that is too difficult for you. So, tell me what my dream means. <verse eid="DAN 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 4:10"/>This is what I dreamed while I was lying on my bed: I saw a large tree <char style="add">growing</char> in the middle of the land. <verse eid="DAN 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 4:11"/>The tree was very strong and had grown very tall; <char style="add">it seemed that</char> its top reached up to the sky, with the result that everyone in the world [HYP] could see it. <verse eid="DAN 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 4:12"/>It had beautiful leaves, and it had produced a lot of fruit for people to eat. Wild animals rested in the shade of that tree, and birds built nests in its branches. All the living creatures everywhere in the world got food from that tree.<verse eid="DAN 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 4:13"/>While I was still lying on my bed, I saw another vision. In the vision I saw a holy angel coming down from heaven. <verse eid="DAN 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 4:14"/>The angel shouted, “Cut down the tree, and cut off its branches! Strip/Shake off all of its leaves, and scatter its fruit. Chase away the animals that are lying in the shade of the tree, and the birds that are in its branches. <verse eid="DAN 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 4:15"/>But leave the stump of the tree and its roots in the ground. Fasten a band of iron and bronze around the stump, and allow it to stay there with grass around it.”<verse eid="DAN 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 4:16"/>
    <char style="add">That tree seems to have represented a man, because the angel also said</char>, “Cause that man to live <char style="add">out in the fields</char> among the animals and plants. Cause the dew from the sky to make his body damp <char style="add">each morning</char>. Do not allow him to <char style="add">continue to</char> have a mind like humans; instead, cause him to have a mind like animals have, for seven years.<verse eid="DAN 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 4:17"/>The holy angels have decided what must happen. They want to inform everyone that the Supreme God rules over all the kingdoms in this world. He is the one who chooses who will rule these kingdoms. He <char style="add">sometimes</char> allows very unimportant people to become rulers.”<verse eid="DAN 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 4:18"/>Belteshazzar, that is what I, King Nebuchadnezzar, saw in my dream. Now tell me what the dream means. No one else can tell me. <char style="add">I asked</char> all the very wise men in my kingdom <char style="add">to tell me</char> what it means, <char style="add">but they were unable to do that</char>. But you can <char style="add">tell me</char>, because the spirit of the holy gods is in you.”<verse eid="DAN 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Daniel explained the dream</para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 4:19"/>I, whose <char style="add">new</char> name was Belteshazzar, did not say anything for some time, <char style="add">because</char> I was very worried/disturbed <char style="add">about the meaning of the dream. Finally</char>, the king said to me, “Belteshazzar, do not be afraid about the dream and about what it means.” I replied, “Sir, I wish that the events that were predicted in your dream would happen to your enemies, <char style="add">and not to you</char>.<verse eid="DAN 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 4:20"/>
    <char style="add">In your dream/vision</char> you saw a very strong and very tall tree. It <char style="add">seemed to</char> reach to the sky, <char style="add">with the result that </char> everyone in the world could see it. <verse eid="DAN 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 4:21"/>It had beautiful leaves and it had produced a lot of fruit for people to eat. Wild animals rested in the shade of that tree, and birds built nests in its branches. <verse eid="DAN 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 4:22"/>◄Your majesty/O King►, that tree <char style="add">represents</char> you! You have become very powerful. <char style="add">It is as though</char> your greatness reaches up to the sky, and you rule people all over the world.<verse eid="DAN 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 4:23"/>
    <char style="add">Then</char> you saw a holy angel coming down from heaven. That angel said, ‘Cut down the tree, and cut off its branches! Strip/Shake off all of its leaves, and scatter its fruit. But leave the stump of the tree and its roots in the ground. Fasten a band of iron and bronze around the stump and <char style="add">allow it to stay there</char> with grass around it. <char style="add">Each morning</char> cause the dew from the sky to make this man, <char style="add">who was represented by the tree</char>, damp. Cause him to live in the fields with the animals for seven years.’<verse eid="DAN 4:23"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 4:24"/>◄Your Majesty/O King►, that is what your dream means. That is what the Supreme God has declared will happen to you. <verse eid="DAN 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 4:25"/><char style="add">Your advisors</char> will force you to live away from other people. You will live in the fields with the wild animals. You will eat grass like cows do, and dew from the sky will cause your <char style="add">body</char> to be damp/wet <char style="add">every morning</char>. You will live that way for seven years, until you learn that it is the Supreme God who rules over the kingdoms of the world, and he appoints the ones whom he chooses <char style="add">to rule them</char>. <verse eid="DAN 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 4:26"/>But the stump of the tree and its roots were left <char style="add">in the ground</char>. That means that you will rule your kingdom again when you learn that it is God [MTY] who is <char style="add">really</char> the ruler. <verse eid="DAN 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 4:27"/>◄Your Majesty/O King►, please do what I am telling you to do. Stop sinning, and do what is right. Turn away from your evil behavior. Act mercifully to poor people. If you do that, perhaps you will continue to be sucessful.”<verse eid="DAN 4:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The dream was fulfilled</para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DAN 4:28"/>But <char style="add">the king refused to stop sinning. So what was predicted in the dream is</char> what happened to him. <verse eid="DAN 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DAN 4:29"/>Twelve months later, <char style="add">one day</char> he was walking <char style="add">on the flat roof</char> of his palace in Babylon. <verse eid="DAN 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DAN 4:30"/>As he <char style="add">looked out over/across the city</char>, he said <char style="add">to those around him</char>, “I have built this great <char style="add">city of</char> Babylon to be the place where I rule! I have built it to display my own power, in order <char style="add">to show people</char> my glory, to show them that I am very great!”<verse eid="DAN 4:30"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="DAN 4:31"/>While he was still saying this, God [MTY] spoke from heaven and said, “King Nebuchadnezzar, this is what I am saying to you: You are no longer the ruler of this kingdom! <verse eid="DAN 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DAN 4:32"/><char style="add">Your advisors</char> will force you to live away from <char style="add">other</char> people. You will live in the fields with wild animals, and you will eat grass like cows do. You will live that way for seven years, until you learn that <char style="add">it is</char> I, the Supreme God, who rules over the kingdoms of this world, and I appoint the ones whom I have chosen to rule them.”<verse eid="DAN 4:32"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="DAN 4:33"/>Immediately what <char style="add">God</char> predicted happened. Nebuchadnezzar <char style="add">became insane, so his advisors</char> forced him to live away from other people. He ate grass like cows <char style="add">do</char>, and dew from the sky caused his body to be damp/wet <char style="add">every morning. He lived like that</char> until his hair was as long as eagles’ feathers, and his fingernails became like birds’ claws.<verse eid="DAN 4:33"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="DAN 4:34"/>“After those <char style="add">seven</char> years ended, I, Nebuchadnezzar, looked up toward heaven, <char style="add">and I acknowledged that what God said was true</char>. Then I could think correctly again. I praised and worshiped the Supreme God, and I honored him, the one who lives forever.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="DAN 4:34"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 4:34">He rules forever;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 4:34">his kingdom will never end.<verse eid="DAN 4:34"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="DAN 4:35"/>All the people in the world are very insignificant;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 4:35">we are not like him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 4:35">He has the power to do whatever he wants to do,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 4:35">among the angels in heaven and among us people who live on the earth.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 4:35">
    <char style="add">So</char> no one can stop him [SYN],</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 4:35">and no one can <char style="add">challenge him</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 4:35">saying to him, ‘Why <char style="add">are you doing these things</char>?’<verse eid="DAN 4:35"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="DAN 4:36"/>When I was able to think correctly again, I was honored again, and I <char style="add">was able to</char> rule my glorious/great kingdom again. My advisors came to me again <char style="add">to talk about what should be done</char>, and I became greater and more powerful than I was before. <verse eid="DAN 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DAN 4:37"/>Now I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and honor [DOU] <char style="add">God</char>, the king who rules in heaven. All of his actions are just and right. And he is able to cause to become humble those who are proud, <char style="add">like I was</char>.”<verse eid="DAN 4:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="DAN 5"/>
  <para style="s1">The writing on the wall</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 5:1"/>
    <char style="add">Several years later,</char> Belshazzar <char style="add">became the</char> king <char style="add">of Babylon. One day </char> he invited 1,000 of his officers to a big feast, and he drank <char style="add">a lot of</char> wine with them. <verse eid="DAN 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 5:2"/>While he was drinking, he commanded that<char style="add">his servants</char> bring to him the gold and silver cups that the previous king, Nebuchadnezzar, had taken from the temple in Jerusalem. <char style="add">He did that</char> because he wanted himself and his officials, his wives, and <char style="add">even</char> his ◄concubines/slave wives► to drink from them, <char style="add">making fun of the god that we Israelis worshiped</char>. <verse eid="DAN 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 5:3"/>So his servants brought in <char style="add">all</char> those gold cups, that had been taken <char style="add">many years previously </char> from the temple of <char style="add">the true </char> God in Jerusalem. Then the king and his officials and his wives and his slave wives drank <char style="add">wine </char> from those cups. <verse eid="DAN 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 5:4"/>They drank to praise/honor their idols that were made of gold, silver, bronze, iron, and <char style="add">even</char> wood and stone.<verse eid="DAN 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 5:5"/>Suddenly they saw a man’s hand writing on the plaster of the wall opposite the lampstand. The king also saw the hand as it was writing. <verse eid="DAN 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 5:6"/>He became very frightened, and his face became pale/white. His knees started shaking, and his legs became very weak, with the result that he could not stand up.<verse eid="DAN 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 5:7"/>
    <char style="add">Then</char> he shouted to summon the men who worked magic, the men who studied the stars, and the fortune-tellers. He said, “I will <char style="add">greatly honor </char> any one of them who can read this writing and tell me what it means. I will give him a purple <char style="add">robe like I wear because I am the king</char>, and I will put a gold chain around his neck. He will become a very important official in my kingdom; there will be only two others who will be more important than he will be.”<verse eid="DAN 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 5:8"/>But when all those wise men came in, none of them could read the writing, or tell him what it meant. <verse eid="DAN 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 5:9"/>So King Belshazzar became more afraid. His face became <char style="add">even</char> paler/whiter. And <char style="add">all</char> his officials <char style="add">who were there at the feast</char> did not know what to do.<verse eid="DAN 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 5:10"/>But when the mother of the king (OR, of the previous king) heard the king and his officials talking <char style="add">loudly about what had happened</char>, she entered the room where they were having the feast. She said <char style="add">to Belshazzar</char>, “◄Your majesty/O King►, I hope you will live for a long time! But do not be pale and afraid about this. <verse eid="DAN 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 5:11"/>There is a man in your kingdom who has the spirit of the holy gods in him. When Nebuchadnezzar was ruling, they discovered that this man understood many things and was wise, just like the gods. The man who was king previously, Nebuchadnezzar, appointed him to be in charge of all the men <char style="add">in Babylon</char> who worked magic, the men who worked sorcery, the men who studied the stars, and the fortune-tellers. <verse eid="DAN 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 5:12"/>That man’s name is Daniel; the king gave him a <char style="add">new</char> name, Belteshazzar. He is very intelligent and is able to know and understand many things. He is <char style="add">even</char> able to tell the meaning of dreams, and explain riddles, and explain things that are very difficult to understand. Summon him, and he will tell you what <char style="add">this writing</char> means.”<verse eid="DAN 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Daniel interpreted the writing</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 5:13"/>So they <char style="add">went and</char> brought me in. The king asked me, “You <char style="add">must</char> be Daniel [RHQ]! <char style="add">They told me that you are</char> one of those who was brought <char style="add">here</char> from Judah by the previous king. <verse eid="DAN 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 5:14"/>I have <char style="add">also</char> heard that the spirit of the gods is in you, and that you are very wise and understand many things. <verse eid="DAN 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 5:15"/>My wise men and men who work magic have tried to read the writing on this wall and tell me what it means, but they are not able to do it. <verse eid="DAN 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 5:16"/><char style="add">Someone</char> told me that you can tell what dreams mean and explain things that are very difficult to understand. If you can read these words and tell me what they mean, <char style="add">I </char>will give you a purple robe <char style="add">like I wear because I am the king</char>, and I will put a gold chain around your neck. You will become a very important official in my kingdom; there will be only two others who will be more important than you will be.”<verse eid="DAN 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 5:17"/>I replied, “<char style="add">I do not want</char> your gifts; keep them, or give them to someone else. But I will read for you the writing <char style="add">on the wall</char>, and I will tell you what it means.<verse eid="DAN 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 5:18"/>◄Your Majesty/O king►, the Supreme God caused the man who was king before you, Nebuchadnezzar, to become a great ruler, who was greatly praised and honored. <verse eid="DAN 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 5:19"/>Because God caused him to become <char style="add">very</char> great, people of many [HYP] people-groups and nations and who spoke many different languages were very much afraid of him. He <char style="add">commanded his soldiers to</char> kill those whom he wanted to be killed, and he ◄spared/allowed to live► those whom he wanted to spare. He honored those whom he wanted to honor, and he caused to be disgraced those whom he wanted to be disgraced. <verse eid="DAN 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 5:20"/>But when he became very proud and stubborn [IDM], he was removed from being king [MTY]. People did not consider him to be glorious/great any more. <verse eid="DAN 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 5:21"/><char style="add">His officials </char> sent him away in order that he would not be near <char style="add">other</char> people. <char style="add">God</char> caused him to have a mind like animals have. He lived among the wild donkeys. He ate grass like cows do, and dew from the sky caused his body to be damp/wet <char style="add">each morning</char>. <char style="add">He was like that</char> until he learned that the Supreme God is <char style="add">really the one who</char> rules the kingdoms of this world, and that he appoints whomever he chooses to rule those kingdoms.<verse eid="DAN 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 5:22"/>Now, Belshazzar, you have become the king. You <char style="add">also</char> knew all those things, but you have not made yourself humble. <verse eid="DAN 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 5:23"/>You have considered yourself to be greater than <char style="add">God</char>, the Lord of heaven. <char style="add">So you have commanded your servants to</char> bring to you these sacred cups, <char style="add">which were dedicated to the Supreme God, and which were taken</char> from his temple <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>. You and your officials and your wives and your ◄concubines/slave wives► have been drinking wine from these cups, while you have been praising <char style="add">your own</char> gods—gods which are made of gold and silver and bronze and iron and wood and stone. <char style="add">Those are gods</char> that cannot see, that cannot hear, and that do not know anything! You have not honored the God who gives you breath and who controls everything that happens to you. <verse eid="DAN 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 5:24"/>So God sent that hand to write a message <char style="add">for you</char>.<verse eid="DAN 5:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 5:25"/>This is the message that it wrote: ‘<char style="sc">Mene, mene, tekel, parsin.</char>’<verse eid="DAN 5:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 5:26"/>This is what those words mean:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="DAN 5:26">
    <char style="sc">Mene</char> <char style="add">means</char> ‘numbered/counted’. <char style="add">That means that</char> God has been counting the days that you will rule, and he has <char style="add">now</char> decided that you will not rule any more.<verse eid="DAN 5:26"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 5:27"/>
    <char style="sc">Tekel</char> <char style="add">means ‘weighed’. It is as though God</char> has weighed you on a scale, and you do not weigh what you should, <char style="add">which means that you have not been doing what you should; you are not fit to be a king</char> [MET].<verse eid="DAN 5:27"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DAN 5:28"/>
    <char style="sc">Parsin</char> <char style="add">means ‘divided’. That means that God</char> has divided your kingdom. Some of it will be ruled by people from Media and some will be ruled by people from Persia.”<verse eid="DAN 5:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DAN 5:29"/>Then Belshazzar <char style="add">did what he had promised</char>. He put on me a purple robe <char style="add">like the one he himself wore. He</char> put a gold chain around my neck. And he proclaimed that there would be only two others who would be more important than me in his kingdom.<verse eid="DAN 5:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DAN 5:30"/>But that same night <char style="add">soldiers from Media entered the city and</char> killed Belshazzar, the King of Babylonia. <verse eid="DAN 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DAN 5:31"/>Darius, the King of Media, became the King <char style="add">of Babylonia</char> when he was 62 years old.<verse eid="DAN 5:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="DAN 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Daniel was thrown into the lions’ den</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 6:1"/>King Darius decided to divide his kingdom into 120 provinces. He appointed a governor to rule each province. <verse eid="DAN 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 6:2"/>He also appointed me and two other men to be administrators, to supervise the governors and to be sure that they did the king’s work <char style="add">properly</char>, in order that the king would not have to worry about anything. <verse eid="DAN 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 6:3"/>I soon showed that I was ◄more capable/able to do the work better► than all the other administrators and the governors. Because of that, the king planned to appoint me to be in charge of the entire empire. <verse eid="DAN 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 6:4"/>Then, the <char style="add">other</char> administrators and the governors <char style="add">became jealous. So they began to</char> try to find something that they could criticize about the way I was working for the king. But I always did my work faithfully and honestly, and was never lazy. So they could not find anything to criticize. <verse eid="DAN 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 6:5"/>They concluded, “The only way we can find something for which we can criticize Daniel will be something concerning the laws that his god <char style="add">his given him</char>.”<verse eid="DAN 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 6:6"/>So the administrators and governors went as one group to the king and said, “◄Your Majesty/O king►, we wish that you will live a long time! <verse eid="DAN 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 6:7"/><char style="add">We</char> administrators and governors and district governors and advisors and other officials have all agreed that you should make a law that everyone must obey. We want you to command that for the next thirty days people may pray only to you. If anyone prays to anyone else, either to a human or to a god, he must be thrown into <char style="add">a pit of </char> lions. <verse eid="DAN 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 6:8"/>And because laws made by <char style="add">our governments of</char> Media and Persia cannot be changed, <char style="add">we want</char> you, <char style="add">the head of our government</char>, to sign it.” <verse eid="DAN 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 6:9"/>So King Darius <char style="add">wrote</char> the law and signed it.<verse eid="DAN 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 6:10"/>But when I found out that <char style="add">the king</char> had <char style="add">written and</char> signed that law, I went home. I knelt down in my upstairs room and prayed. I looked toward Jerusalem, and the windows were open <char style="add">with the result that everyone could see me while I was praying</char>. I prayed three times each day, just as I always did, thanking God. <verse eid="DAN 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 6:11"/>The officials went together <char style="add">to my house</char> and they saw me praying and requesting God to help me. <verse eid="DAN 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 6:12"/>So they returned to the king and said to him, “<char style="add">Do you remember</char> that you wrote a law stating that for the next thirty days people may pray only to you, and if anyone prays to anyone else, either to a human or to a god, he will be thrown into <char style="add">a pit of</char> lions?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DAN 6:12">The king replied, “<char style="add">Yes, that is the law that I wrote</char>. It is a law of <char style="add">our governments of</char> Media and Persia, which cannot be canceled.”<verse eid="DAN 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 6:13"/>Then they said to the king, “Well, that <char style="add">man</char> Daniel, one of the men who were brought from Judah, is not paying any attention to you or the law that you <char style="add">signed</char>. He prays <char style="add">to his god</char> three times each day!” <verse eid="DAN 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 6:14"/>When the king heard that, he was very distressed. He tried to find a way to save me. All the rest of that day he tried to think of a way to rescue me.<verse eid="DAN 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 6:15"/>
    <char style="add">In the evening, many of</char> [HYP] the officials went together to the king and said, “◄Your Majesty/O king►, you know that <char style="add">our governments of</char> Media and Persia have declared that no law that the king signs can be canceled/changed. <char style="add">So Daniel must be thrown to the lions!</char>”<verse eid="DAN 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 6:16"/>So the king gave the order, and his servants brought me and threw me into a pit where the lions <char style="add">were</char>. <char style="add">Before they threw me in</char>, the king said to me, “I hope/wish that your God, whom you worship regularly, will rescue you!”<verse eid="DAN 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 6:17"/>They rolled a huge stone across the entrance to the pit. Then the king <char style="add">fastened a string across the entrance and put wax at each end, and stamped the wax with</char> the seal from his <char style="add">ring</char> and the seals <char style="add">of the rings</char> of his officials, in order that no one could <char style="add">secretly</char> rescue me. <verse eid="DAN 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 6:18"/>Then the king returned to his palace. That night he refused to eat any food. He would not allow anyone to entertain him <char style="add">because he did not want to be happy, with the result that he would forget about me. And that night </char> he was unable to sleep <char style="add">because he was worried about me</char>.<verse eid="DAN 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 6:19"/>At dawn the next morning, the king got up and went quickly to the pit where the lions were. <verse eid="DAN 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 6:20"/>When he came near it, he was very worried. He called out, “Daniel, you who serve the all-powerful God! Was your God, whom you worship regularly, able to save you from the lions?”<verse eid="DAN 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 6:21"/>I answered, “◄Your Majesty/O king►, I hope that you will live a long time! <verse eid="DAN 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 6:22"/><char style="add">Yes</char>, my God sent his angel to shut the lions’ mouths, in order that they would not harm me! <char style="add">He did that</char> because <char style="add">he knows that</char> I have done nothing that he thinks is wrong. And, ◄Your Majesty/O king►, I never did anything wrong to you!”<verse eid="DAN 6:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 6:23"/>The king was extremely happy, and he commanded <char style="add">his servants</char> to lift me out of the pit. <char style="add">When they did that, they</char> saw that the lions had not wounded me at all. <char style="add">God had protected me</char> because I trusted in him.<verse eid="DAN 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 6:24"/>Then the king commanded that the men who had accused me should be seized and be thrown, along with their wives and children, into the pit where the lions were. <char style="add">When they were thrown into the pit</char>, the lions leaped on them and crushed their bones before they fell onto the bottom of the pit!<verse eid="DAN 6:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 6:25"/>Then King Darius wrote <char style="add">this message and sent it throughout his kingdom</char> to the people of every people-group and nation and from all language groups:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="DAN 6:25"/>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DAN 6:25">“I wish/hope that everything is going very well with you!<verse eid="DAN 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 6:26"/>I command that everyone in my kingdom should fear and revere the God that Daniel <char style="add">worships</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 6:26">He is the all-powerful God,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 6:26">and he will live forever.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 6:26">His kingdom will never be destroyed;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 6:26">he will rule forever.<verse eid="DAN 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 6:27"/>He rescues and saves <char style="add">his people</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 6:27">He performs all kinds of miracles</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 6:27">in heaven and on the earth.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 6:27">He rescued Daniel from the power of the lions!”<verse eid="DAN 6:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DAN 6:28"/>So I was successful <char style="add">all</char> during the time that Darius ruled and during the time that Cyrus, <char style="add">the King</char> of Persia, ruled.<verse eid="DAN 6:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="DAN 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Daniel dreamed about four beasts</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 7:1"/>
    <char style="add">Previously,</char> during the first year that Belshazzar was the king of Babylonia, I had a dream and a vision one night as I lay on my bed. <char style="add">The next morning</char> I wrote down what I had dreamed. This is what I wrote:<verse eid="DAN 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 7:2"/>I, Daniel, had a vision last night. In the vision I saw that strong winds were blowing from all four directions, stirring up <char style="add">the water in</char> the ocean. <verse eid="DAN 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 7:3"/>Then <char style="add">I saw</char> four beasts coming out of the ocean. All four of them were different.<verse eid="DAN 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 7:4"/>The first one resembled a lion, but it had wings like an eagle has. But as I watched, something tore off its wings {its wings were pulled off}. The beast was left there, standing on its two hind/rear legs, like a human being stands. And it was given a mind like humans have.<verse eid="DAN 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 7:5"/>The second beast resembled a bear. It was crouching, and it held between its teeth three ribs <char style="add">from another animal that it had killed and eaten</char>. Someone said to it {It was told}, “Stand up and eat as much meat <char style="add">as you want</char>!”<verse eid="DAN 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 7:6"/>Then I saw in front of me the third of those beasts. It resembled a leopard, but it had four wings protruding from its back. The wings were like a bird’s wings. It had four heads. It was given the power/authority to rule <char style="add">people</char>.<verse eid="DAN 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 7:7"/>In the vision I saw a fourth beast. It was stronger than the other beasts, and it was more terrifying. It crushed other creatures with its huge iron teeth and ate their flesh. The parts of animals that it did not grind with its teeth, it trampled <char style="add">on the ground</char>. It was different from the other three beasts: It had ten horns <char style="add">on its head</char>.<verse eid="DAN 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 7:8"/>While I was looking at those horns, I saw a little horn appear <char style="add">on the head of that beast</char>. It tore out three of the other horns. This little horn had eyes like humans have, and it had a mouth <char style="add">with which it spoke</char> very boastfully.<verse eid="DAN 7:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 7:9"/>
    <char style="add">Then</char> while I watched,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 7:9">thrones were put in the places <char style="add">where they belonged</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 7:9">and <char style="add">God</char>, the one who had been living forever, sat on one of the thrones.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 7:9">His clothes were as white as snow,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 7:9">and his hair was as white as pure/clean wool.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 7:9">His throne had wheels that were blazing with fire,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 7:9">and his throne was <char style="add">also</char> blazing.<verse eid="DAN 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 7:10"/>A fire was rushing out of in front of him like a stream.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 7:10">Many thousands <char style="add">of people</char> (OR, <char style="add">angels</char>) <char style="add">were there</char> serving him,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 7:10">and millions <char style="add">of other people</char> (OR, <char style="add">angels</char>) were standing in front of him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DAN 7:10">They started ◄the court session/judging people►,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DAN 7:10">and they opened the books <char style="add">in which they had written the record of all the good and bad things that people had done</char>.<verse eid="DAN 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 7:11"/>While I was watching, I could hear the little horn speaking very boastfully. As I <char style="add">continued to</char> watch, the <char style="add">fourth</char> beast was killed. Its corpse was thrown into a fire and completely burned. <verse eid="DAN 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 7:12"/>The power/authority of the other <char style="add">three</char> beasts was taken away from them, but they were allowed to continue to live for a while.<verse eid="DAN 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 7:13"/>While I <char style="add">continued to</char> see the vision that night, I saw someone who resembled a human being. He was coming <char style="add">closer to me</char>, surrounded by clouds. Then he was taken to <char style="add">God</char>, the one who had been living forever. <verse eid="DAN 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 7:14"/>He was honored and given great authority to rule over all the nations in the world, in order that people from every people-group and every nation, people from all language groups, would worship/serve him. He will rule forever; he will never stop ruling. The kingdom that he rules will never be destroyed.<verse eid="DAN 7:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The explanation of the vision</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 7:15"/>As for me, Daniel, I was very terrified by what I had seen in that vision, and I did not know what to think about it. <verse eid="DAN 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 7:16"/>I went to one of those who were standing in front of the throne of God, and I asked him to tell me what it meant. So he told me the meaning of it.<verse eid="DAN 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 7:17"/>
    <char style="add">He said</char>, “The four huge beasts represent four kingdoms/empires that will exist on the earth. <verse eid="DAN 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 7:18"/>But the Supreme God will give power/authority to his people <char style="add">to rule</char>, and they shall rule forever.”<verse eid="DAN 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 7:19"/>Then I wanted to know what the fourth beast signified—<char style="add">the beast</char> that was different from the other three, the beast that crushed <char style="add">those that it attacked</char> with its bronze claws, and <char style="add">then</char> ate <char style="add">their flesh</char> with its iron teeth, and trampled on the parts of their bodies <char style="add">that it did not eat</char>. <verse eid="DAN 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 7:20"/><char style="add">I also wanted to know about</char> the ten horns on its head, and about the horn that appeared later, which got rid of three of the other horns. <char style="add">I wanted to know what it meant that</char> it had eyes and a mouth with which it spoke very boastfully. <char style="add">The beast that was represented by</char> that horn was more terrifying than the other beasts. <verse eid="DAN 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 7:21"/>While I was having the vision, I saw that this horn attacked God’s people and was defeating them. <verse eid="DAN 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 7:22"/>But then the Supreme God, the one who had been living forever, came and judged in favor of the people who belonged to him. And <char style="add">I knew that</char> it was time for God’s people to receive authority <char style="add">to rule</char>.<verse eid="DAN 7:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 7:23"/>
    <char style="add">Then</char> the man who was standing there said <char style="add">to me</char>, “The fourth beast represents an empire that will exist on the earth; that <char style="add">empire</char> will be different from all <char style="add">other</char> empires. <char style="add">The army of</char> that empire will crush/kill <char style="add">people all over</char> the world and trample <char style="add">on their bodies</char>. <verse eid="DAN 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 7:24"/>As for its ten horns, they represent ten kings who will rule that empire, <char style="add">one after the other</char>. Then another <char style="add">king</char> will appear. He will be different from the previous kings. He will defeat the three kings <char style="add">that were represented by the three horns that were pulled out</char>. <verse eid="DAN 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 7:25"/>He will revile the Supreme God, and he will oppress God’s people. He will try to change the <char style="add">sacred</char> festivals and their <char style="add">religious</char> laws/regulations. He will control them for three and a half years.<verse eid="DAN 7:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 7:26"/>But there will be a session/meeting of the court/judges in heaven, and that king’s authority/power will be taken away, and he will be completely destroyed. <verse eid="DAN 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 7:27"/>Then all the power and the greatness of all the kingdoms on the earth will be given to the people who belong to the Supreme God. The kingdom that he rules (OR, they rule) will endure forever. And the rulers of all the nations on the earth will serve and obey him (OR, them).”<verse eid="DAN 7:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DAN 7:28"/>That is <char style="add">what I saw in</char> my vision/dream. I, Daniel, was terrified, with the result that my face became pale. But I did not tell anyone about the vision <char style="add">that I had seen</char>.<verse eid="DAN 7:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="DAN 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Daniel’s vision of a ram and a goat</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 8:1"/>During the third year that Belshazzar was the King <char style="add">of Babylonia</char>, I had another vision. <verse eid="DAN 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 8:2"/>In that vision I was in Susa, the capital city of Elam Province. I was <char style="add">standing</char> alongside the Ulai Canal. <verse eid="DAN 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 8:3"/>I looked up and saw a ram that was standing alongside the canal. It had two <char style="add">long</char> horns, but the newest one was longer than the other one. <verse eid="DAN 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 8:4"/>The ram butted/knocked away <char style="add">with its horns</char> everything that was west and everything that was north and everything that was south of it. There were no <char style="add">other</char> animals that were able to oppose it, and none that could rescue/save <char style="add">other animals</char> from its power. The ram did whatever it wanted to do and became very powerful.<verse eid="DAN 8:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 8:5"/>While I was thinking <char style="add">about what I had seen, in the vision</char> I saw a goat come from the west. It ran across the land so quickly, that <char style="add">it seemed like</char> its feet did not touch the ground. This goat had one very large horn between its eyes. <verse eid="DAN 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 8:6"/>It was very angry, and it ran <char style="add">straight</char> toward the ram that I had seen <char style="add">previously, the ram</char> that was standing alongside the canal. <verse eid="DAN 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 8:7"/>The goat struck the ram furiously and broke off its two horns, with the result that the ram was unable <char style="add">to defend itself</char>. <char style="add">So</char> the goat knocked the ram down and trampled on it. No one could rescue the ram from the goat’s power. <verse eid="DAN 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 8:8"/>The goat became very powerful. But when its power was very great, its horn was broken off. But four <char style="add">other</char> large horns took its place. They each pointed in a different direction.<verse eid="DAN 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 8:9"/>
    <char style="add">Then</char> from one of those <char style="add">large horns</char> appeared a little horn, which became very big, <char style="add">and pointed</char> toward the south and <char style="add">then</char> toward the east and <char style="add">then</char> toward the beautiful land <char style="add">of Israel</char>. <verse eid="DAN 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 8:10"/><char style="add">The man who was represented by</char> that horn became very strong, with the result that he attacked some of the <char style="add">soldiers of the</char> army of heaven, and (OR, meaning) the stars in the sky <char style="add">which represented God’s people</char>. He threw some of them to the ground and trampled on them. <verse eid="DAN 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 8:11"/>He ◄defied/considered himself to be greater than► the leader of the army <char style="add">of heaven</char>, and prevented <char style="add">priests from</char> offering sacrifices to him. He also ◄defiled the temple/caused the temple to become unholy►. <verse eid="DAN 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 8:12"/>Then God’s people allowed the <char style="add">man who was represented by</char> that horn to control/rule them, with the result that they sinned by offering sacrifices to him. And he threw to the ground the <char style="add">laws that contained the</char> true religion. Everything that he did was successful.<verse eid="DAN 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 8:13"/>Then I heard two angels who were talking to each other. One of them asked, “How long will the things/events that were in this vision continue? How long will the man who rebels against God and causes <char style="add">the temple</char> to be defiled be able to prevent <char style="add">priests from</char> offering sacrifices? How long will he trample on the temple and on the armies of heaven?”<verse eid="DAN 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 8:14"/>The other angel replied, “<char style="add">It will continue</char> for 1,150 days. During all of that time, <char style="add">people will not be permitted to offer sacrifices</char> in the morning or in the evening. After that, the temple will be purified.”<verse eid="DAN 8:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Gabriel explained the vision</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 8:15"/>While I, Daniel, was trying to understand what the vision meant, suddenly <char style="add">an angel</char> who resembled a man stood/appeared in front of me. <verse eid="DAN 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 8:16"/>And I heard a man call out from <char style="add">the other side of</char> the Ulai Canal, saying, “Gabriel, explain to him the meaning of the vision <char style="add">that he saw</char>!”<verse eid="DAN 8:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 8:17"/>So Gabriel came and stood beside me. I was very terrified, with the result that I fell onto the ground. But he said to me, “You human, it is necessary for you to understand that <char style="add">the events that you saw in</char> the vision will occur <char style="add">near</char> the time that <char style="add">the world</char> will end.”<verse eid="DAN 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 8:18"/>While he was speaking, I fainted. I lay there, unconscious, with my face still on the ground. But Gabriel put his hand on me and lifted me up in order that I could stand again.<verse eid="DAN 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 8:19"/>Then he said, “I <char style="add">have come here to</char> tell you what will happen because of <char style="add">God</char> being angry. These things will happen near the time when <char style="add">the world</char> will end. <verse eid="DAN 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 8:20"/>As for the ram with two horns that you saw, those horns <char style="add">represent</char> the kingdoms of Media and Persia. <verse eid="DAN 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 8:21"/>The goat <char style="add">that you saw represents</char> the kingdom of Greece, and the horn that appeared between its eyes <char style="add">represents</char> its first king. <verse eid="DAN 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 8:22"/>As for the four horns that grew after the first horn was broken off, they <char style="add">represent</char> four kingdoms into which that first kingdom will be divided <char style="add">after the first king dies</char>. Those four kingdoms will not be as strong/powerful as the first kingdom was.<verse eid="DAN 8:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 8:23"/>The people <char style="add">in those kingdoms</char> will become very wicked, with the result that it will be necessary for them to be punished. But near the time when those kingdoms will end, one of those kingdoms will have a king who will be very proud/defiant [IDM]. He will <char style="add">also</char> be very fierce and very deceitful. <verse eid="DAN 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 8:24"/>He will become very powerful, but it will not be because of what he himself does. He will terribly destroy things in many places, and he will succeed in doing everything that he wants to. He will get rid of <char style="add">many</char> powerful men, and <char style="add">also</char> some of God’s people. <verse eid="DAN 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 8:25"/>Because he is very cunning/clever, he will succeed by doing things that deceive many people. He will be proud of himself. He will destroy many people when they think that they are safe. He will also rebel against <char style="add">God</char> [EUP], who is the greatest king. But <char style="add">God</char> will destroy him, without the help [MTY] of any human being.<verse eid="DAN 8:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 8:26"/>What you saw in the vision about <char style="add">priests being prevented from making</char> sacrifices in the morning and in the evening, which <char style="add">I</char> explained <char style="add">to you</char>, will surely happen. But <char style="add">for the present time</char>, do not reveal the vision <char style="add">to others</char>, because it will be many years before those things happen.”<verse eid="DAN 8:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 8:27"/>Then I, Daniel, became weak, and I was sick for several days. Then I arose and <char style="add">returned to</char> doing the work that the king <char style="add">had given to me</char>, but I was perplexed/confused about the vision, and I could not understand it.<verse eid="DAN 8:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="DAN 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Daniel’s prayer</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 9:1"/>
    <char style="add">Now I am going to tell you about what happened</char> when Darius, who was from the Mede people-group and who was the son of Xerxes, ruled as the King of Babylonia. <verse eid="DAN 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 9:2"/>During the first year that he was the king, I, Daniel, was studying/reading the <char style="add">holy</char> books/Scriptures the message that Yahweh had given to the prophet Jeremiah. In that message Jeremiah had written that Jerusalem would <char style="add">be destroyed and </char> remain ruined for seventy years. <verse eid="DAN 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 9:3"/><char style="add">After I read that</char>, I pleaded to Yahweh my God <char style="add">to help us</char>, praying and ◄fasting/abstaining from eating food►. <char style="add">While doing that, I was wearing</char> rough cloth and <char style="add">sitting in</char> ashes <char style="add">to show that I was very sad about what was going to happen to us</char>.<verse eid="DAN 9:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 9:4"/>I confessed <char style="add">the sins that we had committed</char>, and <char style="add">this is what I</char> prayed:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DAN 9:4">Lord, you are great and awesome! You have faithfully done what you said that you would do for us. You faithfully love those who love you and who do what you have commanded <char style="add">that they should do</char>. <verse eid="DAN 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 9:5"/>But we <char style="add">Israelis</char> have sinned. We have done things that are wrong. We have done wicked things, and we have rebelled <char style="add">against you</char>. We have turned away from <char style="add">obeying</char> your commands [DOU]. <verse eid="DAN 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 9:6"/>Your prophets spoke for you [MTY], <char style="add">giving your messages to </char>our kings, to our other rulers, to our <char style="add">other</char> ancestors, and to all the Israeli people, but we have refused to ◄pay attention to/heed► those prophets.<verse eid="DAN 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 9:7"/>Lord, you always do what is righteous/just/fair, but we have caused ourselves to be ashamed [IDM]. This is <char style="add">still</char> true about all of the Israelis who live in Jerusalem and who live in other places in Judea. It is <char style="add">also</char> true about all us Israelis whom you scattered, who <char style="add">were taken to</char> other countries, some near <char style="add">Israel</char> and some far away, because we were very unfaithful/disloyal to you. <verse eid="DAN 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 9:8"/>Lord, we and our kings and our other rulers and our <char style="add">other</char> ancestors have done very shameful things and have sinned against you. <verse eid="DAN 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 9:9"/>Although we have rebelled against you, you act mercifully <char style="add">toward us</char> and you <char style="add">are willing/ready</char> to forgive us. <verse eid="DAN 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 9:10"/>Yahweh our God, when you gave your laws to your prophets who served you, and they told us to conduct our lives according to those laws, we did not ◄listen to/heed► you. <verse eid="DAN 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 9:11"/>All <char style="add">of us</char> Israeli people have disobeyed your laws, and we have turned away from <char style="add">obeying</char> what you said. We have sinned against you. As a result, <char style="add">you</char> have caused us to experience the terrible things that your servant Moses said/wrote <char style="add">would happen to us</char> if we sinned against you.<verse eid="DAN 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 9:12"/>You warned us and our rulers that you would punish Jerusalem severely by causing a great disaster there, a disaster that would be worse than any disaster that any other city had ever experienced, and you have done what you said that you would do. <verse eid="DAN 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 9:13"/><char style="add">You</char> punished us just like Moses wrote <char style="add">that you would do</char>. But, Yahweh our God, we still have not tried, by turning away from our sinning and by heeding your truth, to persuade you to act mercifully toward us. <verse eid="DAN 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 9:14"/>So, because we did not obey you, you prepared to punish us, and <char style="add">then</char> you did punish us, because you always do what is righteous/just/fair.<verse eid="DAN 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 9:15"/>O Lord our God, you brought your people out of Egypt by your great power [MTY], and by doing that you have caused people from that time until the present time to know that you are great [IDM] <char style="add">even though</char> we have sinned and done wicked things. <verse eid="DAN 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 9:16"/>Lord, Jerusalem is your city, and <char style="add">your temple was built there</char> on your sacred hill. Now all the people who live in nearby <char style="add">countries/nations</char> despise Jerusalem and <char style="add">us</char> your people because of our sins and because of the evil things that our ancestors did. But <char style="add">now</char>, because you do what is righteous/just, <char style="add">we ask you to</char> not be angry with Jerusalem any longer.<verse eid="DAN 9:16"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 9:17"/>O Lord our God, listen to what I am praying and pleading <char style="add">for you to do</char>. ◄For your own sake/In order that people will know that you are very great►, act kindly [IDM] concerning your temple, which was destroyed <char style="add">by the armies of Babylonia</char>. <verse eid="DAN 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 9:18"/>My God, listen <char style="add">to my prayer</char>. Look <char style="add">at us</char> and see our troubles, and see that this city that belongs to you [MTY] has been ruined/destroyed. We are praying to you because you are merciful, not because we have done what is right/good. <verse eid="DAN 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 9:19"/>Lord, listen <char style="add">to us</char>! Lord, forgive us! Lord, this city and these people belong to you, so <char style="add">we plead with you to</char> heed what we are saying and act <char style="add">to help us</char> right now, ◄for your own sake/in order that people will know that you are very great►!<verse eid="DAN 9:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Gabriel told what would happen in the future</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 9:20"/>I continued praying and confessing the sins that my people and I had committed, and pleading with Yahweh my God that he would restore <char style="add">the temple on</char> the sacred hill <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>. <verse eid="DAN 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 9:21"/>While I was praying, Gabriel, the angel/one whom I had seen in the vision previously, came flying rapidly to me, at the time in the evening when <char style="add">the priests</char> offered sacrifices. <verse eid="DAN 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 9:22"/>He said to me, “Daniel, I have come to you to enable you to understand [DOU] clearly <char style="add">the message that God gave to Jeremiah</char>. <verse eid="DAN 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 9:23"/>When you began to plead <char style="add">with God</char>, he gave me a message <char style="add">to pass on to you</char>. He loves you very much, so <char style="add">he has sent me</char> to tell you what he said to me. So <char style="add">now</char> ◄pay attention/listen carefully► in order that you may understand the meaning of what he revealed <char style="add">to Jeremiah</char>.<verse eid="DAN 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 9:24"/>
    <char style="add">God</char> has determined/declared that there will be 490 years until he frees/saves your people from <char style="add">the guilt of</char> their sins and to atone for the evil things that they have done. Then <char style="add">God</char> will rule everyone justly, and he will do that forever. And <char style="add">what you saw in</char> the vision and what <char style="add">Jeremiah </char> prophesied will ◄come true/be fulfilled►, and the sacred temple will be dedicated <char style="add">to God again</char>.<verse eid="DAN 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 9:25"/>You need to know and understand this: There will be 49 years from the time that <char style="add">the king</char> commands that Jerusalem should be rebuilt until the leader/king that God has chosen will come. Then 434 years later, Jerusalem will be rebuilt, and it will have streets and will have a ◄moat/deep ditch filled with water► around it <char style="add">to protect the city</char>. But that will be a time when <char style="add">God’s people</char> will have <char style="add">a lot of</char> troubles/difficulties/suffering. <verse eid="DAN 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 9:26"/>After those 434 years, the leader/king whom God has appointed will be killed <char style="add">when it seems that</char> he will have accomplished nothing ◄unjustly/without having done anything wrong►. After that, the temple will be destroyed by <char style="add">the army of</char> a powerful ruler. The city and the temple will be destroyed like a flood [MET] <char style="add">destroys everything</char>. That will be the beginning of the war and destruction that <char style="add">God</char> has decreed <char style="add">will happen</char>. <verse eid="DAN 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 9:27"/>That ruler will make a strong agreement with many people. He will promise to do for seven years what he has said in that agreement. But when that time is half finished, he will prevent <char style="add">priests from</char> giving any more offerings and sacrifices <char style="add">to God</char>. A disgusting idol will be put on the highest part of the temple, and it will stay there until <char style="add">God</char> gets rid of the one who put it there, which is what he said that he would do.”<verse eid="DAN 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="DAN 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Daniel’s vision at the Tigris River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 10:1"/>During the third year that Cyrus was the king of Persia, I Daniel, <char style="add">who had been given the</char> name Belteshazzar, received <char style="add">another</char> message <char style="add">from God</char>. The message was true, but it was very difficult for me to understand it. But <char style="add">later</char> I understood the message because of the vision that I had seen.<verse eid="DAN 10:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 10:2"/>At that time I had been sad for three weeks <char style="add">about what had happened to Jerusalem</char>. <verse eid="DAN 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 10:3"/>I did not eat any tasty food or any meat or drink any wine. I did not even put any perfumed oil on my <char style="add">face or hair</char> for those three weeks.<verse eid="DAN 10:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 10:4"/>
    <char style="add">When those three weeks ended,</char> on April 23, <char style="add">my companions and</char> I were standing on the bank of the great Tigris River. <verse eid="DAN 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 10:5"/>I looked up and saw someone there who was wearing fine white/linen clothes and a belt <char style="add">made of</char> pure gold. <verse eid="DAN 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 10:6"/>His body <char style="add">shone</char> like a precious beryl stone. His face was as <char style="add">bright as</char> a flash of lightning. His eyes <char style="add">were/shone</char> like flaming torches. His arms and legs <char style="add">shone</char> like polished bronze. And his voice was <char style="add">very loud</char>, like the roar of a huge crowd.<verse eid="DAN 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 10:7"/>I, Daniel, was the only one who saw this vision. The men who were with me did not see anything, but <char style="add">they sensed that someone was there, and they</char> became terrified. They ran away and hid themselves. <verse eid="DAN 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 10:8"/>So I was left there by myself, looking at this very unusual vision. I had no strength left. My face became very pale, with the result that no one would have recognized me. <verse eid="DAN 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 10:9"/>I saw a man there, and when I heard him speak, I fell to the ground. I ◄fainted/became unconscious►, <char style="add">and I lay there</char> with my face on the ground.<verse eid="DAN 10:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 10:10"/>Suddenly someone’s hand took hold of me and lifted me, with the result that I was on my hands and knees, <char style="add">but I was still</char> trembling. <verse eid="DAN 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 10:11"/>The man said to me, “Daniel, <char style="add">God</char> loves you very much. Stand up and listen to what I am going to say to you, because <char style="add">God</char> sent me to you.” When he said that, I stood up, <char style="add">but I was still</char> trembling.<verse eid="DAN 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 10:12"/>Then he said to me, “Daniel, do not be afraid. God has heard what you have prayed ever since the first day that you determined to humble yourself in order to understand <char style="add">the vision</char>. I have come to you because of what you prayed. <verse eid="DAN 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 10:13"/>The <char style="add">evil spirit who</char> rules the kingdom of Persia resisted/hindered me for 21 days, but Michael, who is one of God’s chief angels, came to help me. I left him there in Persia <char style="add">to resist</char> that evil spirit who rules there. <verse eid="DAN 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 10:14"/>I have come here to enable you to understand what will happen to the Israeli people in the future. <char style="add">Do not forget that</char> the vision <char style="add">that you saw</char> is about <char style="add">things that will happen in</char> the distant future, <char style="add">not about things that will happen very soon</char>.”<verse eid="DAN 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 10:15"/>While he was saying that, I stared at the ground and was unable to say anything <char style="add">because I was very afraid</char>. <verse eid="DAN 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 10:16"/>Suddenly <char style="add">the angel</char>, who resembled a human, touched my lips. Then <char style="add">I was able to speak, and</char> I said to him, “Sir, because <char style="add">I have seen</char> this vision, I have become very weak, with the result that I cannot stop trembling. <verse eid="DAN 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 10:17"/>I am not able [RHQ] to talk to you, my master. I have no strength left, and it is very difficult for me to breathe.”<verse eid="DAN 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 10:18"/>But he took hold of me again, and enabled me to become stronger again. <verse eid="DAN 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 10:19"/>He said to me, “You human, God loves you very much. <char style="add">So</char> do not be afraid. I desire/want things to go well for you and that you will be encouraged.” When he had said that, I felt even stronger, and I said, “Sir, tell me <char style="add">what you want to tell me</char>. You have enabled me to feel stronger.”<verse eid="DAN 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20-21" style="v" sid="DAN 10:20-21"/>Then he said, “◄Do you know why I came to you?/I will tell you why I came to you.► [RHQ] It is to reveal to you what is written in the book which reveals/contains God’s truth. But now I must return to fight against <char style="add">the evil spirit</char> who rules the kingdom of Persia. After I have defeated him, <char style="add">the evil angel</char> who guards Greece will appear <char style="add">and I must defeat him</char>. Michael, who guards you <char style="add">Israeli people</char>, will help me, but there is no one else to help me.”<verse eid="DAN 10:20-21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="DAN 11"/>
  <para style="nb">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 11:1"/>“As for me, during the first year that Darius was king, I helped and encouraged Michael.”<verse eid="DAN 11:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The message about the kings of Egypt and Syria</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 11:2"/>
    <char style="add">The angel also said</char>, “And what I am going to reveal to you now will truly <char style="add">happen</char>. There will be three more kings to rule Persia, <char style="add">one after the other</char>. Then there will be a fourth king, who will be much richer than the others. As a result of <char style="add">his giving</char> a lot of money <char style="add">to people, they will enable him to</char> become very powerful. Then he will incite/persuade many nations [HYP] <char style="add">to fight</char> against the kingdom of Greece.<verse eid="DAN 11:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 11:3"/>Then a very powerful king will appear <char style="add">in Greece</char>. He will rule over a very large empire, and he will do whatever he wants to do. <verse eid="DAN 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 11:4"/>But when he has become very powerful, <char style="add">he will die</char>. Then his kingdom will be divided into four parts. Kings who are not his descendants will rule, but they will not be as powerful as he was. <verse eid="DAN 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 11:5"/>Then the King of Egypt [MTY] will become very powerful. But one of his army generals will become more powerful than he is, and he will rule a bigger area. <verse eid="DAN 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 11:6"/>Several years later, the King of Egypt and the King of Syria will make an ◄alliance/agreement to help each other► [MTY]. The King of Syria will give his daughter to the King of Egypt to become his wife. But she will not be able to influence him [MTY] very long, and that woman, her husband, her child, and her servants will all be killed/assassinated.<verse eid="DAN 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 11:7"/>Soon after that, one of her relatives [MET] will become King <char style="add">of Egypt</char>. His army will attack the army of Syria. They will enter the fortress of the soldiers of Syria and defeat them. <verse eid="DAN 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 11:8"/>They will return to Egypt, taking the statues of the gods <char style="add">of the people of Syria</char> and many items made of silver and gold that had been dedicated to those gods. Then for several years his army will not attack <char style="add">the army of</char> the King of Syria. <verse eid="DAN 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 11:9"/>Then the army of the King of Syria will invade Egypt, but they will soon return to Syria. <verse eid="DAN 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 11:10"/>However, the sons of the King of Syria will prepare to start a war, and they will gather a large army. That army will march <char style="add">south</char> and spread all over <char style="add">Israel</char> like a huge flood. They will attack a strong fortress <char style="add">in the south of Israel</char>.<verse eid="DAN 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 11:11"/>Then the King of Egypt, having become very angry, will march <char style="add">with his army north</char> from Egypt and fight against the army of Syria. The King <char style="add">of Syria</char> will gather together a very large army, but <char style="add">the army of the King of Egypt</char> will defeat them. <verse eid="DAN 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 11:12"/>The King of Egypt will become very proud because of <char style="add">his army</char> having killed a very large number of soldiers <char style="add">from Syria</char>, but his army will not continue to win battles. <verse eid="DAN 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 11:13"/>The King of Syria will again gather together an army that will be bigger than the one that he had before. After a few years, he will again march <char style="add">south on their way to Egypt</char> with a large army and a lot of equipment <char style="add">for fighting battles</char>.<verse eid="DAN 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DAN 11:14"/>At that time, many people in Egypt will rebel against their king. In order to fulfill a vision that <char style="add">one of their leaders had seen</char>, some violent/lawless people from your country <char style="add">of Israel</char> will also rebel <char style="add">in order to not be controlled by Egypt any more</char>, but they will be defeated. <verse eid="DAN 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DAN 11:15"/>Then the King of Syria will come <char style="add">south with his army</char> and pile up dirt against the walls of a city that is well protected, and they will <char style="add">break through those walls and</char> they will capture the city. The soldiers from Egypt <char style="add">who have come to defend that city</char>, even the best troops, will not be strong enough to continue to fight. <verse eid="DAN 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DAN 11:16"/>So the King of Syria will do whatever he wants to, and no one will be able to oppose him. <char style="add">His army</char> will occupy the glorious land <char style="add">of Israel</char> and completely control/subdue it. <verse eid="DAN 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DAN 11:17"/>Then he will decide to march <char style="add">south</char> with all the soldiers from his kingdom. He will make an alliance with the King <char style="add">of Egypt</char> and in order that his own daughter will <char style="add">help him to</char> destroy the kingdom of Egypt, he will give her to the King of Egypt to become his wife. But that plan will fail. <verse eid="DAN 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DAN 11:18"/>After that, the <char style="add">army of</char> the King of Syria will attack the regions that are close to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea, and his <char style="add">army</char> will conquer many of them. But <char style="add">the army of</char> a leader from another country will defeat the army of Syria and will stop their king from continuing to be proud. He will do to the King of Syria what he deserved for being very insolent. <verse eid="DAN 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DAN 11:19"/>Then the King of Syria will return to the fortresses in his own land. But he will be defeated, and he will ◄die/be assassinated► [EUP] there.<verse eid="DAN 11:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DAN 11:20"/>Then another man will ◄succeed him/become king►. That king will send one of his officers to oppress the people <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char> by forcing them to pay big taxes, in order to get more money for his kingdom. But after a few years [HYP] that king will die, but he will not die as a result of people being angry with him or in a battle.<verse eid="DAN 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DAN 11:21"/>The next King of Syria will be an evil man who, <char style="add">because he will not be the son of the previous king,</char> will not have the right to become king. But he will come when people do not expect it, and he will become king by tricking the people. <verse eid="DAN 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DAN 11:22"/>When his army advances, they will attack any armies that oppose him and destroy those armies. They will also kill God’s Supreme Priest. <verse eid="DAN 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DAN 11:23"/>By making treaties/alliances with <char style="add">the rulers of</char> other nations, he will deceive them, and he will become very powerful, even though he rules a nation that does not have a lot of people. <verse eid="DAN 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DAN 11:24"/>Suddenly his <char style="add">army</char> will invade a province that is very wealthy, and they will do things that none of his ancestors did: they will capture in battles all kinds of possessions from the people whom they defeat. Then the king will divide those possessions among his friends. He will also plan <char style="add">for his army</char> to attack fortresses <char style="add">in Egypt</char>, but only for a short time.<verse eid="DAN 11:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DAN 11:25"/>He will courageously/boldly conscript/gather a large and powerful army to attack <char style="add">the army of</char> the king of Egypt. But the King of Egypt will prepare to fight against them with a huge and powerful army. However, someone will deceive him, with the result that his plan will not be successful. <verse eid="DAN 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DAN 11:26"/>Even his most trusted advisors will plan to get rid of him. His army will be defeated and many of his soldiers will be killed. <verse eid="DAN 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DAN 11:27"/>Then the two <char style="add">kings who both want to rule that area</char> will sit down at the same table and eat together, but they will both lie to each other. Neither of them will get what he wants, because it will not be the time <char style="add">that God</char> has determined/set <char style="add">for them to rule Egypt</char>. <verse eid="DAN 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DAN 11:28"/><char style="add">The army of</char> the King <char style="add">of Syria</char> will return to Syria, taking with them all the valuable things <char style="add">that they had captured</char>. The king will be determined to get rid of the Supreme Priest of the Jewish people. He will do what he wants to <char style="add">in Israel</char>, and then return to his own country.<verse eid="DAN 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DAN 11:29"/>When it is the time that God has decided, the King of Syria <char style="add">and his army</char> will invade Egypt again. But this time he will not be successful like he was before. <verse eid="DAN 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DAN 11:30"/>The army of Rome will come in ships and oppose his army and cause him to be afraid. So he will be very angry, and <char style="add">with his army</char> he will return <char style="add">to Israel</char> and try to get rid of the Supreme Priest. The King of Syria will do what those who have abandoned the Jewish religion advise/want him to do for them. <verse eid="DAN 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DAN 11:31"/>Some of his soldiers will do things to ◄defile the temple/cause the temple to become unholy for them►. They will prevent the priests from offering sacrifices each day, and they will put <char style="add">in the temple</char> something that is disgusting/abominable.<verse eid="DAN 11:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DAN 11:32"/>By deceiving those who have abandoned the Jewish religion, he will persuade them to ◄become his supporters/help him to do what he wants to do►. But those who are devoted to their God will firmly oppose them. <verse eid="DAN 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DAN 11:33"/>And wise <char style="add">Israeli</char> leaders will teach others also. But for a while, some of those wise leaders will be killed in battles, and some will be burned to death, and some will be robbed, and some will be put in prison.<verse eid="DAN 11:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="DAN 11:34"/>While God’s people are being persecuted, some people will help them a little bit, although some of those who help them will not do it sincerely. <verse eid="DAN 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DAN 11:35"/>Some of those wise leaders will be killed [EUP], but as a result the others will be purified [DOU]. This suffering will continue until it is the time <char style="add">that God</char> has appointed <char style="add">for it to</char> end.<verse eid="DAN 11:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The King of Syria who praises himself</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="DAN 11:36"/>The King <char style="add">of Syria</char> will do what he wants to. He will boast and say that he is greater than any god. He will even revile the Supreme God. He will be able to do what he wants until the time that <char style="add">God</char> punishes [MTY] him. <char style="add">God</char> will accomplish what he has planned. <verse eid="DAN 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DAN 11:37"/>The <char style="add">King of Syria</char> will ignore the god that his ancestors worshiped and the god that many women love. He will ignore every god, because he will think that he is greater than all of them. <verse eid="DAN 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DAN 11:38"/>But he will honor the god who <char style="add">people think</char> protects fortresses. That is a god whom his ancestors did not honor. And he will give gold, silver, ◄jewels/very valuable stones► and other expensive gifts to that god. <verse eid="DAN 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="DAN 11:39"/>He will ask that god (OR, people who worship a god) from another country to help him to defend his fortresses. He will greatly honor those who allow him <char style="add">to be their ruler</char>. He will appoint <char style="add">some of</char> them to important positions in the government; and to reward them, he will give them some land.<verse eid="DAN 11:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="DAN 11:40"/>But when his time <char style="add">to rule</char> is almost ended, <char style="add">the army of</char> the King of Egypt will attack his <char style="add">army</char>. The <char style="add">army of the</char> King of Syria will fight against them furiously [SIM]. <char style="add">His soldiers will be driving</char> chariots and <char style="add">riding on</char> horses and <char style="add">traveling in</char> many ships. His army will invade many countries and <char style="add">spread all over those countries</char> like a flood [MET]. <verse eid="DAN 11:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="DAN 11:41"/>They will invade the glorious land <char style="add">of Israel</char> and kill [EUP] tens of thousands of people. But the people of the Edom people-group and the people of the Moab people-group and the people of the Ammon people-group who are still alive will escape. <verse eid="DAN 11:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DAN 11:42"/>When the army of Syria invades other countries, even the people of Egypt will be defeated. <verse eid="DAN 11:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DAN 11:43"/>The army of Syria will take away from Egypt gold, silver, and other valuable items. The people of Libya and Ethiopia will allow <char style="add">the King of Syria</char> to rule over them. <verse eid="DAN 11:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DAN 11:44"/>But he will become very frightened/alarmed when he hears reports about what is happening in the east and in the north. So he will become very angry, and send his army to fight furiously and kill many <char style="add">of their enemies</char>. <verse eid="DAN 11:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DAN 11:45"/>The <char style="add">King of Syria</char> will set up his royal tents in the area between the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea and the hill <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char> on which the temple ◄exists/was built►. But he will be killed there, because there will be no one to help him.”<verse eid="DAN 11:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="DAN 12"/>
  <para style="s1">When this world will end</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DAN 12:1"/>
    <char style="add">The angel also said to me,</char> “After those things happen, the great angel Michael, who protects the <char style="add">Israeli</char> people, will appear. Then there will be a time when there will be great troubles/suffering. The troubles will be greater than any troubles/suffering since the nations began. At that time, all of your people whose names have been written in the book <char style="add">containing the names of those who have eternal life</char> will be saved. <verse eid="DAN 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DAN 12:2"/>Many of those who have died [EUP] will become alive again. Some of them will live eternally <char style="add">with God</char>, and some will be eternally shamed/disgraced <char style="add">in hell</char>. <verse eid="DAN 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DAN 12:3"/>Those who were wise will shine as brightly as the sky <char style="add">is bright when the sun is shining</char>. And those who have shown to others the way to live righteously will shine forever, like the stars [SIM]. <verse eid="DAN 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DAN 12:4"/>But as for you, Daniel, close up the scroll <char style="add">on which you are writing</char>, and seal it <char style="add">in order that no one can open it</char> until the end <char style="add">of the world</char> is near. <char style="add">Before that happens,</char> many people will travel rapidly here and there, learning more and more <char style="add">about many things</char>.”<verse eid="DAN 12:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DAN 12:5"/>When <char style="add">that angel finished speaking</char>, I, Daniel, looked up, and suddenly I saw two other <char style="add">angels</char>. One was standing on the side of the river <char style="add">where I was</char>, and one was standing on the other side. <verse eid="DAN 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DAN 12:6"/>One of them <char style="add">called to</char> the other one, who was wearing linen/white clothes, who was now standing further up (OR, above) the river, “How long will it be until these amazing/frightening events end?”<verse eid="DAN 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DAN 12:7"/>The angel who was on the other side of (OR, above) the river raised his hands toward the sky, and solemnly promised, with the authority [MTY] of God, who lives forever, “It will be three and a half years. All these things will end after God’s people stop fighting against those who ◄persecute/cause trouble for/cause suffering for► them.”<verse eid="DAN 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DAN 12:8"/>I heard <char style="add">what he said</char>, but I did not understand it. So I asked, “Sir, what will be the result when these things end?”<verse eid="DAN 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DAN 12:9"/>He replied, “Daniel, you must leave now. <char style="add">I cannot answer your question</char> because what it means must ◄be kept secret/not be revealed► [DOU] until the time when everything ends. <verse eid="DAN 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DAN 12:10"/>Many people will thoroughly purify their inner beings [DOU]. But wicked people will not understand these things. They will continue to be wicked. Only those who are wise will understand <char style="add">these things</char>. <verse eid="DAN 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DAN 12:11"/><char style="add">But I can tell you that before everything ends,</char> there will be 1,290 days, from the time that people are prevented from offering sacrifices each day, that is, from the time that the abominable/disgusting thing is put in the temple. <verse eid="DAN 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DAN 12:12"/>God will be pleased with those who remain faithful until 1,335 days are ended.<verse eid="DAN 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DAN 12:13"/>So <char style="add">now I say</char> to you, continue to faithfully <char style="add">trust God</char> until <char style="add">your life on earth</char> ends. You will die [EUP], but when everything ends, you will receive your reward <char style="add">from God</char>.”<verse eid="DAN 12:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DAN 12"/>
</usx>
