<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="DEU" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">DEUTERONOMY</para>
  <para style="toc1">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc2">Deuteronomy</para>
  <para style="toc3">Deu</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of Moses’ final speeches to the Israeli people. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Deuteronomy</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="DEU 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Introduction to Moses’ first speech</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 1:1"/>In this book is written what Moses/I said to the Israeli people. He/I told them these things when they/we were in the desert, on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. They/We had set up our tents near <char style="add">a place named</char> Suph, between Paran <char style="add">town on the one side of the river</char> and Tophel, Laban, Hazeroth, and Dizahab <char style="add">towns on the other side of the river</char>. <verse eid="DEU 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 1:2"/>To walk from Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char> to the Kadesh-Barnea <char style="add">oasis</char>, people usually travel for only eleven days, going by way of the hilly area named Edom.<verse eid="DEU 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 1:3"/>Forty years after ◄the Israelis/we► left Egypt, in the middle of January, Moses/I told the Israeli people everything that Yahweh had commanded him/me to tell them. <verse eid="DEU 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 1:4"/>This was after they/we had defeated Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group, who lived in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char>, and Og, the king of the Bashan <char style="add">region</char> who lived in Ashtaroth and Edrei <char style="add">towns</char>.<verse eid="DEU 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 1:5"/>Moses/I told them these things while the people were in the Moab region, on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. He/I ◄explained to them/enabled them to understand► God’s laws. This is what he/I said to them:<verse eid="DEU 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 1:6"/>“Yahweh our God said to us when we were at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char>, ‘You have stayed for a very long time at <char style="add">the bottom of</char> this mountain. <verse eid="DEU 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 1:7"/>So now continue traveling. Go to the hilly area where the Amor people-group lives and to the nearby areas—to the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley, to the hilly region, to the western ◄foothills/hills at the bottom of the mountains►, to the desert area to the south, to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Seacoast, to all of Canaan land, to the Lebanon <char style="add">Mountains</char>, and <char style="add">northeast</char> to the great Euphrates River. <verse eid="DEU 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 1:8"/>Note that I will give that land to you. I, Yahweh, promised to your ancestors Abraham and Isaac and Jacob that I would give it to them and to their descendants. So now go and occupy it.’”<verse eid="DEU 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them that he had appointed leaders</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 1:9"/>Moses/I also said to the people, “When <char style="add">we were still at Sinai Mountain</char>, I told your ancestors ‘It is a very big burden/responsibility for me to govern all of you. So I cannot do it by myself. <verse eid="DEU 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 1:10"/>Yahweh our God has caused us Israelis to now become as numerous as the stars in the sky. <verse eid="DEU 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 1:11"/>And I hope/desire that Yahweh, the God whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, will cause us to become 1,000 times as numerous as we are now and that he will bless us just like he promised to do. <verse eid="DEU 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 1:12"/>But I certainly cannot [RHQ] ◄solve/deal with► all of your complaints/problems. <verse eid="DEU 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 1:13"/>So choose some men from your tribes who are wise and who have good sense and who are respected. Then I will appoint them to be your leaders.’<verse eid="DEU 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 1:14"/>Your ancestors replied, ‘What you have suggested is good for us to do.’<verse eid="DEU 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 1:15"/>So I took the wise and respected men <char style="add">that your ancestors chose</char> from your tribes, and I appointed them to be your leaders. I appointed some to ◄rule/have authority► over 1,000 people, some to have authority over 100 people, some to have authority over 50 people, and some to have authority over ten people. I also appointed other officers from throughout your tribes. <verse eid="DEU 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 1:16"/>I instructed/told your leaders, ‘Listen to the disputes that occur among your people. Judge each dispute, including disputes between close relatives and quarrels between your people and people from other countries who live among you. <verse eid="DEU 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 1:17"/>You must ◄be impartial/not favor one person more than another►; you must treat poor people and important people equally. You must not worry about what anyone will think <char style="add">about how you decide matters</char>, because you will decide matters as God <char style="add">wants you to</char>. If any quarrel/dispute is very difficult and you are unable to decide it, bring it to me, and I will decide.’ <verse eid="DEU 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 1:18"/>At that time I also told you other things that you should do.”<verse eid="DEU 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them about sending the spies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 1:19"/>“Then, just like Yahweh our God commanded us, we left Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char> and went through that huge desert that was very ◄dangerous/difficult to travel through►, on the road to the hilly area where the Amor people-group live. We arrived at Kadesh-Barnea. <verse eid="DEU 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 1:20"/>I said to your ancestors, ‘We have now come to the hilly area where the Amor people-group live. This is part of the area that Yahweh our God, the one whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, is giving to us. <verse eid="DEU 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 1:21"/>Note that Yahweh our God is giving this land to us. So go and occupy it as he commanded. Do not be ◄at all/even a little bit► afraid.’<verse eid="DEU 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 1:22"/>But all of your ancestors came to me and said, ‘Before we go, we should <char style="add">first</char> send some men there to explore the land, in order that they can return and tell us which will be the best road to go there and what kind of towns are there.’<verse eid="DEU 1:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 1:23"/>I thought that it would be good to do that, so I chose twelve men, one man from each tribe. <verse eid="DEU 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 1:24"/>They went up into the hilly area as far as Eshcol Valley, and they explored all that area. <verse eid="DEU 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 1:25"/>They picked some of the fruit that they found there and brought it to us. They reported that the land that Yahweh our God was giving to us is very good/fertile.”<verse eid="DEU 1:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them how God punished them when they refused to go</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 1:26"/>“But your ancestors refused to go <char style="add">and conquer that land</char>. They rebelled against what Yahweh our God had commanded them to do, and they would not go into that land. <verse eid="DEU 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 1:27"/>Your ancestors <char style="add">stayed</char> in their tents and complained saying ‘Yahweh hates us. So he has brought us here from Egypt just to allow the Amor people-group to destroy us. <verse eid="DEU 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 1:28"/>◄Why should we go there?/We do not want to go there.► [RHQ] The men whom we sent there have caused us to become very discouraged/afraid. They have told us that the people there are much stronger and taller than we are and that there are extremely high [HYP] walls around their towns. Also they reported that they saw <char style="add">giants there that are</char> descendants of Anak.’<verse eid="DEU 1:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 1:29"/>Then I said to your ancestors, ‘Do not be afraid ◄at all/even a little bit► [DOU] of those people! <verse eid="DEU 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 1:30"/>Yahweh our God will go ahead of you, and he will fight for you, just like you saw him do for you in Egypt <verse eid="DEU 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 1:31"/>and in the desert. You saw how he brought you safely here, like a man would carry his son. [SIM]’<verse eid="DEU 1:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32-33" style="v" sid="DEU 1:32-33"/>
    <char style="add">I reminded them that</char> he always went ahead of them while they traveled <char style="add">in the desert</char>. He directed them by <char style="add">a pillar of</char> fire during the night and a <char style="add">pillar of</char> cloud during the day. He showed them places to set up their tents. But in spite of what I said, your ancestors would not trust Yahweh our God.<verse eid="DEU 1:32-33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 1:34"/>Yahweh heard what they said, and he became angry. He solemnly declared, <verse eid="DEU 1:34"/><verse number="35-36" style="v" sid="DEU 1:35-36"/>‘Caleb, the son of Jephunneh, will enter the land. He has obeyed me completely. So I will give to him and to his descendants <char style="add">some of</char> the land that he explored. He is the only one of all you people who will enter that land. None of these evil people will ever see that good land which I solemnly promised to give to your ancestors.’<verse eid="DEU 1:35-36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 1:37"/>But because of <char style="add">what</char> your ancestors <char style="add">did</char>, Yahweh was also angry with me. He said to me, ‘You also will not enter that land. <verse eid="DEU 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 1:38"/>Joshua, the son of Nun, who is your helper, will enter it. Encourage him, because he is the one who will enable you Israeli people to occupy that land.’<verse eid="DEU 1:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 1:39"/>Then Yahweh said to all of us, ‘You said that your children would be captured by your enemies. Because they are very young, they do not yet know what is good and what is evil. But they are the ones to whom I will give that land, and they will enter it and occupy it. <verse eid="DEU 1:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 1:40"/>But as for you, turn around and go back into the desert, toward the ◄Red Sea/Gulf of Aqaba►.’<verse eid="DEU 1:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 1:41"/>Then your ancestors replied, ‘We have sinned; we have disobeyed Yahweh. So we will go and attack <char style="add">the people who live in</char> that land, just like Yahweh our God commanded us to do.’ And each of their men put on his weapons, and they thought that it would be easy to invade the hilly region.<verse eid="DEU 1:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 1:42"/>But Yahweh said to me, ‘Tell them, “Do not go up there and attack those people, because I will not go with you. If you go, your enemies will defeat you.”’<verse eid="DEU 1:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 1:43"/>So I told that to your ancestors, but they would not heed what I said. They <char style="add">again</char> rebelled against what Yahweh commanded them to do. Their soldiers proudly/arrogantly marched up into that hilly region. <verse eid="DEU 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 1:44"/>Then the men of the Amor people-group who lived in that region came out <char style="add">of their towns</char> and attacked those soldiers. They pursued your ancestors’ soldiers like <char style="add">a swarm of</char> bees pursues people, and they pursued them <char style="add">south</char> from the Edom area and defeated them at Hormah <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="DEU 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 1:45"/>So your ancestors went back <char style="add">to Kadesh-Barnea</char> and cried out to request Yahweh <char style="add">to help them</char>, but he did not heed them. He did not pay any attention to them [DOU]. <verse eid="DEU 1:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 1:46"/>So we stayed there at Kadesh-Barnea for a long time.”<verse eid="DEU 1:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="DEU 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them of their wandering in the desert</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 2:1"/>“Then we turned around and went through the desert toward the ◄Red Sea/Gulf of Aqaba►, as Yahweh told us to do, and we wandered in the Edom area for many years.<verse eid="DEU 2:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 2:2"/>Then Yahweh said to me, <verse eid="DEU 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 2:3"/>‘You have been wandering around this hilly area for a long enough time. Now turn <char style="add">and travel</char> toward the north. <verse eid="DEU 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 2:4"/>And tell the people that they are about to travel near the land that belongs to the descendants of Esau, who are also descendants of Isaac. They live in the <char style="add">hilly</char> Edom region. They will be afraid of you, <verse eid="DEU 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 2:5"/>but do not start to fight against them, because I am not going to give you even a tiny bit [HYP] of their land. I have given that land to the descendants of Esau. <verse eid="DEU 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 2:6"/><char style="add">When you travel near their land</char>, buy food and water from them.’<verse eid="DEU 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 2:7"/>Do not forget that Yahweh our God has blessed you in everything that you [SYN] have done. He knows <char style="add">what has happened to you while</char> you have wandered in this huge desert. But he has been with you during those 40 years, and as a result you have had everything that you needed [LIT].<verse eid="DEU 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 2:8"/>So we continued to travel. We avoided going through the hilly area where the descendants of Esau live. We stayed away from the road through the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley past Ezion-Geber and Elath <char style="add">towns</char>, and we turned and traveled northeast toward the desert area where the Moab people-group lives.<verse eid="DEU 2:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 2:9"/>Yahweh said to me, ‘Do not bother/harass the people of Moab, and do not start to fight against them, because I am not going to give you any of their land. <char style="add">Do not forget that</char> they are descendants of <char style="add">Abraham’s nephew</char> Lot, and I have given to them Ar <char style="add">city, their capital, and the other areas in that country</char>.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 2:10"/>A large group of giants called Emim formerly lived there. They were strong and numerous, and as tall as the giants who were descendants of Anak. <verse eid="DEU 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 2:11"/>They and the descendants of Anak are also called the Repha giants, but the people of Moab call them Emim. <verse eid="DEU 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 2:12"/>The Hor people-group also formerly lived in the Edom area, but the descendants of Esau chased them out. They defeated and killed them and ◄settled in/occupied► their land, just as the Israeli people later expelled their enemies from the land that Yahweh gave to them.<verse eid="DEU 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 2:13"/>
    <char style="add">I also said to the Israeli people</char>, “Then we crossed the Zered Gorge, as Yahweh told us to do. <verse eid="DEU 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 2:14"/>It had been thirty-eight years from the time we first left Kadesh-Barnea until we crossed the Zered Gorge. During those years, all the Israeli ◄fighting men/soldiers► of that generation had died, as Yahweh had vowed would happen. <verse eid="DEU 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 2:15"/>They died because Yahweh opposed them, until he had gotten rid of all of them.<verse eid="DEU 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 2:16"/>After all the men who had been old enough to fight in wars had died [DOU], <verse eid="DEU 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 2:17"/>Yahweh said to me, <verse eid="DEU 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 2:18"/>‘Today you all must cross the border into the Moab region, near Ar, <char style="add">their capital city</char>. <verse eid="DEU 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 2:19"/>When you come near the border of the land where the Ammon people-group live, do not bother/harass them or start to fight against them. They are also descendants of Lot, so I am not going to give you any of the land that I have given to them.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Other groups that lived near Canaan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 2:20"/>That region is also called the land of the Repha giants, who formerly lived there. The Ammon people-group call them the Zamzum group. <verse eid="DEU 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 2:21"/>They were a large and powerful group, who were as tall as the descendants of Anak. But Yahweh got rid of them, and the Ammon people-group expelled them and took their land away from them and started to live there. <verse eid="DEU 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 2:22"/>Yahweh had done the same thing for the descendants of Esau who live in the hilly area of Edom. He got rid of the Hor people-group, with the result that the Edom people-group took their land from them and started to live there. They still live there. <verse eid="DEU 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 2:23"/>People who came from Crete <char style="add">Island</char> got rid of the Av group <char style="add">who previously lived in the land close to the Mediterranean Sea</char>, as far south as Gaza. They took their land from them and started to live there.<verse eid="DEU 2:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them of crossing the Arnon River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 2:24"/>“<char style="add">After we had gone through the Moab region</char>, Yahweh said to us, ‘Now cross the Arnon <char style="add">River</char>. I will help you to defeat [IDM] <char style="add">the army of</char> Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group, who lives in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char>. So attack their army and start to take their land from them. <verse eid="DEU 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 2:25"/>Today I will begin to cause everyone, everywhere, to be afraid of you. Everyone who hears about you will tremble and be terrified.’<verse eid="DEU 2:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 2:26"/>Then I sent messengers to go from the desert to King Sihon at Heshbon. I told them to give this peaceful message to the king: <verse eid="DEU 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 2:27"/>‘Please allow us to travel through your land. We <char style="add">promise that we</char> will stay on the road; we will not turn off to the right or to the left. <verse eid="DEU 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 2:28"/>We will pay for any food or water that you allow us to buy. We want only to walk through your country, <verse eid="DEU 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 2:29"/>until we cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> into the land that Yahweh our God is giving to us. Do for us just as the descendants of Esau who live in the Edom area and the Moab people-group did for us when they allowed us to go through their areas.’ <verse eid="DEU 2:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 2:30"/>But King Sihon would not allow us to go through his country. That was because Yahweh our God caused him to be stubborn [IDM]. The result was that Yahweh enabled us to defeat his army and take his land [IDM], which we still live in.<verse eid="DEU 2:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 2:31"/>Yahweh said to me, ‘Listen! I am about to allow you to defeat Sihon’s <char style="add">army</char> and to take the people’s land from them. So start to occupy it!’<verse eid="DEU 2:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 2:32"/>Then Sihon came out <char style="add">of the city</char> with all his army to fight against us at Jahaz <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="DEU 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 2:33"/>But God enabled us to defeat [DOU] them, and we killed Sihon and his sons and all his soldiers. <verse eid="DEU 2:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 2:34"/>We captured all their cities and destroyed them all. We killed all the men and women and children; we did not allow any of them to remain alive. <verse eid="DEU 2:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 2:35"/>We took the valuable things that were in the cities that we captured and also their cattle. <verse eid="DEU 2:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 2:36"/>Yahweh our God enabled us to capture [IDM] all their towns from Aroer <char style="add">in the south</char>, which is at the edge of the Arnon River <char style="add">Valley</char>, to the Gilead <char style="add">region in the north</char>. Some of their cities had <char style="add">walls around them</char>, but we were able to <char style="add">climb over them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 2:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 2:37"/>But we did not go near the area where the Ammon people-group live, or the banks of the Jabbok riverbed, or the towns in the hilly area, or any other place where Yahweh our God told us not to go.”<verse eid="DEU 2:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="DEU 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them of the defeat of King Og</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 3:1"/>“Then we turned <char style="add">north</char> and went toward the Bashan region. Og, the king <char style="add">of that area</char>, and all his soldiers marched <char style="add">south</char> to fight against us at Edrei <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="DEU 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 3:2"/>Yahweh said to me, ‘Do not be afraid of him, because I will enable your <char style="add">army</char> to defeat [MTY] him and all his army and to capture all their land. Do to him what you did to Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group, who ruled in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char>.’<verse eid="DEU 3:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 3:3"/>“So Yahweh enabled us to defeat [IDM] King Og and all his army. We killed them all; we did not allow any of them to remain alive. <verse eid="DEU 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 3:4"/>There were 60 cities in that region near Argob, in King Og’s kingdom of Bashan. But we captured all of them <verse eid="DEU 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 3:5"/>All those cities had high walls <char style="add">around them</char> with gates and bars. We also captured many villages that did not have walls <char style="add">around them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 3:6"/>We completely destroyed everything, just as we had done <char style="add">in the area that</char> King Sihon ruled. We killed all the men, women, and children. <verse eid="DEU 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 3:7"/>But from those cities we took for ourselves all the livestock and other valuable things.<verse eid="DEU 3:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 3:8"/>“So at that time we took from those two kings of the Amor people-group all the land east of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, from the Arnon <char style="add">River</char> gorge <char style="add">in the south</char> to Hermon Mountain <char style="add">in the north</char>.” <verse eid="DEU 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 3:9"/>(That mountain is called Sirion by the people of Sidon <char style="add">city</char> and is called Senir by the Amor people-group.) <verse eid="DEU 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 3:10"/>“We captured all the towns on the ◄plateau/high level land►, and all the Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, and all the Bashan <char style="add">region</char> as far east as Edrei and Salecah towns, which also belonged to Og’s kingdom.” <verse eid="DEU 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 3:11"/>(Og was the last king who was a descendant of the Repha giants. His bed was made of iron. It was almost ◄14 feet/4 meters► long and ◄6 feet/2 meters► wide. It is still [RHQ] in Rabbah <char style="add">city</char> in the Ammon area.)<verse eid="DEU 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them of dividing the land east of the Jordan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 3:12"/>“From the land that we captured at that time, I allotted to the tribes of Reuben and Gad the land <char style="add">north</char> of Aroer <char style="add">town</char> near the Arnon <char style="add">River</char>, and some of the hilly area of the Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, along with the nearby towns. <verse eid="DEU 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 3:13"/>The other part of the Gilead <char style="add">region</char> and all of the Bashan <char style="add">region</char>, which was the Argob <char style="add">region</char> that King Og had ruled, I allotted to half of the tribe of Manasseh.” (The entire Bashan <char style="add">region</char> is called the land of the Repha giants.) <verse eid="DEU 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 3:14"/>“Jair, from the tribe of Manasseh, conquered all the Bashan area as far <char style="add">north</char> as the border of the Geshur and Maacah territories. He gave his own name to the villages there, and they are still called the villages of Jair.<verse eid="DEU 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 3:15"/>The <char style="add">northern part of the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> I allotted to the Machir <char style="add">clan, who are descendants of the tribe of Manasseh</char>. <verse eid="DEU 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 3:16"/>I allotted to the tribes of Reuben and Gad the southern part of the Gilead <char style="add">region, extending south</char> to the Arnon <char style="add">River</char>. The middle of the river is the <char style="add">southern</char> boundary. The <char style="add">northern</char> boundary is the Jabbok River, which is part of the border of the Ammon area. <verse eid="DEU 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 3:17"/><char style="add">To the west their territory extended</char> to the Jordan <char style="add">River </char> Valley, from Galilee Lake <char style="add">in the north</char> to the Dead Sea <char style="add">in the south</char> and to the slopes of Pisgah <char style="add">Mountain</char> to the east.<verse eid="DEU 3:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 3:18"/>At that time, I told you three tribes, ‘Yahweh our God is giving you this land <char style="add">east of the Jordan River</char>, for you to occupy/capture. So now, give your soldiers weapons, and send them <char style="add">across the Jordan River</char> ahead of the men from the other Israeli tribes <char style="add">to help them to conquer/capture the land that has been allotted to them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 3:19"/>But your wives and children and your very numerous cattle must stay in the towns that I have allotted to you. <verse eid="DEU 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 3:20"/><char style="add">Your men must help your fellow Israelis</char> until Yahweh enables them to live there peacefully after they capture all the land that Yahweh our God is giving to them on the west side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, just like he did for you <char style="add">here on the east side of the river</char>. After that, you all may return to this land that I have allotted to you.’<verse eid="DEU 3:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 3:21"/>And I told Joshua, ‘You [SYN] have seen everything that Yahweh our God did to those two kings, <char style="add">Sihon and Og</char>. He will do the same thing to the people <char style="add">who are now</char> in the land that you will be entering. <verse eid="DEU 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 3:22"/>Do not be afraid of those people, because Yahweh our God is the one who will fight for you all.’”<verse eid="DEU 3:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them that he was not allowed to enter Canaan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 3:23"/>“At that time, I earnestly prayed, saying <verse eid="DEU 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 3:24"/>‘Yahweh our Lord, you have merely begun to show me that you are very great and to show me the powerful things that you can do [MTY]. There is certainly no [RHQ] god in heaven or on earth who can do the powerful things/deeds that you <char style="add">have done</char>. <verse eid="DEU 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 3:25"/>So please allow me to cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and to see the good/fertile land on the west side, the beautiful hilly area and <char style="add">the mountains in</char> Lebanon.’<verse eid="DEU 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 3:26"/>But Yahweh was angry with me because of <char style="add">what</char> your ancestors <char style="add">had made me do</char>, so he would not pay attention to me. Instead, he said, ‘That is enough <char style="add">talk from you</char>! Do not talk to me about that again! <verse eid="DEU 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 3:27"/>Climb up to the top of Pisgah <char style="add">Mountain</char> and look toward the west and to the east, toward the north and to the south. Look at [MTY] it all carefully, because you will not cross the Jordan <char style="add">River to see the land from there</char>. <verse eid="DEU 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 3:28"/>But tell Joshua what he must do and encourage him to be strong, because he is the one who will lead the people <char style="add">across the river in order that they can</char> occupy/capture the land that you will see <char style="add">from the top of the mountain</char>.’<verse eid="DEU 3:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 3:29"/>So we remained in the <char style="add">Jordan River</char> Valley close to Beth-Peor <char style="add">town</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 3:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="DEU 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses urged the people to obey God’s laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 4:1"/>“Now, you Israeli people, obey all the rules and regulations [DOU] that I will teach you. If you do that, you will remain alive and you will enter and occupy/capture the land that Yahweh, the God whom your ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 4:2"/>Do not add anything to what I command you, and do not take anything away from what I tell you. Obey all the commands of Yahweh our God that I am giving to you.<verse eid="DEU 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 4:3"/>“You have seen what Yahweh did at Baal-Peor <char style="add">Mountain</char>. He got rid of all the people who worshiped <char style="add">the god</char> Baal there, <verse eid="DEU 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 4:4"/>but you who faithfully <char style="add">continued to worship</char> Yahweh our God are still alive today.<verse eid="DEU 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 4:5"/>“Note that I have taught you all the rules and regulations, just like Yahweh our God told me to do. He wants you to obey them <char style="add">when you are living</char> in the land that you are about to enter and occupy. <verse eid="DEU 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 4:6"/>Obey them faithfully because, <char style="add">if you do that</char>, you will show the people of other nations that you are very wise. When they hear about all these laws, they will say, ‘The people of this great nation <char style="add">of Israel</char> are certainly very wise [DOU]!’ <verse eid="DEU 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 4:7"/>Even if other nations are great, there is none [RHQ] of them that has a god who is as near to them as Yahweh our God is to us! Whenever we call out to him <char style="add">to help us, he answers/helps us</char> <verse eid="DEU 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 4:8"/>And there is no [RHQ] other nation, even if it is a great nation, that has laws that are as just/fair as the laws that I am telling to you today.<verse eid="DEU 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 4:9"/>“But be very careful! [DOU, IDM] Do not forget what you [SYN] have seen <char style="add">God do</char>. Remember those things as long as you are alive. Tell them to your children and your grandchildren. <verse eid="DEU 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 4:10"/>Tell them about the day that your ancestors stood in the presence of Yahweh our God at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char>, when he said to me, ‘Gather the people together, in order that they can hear what I say. I want them to learn to have an awesome respect for me as long as they are alive, and I want them to teach their children to do that also.’ <verse eid="DEU 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 4:11"/><char style="add">Tell them that</char> your ancestors came near the bottom of the mountain, while the mountain burned with a fire that went up to the sky, and the mountain was covered with dark clouds and black <char style="add">smoke</char>. <verse eid="DEU 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 4:12"/>Then Yahweh spoke to your ancestors out of the middle of the fire. Your ancestors heard him speak, but they did not see him. They only heard his voice. <verse eid="DEU 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 4:13"/>And he declared to them his agreement. That agreement contained the Ten Commandments that he wants you to obey. He wrote those on two stone tablets. <verse eid="DEU 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 4:14"/>Yahweh commanded me to teach all the rules and regulations to you, in order that you would obey them in the land that you are about to enter and occupy.”<verse eid="DEU 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses warned them about worshiping idols</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 4:15"/>“On the day that Yahweh spoke to your ancestors at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char>, he was invisible. So, be careful <verse eid="DEU 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 4:16"/>that you do not sin by making for yourselves any idol <char style="add">of something that can be seen! </char>Do not make an idol that resembles any person, either a man or a woman, <verse eid="DEU 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 4:17"/>or that resembles any animal or any bird <verse eid="DEU 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 4:18"/>or any ◄reptile/creature that scurries across the ground► or any fish in the deep ocean. <verse eid="DEU 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 4:19"/>And be careful to not look up toward the sky and be tempted to worship anything that you see there—the sun or the moon or the stars. Yahweh our God has given those to <char style="add">be a blessing to</char> all people everywhere, <char style="add">but you must not worship them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 4:20"/>Yahweh has brought your ancestors out of Egypt, where <char style="add">they were suffering as though</char> they were in a blazing furnace, in order that they would be people who belong to him, which is what you are today.<verse eid="DEU 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 4:21"/>“But Yahweh was angry with me because of <char style="add">what</char> your ancestors <char style="add">made me do</char>. He vowed that I would not cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to enter the good/fertile land that he is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 4:22"/>He said that I must die here in this land and never cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. But you will go across it, and you will occupy that land. <verse eid="DEU 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 4:23"/>Be sure that you do not forget the agreement that Yahweh our God made with you. He commanded you to not make any kind of idol, because he has forbidden that. <verse eid="DEU 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 4:24"/><char style="add">You must not do that</char> because Yahweh your God will destroy <char style="add">anyone who worships idols,</char> like [MET] a fire completely destroys things. He <char style="add">wants people to worship only him, he</char> ◄cannot accept/will punish► people who worship anyone or anything else.<verse eid="DEU 4:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 4:25"/>“When you have been in the land <char style="add">of Canaan</char> for a long time and you have children and grandchildren, do not sin by making an idol that represents anything at all, because Yahweh says that is evil, and if you do that, you will cause him to become angry with you <char style="add">and punish you</char>. <verse eid="DEU 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 4:26"/>Today I am requesting everyone who is in heaven and everyone who is on the earth [MTY] to watch what you are doing. <char style="add">If you disobey what I am telling you</char>, you will soon all die in the land that you will be crossing the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to occupy. You will not live very long there; Yahweh will completely get rid of many [HYP] of you. <verse eid="DEU 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 4:27"/>And <char style="add">the rest of you</char>, Yahweh will force you to go and live among the people of many other nations. Only a few of you will ◄survive/remain alive► there. <verse eid="DEU 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 4:28"/>When you are in those nations, you will worship gods that are made of wood and stone, gods made by humans, gods that cannot see anything or hear anything or eat anything or smell anything. <verse eid="DEU 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 4:29"/>But while you are there, if you will try to know Yahweh your God, and if you try with your entire inner being to know him, he will ◄answer/reveal himself to► you. <verse eid="DEU 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 4:30"/>In the future, after you have been mistreated there and all those bad things happen to you, you will again worship only Yahweh and obey him. <verse eid="DEU 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 4:31"/>Yahweh is a God who acts mercifully. <char style="add">If you continue to obey him</char>, he will not abandon you or destroy you or forget the agreement that he solemnly made with your ancestors.”<verse eid="DEU 4:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Only Yahweh is God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 4:32"/>“Now think about the past, about the time before you were born, about all the time since God first created people here on the earth. You could search everywhere, in heaven and on the earth. ◄Has anything like this ever happened that is as great as <char style="add">what Yahweh did for the Israeli people</char>?/Certainly nothing has ever happened that is as great <char style="add">as what Yahweh did for the Israeli people</char>.► [RHQ] ◄Has anyone ever heard of anything like this?/Certainly no one has ever heard of anything like this.► [RHQ] <verse eid="DEU 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 4:33"/>◄Has any group ever remained alive after they heard a god speak to them from the middle of a fire, like we did?/Certainly no group has ever remained alive after they heard a god speak to them from the middle of a fire, like we did.► [RHQ] <verse eid="DEU 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 4:34"/>Certainly no other god has ever tried to take a <char style="add">huge</char> group of people from one nation <char style="add">to another location</char>, like he did for us when he brought us out of Egypt. We saw Yahweh our God use great power [MTY, DOU] when he performed many kinds of [DOU] miracles, and sent plagues, and did many other very terrifying things in Egypt for us, <char style="add">and rescued us when the army of Egypt tried to fight against us</char>.<verse eid="DEU 4:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 4:35"/>“Yahweh showed all these things to you, in order that you would know that only he is truly God, and that there is no other God. <verse eid="DEU 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 4:36"/>He allowed your ancestors to hear him speak from heaven in order that he could discipline them. Here on the earth he allowed them to see his great fire <char style="add">on Sinai Mountain</char>, and he spoke to them from the middle of the fire. <verse eid="DEU 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 4:37"/>Because he loved our ancestors, he chose you Israelis who are their descendants, and by his great power he brought your ancestors out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 4:38"/><char style="add">As they advanced</char>, he expelled the people of nations that were greater and more powerful than they were, in order that he could allow them to capture their land and cause it to become yours, which is <char style="add">what is happening</char> now.<verse eid="DEU 4:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 4:39"/>“So today you should ◄meditate on/think about► the fact that Yahweh is God, that he is/rules in heaven and also on the earth, and that there is no other god. <verse eid="DEU 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 4:40"/>Obey all the rules and regulations that I am giving to you today, in order that things will go well for you and for your descendants, and that you will live a long time in the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you, <char style="add">to belong to you</char> forever.”<verse eid="DEU 4:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The cities of refuge</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 4:41"/>Then Moses/I set apart three cities that are on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="DEU 4:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 4:42"/>If someone accidentally killed another person, a person who had not been his enemy previously, he could escape to one of those cities. He would be safe/protected in one of those cities <char style="add">because the people there would protect him</char>. <verse eid="DEU 4:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 4:43"/>For the tribe of Reuben, Moses/I set apart Bezer <char style="add">city</char> in the ◄plateau/high level► area. For the tribe of Gad, Moses/I set apart Ramoth <char style="add">city</char> in the Gilead <char style="add">area</char>. For the tribe of Manasseh, Moses/I set apart Golan <char style="add">city</char> in the Bashan <char style="add">region</char>.<verse eid="DEU 4:43"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Where Moses gave them God’s laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 4:44"/>Moses/I gave <char style="add">God’s</char> laws to the Israeli people. <verse eid="DEU 4:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 4:45"/>They included all the rules and instructions and commands that Moses/I gave to them, after they/we had come out of Egypt, <verse eid="DEU 4:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 4:46"/>when they/we were in the valley east of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. They/We were across from Beth-Peor <char style="add">town</char>, in the land that <char style="add">previously</char> was ruled by Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group, who lived in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char>. Moses/I and the other Israelis had defeated his <char style="add">army</char> when they/we came out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 4:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 4:47"/>They/We captured Sihon’s land and the land that Og, the king of the Bashan <char style="add">region</char>, ruled. They were the two kings who ruled the Amor people-group <char style="add">in the area</char> east of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="DEU 4:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 4:48"/>Their land extended from Aroer <char style="add">town in the south</char> along the Arnon <char style="add">River</char>, as far <char style="add">north</char> as Sirion Mountain, which <char style="add">most people</char> call Hermon Mountain. <verse eid="DEU 4:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 4:49"/>It also included all the area east of the Jordan <char style="add">River </char> Valley, all the way south to the Dead Sea and east to the slopes of Pisgah <char style="add">Mountain</char>.<verse eid="DEU 4:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="DEU 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses repeated for them the Ten Commandments</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 5:1"/>Moses/I summoned all the people of Israel and said to them,</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DEU 5:1">“You Israeli people, listen to all the rules and regulations that I am giving to you today. Learn them and be sure to obey them. <verse eid="DEU 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 5:2"/>When we were at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char>, Yahweh our God made an agreement with us. <verse eid="DEU 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 5:3"/>But this agreement was not only for our ancestors. He made it also for us who are alive now. <verse eid="DEU 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 5:4"/>Yahweh spoke with us face-to-face on that mountain, from the middle of the fire. <verse eid="DEU 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 5:5"/>On that day, I stood between your ancestors and Yahweh to tell them what he said, because they were afraid of the fire, and they did not climb up the mountain. This is what Yahweh said:<verse eid="DEU 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="mi">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 5:6"/>‘I am Yahweh your God, the one you <char style="add">worship</char>. I am the one who brought you out of the land of Egypt. I am the one who freed you from being slaves <char style="add">there</char>.<verse eid="DEU 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 5:7"/>
    <char style="add">You must worship only</char> me; you must not worship any other god.<verse eid="DEU 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 5:8"/>You must not carve/make for yourselves any idol that represents anything in the sky or anything that is on the ground or anything that swims in the water.<verse eid="DEU 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 5:9"/>You must not bow down to any idol and worship it, because I am Yahweh God, and I ◄am very jealous/want you to worship me only►. I punish those who sin and hate me. I punish not only them, but I will punish ◄their descendants, down to the third and fourth generation/their children and grandchildren and great-grandchildren►. <verse eid="DEU 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 5:10"/>But I will steadfastly love ◄thousands of generations/all the descendants► of those who love me and obey my commandments (OR, I will love for thousands of generations).<verse eid="DEU 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 5:11"/>Do not use/speak my name carelessly (OR, for wrong/evil purposes), because I am Yahweh God, the one whom you <char style="add">should worship</char>, and I will certainly punish those who use/speak my name for wrong/evil purposes [LIT].<verse eid="DEU 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 5:12"/>Do not forget that the seventh day <char style="add">of every week</char> is mine. Dedicate those days to me just like I, Yahweh your God, am commanding you.<verse eid="DEU 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 5:13"/>There are six days each week for you to do all your work, <verse eid="DEU 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 5:14"/>but the seventh day is a rest day, a day dedicated to me, Yahweh your God. On that day you must not do any work. You and your sons and daughters and your male and female slaves must not work. You must not even force your livestock to work, and you must not tell foreigners to work, those who are living in your country. You must allow your slaves to rest on that day just like you do. <verse eid="DEU 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 5:15"/>Do not forget that you were slaves in Egypt, and that I, Yahweh your God, brought you out from there by my very great power. [DOU, MTY] That is the reason that I am commanding that <char style="add">all of</char> you must rest on the seventh/Sabbath day <char style="add">each week</char>.<verse eid="DEU 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 5:16"/>Honor/Respect your fathers and your mothers, just like I, Yahweh your God, am commanding you, in order that you may live a long time in the land that I, Yahweh your God, will give you, and in order that things will go well for you there.<verse eid="DEU 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 5:17"/>Do not murder anyone.<verse eid="DEU 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 5:18"/>Do not ◄commit adultery/have sex with anyone other than your spouse►.<verse eid="DEU 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 5:19"/>Do not steal anything.<verse eid="DEU 5:19"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 5:20"/>Do not tell lies about anyone <char style="add">when you are speaking in a court</char>.<verse eid="DEU 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 5:21"/>Do not ◄covet/desire to have► someone else’s wife, someone else’s house, someone else’s fields, someone else’s male slave or female slave, someone else’s livestock, someone else’s donkeys, or anything else that another person owns.’<verse eid="DEU 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 5:22"/>Those are the commandments that Yahweh spoke to your ancestors. When they were gathered there at <char style="add">the bottom of</char> the mountain, he spoke with a very loud voice from the middle of the fire, and there were dark clouds surrounding the mountain. He spoke only those <char style="add">ten</char> commandments, no more. Then he wrote them on two stone tablets and gave them to me.<verse eid="DEU 5:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 5:23"/>After your ancestors heard <char style="add">Yahweh’s</char> voice when he spoke to them out of the darkness, while there was a big fire burning on the mountain, their leaders and elders came to me, <verse eid="DEU 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 5:24"/>and <char style="add">one of</char> them said, ‘Listen to us! Yahweh our God showed us that he is very great and glorious when we heard him speak [MTY] from the fire. Today we have realized that it is possible for us humans to continue to live even though God has spoken to us. <verse eid="DEU 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 5:25"/>But we are afraid that we will die [RHQ] if we hear Yahweh our God speak [MTY] to us again; his terrible fire will destroy/kill us. <verse eid="DEU 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 5:26"/>◄Who has/Certainly no human has► remained alive after hearing the all-powerful God speak [MTY] to them from a fire. <verse eid="DEU 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 5:27"/><char style="add">So Moses</char>, you go <char style="add">up the mountain</char> and listen to everything that Yahweh our God will say. Then <char style="add">come back and</char> tell us everything that he has said, and we will listen to what he has said and obey it.’<verse eid="DEU 5:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 5:28"/>Yahweh heard your leaders say that, so <char style="add">when I went back up the mountain</char>, Yahweh said to me, ‘I have heard what your leaders have said, and what they have said is right/correct. <verse eid="DEU 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 5:29"/>I surely wish that they would always think like that and revere me and obey all my commandments, in order that things may go well for them and for their descendants forever.<verse eid="DEU 5:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 5:30"/>So go <char style="add">down</char> and tell them to return to their tents. <verse eid="DEU 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 5:31"/>But <char style="add">then</char> you <char style="add">come back up here and</char> stand near me, and I will give to you all the rules and regulations that I <char style="add">want them to obey</char>. Then you can teach them to the people, in order that they will obey them when they are in the land that I am giving to them.’<verse eid="DEU 5:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 5:32"/>
    <char style="add">So I went back down to the people, and I said to them</char>, ‘Be sure that you do everything that Yahweh our God has commanded us to do. Do not disobey any of his laws. <verse eid="DEU 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 5:33"/>Conduct your lives as Yahweh our God has commanded us to do, in order that you may live a long time, and in order that things will go well for you <char style="add">when you are living</char> in the land that you will occupy.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 5:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="DEU 6"/>
  <para style="s1">The commandment to love God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 6:1"/>“These are the commandments and rules and regulations that Yahweh our God commanded me to teach to you. He wants you to obey them in the land that you are about to enter and occupy. <verse eid="DEU 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 6:2"/>He wants you to revere him, and he wants you and your descendants to always obey all these rules and regulations that I am giving to you, in order that you may live for a long time. <verse eid="DEU 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 6:3"/>So, you Israeli people, listen to them carefully and obey them. If you do that, things will go well with you, and you will become a nation with a very large population when you are living in that very fertile [IDM] land. That is what Yahweh, the God whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, promised <char style="add">would happen</char>.<verse eid="DEU 6:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 6:4"/>“You Israeli people, listen! Only Yahweh is our God. <verse eid="DEU 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 6:5"/>You must love him with all your inner being and with all that you feel and with all that you do. <verse eid="DEU 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 6:6"/>Never forget [IDM] these commands that I am giving to you today. <verse eid="DEU 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 6:7"/>Teach them to your children again and again. Talk about them <char style="add">all the time</char>: When you are in your houses and when you are walking outside; talk about them when you are lying down and when you are doing things. <verse eid="DEU 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 6:8"/><char style="add">Write them on tiny scrolls and</char> fasten them to your arms/wrists, and write them on bands that you fasten to your foreheads <char style="add">to help you to remember them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 6:9"/>Write them on the doorposts and on the gates of your houses.<verse eid="DEU 6:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 6:10"/>“Yahweh our God vowed to your ancestors Abraham and Isaac and Jacob that he will give you a land that already has in it large and prosperous cities that you did not build. <verse eid="DEU 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 6:11"/>He said that the houses in those cities will already be full of many good things that <char style="add">others put there</char>; you did not put them there. There will be wells that others have dug. There will be vineyards and olive trees that others planted. So when Yahweh brings you into that land, and you have all that you want to eat, <verse eid="DEU 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 6:12"/>be sure that you do not forget Yahweh who rescued you from being slaves <char style="add">in Egypt and gave all these things to you</char>.<verse eid="DEU 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 6:13"/>“You must revere Yahweh our God, and you must serve only him and say that he should [MTY] punish you if you do not do what you have promised. <verse eid="DEU 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 6:14"/>You must not worship any other gods, the gods that the people-groups who will live near you worship. <verse eid="DEU 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 6:15"/>Yahweh our God, who lives among you, ◄will not accept/will punish► people who worship anyone or anything else. So if you worship any other god, Yahweh will be very angry with you, and he will get rid of you completely. <verse eid="DEU 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 6:16"/>Do not do sinful things to find out if you can do them without Yahweh our God punishing you, like your ancestors did at Massah. <verse eid="DEU 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 6:17"/>Be sure that you always obey all the laws, the commandments, the rules, and the regulations that he has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 6:18"/>Do what Yahweh says is right and good. If you do that, things will go well with you. You will be able to enter and occupy the good/fertile land that Yahweh vowed to give to our ancestors. <verse eid="DEU 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 6:19"/>He will do that by expelling your enemies from that land, just like he promised to do.<verse eid="DEU 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 6:20"/>“In the future, when your children ask you, ‘Why did Yahweh our God command us to obey all these rules and regulations?’ <verse eid="DEU 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 6:21"/>tell them, ‘Our ancestors were slaves of the king in Egypt, but Yahweh brought them out of Egypt by his great power [MTY]. <verse eid="DEU 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 6:22"/>They saw him do many kinds of miracles [DOU] and do terrifying things to the people of Egypt and to the king and his officials. <verse eid="DEU 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 6:23"/>He rescued our ancestors from Egypt and brought them here to give them this land, just like he vowed that he would do. <verse eid="DEU 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 6:24"/>And he commanded us to obey all these laws and to revere him, for our own good and in order that he would protect our nation and enable us to prosper, as he is doing now. <verse eid="DEU 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 6:25"/>Yahweh our God will ◄approve of us/consider us to be righteous► if we carefully obey everything that he has commanded us to do.’ ”<verse eid="DEU 6:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="DEU 7"/>
  <para style="s1">The blessings of worshiping God only</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 7:1"/>“Yahweh our God will bring you to the land that you will soon enter and occupy. As you advance, he will expel from that land seven people-groups that are more powerful and more numerous than you are. He will expel the Heth people-group, the Girgash people-group, the Amor people-group, the Canaan people-group, the Periz people-group, the Hiv people-group, and the Jebus people-group. <verse eid="DEU 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 7:2"/>When Yahweh our God enables you to defeat [DOU] them, you must kill all of them. You must not make ◄an alliance/a peace treaty► with any of them. You must not act mercifully toward them. <verse eid="DEU 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 7:3"/>You must not marry any of them. You must not allow your daughters to marry any of their sons or allow your sons to marry any of their daughters. <verse eid="DEU 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 7:4"/>Because, if you did that, those people would cause your children to stop worshiping Yahweh and to worship other gods. If that happens, Yahweh will be very angry with you and he will get rid of you immediately. <verse eid="DEU 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 7:5"/>This is what you must do to those people: Tear down their ◄altars/places for sacrificing animals►, break apart the stone pillars <char style="add">that are dedicated to their male god Baal</char>, cut down the <char style="add">poles that they use when they worship the goddess</char> Asherah, and burn their <char style="add">wooden</char> idols. <verse eid="DEU 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 7:6"/>You must do that because you are a group of people who belong to Yahweh our God. He has chosen you from among all the people-groups in the world to be his own special people.<verse eid="DEU 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 7:7"/>“It was not because you were more numerous than any other people-group that Yahweh preferred you; you are one of the smallest people-groups on the earth. <verse eid="DEU 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 7:8"/>Instead, it is because Yahweh loved you and because he wanted to do what he vowed to your ancestors. That is the reason that he rescued you by his great power [MTY], and freed you from being slaves [MTY] of the king of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 7:9"/>So do not forget that Yahweh our God is the only/true God. He will do what he agreed to do for you, and he will faithfully love ◄for 1,000 generations/forever► all those who love him and who obey his commandments. <verse eid="DEU 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 7:10"/>But for those who hate him, he will ◄pay them back/do to them what they deserve►; he will punish them and quickly get rid of them.<verse eid="DEU 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 7:11"/>“So you must be sure to obey all the commandments and rules and regulations that I am giving to you today. <verse eid="DEU 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 7:12"/>If you heed these commands and obey them faithfully, Yahweh our God will do what he has agreed to do for you, and he will faithfully love you, which is what he vowed to your ancestors that he would do. <verse eid="DEU 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 7:13"/>He will love you and bless you. He will enable you to have many children [DOU]. He will bless your fields, with the result that you will have plenty of grain and <char style="add">grapes to make</char> wine and plenty of <char style="add">olive</char> oil. You will have many cattle and sheep. He will do all these things for you in the land that he promised to your ancestors that he would give to you. <verse eid="DEU 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 7:14"/>He will bless you more than he will bless any other people-group. All of you will be able to have/produce children [LIT]. All of your livestock will be able to produce offspring. <verse eid="DEU 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 7:15"/>And Yahweh will protect you from all illnesses. You will not be afflicted with any of the dreadful diseases that <char style="add">our ancestors knew about</char> in Egypt, but all your enemies will be inflicted with those diseases. <verse eid="DEU 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 7:16"/>You must get rid of all the people-groups that Yahweh our God will enable you to conquer. Do not [SYN] act mercifully toward any of them. And do not worship their gods, because if you do that, it would be like falling into a trap <char style="add">from which you will never be able to escape</char>.<verse eid="DEU 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 7:17"/>“Do not think to yourselves, ‘These people-groups are more numerous/powerful than we are, so we certainly cannot [RHQ] expel them.’ <verse eid="DEU 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 7:18"/>Do not be afraid of them. Instead, think about what Yahweh our God did to the king of Egypt and to all the people whom he <char style="add">ruled</char>. <verse eid="DEU 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 7:19"/>Do not forget the terrible plagues that your ancestors saw <char style="add">Yahweh inflict on the people of Egypt</char>, and the many [DOU] miracles <char style="add">that he performed</char>, and the very powerful [DOU, MTY] way by which he brought your ancestors out <char style="add">of Egypt</char>. Yahweh our God will do the same kind of things to the people-groups that you are afraid of now. <verse eid="DEU 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 7:20"/>Furthermore, he will cause them to become terrified, and he will destroy those who remain alive and run away to hide from you. <verse eid="DEU 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 7:21"/>Do not be afraid of those people, because Yahweh our God will be with/among you. He is a great God; he is the one you should be afraid of. <verse eid="DEU 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 7:22"/>He will expel those people-groups gradually. You should not <char style="add">try to</char> expel all of them at one time, because if you did that, the number of wild animals would quickly increase, <char style="add">and you would not be able to get rid of them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 7:23"/>Instead, Yahweh will enable you to defeat your enemies <char style="add">one people-group at a time</char>. He will cause them to panic until they are destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 7:24"/>He will enable you to defeat [IDM] their kings. After you kill them, their names will be forgotten {people will forget about them}. No people-group will be able to stop you; you will destroy all of them. <verse eid="DEU 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 7:25"/>You must burn the wooden idols <char style="add">that represent</char> their gods. Do not desire to take the silver or gold <char style="add">decorations</char> that are on those idols, because if you take them for yourselves, they will be like a trap <char style="add">to cause you to want to worship those idols</char>. Yahweh hates <char style="add">the worship of those idols</char>. <verse eid="DEU 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 7:26"/>You must not bring any of those disgusting idols into your houses, because if you do that, God will curse you like he curses them. You must hate and despise [DOU] those idols, because they are things that <char style="add">Yahweh</char> has cursed.”<verse eid="DEU 7:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="DEU 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses urged them to remember and obey</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 8:1"/>“You must faithfully obey all the commandments that I am giving you today. If you do that, you will live <char style="add">a long time</char>, you will become very numerous, and you will occupy the land that Yahweh solemnly promised your ancestors that he would give <char style="add">to you</char>. <verse eid="DEU 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 8:2"/>And do not forget how Yahweh our God led us as we traveled through the desert during these past 40 years. He <char style="add">caused you to have many problems/difficulties</char>, because he wanted to cause you to realize that you needed to trust him and not yourselves. And he wanted to test you, to find out what you intended to do [IDM], whether you would obey his commandments or not. <verse eid="DEU 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 8:3"/>So he caused you to have/experience difficulties. He allowed you to become hungry. Then he gave you manna <char style="add">food from heaven</char>, food that you and your ancestors had never eaten before. He did that to teach you that people need food <char style="add">for their bodies</char>; but <char style="add">they also need food for their spirits, which comes from paying attention to</char> everything that Yahweh says [MTY]. <verse eid="DEU 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 8:4"/>During those 40 years <char style="add">of walking through the desert</char>, our clothes did not wear out and our feet did not swell <char style="add">from walking a very long way through the desert</char>. <verse eid="DEU 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 8:5"/>Do not forget that Yahweh our God disciplines us, like parents discipline their children.<verse eid="DEU 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 8:6"/>“Do obey the commandments of Yahweh our God, and conduct your lives as he wants you to do, and revere him. <verse eid="DEU 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 8:7"/>He is about to bring you into a good/fertile land, which has streams which flow down from the hills and pour/flow out of springs in the valleys. <verse eid="DEU 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 8:8"/>It is a land on which wheat and barley grow, a land where there are fig trees and pomegranates, and a land where there are olive trees and honey. <verse eid="DEU 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 8:9"/>It is a land where there will be plenty of food for you, where you will ◄not lack anything/have everything that you need► [LIT], a land which has iron <char style="add">ore</char> in its rocks and from which you can dig copper <char style="add">ore</char> from its hills. <verse eid="DEU 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 8:10"/><char style="add">Every day</char> you will eat until your stomachs are full, and you will thank Yahweh our God for the fertile/good land that he has given you.<verse eid="DEU 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 8:11"/>But, <char style="add">when that happens</char>, be sure not to forget Yahweh our God by disobeying his commandments and rules and regulations that I am giving to you today. <verse eid="DEU 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 8:12"/>When your stomachs are full <char style="add">every day</char>, and when you have built good houses and are living in them, <verse eid="DEU 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 8:13"/>and when the number of your cattle and sheep has greatly increased, and when you have accumulated a large amount of silver and gold, and the amount of all your other possessions has greatly increased, <verse eid="DEU 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 8:14"/>be sure that you do not become proud [IDM] and forget Yahweh our God, who rescued your ancestors from being slaves in Egypt and brought them out from there. <verse eid="DEU 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 8:15"/>Do not forget that he led them <char style="add">while they traveled</char> through that huge and terrible desert, where there were poisonous snakes and scorpions. And do not forget that where the ground was very dry and there was no water, he caused water to flow for them out of ◄solid/very hard► rock. <verse eid="DEU 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 8:16"/>Do not forget that in that desert he gave your ancestors manna to eat, food that they had never eaten before. He <char style="add">caused them to have/experience many problems/difficulties</char>, because he wanted them to realize that they needed to trust him and not themselves. And he wanted to test them, to find out whether they intended to obey him, in order that when <char style="add">those difficulties</char> ended, he would do many good things for them. <verse eid="DEU 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 8:17"/>Be sure that you do not think to yourselves, ‘I have acquired all these things by my own power [MTY] and ability.’ <verse eid="DEU 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 8:18"/>Do not forget that it is Yahweh our God who has enabled you to become rich. He does this because he faithfully does what he solemnly promised our ancestors that he would do.<verse eid="DEU 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 8:19"/>“ solemnly warn you that if you forget Yahweh our God and turn to other gods and start to serve them and worship them, you will certainly be destroyed. <verse eid="DEU 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 8:20"/>If you do not obey Yahweh our God, he will certainly destroy you just like he will destroy the people-groups that you will fight against.”<verse eid="DEU 8:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="DEU 9"/>
  <para style="s1">The reason that God will enable them to be victorious</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 9:1"/>“You people of Israel, listen to me! You will soon [HYP] cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. In the land that you will enter, there are large cities that have very high walls <char style="add">around them</char> that <char style="add">seem to</char> [HYP] extend up to the sky. There are people-groups in that land that are more numerous and more powerful than you are. <verse eid="DEU 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 9:2"/>Those people are very tall and strong. <char style="add">Some of them</char> are giants who are descendants of Anak. You know about them, and you have heard people say that no one [RHQ] can defeat the descendants of Anak. <verse eid="DEU 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 9:3"/>But I want you to know that Yahweh our God will go ahead of you. He will be like a raging/roaring fire. While you advance, he will defeat and destroy them. As a result, you will quickly be able to expel some of them and kill the others, which is what Yahweh promised that you would do.<verse eid="DEU 9:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 9:4"/>“After Yahweh our God has expelled them for you, do not say to yourselves, ‘It is because we are righteous that Yahweh has enabled us to capture this land.’ The truth is that it is because the people in that land are wicked that Yahweh will expel them as you advance. <verse eid="DEU 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 9:5"/><char style="add">I say again that</char> it is not because you are righteous or because you do things that are righteous that you will enter and capture that land. It is because those people-groups are very wicked that Yahweh our God will expel them as you advance, and because he intends to do what he vowed to your ancestors Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob that he would do. <verse eid="DEU 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 9:6"/>I want you to know that it is not because you are righteous that Yahweh our God is giving you this good/fertile land. I say that because <char style="add">you are not righteous</char>; you are a very stubborn [IDM] people.”<verse eid="DEU 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them of the golden calf</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 9:7"/>“Never forget what your ancestors did in the desert that caused Yahweh our God to become angry. From the day that we left Egypt until the day that we arrived here, you and your ancestors have continually rebelled against him. <verse eid="DEU 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 9:8"/>Even at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char> your ancestors caused Yahweh to become angry. Because he was very angry, he was ready to get rid of <char style="add">all of</char> them. <verse eid="DEU 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 9:9"/>When I climbed the mountain to receive from him the stone tablets on which he had written the Ten Commandments that he was giving to them, I stayed there 40 days and nights, and <char style="add">during that time</char> I did not eat or drink anything. <verse eid="DEU 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 9:10"/>Yahweh gave me the two stone tablets on which he had written <char style="add">the commandments</char> with his own fingers. They were the words/commandments that he had spoken to your ancestors from the fire on that mountain, when they were gathered together <char style="add">at the bottom of the mountain</char>.<verse eid="DEU 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 9:11"/>“At the end of those 40 days and nights, Yahweh gave me those two stone tablets on which he had written those commandments. <verse eid="DEU 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 9:12"/>But then he said to me, ‘Go down the mountain immediately, because <char style="add">the people whom you are leading</char>, the people whom you led out of Egypt, have committed a terrible sin! They have very quickly done what I commanded them not to do. They have made for themselves a metal statue <char style="add">of a calf to worship</char>.’<verse eid="DEU 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 9:13"/>Then Yahweh said to me, ‘I have been watching these people, and I see that they are very stubborn. <verse eid="DEU 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 9:14"/>So do not try to stop me. I am going to destroy all of them, with the result that no one anywhere will remember ◄their names [MTY]/that they ever existed►. Then I will enable you to become <char style="add">the ancestor of</char> a nation that will be more numerous and more powerful than they are.’<verse eid="DEU 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 9:15"/>So I turned and went down the mountain, carrying in my hands the two stone tablets on which the Ten Commandments were <char style="add">written</char>. Fire was burning all over the mountain. <verse eid="DEU 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 9:16"/>I looked, and I was shocked to see that your ancestors had committed a <char style="add">great</char> sin against Yahweh. They very quickly had begun to do what Yahweh our God had commanded them not to do. They had <char style="add">requested Aaron to</char> make for them <char style="add">a metal image of</char> a calf <char style="add">to worship</char>. <verse eid="DEU 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 9:17"/>So while they were watching, I lifted up those two stone tablets and threw them <char style="add">on the ground</char>, and they broke into pieces.<verse eid="DEU 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 9:18"/>Then I ◄prostrated myself/lay► on the ground in Yahweh’s presence as I had done before, and I did not eat or drink anything for 40 days and nights. I did that because your ancestors had sinned against Yahweh and caused him to become very angry. <verse eid="DEU 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 9:19"/>I was afraid/worried that because Yahweh was very angry with them, he would get rid of all of them. <char style="add">But again I prayed that he would not do that</char>, and again he listened to me <char style="add">and answered my prayer</char>. <verse eid="DEU 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 9:20"/>Yahweh was also very angry with Aaron <char style="add">for making that golden calf</char> and was ready to kill Aaron. But at the same time I prayed for Aaron also, <char style="add">and Yahweh answered my prayer</char>. <verse eid="DEU 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 9:21"/>Your ancestors had sinned by <char style="add">requesting Aaron to</char> make <char style="add">a metal statue of</char> a calf. So I took that statue and <char style="add">I melted it</char> in a fire and crushed it and ground it into very tiny pieces [HYP]. Then I threw those tiny pieces into the stream that flowed down the mountain.<verse eid="DEU 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 9:22"/>Your ancestors also caused Yahweh to become very angry <char style="add">by what they did</char> at <char style="add">places which they named</char> Taberah, Massah, and Kibroth-Hattaavah.<verse eid="DEU 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 9:23"/>And when we were at Kadesh-Barnea, Yahweh said to your ancestors, ‘Go up and capture the land that I am about to give to you!’ But they rebelled against him. They did not trust him, and they did not obey what he told [MTY] them to do. <verse eid="DEU 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 9:24"/>Your ancestors rebelled against Yahweh from the first day that I knew them, <char style="add">in Egypt</char>.<verse eid="DEU 9:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 9:25"/>So, <char style="add">as I said</char>, I lay on the ground in Yahweh’s presence for 40 days and nights, because Yahweh had said that he would get rid of your ancestors. <verse eid="DEU 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 9:26"/>And I prayed to Yahweh, saying, ‘Lord God, these people belong to you; do not destroy them. They are people whom you rescued and brought out of Egypt by your very great power. [DOU, MTY] <verse eid="DEU 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 9:27"/>Do not forget <char style="add">what you promised to</char> Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Please ignore these stubborn and wicked people and the sin that they have committed. <verse eid="DEU 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 9:28"/>If you do not do that, <char style="add">and if you get rid of them</char>, the people of Egypt will <char style="add">hear about it and</char> say that you were not able to bring them into the land that you promised to give to them. They will say that you took them into the desert only to kill them there because you hated them. <verse eid="DEU 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 9:29"/><char style="add">Do not forget that</char> they are your people. <char style="add">You chose them to</char> belong to you. You brought them out <char style="add">from Egypt</char> by your very great power [DOU, MTY].’ ”<verse eid="DEU 9:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="DEU 10"/>
  <para style="s1">A new copy of the Ten Commandments</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 10:1"/>“Then Yahweh said to me, ‘Cut two stone tablets like the first ones. And make a wooden chest to put them in. Then <char style="add">bring the tablets</char> up to me on this mountain. <verse eid="DEU 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 10:2"/>I will write on those tablets the same words that I wrote on the first tablets, the ones that you broke. Then you can put them in the chest.’<verse eid="DEU 10:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 10:3"/>“So I made a chest. I used wood from an acacia tree to make it. Then I cut two tablets of stone like the first ones, and I went up the mountain carrying the tablets. <verse eid="DEU 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 10:4"/>There Yahweh wrote on the tablets the <char style="add">same</char> Ten Commandments <char style="add">that he had written on the first tablet</char>. They are the commandments that he told to your ancestors from the middle of the fire on the mountain, when they were gathered <char style="add">at the bottom of the mountain</char>. Then Yahweh gave the tablets to me, <verse eid="DEU 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 10:5"/>and I turned and went down the mountain. Then, just as he had commanded, I put them in the chest that I had made. And they are still there.”<verse eid="DEU 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 10:6"/>(Then, from the wells that belonged to the people of Jaakan, the Israeli people traveled to Moserah. There Aaron died and was buried, and his son Eleazar took his place and became the Supreme Priest. <verse eid="DEU 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 10:7"/>From there, the Israelis traveled to Gudgodah, and from there to Jotbathah, which was a place that had many streams. <verse eid="DEU 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 10:8"/>At that time, Yahweh ◄set apart/appointed► the tribe of Levi to carry the chest that contained <char style="add">the tablets on which were written</char> the Ten Commandments, and to stand in Yahweh’s presence <char style="add">in the sacred tent</char>, to offer sacrifices, and to pray for Yahweh to bless <char style="add">the people. They are still doing those things</char> at the present time. <verse eid="DEU 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 10:9"/>That is the reason that the tribe of Levi did not receive any land like the other tribes did. What they received was the work/privilege of being Yahweh’s <char style="add">priests</char>, which is what he said that they should do.)<verse eid="DEU 10:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 10:10"/>“I stayed on the mountain 40 days and nights, just like I did the first time. <char style="add">I prayed to</char> Yahweh, and he ◄answered my prayers/did what I requested► again and said that he would not destroy your ancestors. <verse eid="DEU 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 10:11"/>Then Yahweh said to me, ‘Continue your journey, going in front of the people, to occupy the land that I vowed your ancestors that I would give to you.’”<verse eid="DEU 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">What Yahweh required</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 10:12"/>“Now, you Israeli people, <char style="add">I will tell you</char> [RHQ] what Yahweh our God requires/demands that you do. He requires you to revere him, to conduct your lives as he wants you to, to love him, and to serve him wholeheartedly [DOU], <verse eid="DEU 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 10:13"/>and to obey all of his commandments [DOU] which I am giving to you today for your benefit.<verse eid="DEU 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 10:14"/>“Do not forget that Yahweh our God owns even the sky and everything that is in it. He also owns the earth and everything that is on it. <verse eid="DEU 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 10:15"/>But <char style="add">in spite of owning all those things</char>, Yahweh loved your ancestors, and from all the people-groups <char style="add">on the earth</char> he chose us, their descendants, and we are still his people. <verse eid="DEU 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 10:16"/>So you must stop sinning [MET] and stop being stubborn [IDM]! <verse eid="DEU 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 10:17"/>Yahweh our God is greater than all gods, and he is greater than all rulers. He is very powerful [DOU] and awesome. He ◄is impartial/does not do things that favor one ◄group/person► more than others►, and he does not accept bribes. <verse eid="DEU 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 10:18"/>He makes sure that orphans and widows are treated fairly. He loves even ◄foreigners/people from other countries► who live among us Israeli people, and he gives them food and clothes. <verse eid="DEU 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 10:19"/>So you must love those foreigners too, because you were once foreigners when you were living in Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 10:20"/>Revere Yahweh our God and worship only him. ◄Be faithful to/Have a close relationship with► him, and say that he should punish you if you do not do what you promise. <verse eid="DEU 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 10:21"/>He is the one whom you must praise. He is our God, and we have seen the great and amazing things that he has done for us. <verse eid="DEU 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 10:22"/>When our ancestors, <char style="add">Jacob and his family</char>, went down to Egypt, there were only seventy of them. But now Yahweh our God has caused us to be as numerous as the stars in the sky.”<verse eid="DEU 10:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="DEU 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses reminded them of the great things that God did</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 11:1"/>“<char style="add">Because of all that</char> Yahweh your God <char style="add">has done for you</char>, you must love him and continually obey all his rules and regulations and commandments. <verse eid="DEU 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 11:2"/>It was you and your ancestors, not your children, whom he disciplined <char style="add">by causing all of you to have/experience difficulties</char>. So, starting today, continue to think about how very great and very powerful he is [DOU, MTY]. <verse eid="DEU 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 11:3"/>Think about the various miracles [DOU] that he performed in Egypt. Think about what he did to the king of Egypt and to his country. <verse eid="DEU 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 11:4"/>Think about what he did to the army of Egypt, to their horses and their chariots. Think about how he caused the Red Sea to flood/cover over them while they were pursuing your ancestors, and how the army of Egypt was completely ◄wiped out/destroyed►. <verse eid="DEU 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 11:5"/>Think about what Yahweh did for your ancestors in the desert before you arrived at this place. <verse eid="DEU 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 11:6"/>Think about what he did to Dathan and Abiram, the two sons of Eliab from the tribe of Reuben. While all of your ancestors were watching, the earth split open, and they fell into the opening <char style="add">and disappeared</char>, along with their families and their tents, their servants, and their animals. <verse eid="DEU 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 11:7"/>You [SYN] and your ancestors have seen all these miracles that Yahweh performed.<verse eid="DEU 11:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 11:8"/>So, obey all the commandments that I am giving you today, in order that you will be strong and able to cross the river and occupy the land that you are about to enter, <verse eid="DEU 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 11:9"/>and in order that you will live for a long time in that land, the land that Yahweh solemnly promised your ancestors that he would give to them and to their descendants, a land that is very fertile [IDM]. <verse eid="DEU 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 11:10"/>The land that you are about to enter and occupy is not like the land of Egypt, where your ancestors lived. In Egypt, after they planted seeds, it was necessary for them to work hard [MTY] to water <char style="add">the plants that grew</char>. <verse eid="DEU 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 11:11"/>But the land that you are about to enter is a land where there are many hills and valleys, where there is plenty of rain. <verse eid="DEU 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 11:12"/>Yahweh takes care of that land. He [SYN] watches over it every day, from the beginning of each year to the end of each year.<verse eid="DEU 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 11:13"/>Today I am commanding you to love Yahweh our God and to serve him with your entire inner beings. If you do that, <verse eid="DEU 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 11:14"/>each year he will send rain on your land at the ◄right times/times when it is needed►, ◄in the autumn/at the end of the dry season► and ◄in the spring/before the next dry season starts►. As a result, you will have grain and <char style="add">grapes to make</char> wine and <char style="add">olives to make olive</char> oil. <verse eid="DEU 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 11:15"/>And he will cause grass to grow in your fields for your livestock <char style="add">to eat</char>. You will have all the food that you want.<verse eid="DEU 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 11:16"/>“But I warn you, do not turn away from Yahweh our God and start to worship other gods, <verse eid="DEU 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 11:17"/>because if you do that, Yahweh will become very angry with you. He will prevent any rain from falling. As a result, the crops will not grow, and you will soon die <char style="add">from hunger</char> in the good land that Yahweh is about to give to you. <verse eid="DEU 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 11:18"/>So, keep thinking [IDM] about these commands. Write them <char style="add">on tiny scrolls</char> and fasten them to your arms/wrists, and write them on bands that you fasten to your foreheads <char style="add">to help you to remember them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 11:19"/>Teach them to your children again and again. Talk about them <char style="add">all the time</char>: When you are in your houses and when you are walking outside; talk about them when you are lying down at night and when you are getting up in the morning. <verse eid="DEU 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 11:20"/>Write them on the doorposts and on the gates of your houses. <verse eid="DEU 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 11:21"/>Do that in order that you and your children will live for a long time in the land that Yahweh promised to our ancestors that he would give to them. That land will belong to you <char style="add">and your descendants</char> as long as there is a sky above the earth.<verse eid="DEU 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 11:22"/>“Faithfully continue to obey what I am commanding you to do—to love Yahweh our God, and to conduct your lives as he wants you to do, and to ◄be faithful to/have a close relationship with► him. <verse eid="DEU 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 11:23"/>If you do that, Yahweh will expel all the people-groups in that land as you advance, people-groups that are more numerous and more powerful than you are. <verse eid="DEU 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 11:24"/>All the ground <char style="add">in that land</char> on which you walk will be yours. Your territory will extend from the desert <char style="add">in the south</char> to the Lebanon <char style="add">Mountains in the north</char>, and from the Euphrates River <char style="add">in the east</char> to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea in the west. <verse eid="DEU 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 11:25"/>Yahweh our God will cause all the people in that land to be afraid of you, which is what he promised, with the result that no people-group will be able to stop you.<verse eid="DEU 11:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 11:26"/>“Listen carefully: Today I am telling you <char style="add">that Yahweh will either</char> bless <char style="add">you or he will</char> curse you. <verse eid="DEU 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 11:27"/>If you obey the commandments of Yahweh our God that I am giving to you today, he will bless you. <verse eid="DEU 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 11:28"/>If you do not obey them, and if you turn away from him to worship other gods that you have never known about before, he will curse you. <verse eid="DEU 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 11:29"/>And when Yahweh brings you into the land that you are about to enter and occupy, <char style="add">some of you must stand on top of</char> Gerizim Mountain and proclaim what will cause Yahweh to bless you, and <char style="add">the others must stand on top of</char> Ebal Mountain and proclaim <char style="add">what will cause Yahweh to</char> curse you.” <verse eid="DEU 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 11:30"/>(Those two mountains are [RHQ] west of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, west of the Jordan Valley near the huge oak tree at Moreh <char style="add">village</char> in the land where the Canaan people-group lives. They live close to the sacred trees near Gilgal.) <verse eid="DEU 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 11:31"/>“You will soon cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to occupy the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you. When you enter that land and start to live there, <verse eid="DEU 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 11:32"/>be sure to obey all the rules and regulations that I am giving to you today.”<verse eid="DEU 11:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="DEU 12"/>
  <para style="s1">The one place for worship</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 12:1"/>“◄I will now tell you again/These, <char style="add">again</char>, are► the rules and regulations that you must faithfully obey in the land that Yahweh, the God whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, is giving to you to occupy. You must obey these laws all the time that you are alive. <verse eid="DEU 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 12:2"/>You must destroy all the places where the people-groups that you will expel worship their gods, on the tops of mountains and hills and under big green trees. <verse eid="DEU 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 12:3"/>You must tear down their altars and smash their sacred pillars. Completely burn the statues of their goddess Asherah in fires, and chop down their wooden idols, in order that no one will ever worship them [MTY] in those places again.<verse eid="DEU 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 12:4"/>“Do not worship Yahweh like <char style="add">the people in Canaan worship their gods</char>. <verse eid="DEU 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 12:5"/>Instead, you must go to the place that Yahweh will choose. It will be in the area where one of your tribes will live. That is where you must go to worship Yahweh. <verse eid="DEU 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 12:6"/>That is the place where you must bring your sacrifices that will be completely burned on the altar, and your other sacrifices, ◄your tithes/ten percent of all of your crops►, other offerings that you decide to give, and the firstborn animals from your cattle and sheep. <verse eid="DEU 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 12:7"/>There, in the presence of Yahweh our God, who has <char style="add">greatly</char> blessed you, you and your families will eat the good things that you have worked to produce, and you will be happy.<verse eid="DEU 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 12:8"/>“<char style="add">When you are in that land</char>, you must not do some of the things that we have been doing. Until now, you have all been worshiping <char style="add">Yahweh</char> the way you wanted to, <verse eid="DEU 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 12:9"/>because you have not yet arrived in the land which Yahweh is giving to you, where you will be able to live peacefully. <verse eid="DEU 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 12:10"/>But when you cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, you will start to live in the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you. He will protect you from all your enemies that will surround you, and you will live peacefully/safely.<verse eid="DEU 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 12:11"/>“Yahweh will choose one place where he wants you to worship him. That is the place to which you must bring all the offerings that I command you to bring: The sacrifices that must be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, your other sacrifices, other offerings that you yourselves decide to give, ◄your tithes/ten percent of all your crops►, and all the special offerings that you will solemnly promise to give to Yahweh. <verse eid="DEU 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 12:12"/>Rejoice there in the presence of Yahweh, along with your children, your male and female servants, and the descendants of Levi who live in your towns. Do not forget that the descendants of Levi will not have their own land, like you will have. <verse eid="DEU 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 12:13"/>Be sure that you do not offer sacrifices anywhere you want to. <verse eid="DEU 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 12:14"/>You must offer them only in the place that Yahweh will choose for you, in an area that belongs to one of your tribes. That is the only place where he wants you to offer sacrifices that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and to do the other things that I am commanding you to do <char style="add">when you worship him</char>.<verse eid="DEU 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 12:15"/>“However, you will be permitted to kill and eat the meat of your animals in the places where you live. As often as you want to, you may eat the meat of the animals that Yahweh our God will bless you by giving them to you. Those who have done things that cause them to become unacceptable to God and those who have not done things like that may all eat that meat, just like you would eat the meat of a deer or an antelope. <verse eid="DEU 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 12:16"/>But you must not eat the blood <char style="add">of any animals</char>; you must let the blood drain onto the ground <char style="add">before you cook the meat</char>. <verse eid="DEU 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 12:17"/>In the places where you live, you must not eat the things that you are offering <char style="add">to Yahweh</char>: You must not eat the ◄tithes/ten percent► of your grain or of your wine, or of your <char style="add">olive</char> oil, or the firstborn of your cattle and sheep, or the offerings that you yourselves decide to give to Yahweh, or any other offerings. <verse eid="DEU 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 12:18"/>Instead, you and your children and your male and female servants and the descendants of Levi who live in your towns must go to the place that he has chosen and eat those things there in the presence of Yahweh. And you should rejoice in the presence of Yahweh about everything that you do. <verse eid="DEU 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 12:19"/>Be sure that you take care of the descendants of Levi all during the time that you live in your land.<verse eid="DEU 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 12:20"/>“When Yahweh our God gives you much more land <char style="add">than you will have when you first occupy it</char>, which is what he has promised to do, and you say ‘I would like some meat to eat’ because you are craving/wanting some meat, you will be permitted to eat meat whenever you want to. <verse eid="DEU 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 12:21"/>If the place that Yahweh our God chooses to be the place for you to worship him is far <char style="add">from where you live</char>, you are permitted to kill some of your cattle or sheep that Yahweh has given to you, and you may eat that meat at the places where you live, just like I have told you to do. <verse eid="DEU 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 12:22"/>Those who have done things that cause them to become unacceptable to God, and those who have not done things like that, are all permitted to all eat that meat, just like you would eat the meat of a deer or an antelope. <verse eid="DEU 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 12:23"/>But be sure that you do not eat the blood <char style="add">of any animal</char>, because it is the blood that sustains life in living beings, and so you must not eat the life along with the meat. <verse eid="DEU 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 12:24"/>Do not eat the blood; instead, let it drain onto the ground. <verse eid="DEU 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 12:25"/>If you obey this command and do what Yahweh says is right <char style="add">for you to do</char>, things will go well for you and for your descendants.<verse eid="DEU 12:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 12:26"/>“But the sacred offerings that Yahweh has told you to give and the other offerings that you yourselves decide to give, you must take to the place that Yahweh will choose. <verse eid="DEU 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 12:27"/>You must offer there the sacrifices that will be completely burned <char style="add">on Yahweh’s altar</char>. You must also offer there the sacrifices from which you may eat some of meat after you <char style="add">kill the animals and</char> drain out the blood and some of it is thrown on the <char style="add">sides of the</char> altar. <verse eid="DEU 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 12:28"/>Faithfully obey all these things that I have commanded you. If you do that, things will go well forever for you and your descendants, because you will be doing what Yahweh our God says is right <char style="add">for you to do</char> and what pleases him.<verse eid="DEU 12:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 12:29"/>“When you enter the land that you will occupy, as you advance, Yahweh our God will get rid of the people-groups that live there. <verse eid="DEU 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 12:30"/>After he does that, be sure that you do not <char style="add">worship the gods</char> that they have been worshiping, because if you do that, you will be caught in the same trap <char style="add">that they were caught in</char> [MET]. Do not ask anyone about those gods, saying, ‘Tell me how they worshiped their gods, in order that I can <char style="add">worship them</char> also.’ <verse eid="DEU 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 12:31"/>Do not try to worship Yahweh our God like they have worshiped their gods, because when they worship them, they do disgusting things, things that Yahweh hates. <char style="add">The worst thing that they do is</char> that they sacrifice their own children and burn them <char style="add">on their altars</char>.<verse eid="DEU 12:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 12:32"/>“Be sure to do everything that I have commanded you to do. Do not add anything to these commands, and do not take anything away from them.”<verse eid="DEU 12:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="DEU 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses warned them against idolatry</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 13:1"/>“Possibly there will be people among you who <char style="add">say that they</char> are prophets. They may say that they are able to interpret the meaning of dreams or perform various kinds of miracles [DOU]. <verse eid="DEU 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 13:2"/>They will say those things in order to induce/persuade you to worship gods that you have never known about before. But even if what they predict happens, <verse eid="DEU 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 13:3"/>do not pay attention to what they say. Yahweh our God will be testing you to find out if you love him with all your inner being. <verse eid="DEU 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 13:4"/>You must conduct your lives as Yahweh our God wants you to, and you must revere him, and do what he tells you to do [MTY], and worship only him, and ◄be faithful to/have a close relationship with► him.<verse eid="DEU 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 13:5"/>“But you must execute anyone who <char style="add">falsely says that he</char> is a prophet, or someone who <char style="add">falsely</char> says that he can interpret dreams, or who tells you to rebel against Yahweh our God, who rescued your ancestors from being slaves in Egypt. People like that are only wanting to cause you to stop conducting your lives as Yahweh has commanded you to do. Execute them, to get rid of this evil among you. <verse eid="DEU 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 13:6"/>It does not matter if even your brother or your daughter or your wife or some close/dear friend secretly urges you, saying ‘Let’s worship other gods. They are gods which you or your ancestors have never known about. <verse eid="DEU 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 13:7"/>Some of them may encourage you to worship gods that people-groups that live near you worship, or gods that groups who live far away worship. <verse eid="DEU 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 13:8"/>Do not [SYN] do what they suggest. Do not even listen to them. Do not even be merciful to them, and do not keep secret what they have done. <verse eid="DEU 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 13:9"/>Execute them! You <char style="add">who are their relative</char> must be the first one to <char style="add">throw stones at them to</char> kill them, and then let everyone else [MTY] throw stones at them, too. <verse eid="DEU 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 13:10"/>Kill such people by throwing stones at them, because they are trying to cause you to stop worshiping Yahweh our God, who rescued your ancestors from being slaves in Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 13:11"/>When they are executed, all the Israeli people will hear <char style="add">what happened</char>, and they will become afraid, and none of them will do such an evil thing again.<verse eid="DEU 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 13:12"/>“When you are living in one of the towns in the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you, you may hear <verse eid="DEU 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 13:13"/>that some worthless people there among you [IDM] are deceiving the people of their town, saying, ‘Let’s go and worship other gods,’ but they are gods that you have never heard about before. <verse eid="DEU 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 13:14"/>Investigate it thoroughly/carefully. If <char style="add">you find out that</char> it is true that such a disgraceful thing has happened, <verse eid="DEU 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 13:15"/>kill all the people in that town. And kill all their livestock, too. Destroy the town completely. <verse eid="DEU 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 13:16"/>Gather all the possessions that belonged to the people who lived there and pile them up in the city plaza. Then burn the town and everything in it, as though it were an offering to Yahweh that would be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. The ruins/ashes must stay there forever; the town must never be rebuilt. <verse eid="DEU 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 13:17"/>None of you Israelis must take for yourselves [IDM] anything that Yahweh has said must be destroyed. But if you do what I say, Yahweh will stop being angry with you, and he will act mercifully toward you. And he will cause you to have many children/descendants, which is what he promised our ancestors that he would do. <verse eid="DEU 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 13:18"/>Yahweh our God will do all those things if you do what he is telling you to do, and if you obey all the commandments that I am giving to you today and do what Yahweh says is right <char style="add">for you to do</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 13:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="DEU 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Creatures that were forbidden to be eaten</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 14:1"/>“We are people who belong to Yahweh our God. So, when people die, do not show that you are grieving by gashing/cutting yourselves or by shaving the hair on your foreheads <char style="add">like the other people-groups do</char>. <verse eid="DEU 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 14:2"/>We belong to Yahweh alone. Yahweh chose us from all the other people-groups on the earth to be his special people.<verse eid="DEU 14:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 14:3"/>“Do not eat anything that <char style="add">Yahweh</char> detests. <verse eid="DEU 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 14:4"/>The animals <char style="add">whose meat</char> you are permitted to eat are cattle, sheep, goats, <verse eid="DEU 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 14:5"/>deer, gazelles, wild goats, antelopes, and mountain sheep. <verse eid="DEU 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 14:6"/>Those are animals that have split hoofs and that also ◄chew their cuds/regurgitate their food <char style="add">from their stomachs</char> to chew it again►. <verse eid="DEU 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 14:7"/>But there are other animals that chew their cuds that you must not eat. Those are camels, rabbits, and rock badgers. They chew their cuds, but their hooves are not split. So they are not acceptable for you to eat. <verse eid="DEU 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 14:8"/>Do not eat pigs. They are unacceptable for you to eat; their hooves are split, but they do not chew cud. Do not eat the meat of those animals; do not even touch their dead bodies. <verse eid="DEU 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 14:9"/>You are permitted to eat any fish that has scales and fins. <verse eid="DEU 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 14:10"/>But anything else <char style="add">that lives in the water</char> that does not have scales and fins, you must not eat, because <char style="add">if you eat them</char>, you will become unacceptable <char style="add">to Yahweh</char>.<verse eid="DEU 14:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 14:11"/>“You are permitted to eat the flesh of any bird that is acceptable <char style="add">to Yahweh</char>. <verse eid="DEU 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 14:12"/>But eagles, vultures, black vultures, <verse eid="DEU 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 14:13"/>buzzards, all kinds of kites, <verse eid="DEU 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 14:14"/>all kinds of crows, <verse eid="DEU 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 14:15"/>ostriches, seagulls, <verse eid="DEU 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 14:16"/>owls, hawks, falcons, <verse eid="DEU 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 14:17"/>pelicans, vultures that eat dead animals, cormorants, <verse eid="DEU 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 14:18"/>storks, herons, hoopoes, and bats, you must not eat.<verse eid="DEU 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 14:19"/>“All insects with wings <char style="add">and which walk on the ground</char> are unacceptable <char style="add">to Yahweh</char>; do not eat them. <verse eid="DEU 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 14:20"/>But other insects with wings <char style="add">and which hop along the ground</char> are acceptable to eat.<verse eid="DEU 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 14:21"/>“Do not eat any animal that has died naturally, <char style="add">because its blood has not been drained out</char>. You may allow foreigners who live among you to eat those things or you may sell them to other foreigners. But you belong to Yahweh our God; <char style="add">and those who belong to him are not permitted to eat the meat of animals whose blood has not been drained out</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="DEU 14:21">“You must not cook a young sheep or goat in its mother’s milk.”<verse eid="DEU 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Giving tithes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 14:22"/>“Once each year you must set apart ◄a tithe/10 percent► of all the crops that are produced/harvested in your fields. <verse eid="DEU 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 14:23"/>Take those things to the place that Yahweh our God will choose <char style="add">for you to worship him</char>. There eat the tithes of your grain, your wine, your <char style="add">olive</char> oil, and the meat of the firstborn male animals of your cattle and your sheep. Do this in order that you may learn to always revere Yahweh, <char style="add">the one who has blessed you by giving you these things</char>. <verse eid="DEU 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 14:24"/>If the place that Yahweh has chosen <char style="add">for you to worship him</char> is very far from your home, with the result that you are not able to take there the tithes <char style="add">of your crops</char> with which Yahweh has blessed you, do this: <verse eid="DEU 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 14:25"/>Sell [IDM] the tithes of your crops, wrap the money carefully <char style="add">in a cloth</char>, and take it with you to the place of worship that Yahweh has chosen. <verse eid="DEU 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 14:26"/>There, <char style="add">with that money</char>, you may buy whatever you want to—beef or lamb or wine or fermented drinks. And there, in the presence of Yahweh, you and your families should eat <char style="add">and drink</char> those things and be happy. <verse eid="DEU 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 14:27"/>But be sure to not neglect/forget <char style="add">to help</char> the descendants of Levi who live in your towns, because they will not own any land.<verse eid="DEU 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 14:28"/>“At the end of every three years, bring a tithe of all your crops that have been produced/harvested in that year and store it in your towns. <verse eid="DEU 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 14:29"/>That food is for the descendants of Levi, because they do not have their own land, and for foreigners <char style="add">who live among you</char>, and for orphans and widows who live in your towns. They are permitted to come <char style="add">to where the food is stored</char> and take what they need. Do that in order that Yahweh our God will bless you in everything that you do.”<verse eid="DEU 14:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="DEU 15"/>
  <para style="s1">The year for canceling debts</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 15:1"/>“At the end of every seven years, you must ◄cancel all debts/tell people who owe you money that they do not need to pay it back►. <verse eid="DEU 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 15:2"/>Do it like this: Each of you who has lent money to a fellow Israeli must cancel that debt. You must not insist that he pay it back. You must do that because Yahweh has declared that the debts must be canceled <char style="add">every seven years</char>. <verse eid="DEU 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 15:3"/><char style="add">During that year</char> you may require foreigners <char style="add">who live among you</char> to pay what they owe you, but you must not try to require that any fellow Israeli pay you what he owes you. <verse eid="DEU 15:3"/><verse number="4-5" style="v" sid="DEU 15:4-5"/>Yahweh our God will bless you in the land that he is giving to you. If you obey Yahweh our God and obey all the commandments that I am giving to you today, there will not be any poor people among you. <verse eid="DEU 15:4-5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 15:6"/>Yahweh our God will bless you like he has promised to do, and you will <char style="add">be able to</char> lend money to people of other people-groups, but you will not <char style="add">need to</char> borrow from any of them. You will control <char style="add">the finances of</char> many people-groups, but they will not control your <char style="add">finances</char>.<verse eid="DEU 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 15:7"/>“In the towns that Yahweh our God is giving to you, if there are any Israelis who are poor, do not be selfish [IDM] and refuse [IDM] to help them. <verse eid="DEU 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 15:8"/>Instead, be generous [IDM] and lend to them the money that they need. <verse eid="DEU 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 15:9"/>Be sure that you do not say to yourself, ‘The year when debts will be canceled is near, <char style="add">so I do not want to lend anyone any money now, because he will not need to pay it back when that year comes</char>.’ It would be evil to even think that. If you act in an unfriendly way toward a needy fellow Israeli, and give him nothing, he will cry out to Yahweh about you, and <char style="add">Yahweh will say that</char> you have sinned <char style="add">by not helping that person</char>. <verse eid="DEU 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 15:10"/>Give freely to poor people and give generously [IDM]. <verse eid="DEU 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 15:11"/>If you do that, Yahweh will bless you in everything that you do. There will always be some poor people in your land, so I command you to give generously to poor [DOU] people.”<verse eid="DEU 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Freeing slaves</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 15:12"/>“If any of your fellow Israeli men or women sell themselves to one of you <char style="add">to become your slave</char>, you must free them after they have worked for you for six years. When the seventh year comes, you must free them. <verse eid="DEU 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 15:13"/>When you free them, do not allow them to go ◄empty-handed/without giving them anything►. <verse eid="DEU 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 15:14"/>Give to them generously from the things with which Yahweh has blessed you—sheep, grain, and wine. <verse eid="DEU 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 15:15"/>Do not forget that your ancestors were once slaves in Egypt, and Yahweh our God freed them. That is the reason that I am now commanding you to do this.<verse eid="DEU 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 15:16"/>“But one of your slaves may say, ‘I do not want to leave you.’ He loves you and your family, because you have treated him well. <verse eid="DEU 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 15:17"/>If he says that, take him to the door of your house and, <char style="add">while he stands against the doorway</char>, pierce one of his earlobes with ◄an awl/a sharp pointed tool►. That will indicate that he will be your slave for the rest of his life. Do the same thing to any female slave <char style="add">who does not want to leave you</char>.<verse eid="DEU 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 15:18"/>“Do not complain when you are required to free your slaves. <char style="add">Keep in mind that</char> they served you for six years, and you paid them only half as much as you pay the servants that you hire. <char style="add">If you free them,</char> Yahweh our God will bless you in everything that you do.”<verse eid="DEU 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Rules about sacrificing firstborn animals</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 15:19"/>“◄Set aside for/Dedicate to► Yahweh our God the firstborn male animals from your cattle and sheep. Do not force them to do any work for you, and do not ◄shear/cut off► the wool <char style="add">of the firstborn animals to sell the wool</char>. <verse eid="DEU 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 15:20"/>You and your family may <char style="add">kill them and</char> eat their meat in the presence of Yahweh at the place that Yahweh chooses <char style="add">for you to worship him</char>. <verse eid="DEU 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 15:21"/>But if the animals have any defects, if they are lame or blind, or if they have any other serious defect, you must not sacrifice them to Yahweh our God. <verse eid="DEU 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 15:22"/>You may <char style="add">kill and</char> eat <char style="add">the meat of those animals</char> at your homes. Those who have done things that cause them to become unacceptable to God and those who have not done such things are permitted to eat that meat, just like anyone is permitted to eat the meat of a deer or an antelope. <verse eid="DEU 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 15:23"/>But you must not eat any of the blood; you must drain all the blood on the ground <char style="add">when you kill those animals</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 15:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="DEU 16"/>
  <para style="s1">The Passover Festival</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 16:1"/>“<char style="add">Each year</char> honor Yahweh our God by celebrating the Passover <char style="add">Festival</char> in the month of Abib <char style="add">in early spring</char>. It was on a night in that month that Yahweh rescued your ancestors from Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 16:2"/><char style="add">In order to celebrate that festival</char>, go to the place that Yahweh will choose <char style="add">for you to worship him</char>, and offer <char style="add">there one young animal</char> from your cattle or your sheep to be the Passover sacrifice, to honor Yahweh [MTY]. <verse eid="DEU 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 16:3"/><char style="add">When you eat the Passover meal</char>, the bread that you eat must not have yeast in it. You must eat this kind of bread, which will be called the bread of suffering/misery, for seven days. This is to help you to remember all during the time that you are alive that when your ancestors left Egypt, <char style="add">where they were suffering because they were slaves</char>, they left very quickly. <char style="add">They did not put in yeast and wait for the dough to swell up</char>. <verse eid="DEU 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 16:4"/><char style="add">During that festival</char>, you must not have any yeast in any house in your land for seven days. Furthermore, the meat <char style="add">of the animals</char> that you sacrifice on the evening of the first day <char style="add">of the Passover Festival must be eaten during that night</char>; do not allow any of it to remain until the next day.<verse eid="DEU 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5-6" style="v" sid="DEU 16:5-6"/>“To honor Yahweh our God, you must offer the Passover sacrifice only at the place that he chooses for you <char style="add">to worship him</char>; do not offer that sacrifice in any other town in the land that Yahweh is giving to you. Offer that sacrifice when the sun is setting, at the same time of day that your ancestors <char style="add">started to</char> leave Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 16:5-6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 16:7"/>Boil <char style="add">the meat</char> and eat it at the place <char style="add">of worship</char> that Yahweh our God chooses. The next morning, you may return to your tents. <verse eid="DEU 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 16:8"/>Each day for six days the bread that you eat must have no yeast in it. On the seventh day, you must all gather to worship Yahweh our God. <char style="add">It will be a day of rest</char>; you must not do any work on that day.”<verse eid="DEU 16:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The festival for harvesting grain</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 16:9"/>“<char style="add">Each year</char>, from the day that you start to harvest your grain, count seven weeks. <verse eid="DEU 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 16:10"/>Then, to honor Yahweh our God, celebrate the Harvest Festival. Do that by bringing to him an offering <char style="add">of grain</char>. Yahweh has blessed you <char style="add">by causing it to grow in your fields during that year</char>. If you had a big harvest, bring a big offering. If you had a small harvest, bring a small offering. <verse eid="DEU 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 16:11"/><char style="add">Each married couple</char> should be joyful in the presence of Yahweh. Their children, their servants, the descendants of Levi <char style="add">who are in that town</char>, and the foreigners, orphans, and widows <char style="add">who are living among you</char>, should also be joyful. Bring those offerings to the place of worship that Yahweh will choose.<verse eid="DEU 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 16:12"/>
    <char style="add">“When you celebrate these festivals</char> by obeying these commands, remember that your ancestors were previously slaves in Egypt.”<verse eid="DEU 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festival of Living in Shelters</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 16:13"/>“<char style="add">Each year</char>, after you have threshed all your grain and pressed <char style="add">the juice from</char> all your grapes, you must celebrate the Festival of <char style="add">Living in Temporary</char> Shelters for seven days. <verse eid="DEU 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 16:14"/><char style="add">Each married couple</char> along with their children, their servants, the descendants of Levi <char style="add">who are in that town</char>, and the foreigners, orphans, and widows <char style="add">who are living among you</char>, should be joyful in the presence of Yahweh. <verse eid="DEU 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 16:15"/>Honor Yahweh our God by celebrating this festival for seven days in the place that Yahweh chooses <char style="add">for you to worship him</char>. You should all be joyful, because Yahweh will have blessed your harvest and all the other work that you have done.<verse eid="DEU 16:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 16:16"/>“So, each year all of you Israeli men must gather <char style="add">with your families</char> to worship Yahweh our God at the place that he will choose, <char style="add">to celebrate three festivals</char>: The Passover Festival, the Harvest Festival, and the Festival of Living in Temporary Shelters. Each of you men must bring [LIT] an offering <char style="add">for Yahweh to these festivals</char> <verse eid="DEU 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 16:17"/>in proportion to the blessings that Yahweh has given you <char style="add">during that year</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Judging people fairly</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 16:18"/>“Appoint judges and other officials throughout your tribes, in all the towns <char style="add">in the land</char> that Yahweh our God is giving to you. They must judge people fairly/justly. <verse eid="DEU 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 16:19"/>They must not judge unjustly. They must not favor one person more than another. The judges must not accept bribes, because if a judge accepts a bribe, even if he is wise and honest, it will be very difficult for him to judge fairly [IDM]; <char style="add">he will do what the person who gave him the bribe wants him to do and declare that</char> the righteous/innocent people <char style="add">must be punished</char>. <verse eid="DEU 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 16:20"/>You must be completely fair and just [DOU], in order that you will enter and occupy the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you.”<verse eid="DEU 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Warning against worshiping other gods</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 16:21"/>“When you make an altar to worship Yahweh our God, do not put next to it any wooden statue <char style="add">that represents</char> the goddess Asherah. <verse eid="DEU 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 16:22"/>And do not set up any <char style="add">stone</char> pillar <char style="add">to worship any idol, because</char> Yahweh hates them.”<verse eid="DEU 16:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="DEU 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Warning against sacrificing defective animals</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 17:1"/>“Do not sacrifice to Yahweh our God any cattle or sheep or goats that have any defects, because Yahweh hates that kind of gift.”<verse eid="DEU 17:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Punishment for idolatry</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 17:2"/>“When you are living in any of the towns <char style="add">in the land</char> that Yahweh our God is giving to you, suppose you hear that there is some man or woman who sins by disobeying the agreement that Yahweh has made with you. <verse eid="DEU 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 17:3"/>Suppose someone tells you that that person has worshiped and served other gods, or the sun, or the moon, or the stars. <verse eid="DEU 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 17:4"/>If you hear that some person has been doing that, you must investigate it thoroughly. If <char style="add">you find out that</char> it is true that this detestable thing has happened in Israel, <verse eid="DEU 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 17:5"/>you must take outside the town the man or woman who has done it. Then you must kill that person by throwing stones at him or her. <verse eid="DEU 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 17:6"/>But you are allowed to execute such people only if at least two witnesses testify that they saw them <char style="add">doing that</char>. They must not be executed if there is only one witness. <verse eid="DEU 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 17:7"/>The ◄witnesses/ones who saw them doing it► must be the first ones to throw stones at them. Then the other people [MTY] <char style="add">should throw stones at them</char>. By doing that, you will get rid of this evil practice among you.”<verse eid="DEU 17:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Judging difficult cases</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 17:8"/>“Sometimes it will be very difficult for a judge to decide what really happened. He might be trying to decide whether, when someone injured or killed another person, he did it accidentally or deliberately. Or he might be trying to decide if some person is suing another person unfairly. If in some town it is very difficult to know what really happened, with the result that the judge cannot decide it, you should go to the place that Yahweh our God has chosen for you <char style="add">to worship him</char>. <verse eid="DEU 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 17:9"/>There you should present the case to the descendants of Levi who are the priests, and to the judge who is serving at that time, and they should decide what should be done. <verse eid="DEU 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 17:10"/>After they make their decision, you must do what they tell you to do. <verse eid="DEU 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 17:11"/>Accept what they have decided, and do what they say that you should do. Do not try to change in any way what they have decided [IDM]. <verse eid="DEU 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 17:12"/>You must execute anyone who proudly/arrogantly disobeys the judge or the priest who stands there in the presence of Yahweh <char style="add">and decides what should be done</char>. By doing that, you will get rid of evil practices among you. <verse eid="DEU 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 17:13"/>Then <char style="add">after that person is executed</char>, all the people will hear about it, and they will be afraid, and none of them will act that way any more.”<verse eid="DEU 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Proper behavior for a king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 17:14"/>“<char style="add">I know that</char> after you have occupied the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you, and you are living there, you will say, ‘We should have a king to rule over us, like the kings that other nations around us have.’ <verse eid="DEU 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 17:15"/>Yahweh our God will permit you to have a king, but be sure that you appoint someone whom he has chosen. That man must be an Israeli; you must not appoint someone who is a foreigner to be your king. <verse eid="DEU 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 17:16"/><char style="add">After he becomes the king</char>, he should not acquire a large number of horses for himself. He should not send people to Egypt to buy horses for him, because Yahweh said to you, ‘Never return to Egypt <char style="add">for anything’</char>! <verse eid="DEU 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 17:17"/>And he must not have a lot of wives, because if he did that, they would turn him [SYN] away from <char style="add">worshiping only</char> Yahweh. And he must not acquire a lot of silver and gold.<verse eid="DEU 17:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 17:18"/>“When he becomes your king, he must <char style="add">appoint someone to</char> copy these laws. He must copy them from the scroll that is kept by the priests who are descended from Levi. <verse eid="DEU 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 17:19"/>He must keep this new scroll near him and read from it every day of his life, in order that he may learn to revere Yahweh, and to faithfully obey [DOU] all the rules and regulations <char style="add">that are written</char> in these laws. <verse eid="DEU 17:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 17:20"/>If he does that, he [SYN] will not think that he is ◄better/more important► than [IDM] his fellow Israelis, and he will completely obey [LIT] Yahweh’s commands. As a result, he and his descendants will rule as kings in Israel for many years.”<verse eid="DEU 17:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="DEU 18"/>
  <para style="s1">What the priests were to receive</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 18:1"/>“The priests, who are all from the tribe of Levi, will not receive any land in Israel. Instead, they will receive some of the food that other people offer to be burned <char style="add">on the altar to be sacrificed</char> to Yahweh and some of the other sacrifices that will be offered to Yahweh. <verse eid="DEU 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 18:2"/>They will not be allotted any land like the other tribes will be. What they will receive is the work/privilege of being Yahweh’s <char style="add">priests</char>, which is what he said that they should have.<verse eid="DEU 18:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 18:3"/>“When the people bring an ox or a sheep to be sacrificed, they must give to the priests the shoulder, the cheeks/jaws, and the stomach of those animals. <verse eid="DEU 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 18:4"/>You must also give to them the first part of the grain that you <char style="add">harvest</char>, and the first part of the wine <char style="add">that you make</char>, and the first part of the <char style="add">olive</char> oil <char style="add">that you make</char>, and the first part of the wool that you shear from your sheep. <verse eid="DEU 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 18:5"/>You must do this because Yahweh our God has chosen the tribe of Levi from all of your tribes, in order that men <char style="add">from that tribe</char> would always be the priests who would serve him.<verse eid="DEU 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 18:6"/>“If any man from the tribe of Levi <char style="add">who has been living</char> in one of the towns in Israel wants to come from there to the place of worship that Yahweh has chosen, <char style="add">and start living there</char>, <verse eid="DEU 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 18:7"/>he is permitted to serve Yahweh there as a priest, just like the other men from the tribe of Levi who have been serving there. <verse eid="DEU 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 18:8"/>He must be given the same amount of food <char style="add">that the other priests receive</char>. He is permitted to keep the money <char style="add">that his relatives give him</char> for selling some of their possessions.<verse eid="DEU 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A warning about pagan practices</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 18:9"/>When you enter the land that Yahweh our God is giving you, you must not imitate the disgusting things that the people-groups who are there now do. <verse eid="DEU 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 18:10"/>You must not sacrifice any of your children by burning them <char style="add">on your altars</char>. Do not practice ◄divination/using supernatural power to reveal <char style="add">what will happen in</char> the future►. Do not do/practice ◄soothsaying/magic to find out what will happen in the future►. Do not ◄interpret omens/say that because of something that you have seen you know what will happen►. Do not practice sorcery/witchcraft. Do not practice ◄putting spells on people/saying things to cause bad things to happen to others►. <verse eid="DEU 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 18:11"/>Do not try to talk with spirits of dead people. Do not do/practice magic. <verse eid="DEU 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 18:12"/>Yahweh hates people who do any of those disgusting things. And as you advance through that land, he is going to expel the people-groups because they do/practice those disgusting things. <verse eid="DEU 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 18:13"/>But you must always avoid doing any of those things.<verse eid="DEU 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The promise to send a prophet like Moses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 18:14"/>The people-groups that you are about to expel <char style="add">from the land that you will occupy</char> ◄consult/seek advice from► soothsayers and those who practice divination. But as for you, Yahweh our God does not allow you to do that. <verse eid="DEU 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 18:15"/><char style="add">Some day</char> he will send from among you a prophet like me. <char style="add">He is the one who will tell you what will happen in the future</char>, and he is the one whom you must heed. <verse eid="DEU 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 18:16"/>On the day that your ancestors were gathered at the bottom of Sinai Mountain, they pleaded with me saying, ‘We do not want Yahweh to speak [MTY] to us again, and we do not want to see this huge fire <char style="add">that is burning on the mountain</char>!’ <char style="add">Your ancestors said that because they were afraid</char> that they would die <char style="add">if Yahweh spoke to them again</char>.<verse eid="DEU 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 18:17"/>Then Yahweh said to me, ‘What they have said is true/wise. <verse eid="DEU 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 18:18"/>So I will send from among them a prophet who will be like you. I will tell him what to say, and then he will tell people everything that I tell him to say. <verse eid="DEU 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 18:19"/>He will speak for me. And I will punish anyone who does not heed what he says. <verse eid="DEU 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 18:20"/>But if any other <char style="add">person says that he is a</char> prophet <char style="add">and</char> dares to speak a message which he falsely says comes from me but which I did not tell him to speak, or if anyone who speaks a message that he says other gods [MTY] have revealed to him, he must be executed <char style="add">for doing that</char>.’<verse eid="DEU 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 18:21"/>But if you say to yourself, ‘How can we know if a message <char style="add">that someone tells us</char> does not come from Yahweh?’ <verse eid="DEU 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 18:22"/><char style="add">The answer is that</char> when someone speaks a message <char style="add">about what will happen in the future</char>, a message that he says was revealed by Yahweh, if what he says does not happen, <char style="add">you will know that</char> the message did not come from Yahweh. That person has wrongly claimed that it was revealed to him by Yahweh. So you do not need to be afraid of <char style="add">anything that</char> he <char style="add">says</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 18:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="DEU 19"/>
  <para style="s1">The cities of refuge</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 19:1"/>After Yahweh our God has gotten rid of the people-groups from the land that he is giving to you, and after you have expelled them from their cities and you start to live in their houses, <verse eid="DEU 19:1"/><verse number="2-3" style="v" sid="DEU 19:2-3"/>you must divide into three parts the land that he is giving to you. Then choose a city in each part. You must make good roads <char style="add">in order that people can get to those cities easily</char>. Someone who kills another person can escape to one of those cities <char style="add">to be safe/protected</char>.<verse eid="DEU 19:2-3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 19:4"/>“This is the rule about someone who has killed another person. If someone ◄accidentally/without planning to► kills another person who was not his enemy, he may escape to one of those cities and be safe/protected there. <verse eid="DEU 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 19:5"/>For example, if two men go into the forest to cut some wood, if the axe head comes off the handle while one of them is chopping down a tree and the axe head strikes and kills the other man, the man <char style="add">who was using the axe</char> will be allowed to run to one of those cities and be safe there, <char style="add">because the people of that city will protect him</char>. <verse eid="DEU 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 19:6"/>Because he accidentally killed someone, and because the man was not his enemy, he can try to run to one of those cities. If there were only one city, it may be a long distance to that city. Then if the relative of the man who was killed [MTY], the man who is supposed/expected to get revenge, is very angry, he may be able to catch the other person before he arrives at that city. <verse eid="DEU 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 19:7"/><char style="add">To prevent that from happening</char>, you must choose three cities, not only one, <char style="add">in order that someone can get to one of those cities quickly</char>.<verse eid="DEU 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8-9" style="v" sid="DEU 19:8-9"/>“If you do everything that I am today commanding you to do, and if you love Yahweh our God, and if you conduct your lives as he wants you to do, Yahweh our God will give you much more land than you will have when you first occupy it, which is what he promised to do. He will give you all the land which he promised your ancestors that he would give to you. When he gives you that land, you must select three more cities <char style="add">to which people may escape</char>. <verse eid="DEU 19:8-9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 19:10"/>Do this in order that people who ◄are innocent/have killed someone else without planning to► will not die, and you will not be guilty for <char style="add">allowing</char> them to be executed, in the land that Yahweh is giving to you.<verse eid="DEU 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 19:11"/>“But suppose someone hates his enemy and hides and waits for that person <char style="add">to come along the road</char>. Then <char style="add">when he passes by, suddenly</char> he attacks him and murders him. If the attacker flees to one of those cities <char style="add">to be protected there</char>, <verse eid="DEU 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 19:12"/>the elders of the city <char style="add">where the murdered man lived must not protect the attacker. They</char>. must send someone to the city to which the other man escaped, and bring him to [MTY] the relative who is supposed/expected to get revenge, so that he may execute that man. <verse eid="DEU 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 19:13"/>You must not pity those who murder other people! Instead, you must execute them, in order that the people in the land of Israel will not murder [MTY] innocent people, and in order that things will go well for you.”<verse eid="DEU 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Warning against moving boundaries</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 19:14"/>“<char style="add">When you are living</char> in the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you, do not move the markers of your neighbors’ property boundaries which were placed there long ago.”<verse eid="DEU 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Warnings about witnesses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 19:15"/>“If someone is accused of committing a crime, one ◄witness/person who says, ‘I saw him do it’► is not enough. There must be at least two ◄witnesses/people who say, ‘We saw him do it’►. <char style="add">If there is only one witness</char>, the judge must not believe that what he says is true.<verse eid="DEU 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 19:16"/>“If someone tries to do wrong to another person by falsely accusing him, <verse eid="DEU 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 19:17"/>both of them must go to the place where the people worship, to <char style="add">talk to</char> the priests and judges who are serving at that time. <verse eid="DEU 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 19:18"/>The judges must ◄investigate the case carefully/try to find out which one is telling the truth►. If <char style="add">the judges determine that</char> one of them has accused the other falsely, <verse eid="DEU 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 19:19"/>that person must be punished in the same way that the other one would have been punished <char style="add">if the judge decided that he ◄was guilty/had done what is wrong►</char>. By punishing such people, you will get rid of this evil practice among you. <verse eid="DEU 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 19:20"/>And/Because when that person is punished, everyone will hear what has happened, and they will be afraid, and no one will dare to act that way any more. <verse eid="DEU 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 19:21"/>You must not pity people who are punished like that. The rule should be that a person who has murdered someone else must be executed; one of a person’s eyes must be gouged out if he has gouged out someone else’s eye, one tooth of a person who has knocked out the tooth of another person must be knocked out; one hand of a person who has cut off the hand of another person must likewise be cut off; one foot of a person who has cut off the foot of another person must also be cut off.”<verse eid="DEU 19:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="DEU 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules concerning fighting wars</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 20:1"/>“When your <char style="add">soldiers</char> go to fight your enemies, and you see that they have many horses and chariots and that their army is much bigger than yours, do not be afraid of them, because Yahweh our God, who brought your <char style="add">ancestors safely</char> out of Egypt, will be with you. <verse eid="DEU 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 20:2"/>When you are ready to start the battle, the Supreme Priest must stand in front of the troops. <verse eid="DEU 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 20:3"/>He must say to them, ‘You Israeli men, listen to me! Today you are going to fight against your enemies. Do not be timid or afraid [DOU] or tremble or panic [DOU], <verse eid="DEU 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 20:4"/>because Yahweh our God will go with you. He will fight your enemies for you, and he will enable you to defeat them.’<verse eid="DEU 20:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 20:5"/>Then the army officers must say to the troops, ‘If anyone among you has just built a new house [RHQ] and has not dedicated it <char style="add">to God</char>, he should go home <char style="add">and dedicate the house</char>. If he does not do that, if he dies in the battle, someone else will dedicate the house <char style="add">and live in it</char>. <verse eid="DEU 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 20:6"/>If anyone among you has planted a vineyard and has not yet harvested any grapes from it [RHQ], he should go home. If he <char style="add">stays here and</char> dies in the battle, someone else will <char style="add">harvest the grapes and</char> enjoy <char style="add">the wine made from them</char>. <verse eid="DEU 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 20:7"/>If anyone among you has become engaged to marry a woman <char style="add">but has not married her yet</char> [RHQ], he should go home. If <char style="add">he stays here and</char> dies in the battle, someone else will marry her.’<verse eid="DEU 20:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 20:8"/>“Then the officers must also say, ‘If anyone among you is afraid or timid [RHQ], he should go home, in order that he does not cause his fellow soldiers to also stop being courageous.’ <verse eid="DEU 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 20:9"/>And when the officers have finished speaking to the troops, they must appoint commanders <char style="add">to lead the groups of soldiers</char>.<verse eid="DEU 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 20:10"/>“When you come near a city <char style="add">that is far away</char> to attack it, first tell the people there that if they surrender, you will not attack them. <verse eid="DEU 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 20:11"/>If they open the gates of the city and surrender, they all will become your slaves to work for you. <verse eid="DEU 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 20:12"/>But if they refuse to <char style="add">surrender</char> peacefully, and decide instead to fight against you, your troops must surround the city <char style="add">and break through the walls</char>. <verse eid="DEU 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 20:13"/>Then, when Yahweh our God enables you to capture [IDM] the city, you must kill all the men in the city. <verse eid="DEU 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 20:14"/>But you are allowed to take for yourselves the women, the children, the livestock, and everything else <char style="add">that you want to take</char> from the city. You will be allowed to enjoy all the things that belonged to your enemies; it is Yahweh our God who has given those things to you. <verse eid="DEU 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 20:15"/>You should do that in all the cities that are far from the land in which you will settle.<verse eid="DEU 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 20:16"/>“But in the cities that are in the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you, you must kill all the people and all the animals [LIT]. <verse eid="DEU 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 20:17"/>You must get rid of them completely. Get rid of the Heth people-group, the Amor people-group, the Canaan people-group, the Periz people-group, the Hiv people-group, and the Jebus people-group; that is what Yahweh our God commanded you to do. <verse eid="DEU 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 20:18"/>If you do not do that, they will teach you to sin against Yahweh our God and do the disgusting things that they do when they worship their gods.<verse eid="DEU 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 20:19"/>“When you surround a city for a long time, trying to capture it, do not cut down the fruit trees <char style="add">outside the city</char>. You are allowed to eat the fruit from the trees, but do not get rid of the trees, because they certainly are not [RHQ] your enemies. <verse eid="DEU 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 20:20"/>You are permitted to cut down the other trees and use the wood to make ladders and towers to enable you to <char style="add">go over the walls and</char> capture the city.”<verse eid="DEU 20:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="DEU 21"/>
  <para style="s1">When no one knows who murdered someone</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 21:1"/>“Suppose someone has been murdered in a field in the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you, and you do not know who killed that person. <verse eid="DEU 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 21:2"/><char style="add">If that happens</char>, your elders and judges must go out to where that person’s corpse was found and measure the distance from there to each of the nearby towns. <verse eid="DEU 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 21:3"/>Then the elders in the town that is closest to where the corpse was found must select a young cow that has never been used for doing work. <verse eid="DEU 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 21:4"/>They must take it to a place near a stream where the ground has never been plowed or planted. They must break its neck there in that valley. <verse eid="DEU 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 21:5"/>The priests must go there also, because Yahweh our God has chosen them from the tribe of Levi to serve him and to be his representatives [MTY] when they bless people. And he has also chosen them to settle disputes in which someone has been injured. <verse eid="DEU 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 21:6"/>The elders from the closest town must wash their hands over the young cow whose neck was broken, <verse eid="DEU 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 21:7"/>and they must say, ‘We did not murder this person [MTY], and we did not see who did it. <verse eid="DEU 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 21:8"/>Yahweh, forgive us, your Israeli people whom you rescued <char style="add">from Egypt</char>. Do not consider ◄us to be guilty/that we should be punished because► of murdering someone who ◄is innocent/had not done something that is wrong►. Instead, forgive us.’ <verse eid="DEU 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 21:9"/>By doing that, you will be doing what Yahweh considers to be right, and you will not be considered to be guilty for murdering that person.”<verse eid="DEU 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The rule about marrying women who are captured</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 21:10"/>“When you <char style="add">soldiers</char> go to fight against your enemies, and Yahweh our God enables you to defeat them [IDM], and ◄they become your prisoners/you capture them►, <verse eid="DEU 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 21:11"/>one of you may see among them a beautiful woman that he likes, and he may want to marry her. <verse eid="DEU 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 21:12"/>He should take her to his home, and there she must shave <char style="add">all the hair off</char> her head and cut her fingernails <char style="add">to signify that now she does not belong to her people-group any more, but instead she is becoming an Israeli</char>. <verse eid="DEU 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 21:13"/>She must take off the clothes that she was wearing when she was captured, <char style="add">and put on Israeli clothes</char>. She must stay in that man’s house and mourn for a month because of <char style="add">leaving</char> her parents. After that, he will be allowed to marry her. <verse eid="DEU 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 21:14"/>Later, if he no longer is pleased with her, he will be permitted to allow her to leave him. But because she was forced to have sex with him, he will not be allowed to treat her like a slave <char style="add">and sell her to someone else</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The oldest son’s inheritance</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 21:15"/>“Suppose that a man has two wives, but he likes one of them and dislikes the other one. And suppose that they both give birth to sons, and the oldest son is the child of the woman that he does not like. <verse eid="DEU 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 21:16"/>On the day when that man decides how he will divide his possessions for his sons to possess <char style="add">after he dies</char>, he must not favor the son of the wife that he loves by giving him <char style="add">a bigger share,</char> the share that the older son should receive. <verse eid="DEU 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 21:17"/>He must give to the older son, the son of the wife whom he does not like, twice as much of his possessions. That son is his firstborn son, and he must be given the share that he should receive because of his being that man’s firstborn son.”<verse eid="DEU 21:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A rebellious son</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 21:18"/>“Suppose there is a boy who is very stubborn and always ◄rebelling against/disobeying► <char style="add">his parents</char>, and who will not heed what they say to him. And suppose that they punish him but he still does not pay attention to what they tell him [MTY]. <verse eid="DEU 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 21:19"/>If that happens, his parents must take him to the ◄gate of/central meeting place in► the city where he lives and have him stand in front of the elders of the city. <verse eid="DEU 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 21:20"/>Then the parents must say to the elders of that city, ‘This son of ours is stubborn and always rebelling against us. He will not pay attention to what we tell him [MTY]. He wastes a lot of money (OR, eats too much food) and gets drunk.’ <verse eid="DEU 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 21:21"/>Then all the elders of that city must execute him by throwing stones at him. By doing that, you will get rid of this evil practice among you. And everyone in Israel will hear <char style="add">about what happened</char> and they will be afraid <char style="add">to do what he did</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 21:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Burying criminals</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 21:22"/>“If someone is executed for having committed a crime for which he deserves to die, and you hang his corpse on a post, <verse eid="DEU 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 21:23"/>you must not allow his corpse to remain there all night. You must bury it on the day that he died, because <char style="add">God</char> has cursed anyone whose corpse is allowed to remain on a post. <char style="add">You must bury the corpse that day</char>, in order that you do not defile the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you.”<verse eid="DEU 21:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="DEU 22"/>
  <para style="s1">Various other laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 22:1"/>“If you see some Israeli’s ox or sheep that has strayed away, do not act as though you did not see it. Take it back <char style="add">to its owner</char>. <verse eid="DEU 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 22:2"/>But if the owner does not live near you, or if you do not know who the owner is, take the animal to your house. <char style="add">It can stay with you</char> until the owner comes, searching for it. Then you must give the animal to him. <verse eid="DEU 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 22:3"/>You must do the same thing if you see a donkey, or a piece of clothing, or anything else that someone has lost. Do not refuse to do what you should do.<verse eid="DEU 22:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 22:4"/>“And if you see a fellow Israeli’s donkey or cow that has fallen down on the road, do not act as though you did not see it. Help the owner to lift the animal up <char style="add">so that it can stand on its feet again</char>.<verse eid="DEU 22:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 22:5"/>“Women must not wear men’s clothes, and men must not wear women’s clothes. Yahweh our God hates people who do things like that.<verse eid="DEU 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 22:6"/>“If you happen to find a bird’s nest in a tree or on the ground, and the mother bird is sitting in the nest on its eggs or with the baby birds, do not take the mother bird <char style="add">and kill it</char>. <verse eid="DEU 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 22:7"/>You are permitted to take the baby birds, but you must allow the mother bird to fly away. Do this in order that things will go well for you and that you will live for a long time.<verse eid="DEU 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 22:8"/>“If you build a new house, you must put a ◄railing/low wall► around the edge of the roof. If you do that, and if someone falls off the roof <char style="add">and dies</char>, ◄you will not be guilty of causing that person to die/his death [MTY] will not be your fault►.<verse eid="DEU 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 22:9"/>“Do not plant any crop in the area where your grapevines are growing. If you do, you are not allowed to harvest the crops that you have planted or to harvest the grapes <char style="add">to make wine from them</char>.<verse eid="DEU 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 22:10"/>“Do not hitch together an ox and a donkey <char style="add">for plowing your fields</char>.<verse eid="DEU 22:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 22:11"/>“Do not wear clothing that is made by weaving together ◄wool and linen/two different kinds of thread►.<verse eid="DEU 22:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 22:12"/>“<char style="add">Twist threads together to</char> make tassels and sew/fasten them on the four bottom corners of your cloak.<verse eid="DEU 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Rules concerning sex</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 22:13"/>“Suppose a man marries a young woman and has sex with her and later decides that he does not want her any more, <verse eid="DEU 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 22:14"/>and he says false things about her, and claims that she was not a virgin when he married her. <verse eid="DEU 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 22:15"/>If that happens, the young woman’s parents must take the sheet that was on the bed when that man and their daughter were married, which still has bloodstains on it, and show it to the elders of the city at the ◄gate of/central meeting place in► the city. <verse eid="DEU 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 22:16"/>Then the father of the young woman must say to the elders, ‘I gave my daughter to this man to be his wife. But now he says that he doesn’t want her any more. <verse eid="DEU 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 22:17"/>And he has falsely said that she was not a virgin when he married her. But look! Here is what proves that my daughter was a virgin! Look at the bloodstains on the sheet where they slept the night that they were married!’ And he will show the sheet to the elders. <verse eid="DEU 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 22:18"/>Then the elders of that city must take that man and whip him. <verse eid="DEU 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 22:19"/>They shall require that he pay a fine of 100 pieces of silver and give the money to the father of the young woman, because the man caused an Israeli young woman to be disgraced. Also, that woman must continue to live with him; she is his wife. He is not allowed to divorce her during the rest of his life.<verse eid="DEU 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 22:20"/>“But if what the man said is true, and there is nothing to prove that she was a virgin when he married her, <verse eid="DEU 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 22:21"/>they must take that young woman to the door of her father’s house. Then the men of that city must execute her by throwing stones at her. They must do that because she has done something in Israel that is very disgraceful, by having sex with some man <char style="add">while she was still living</char> in her father’s house. By executing her like that, you will get rid of this evil practice among you.<verse eid="DEU 22:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 22:22"/>“If a man is caught while he is having sex with another man’s wife, both of them must be executed. By doing that, you will get rid of this evil practice in Israel.<verse eid="DEU 22:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 22:23"/>“Suppose in some town a man sees a young woman who is engaged/promised to be married to another man, and he is caught having sex with [EUP] her. <verse eid="DEU 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 22:24"/>You must take both of them to the ◄gate of/central meeting place in► that town. There you must execute them both by throwing stones at them. You must execute the young woman because she did not shout for help even though she was in the town. And the man must be executed because he had sex [EUP] with someone who was already engaged/promised to be married. By doing that, you will get rid of this evil practice among you.<verse eid="DEU 22:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 22:25"/>“But suppose out in the open countryside a man meets a young woman who is engaged/promised to be married, and he rapes her. If that happens, only that man must be executed. <verse eid="DEU 22:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 22:26"/>You must not punish the young woman, because she did not do anything for which she deserves to be executed. This case is like when one man attacks another man <char style="add">in the countryside</char> and murders him, <verse eid="DEU 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 22:27"/>because the man who raped her saw her when she was in the open countryside, and even though she called out for help, there was no one there who could rescue her.<verse eid="DEU 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 22:28"/>“If a man rapes a young woman who is not engaged/promised to be married, if someone sees him while he is doing that, <verse eid="DEU 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 22:29"/>that man must pay 50 pieces of silver to the young woman’s father, and he must marry her, because he forced her to have sex with him. He is not allowed to divorce her for the rest of his life.<verse eid="DEU 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 22:30"/>“ man must not disgrace his father by having sex with any of his father’s wives.”<verse eid="DEU 22:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="DEU 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Exclusion from Yahweh’s people</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 23:1"/>“Any man whose testicles are crushed or whose penis is cut off shall not be ◄included as one of/allowed to worship with► Yahweh’s people.<verse eid="DEU 23:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 23:2"/>“No ◄illegitimate person/person whose mother and father were not married►, or descendant of that person, extending to the tenth generation, shall be included as one of Yahweh’s people.<verse eid="DEU 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 23:3"/>“No one from the Ammon or Moab people-groups shall be ◄included as one of/allowed to worship with► Yahweh’s people, extending to the tenth generation. <verse eid="DEU 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 23:4"/>One reason is that their <char style="add">leaders</char> refused to give your ancestors food and water when they were traveling from Egypt <char style="add">to Canaan</char>. Another reason is that they wanted to pay Balaam, the son of Beor from Pethor <char style="add">town</char> in Mesopotamia, to curse you Israelis. <verse eid="DEU 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 23:5"/>But Yahweh our God did not pay attention to Balaam; instead, he caused Balaam to bless your ancestors, because Yahweh loved them. <verse eid="DEU 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 23:6"/>As long as Israel is a nation, you must not do anything to cause things to go well for those two people-groups or enable them to prosper.<verse eid="DEU 23:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 23:7"/>“But do not despise anyone from the Edom people-group, because they are <char style="add">descendants of your ancestor Jacob</char>, just like you are. And do not despise people from Egypt, because <char style="add">they treated your ancestors well when</char> they first lived in Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 23:8"/>The children and grandchildren of people from Edom and Egypt <char style="add">who live among you</char> may be ◄included among/allowed to worship with► Yahweh’s people.”<verse eid="DEU 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Keeping the camp clean</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 23:9"/>“When your soldiers are living in tents at a time of fighting your enemies, they must avoid doing things that would make them unacceptable to God. <verse eid="DEU 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 23:10"/>If any soldier becomes unacceptable to God because semen comes out of his body during the night, <char style="add">the next morning</char> he must go outside the camp and stay there during that day. <verse eid="DEU 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 23:11"/>But in the evening of that day, he must bathe himself, and at sunset he is allowed to come back into the camp.<verse eid="DEU 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 23:12"/>“Your soldiers must have a toilet area outside the camp where you can go <char style="add">when you need to</char>. <verse eid="DEU 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 23:13"/><char style="add">When you go to fight against your enemies</char>, carry a stick along with your weapons, in order that when you need to defecate [EUP], you can dig a hole with the stick, and then cover up the hole <char style="add">when you have finished defecating</char>. <verse eid="DEU 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 23:14"/>You must keep the camp acceptable to Yahweh our God, because he is with you in your camp to protect you and to enable you to defeat your enemies. Do not do anything disgraceful/indecent that would cause Yahweh to abandon you.”<verse eid="DEU 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Various other laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 23:15"/>“If slaves who escape from their masters come to you <char style="add">and request you to protect them</char>, do not send them back to their masters. <verse eid="DEU 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 23:16"/>Allow them to stay/live among you, in whatever town they choose, and do not mistreat them.<verse eid="DEU 23:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 23:17"/>“Do not <char style="add">allow</char> any Israeli man or woman <char style="add">to</char> become a prostitute at the temple. <verse eid="DEU 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 23:18"/>Also, do not allow any people who earned money from being a prostitute to bring any of that money into the temple of Yahweh our God, even if they solemnly promised to pay that money to Yahweh. Yahweh hates those who are prostitutes.<verse eid="DEU 23:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 23:19"/>“When you lend money or food or anything else to a fellow Israeli, do not charge them interest. <verse eid="DEU 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 23:20"/>You are allowed to charge interest when you lend money to foreigners <char style="add">who live in your land</char>, but not when you lend money to Israelis. Do this in order that Yahweh our God will bless you in everything that you do in the land that you are about to enter and occupy.<verse eid="DEU 23:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 23:21"/>“When you vow to give something to Yahweh your God <char style="add">or to do something for him</char>, do it as soon as you can. Yahweh expects you to do what you promised, and if you do not do it, you will be committing a sin. <verse eid="DEU 23:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 23:22"/>But if you [SYN] do not vow <char style="add">to do something</char>, that is not sinful. <verse eid="DEU 23:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 23:23"/>But if you voluntarily promise to do something, you must do it.<verse eid="DEU 23:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 23:24"/>“When you walk through someone else’s vineyard, you are allowed to <char style="add">pick and</char> eat as many grapes as you want, but you must not <char style="add">cut some from a vine and carry them away</char> in a container. <verse eid="DEU 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 23:25"/>When you walk <char style="add">along a path</char> in someone else’s field of grain, you are allowed to pluck/pick some of the grain and eat it, but you must not cut any grain with a sickle <char style="add">and take it with you</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 23:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="DEU 24"/>
  <para style="s1">Laws about divorcing and remarrying</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 24:1"/>“Suppose a man marries a woman and later decides that he does not want her because there is something about her that he doesn’t like. And suppose he writes on paper that he is divorcing her, and he gives the paper to her [SYN] and sends her away from his house. <verse eid="DEU 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 24:2"/>Then suppose that she goes and marries another man, <verse eid="DEU 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 24:3"/>and that man <char style="add">later also</char> decides that he does not like her, and he also writes on paper that he is divorcing her, and he sends her away from his house. Or, suppose that the second husband dies. <verse eid="DEU 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 24:4"/>If either of those things happens, her first husband must not marry her again. He must consider that she has become unacceptable to Yahweh. Yahweh would consider it to be disgusting <char style="add">if he married her again</char>. You must not sin [MTY] by doing that in the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you.”<verse eid="DEU 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Various laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 24:5"/>“When some man has recently become married, he must not <char style="add">be required to</char> become a soldier in the army or be required to do any other work <char style="add">for the government</char> for one year <char style="add">after being married</char>. He should stay happily at home with his wife for that year.<verse eid="DEU 24:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 24:6"/>“Anyone who lends money to someone else <char style="add">is allowed to require that person to give him something</char> to guarantee <char style="add">that he will pay back the money that he borrowed. But</char> he must not take from him his ◄millstone/stone for grinding grain►. That would be taking <char style="add">the millstone that his family needs to grind the grain to make the bread</char> they need to stay alive.<verse eid="DEU 24:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 24:7"/>“If someone kidnaps/steals a fellow Israeli to cause that person to become his slave or to sell him <char style="add">to become someone else’s slave</char>, you must execute the person who did that. By doing that, you will get rid of this evil among you.<verse eid="DEU 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 24:8"/>“If you are suffering from ◄leprosy/a dreaded skin disease►, be sure to do everything that the priests, who are from the tribe of Levi, tell you to do. Obey carefully the instructions that I have given to them. <verse eid="DEU 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 24:9"/>Do not forget what Yahweh our God did to Miriam, <char style="add">when she became a leper</char>, after your ancestors left Egypt.<verse eid="DEU 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 24:10"/>“When you lend something to someone, do not go into his house to take the cloak that he says that he will give you to guarantee <char style="add">that he will return what he has borrowed</char>. <verse eid="DEU 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 24:11"/>Stand outside his house, and the man to whom you are lending something will bring the cloak out to you. <verse eid="DEU 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 24:12"/>But if he is poor, do not keep that cloak all night. <verse eid="DEU 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 24:13"/>When the sun sets, take the cloak back to him, in order that he may wear it while he sleeps. If you do that, he will <char style="add">ask God to</char> bless you, and Yahweh our God will be pleased with you.<verse eid="DEU 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 24:14"/>“Do not mistreat any servants whom you have hired who are poor and needy [DOU], whether they are Israelis or foreigners who are living in your town. <verse eid="DEU 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 24:15"/>Every day, before sunset, you must pay/give them the money that they have earned. They are poor and they need to get their pay. If you do not pay them right away, they will cry out against you to Yahweh, and he will punish [MTY] you for having sinned like that.<verse eid="DEU 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 24:16"/>“Parents must not be executed for crimes that their children have committed, and children must not be executed for crimes that their parents have committed. People should be executed only for the crimes that they themselves have committed.<verse eid="DEU 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 24:17"/>“You must [LIT] do for foreigners <char style="add">who live</char> among you and for orphans what the laws state must be done for them. And <char style="add">if you lend something to</char> a widow, do not take her coat from her as a guarantee <char style="add">that she will return it</char>. <verse eid="DEU 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 24:18"/>Do not forget that <char style="add">you had great hardships/troubles when</char> you were slaves in Egypt, and Yahweh our God rescued you from there. That is why I am commanding you <char style="add">to help others who have troubles</char>.<verse eid="DEU 24:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 24:19"/>“When you harvest your crops, if you have forgotten <char style="add">that you left</char> one bundle in the field, do not go back to get it. <char style="add">Leave it there</char> for foreigners, orphans, and widows. If you do that, Yahweh will bless you in everything that you do. <verse eid="DEU 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 24:20"/>And when you have harvested/picked all your olives from the trees once, do not go back <char style="add">to pick the ones that are still</char> on the trees. <verse eid="DEU 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 24:21"/><char style="add">Similarly</char>, when you pick the grapes in your vineyard, do not go back a second time <char style="add">to try to find more</char>. Leave them for the foreigners, orphans, and widows <char style="add">among you</char>. <verse eid="DEU 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 24:22"/>Do not forget that <char style="add">Yahweh was kind to you when</char> you were slaves in Egypt. That is why I am commanding you <char style="add">to be kind to those who are needy</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 24:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="DEU 25"/>
  <para style="s1">Whipping criminals</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 25:1"/>“If <char style="add">two</char> Israelis have a dispute and they go to a court, the judge will <char style="add">probably</char> decide/declare that one of them ◄is innocent/did not do any wrong► and the other one is guilty. <verse eid="DEU 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 25:2"/>If the judge says that the guilty person must be punished, he shall command him to lie <char style="add">with his face</char> on the ground and be whipped. The number of times he is struck with a whip will depend on <char style="add">what kind of</char> crime he committed. <verse eid="DEU 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 25:3"/>It is permitted that he be struck as many as 40 times, but no more than that. If he is struck more than 40 times, he would be humiliated publicly.<verse eid="DEU 25:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Don’t muzzle your ox</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 25:4"/>When your ox is treading/walking on the grain <char style="add">to separate the chaff from the grain</char>, do not ◄muzzle it/put a covering on its mouth► <char style="add">to prevent it from eating some of the grain</char>.<verse eid="DEU 25:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Responsibility to a dead brother</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 25:5"/>If two brothers live on the same property, and one of them who has no son dies, the man’s widow should not marry someone who is not a member of his family. The dead man’s brother must marry her and have sex [EUP] with her. It is his duty to do that. <verse eid="DEU 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 25:6"/>If she later gives birth to a son, that son is to be considered [MTY] the son of the man who died, in order that the dead man’s name will not disappear from Israel.<verse eid="DEU 25:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 25:7"/>“But if the dead man’s brother does not want to marry that woman, she must stand at the ◄gate/central meeting place► of the town and say to the <char style="add">town</char> elders, ‘My husband’s brother will not do ◄his duty/what he is supposed to do►. He refuses to <char style="add">marry me in order that I may give birth to a son who will </char> prevent my dead husband’s name from disappearing in Israel.’ <verse eid="DEU 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 25:8"/>Then the elders must summon that man and talk to him. If he still refuses to marry that widow, <verse eid="DEU 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 25:9"/>she must go up to him while the elders are watching, and take off one of his sandals <char style="add">to symbolize/show that he would not receive any of her property</char>, and spit in his face, and say to him, ‘This is what happens to the man who refuses to do what is needed <char style="add">to allow his dead brother to have a son</char> in order that our family name does not disappear.’ <verse eid="DEU 25:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 25:10"/>After that happens, that man’s family will be known as ‘the family of the man whose sandal was pulled off’.<verse eid="DEU 25:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Two other laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 25:11"/>When <char style="add">two</char> men are fighting with each other, and the one man’s wife comes near to help her husband by grabbing hold of the other man’s genitals, <verse eid="DEU 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 25:12"/>do not act mercifully toward her; cut off her hand.<verse eid="DEU 25:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13-14" style="v" sid="DEU 25:13-14"/>“<char style="add">When you are buying or selling things</char>, do not try to cheat people by having two kinds of weights, <char style="add">one which you use when you buy something and one which you use when you sell something</char>, and two kinds of measuring baskets, <char style="add">one which you use when you buy something and one which you use when you sell something</char>. <verse eid="DEU 25:13-14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 25:15"/>Always use correct weights and correct measuring baskets, in order that Yahweh our God will allow you to live a long time in the land that he is giving to you. <verse eid="DEU 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 25:16"/>Yahweh hates all those who act dishonestly, <char style="add">and he will punish them</char>.<verse eid="DEU 25:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Getting revenge on the Amalek people-group</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 25:17"/>Continue to remember what the Amalek people-group did to your ancestors when they were coming out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 25:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 25:18"/>They attacked your ancestors as your ancestors were traveling, when they were weak and exhausted. Those people were not afraid of God at all, so they attacked your ancestors from the rear and killed all those who were unable to walk as fast as the others. <verse eid="DEU 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 25:19"/>Therefore, when Yahweh our God has given you the land <char style="add">that he promised to give you</char>, and when he has enabled you to rest from <char style="add">fighting</char> all your enemies around you, kill all the Amalek people-group, with the result that no one will remember them any more. Do not forget <char style="add">to do this</char>!”<verse eid="DEU 25:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="DEU 26"/>
  <para style="s1">Offerings at harvest time</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 26:1"/>“After you occupy the land that Yahweh our God is giving to you, and you ◄have settled/are living► there, <verse eid="DEU 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 26:2"/><char style="add">each of</char> you must take some of the first crops that you harvest, put them in a basket, and take them to the place that Yahweh will have chosen for you to worship [MTY] there. <verse eid="DEU 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 26:3"/>Go to the Supreme Priest who is serving at that time and say to him, ‘<char style="add">By giving you this first part of my harvest</char> today, I am declaring to Yahweh our God that I have <char style="add">picked it in</char> the land that he vowed to our ancestors to give to us.’ <verse eid="DEU 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 26:4"/>Then the priest must take the basket of food from your hand and put it on the altar where sacrifices are offered to Yahweh our God. <verse eid="DEU 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 26:5"/>Then in Yahweh’s presence you must say this: ‘My ancestor <char style="add">Jacob</char> was a man from Aram/Syria who was continually wandering <char style="add">from one place to another</char>. He took his family to Egypt. They were a small group <char style="add">when they went there</char>, but they lived there and their descendants became a very large/populous [DOU] and powerful nation. <verse eid="DEU 26:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 26:6"/>Then the people of Egypt treated them very harshly [DOU], and they forced them to become their slaves and to work very hard. <verse eid="DEU 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 26:7"/>Then our ancestors cried out to you, Yahweh our God, and you heard them. You saw that they were suffering, and that they were forced to work very hard, and were being oppressed. <verse eid="DEU 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 26:8"/>Then by your great power [MTY] and by performing many kinds of miracles [DOU], and other terrifying things, you brought them out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 26:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 26:9"/>You brought us to this land and gave it to us, a land that is very fertile [IDM]. <verse eid="DEU 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 26:10"/>So now, Yahweh, I have brought to you the first part of the harvest from the land that I received.’ Then you must set the basket down in Yahweh’s presence and worship him there. <verse eid="DEU 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 26:11"/>And you must celebrate <char style="add">by eating a meal together to thank</char> Yahweh our God for all the good things that he has given to you and to your family. And you must invite the descendants of Levi and the foreigners who are living among you to also rejoice <char style="add">and eat</char> with you.<verse eid="DEU 26:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The tithes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 26:12"/>Every third year, you must bring to the descendants of Levi and to the foreigners <char style="add">who are living among you</char> and the orphans and the widows ◄a tithe/10 percent► of your crops, in order that in every town they will have plenty to eat. <verse eid="DEU 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 26:13"/>Then you must say to Yahweh, ‘I have brought to you, from my house, all of the sacred tithe <char style="add">from my harvest this year</char>. I am giving it to the descendants of Levi, to the foreigners, the orphans, and the widows, as you commanded us to do. I have not disobeyed any of your commands <char style="add">about the tithes</char>, and I have not forgotten any of your commands <char style="add">about tithes</char>. <verse eid="DEU 26:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 26:14"/><char style="add">I declare that</char> I have not eaten any food from the tithe while I was mourning <char style="add">for someone who died</char>. And I have not touched any of it while I was unacceptable to you; I have not offered any of it to <char style="add">spirits of</char> dead people. Yahweh, I have obeyed you and done everything that you have commanded us <char style="add">concerning the tithe</char>. <verse eid="DEU 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 26:15"/>So <char style="add">please</char> look down from your holy place in heaven, and bless us, your Israeli people. Also bless this very fertile [IDM] land which you have given to us, which is what you promised our ancestors that you would do.’<verse eid="DEU 26:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh’s own people</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 26:16"/>Today Yahweh our God is commanding you to obey all these rules and regulations. So obey them faithfully, with your entire inner being [DOU]. <verse eid="DEU 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 26:17"/>Today you have declared that Yahweh is your God, and that you will conduct your lives as he wants you to do, and that you will obey all his commands and rules and regulations, and that you will do all that he tells you to do. <verse eid="DEU 26:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 26:18"/>And today Yahweh has declared that you are his people, which is what he promised that you would be, and he commands you to obey all his commands. <verse eid="DEU 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 26:19"/>If you do that, he will cause you to become greater than any other nation that he has established, and he will enable you to praise him and honor him [DOU]. You will truly belong to Yahweh our God, which is what he has promised.”<verse eid="DEU 26:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="DEU 27"/>
  <para style="s1">The stone tablets set up on Ebal Mountain</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 27:1"/>Moses/I, along with the other Israeli leaders, said this to the people: “Obey all the commandments that I am giving to you today. <verse eid="DEU 27:1"/><verse number="2-4" style="v" sid="DEU 27:2-4"/><char style="add">Soon</char> you will cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and enter the land that Yahweh, the God whom our ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, promised to give to you. There, in that very fertile [IDM] land on the <char style="add">west</char> side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, set up some large stones <char style="add">on Ebal Mountain</char>, and cover them with plaster. Then write on those stones all these laws and teachings/instructions. <verse eid="DEU 27:2-4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 27:5"/>And build a stone altar there to offer sacrifices to Yahweh, but do not cut those stones with iron tools. <verse eid="DEU 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 27:6"/>The altar that you make to burn sacrifices to Yahweh our God must be made with uncut stones. <verse eid="DEU 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 27:7"/>And there you must sacrifice offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh, and you must eat <char style="add">your share of those offerings</char> and rejoice/celebrate in the presence of Yahweh. <verse eid="DEU 27:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 27:8"/>And, when you write these laws on those stones, you must write them very clearly.”<verse eid="DEU 27:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 27:9"/>Then Moses/I, along with the priests, said to all the Israeli people, “You Israeli people, be quiet and listen <char style="add">to what I am saying</char>. Today you have become the people who belong to Yahweh, our God. <verse eid="DEU 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 27:10"/>So, you must do what he tells you, and obey all the rules and regulations that I am giving to you today.”<verse eid="DEU 27:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The curses from disobeying God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 27:11"/>On that same day Moses/I said to the Israeli people, <verse eid="DEU 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 27:12"/>“After you have crossed over the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, the tribes of Simeon, Levi, Judah, Issachar, Joseph, and Benjamin must stand on Gerizim Mountain and <char style="add">request Yahweh to</char> bless the people. <verse eid="DEU 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 27:13"/>And the tribes of Reuben, Gad, Asher, Zebulun, Dan, and Naphtali must stand on Ebal Mountain and listen to the things that Yahweh will do when he curses the people.<verse eid="DEU 27:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 27:14"/>The descendants of Levi must shout these words loudly:<verse eid="DEU 27:14"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 27:15"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who makes an idol of stone, or of wood, or of metal, and secretly sets it up <char style="add">and worships it</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:15">Yahweh considers that those things, made by humans [SYN], are detestable/disgusting.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:15">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 27:16"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who dishonors his father or his mother.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:16">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 27:17"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who removes someone else’s markers of property boundaries.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:17">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 27:18"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who leads a blind person to go ◄in the wrong direction/where that person does not want to go►.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:18">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 27:19"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who deprives foreigners or orphans or widows of the things that the laws state must be done for them.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:19">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 27:20"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who ◄shows no respect for/disgraces his father►</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:20">by having sex with [EUP] any of his father’s wives.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:20">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 27:21"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who has sex [EUP] with any animal.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:21">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 27:22"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who has sex with his sister or with his half-sister.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:22">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 27:23"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who has sex with [EUP] his mother-in-law.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:23">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 27:24"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who secretly murders someone else.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:24">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 27:25"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who accepts a bribe to murder someone who ◄is innocent/has not done something that is wrong.►’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:25">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’<verse eid="DEU 27:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 27:26"/>‘Yahweh will curse anyone who disobeys these laws and refuses to declare that these laws <char style="add">are good</char>.’</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 27:26">And all the people must reply, ‘◄Amen/We want that to happen►.’”<verse eid="DEU 27:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="DEU 28"/>
  <para style="s1">The blessings from obeying God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 28:1"/>“If you do what Yahweh our God tells you to do and faithfully obey everything that I am today commanding you to do, he will cause you to become greater than any other nation on the earth. <verse eid="DEU 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 28:2"/>If you obey Yahweh, this is what he will do to bless you:<verse eid="DEU 28:2"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 28:3"/>He will bless everything that you do when you are in the cities</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:3">and he will bless everything that you do when you are <char style="add">working</char> in the fields.<verse eid="DEU 28:3"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 28:4"/>He will bless you by giving you many children [IDM] and by giving you abundant crops, and plenty of cattle and sheep.<verse eid="DEU 28:4"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 28:5"/>He will bless you by causing you to have good harvests with plenty of grain [MTY] to make bread.<verse eid="DEU 28:5"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 28:6"/>He will bless you <char style="add">everywhere</char>—when you go out <char style="add">of your houses</char> and when you come into <char style="add">your houses</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 28:7"/>Yahweh will enable you to defeat <char style="add">the armies of</char> your enemies;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:7">they will attack you from one direction, but they will run away from you in seven/many directions.<verse eid="DEU 28:7"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 28:8"/>Yahweh will bless you <char style="add">by filling</char> your barns <char style="add">with grain</char>, and he will bless all the work that you do;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:8">he will bless you in the land that he is giving to you.<verse eid="DEU 28:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 28:9"/>“If you obey all the commandments that Yahweh our God <char style="add">has given to you</char> and if you conduct your lives as he wants you to do, you will continue to be his people, which is what he promised.<verse eid="DEU 28:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 28:10"/>“When all the people-groups on the earth will realize that you belong to [MTY] Yahweh, and they will be afraid of you.<verse eid="DEU 28:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 28:11"/>“And Yahweh will cause you to prosper very much. He will give you many children [IDM], many cattle, and abundant crops in the land that he vowed to our ancestors that he would give to you.<verse eid="DEU 28:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 28:12"/>“When rain is needed, Yahweh will send it from where he stores it in the sky, and he will bless all your work, with the result that you <char style="add">will be able to</char> lend money to many other nations, but you will not need to borrow <char style="add">money from them</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 28:13"/>If you faithfully obey all of the commands of Yahweh our God that I am giving you today, Yahweh will cause your nation to be a leader among the nations, not inferior to them; you will always be prosperous and never be needy/poor [IDM].<verse eid="DEU 28:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 28:14"/>
    <char style="add">Yahweh will do all these things for you</char> if you do not turn away from <char style="add">obeying</char> what I am commanding you today, and if you never worship or serve other gods.<verse eid="DEU 28:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The curses from disobeying God</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 28:15"/>But if you do not do what Yahweh our God is telling you to do, and if you do not faithfully obey all his rules and regulations that I am giving to you today, this is what he will do to curse you:<verse eid="DEU 28:15"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 28:16"/>He will curse you when you are in the cities</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:16">and he will curse you when you are <char style="add">working</char> in the fields.<verse eid="DEU 28:16"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 28:17"/>He will curse you by not allowing you to have good harvests with plenty of grain [MTY] to make bread.<verse eid="DEU 28:17"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 28:18"/>He will curse you by giving you only a few children [IDM], by causing you to have poor crops, and by not enabling you to have many cattle and sheep.<verse eid="DEU 28:18"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 28:19"/>He will curse you <char style="add">everywhere</char>—when you go out <char style="add">of your houses</char> and when you come into <char style="add">your houses</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 28:20"/>If you do evil things and reject Yahweh,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:20">he will curse you by causing you to ◄be confused/not know what to do►, and to be frustrated in everything that you do,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:20">until <char style="add">your enemies</char> quickly and completely destroy you {you will be quickly and completely destroyed}.<verse eid="DEU 28:20"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 28:21"/>Yahweh will cause you to experience terrible diseases,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:21">until not one of you remains alive in the land that you are about to enter and occupy.<verse eid="DEU 28:21"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 28:22"/>Yahweh will strike/afflict you with diseases that shrivel your bodies, with fever, with inflammation/swelling.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:22">It will be extremely hot, and it will not rain.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:22">There will be scorching winds, and <char style="add">Yahweh will cause</char> your crops to rot.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:22">All these things will strike you until you die.<verse eid="DEU 28:22"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 28:23"/>There will be no rain [MET], <char style="add">with the result that</char> the ground will be <char style="add">as hard as</char> iron [MET].<verse eid="DEU 28:23"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 28:24"/>Instead of sending rain, Yahweh will send strong winds to blow sand and dust over your land, until your land is ruined.<verse eid="DEU 28:24"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 28:25"/>Yahweh will enable your enemies to defeat you;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:25">your soldiers will attack your enemies from one direction, but they will run away from your enemies in seven/many directions,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:25">and when the people of other nations see what is happening to you, they will say that it is horrible.<verse eid="DEU 28:25"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 28:26"/>
    <char style="add">You will die</char>, and birds and wild animals will come and eat your corpses,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:26">and there will not be anyone to scare/shoo them away.<verse eid="DEU 28:26"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 28:27"/>Yahweh will cause you to have boils on your skin, like he caused the people of Egypt to have <char style="add">many years ago</char>.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:27">He will cause you to have tumors, open sores, and your skin will itch, and there will be nothing that will cure those diseases.<verse eid="DEU 28:27"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 28:28"/>Yahweh will cause <char style="add">some of</char> you to become insane; he will cause some of you to become blind, and he will cause <char style="add">some of</char> your minds to become confused.<verse eid="DEU 28:28"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 28:29"/>
    <char style="add">Because you will not be able to see where you are going</char>, at midday you will ◄grope/feel your way► around with your hands, like people do in the darkness.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:29">You will continually be oppressed and robbed, and no one will help you.<verse eid="DEU 28:29"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 28:30"/>Some of you men will be engaged/promised to marry a young woman, but someone else will rape her.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:30">You will build houses, but you will never live in them.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:30">You will plant grapevines, but you will not eat the grapes; <char style="add">someone else will eat them</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:30"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 28:31"/>Your enemies will butcher your cattle while you watch them, and you will not get any of the meat to eat.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:31">They will drag away your donkeys while you watch them do it, and they will not give them back to you.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:31">They will take away your sheep; and no one will help you <char style="add">rescue them</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:31"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 28:32"/>While you watch, your sons and daughters will be given to foreigners to become their slaves. Every day you will very sadly watch for your children to return, but ◄you will watch in vain/they will never return►.<verse eid="DEU 28:32"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 28:33"/>People from a foreign nation will take all the crops that you worked hard to produce,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:33">and they will constantly treat you harshly and cruelly [DOU].<verse eid="DEU 28:33"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 28:34"/>The result will be that all these terrible things that you see/experience will cause you to become insane.<verse eid="DEU 28:34"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 28:35"/>Yahweh will cause your legs <char style="add">to be covered with</char> painful boils that cannot be healed,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:35">and you will have boils from the bottoms of your feet to the tops of your heads.<verse eid="DEU 28:35"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 28:36"/>Yahweh will cause your king and the rest of you to be taken to another country, to a place in which you and your ancestors have never lived before,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:36">and there you will worship and serve gods that are made of wood or stone.<verse eid="DEU 28:36"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 28:37"/>When the people-groups in nearby countries see what has happened to you, they will be shocked/horrified;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:37">they will make fun [DOU] of you.<verse eid="DEU 28:37"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 28:38"/>You will plant plenty of seeds in your fields, but you will reap only a small harvest, because locusts will eat the crops.<verse eid="DEU 28:38"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 28:39"/>You will plant grapevines and take care of them, but you will not pick any grapes to make wine, because worms will eat the vines.<verse eid="DEU 28:39"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 28:40"/>Olive trees will grow everywhere in your land, but you will not get any olive oil to rub on your skin because the olives will drop <char style="add">on the ground before they are ripe</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:40"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 28:41"/>You will have sons and daughters, but they will not stay with you, because they will be captured and taken away.<verse eid="DEU 28:41"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 28:42"/>Swarms of locusts/insects will eat your crops and <char style="add">the leaves of</char> all your trees.<verse eid="DEU 28:42"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 28:43"/>Foreigners who live in your land will become more and more <char style="add">powerful</char>, and you will become less and less <char style="add">powerful</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:43"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 28:44"/>They will <char style="add">have money to </char> lend to you, but you will not <char style="add">have any money to</char> lend to them.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="DEU 28:44">They will be superior [IDM] to you, and you will be inferior to them [IDM].<verse eid="DEU 28:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 28:45"/>“You will experience all these disasters, and you will continue to experience them you until you are destroyed, if you do not do what Yahweh your God told you to do, and do not obey all the rules and regulations that he gave to you.<verse eid="DEU 28:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 28:46"/>“These disasters will warn [DOU] you and your descendants forever <char style="add">about what happens to groups who disobey Yahweh</char>.<verse eid="DEU 28:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 28:47"/>“Because Yahweh blessed you abundantly in many ways, you should have served him very joyfully [DOU], but you did not do that.<verse eid="DEU 28:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 28:48"/>“Therefore, you will work for the enemies whom Yahweh will send to attack you. You will be hungry and thirsty; you will not have clothes to wear; and you will lack everything else that you need. And Yahweh will cause you to become slaves [MET] and work hard until he gets rid of you.<verse eid="DEU 28:48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 28:49"/>“Yahweh will cause an army from very far away [HYP] to attack you, whose soldiers speak a language that you do not know/understand. They will swoop down on you <char style="add">quickly</char> like an eagle [SIM] attacks its prey. <verse eid="DEU 28:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 28:50"/>They will be fierce looking. They will not act mercifully toward anyone, not even young children and old people. <verse eid="DEU 28:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 28:51"/>They will <char style="add">kill and</char> eat your livestock, and they will eat your crops, and you will ◄starve/die because you do not have anything to eat►. They will not leave for you any grain or wine or <char style="add">olive</char> oil or cattle or sheep; and you will all die <char style="add">from hunger</char>. <verse eid="DEU 28:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 28:52"/>Your enemies will surround your towns throughout the land that Yahweh your God is about to give to you, and they will break down the high and strong walls <char style="add">around your towns</char>, walls which you trusted/thought would protect you.<verse eid="DEU 28:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="DEU 28:53"/>“When your enemies are surrounding <char style="add">your towns</char>, you will be extremely hungry, with the result that you will eat the flesh of your own sons and daughters that Yahweh your God has given to you. <verse eid="DEU 28:53"/><verse number="54-55" style="v" sid="DEU 28:54-55"/>When your enemies have surrounded your towns, even the most gentle and sensitive men among you will want food very desperately, with the result that they will <char style="add">kill their own children and</char> eat their flesh, because they will not have anything else to eat. They will not even share any of it with their brothers or wives whom they love very much or with any of their children who are still alive. <verse eid="DEU 28:54-55"/><verse number="56-57" style="v" sid="DEU 28:56-57"/>Even the most gentle and sensitive/kind women among you, who are very refined/rich with the result that they have never had to walk anywhere [HYP], will do the same thing. When your enemies have surrounded your towns, those women will be extremely hungry, with the result that after they give birth to a baby, they will secretly <char style="add">kill it and</char> eat its flesh and also eat its afterbirth. And they will not share any of it with their husbands whom they love very much or with any of their other children.<verse eid="DEU 28:56-57"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="DEU 28:58"/>“If you do not faithfully obey all of the laws that I am writing, and if you do not revere Yahweh our glorious God [MTY], <verse eid="DEU 28:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="DEU 28:59"/>he will <char style="add">punish you by</char> causing you and your descendants to experience great afflictions and plagues which will last for many years. <verse eid="DEU 28:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="DEU 28:60"/>He will cause you to experience the plagues that he sent on the people of Egypt, and you will never be healed. <verse eid="DEU 28:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="DEU 28:61"/>He will also cause you to experience many other sicknesses and diseases that I have not talked about in these laws, until you all will die. <verse eid="DEU 28:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="DEU 28:62"/>You became as numerous as the stars in the sky, but only a few of you will remain alive, if you do not obey Yahweh your God. <verse eid="DEU 28:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="DEU 28:63"/>Yahweh was very happy to do good things for you and to cause you to become very numerous, but now he will be happy to ruin you and get rid of you. <char style="add">Those of</char> you <char style="add">who do not die from these plagues</char> will be snatched away from the land that you will soon be entering to possess.<verse eid="DEU 28:63"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="64" style="v" sid="DEU 28:64"/>“Yahweh will scatter you among many people-groups, all over the earth, and in those areas/places you will serve other gods that are made of wood or stone, gods which you and your ancestors have never known/worshiped. <verse eid="DEU 28:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="DEU 28:65"/>In those places you will be restless. Yahweh will cause you to be constantly worried/anxious, feel hopeless, and discouraged. <verse eid="DEU 28:65"/><verse number="66" style="v" sid="DEU 28:66"/>You will always be afraid that your enemies will kill you. You will be very fearful, all day and all night. <verse eid="DEU 28:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="DEU 28:67"/>Because you will be very fearful/afraid because of the <char style="add">terrible</char> things that you see, each morning you will say ‘I wish it were evening already!’ and each evening you will say ‘I wish it were morning already!’ <verse eid="DEU 28:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="DEU 28:68"/>Yahweh will send <char style="add">some of</char> you back to Egypt in ships, even though he promised that you would never <char style="add">be forced to</char> go there again. There in Egypt you will try to sell yourselves to become slaves of your enemies <char style="add">in order to have food to eat</char>, but no one will buy you. <char style="add">All those things will happen to you if you do not obey the laws that Yahweh is giving to you</char>.”<verse eid="DEU 28:68"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="DEU 29"/>
  <para style="s1">The agreement made in Moab</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 29:1"/>These are the things that the Israelis were required to do to keep the agreement that Yahweh was making with them. Moses/I commanded them to keep this agreement <char style="add">when they/we were</char> in the Moab region <char style="add">on the east side of the Jordan River</char>. This was in addition to the agreement that Yahweh had made with them/us at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char>.<verse eid="DEU 29:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 29:2"/>Moses/I summoned all the Israeli people and said to them, “You saw [SYN] for yourselves what Yahweh did to the king of Egypt and to his officials and to his entire country. <verse eid="DEU 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 29:3"/>You [SYN] saw all the plagues <char style="add">that Yahweh caused them to experience</char>, and all the various miracles [DOU] <char style="add">that Yahweh performed</char>. <verse eid="DEU 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 29:4"/>But until now, Yahweh has not enabled you to understand <char style="add">the meaning of</char> all that you have seen and heard. <verse eid="DEU 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 29:5"/>For 40 years Yahweh has led you while you traveled/walked through the desert. During that time, your clothes and your sandals have not worn out. <verse eid="DEU 29:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 29:6"/>You did not have bread to eat or wine or other fermented/strong drinks to drink, but Yahweh <char style="add">took care of you</char>, in order that you would know that he is your God.<verse eid="DEU 29:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 29:7"/>“And when we came to this place, Sihon, the king who ruled in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char>, and Og, the king who ruled the Bashan <char style="add">region</char>, came <char style="add">with their armies</char> to attack us, but we defeated them. <verse eid="DEU 29:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 29:8"/>We took/conquered their land and divided it among the tribes of Reuben and Gad, and half of the tribe of Manasseh.<verse eid="DEU 29:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 29:9"/>“So faithfully keep all of this agreement, in order that you will be successful in everything that you do. <verse eid="DEU 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 29:10"/>Today all of us are standing in the presence of Yahweh our God. The leaders of all our tribes, our elders, our officials, all you Israeli men, <verse eid="DEU 29:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 29:11"/>your wives, your children, and the foreigners who live among you and cut wood for you and carry water for you, are here. <verse eid="DEU 29:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 29:12"/><char style="add">We are here</char> today to promise to keep this solemn agreement with Yahweh. <verse eid="DEU 29:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 29:13"/><char style="add">He is making this agreement with you</char> in order to confirm that you are his people, and that he is your God. This agreement is what he promised you, and which is what he vowed to give to your ancestors Abraham, Isaac and Jacob. <verse eid="DEU 29:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 29:14"/>This agreement is not only with you. <verse eid="DEU 29:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 29:15"/>He is making this agreement with us <char style="add">who are here today</char> and also with our descendants who are not yet born.<verse eid="DEU 29:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 29:16"/>“You remember <char style="add">the things that our ancestors suffered</char> in Egypt, and how they traveled through the land that belonged to other nations <char style="add">after they came out of Egypt</char>. <verse eid="DEU 29:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 29:17"/>In those countries they saw those disgusting idols made of wood and stone and <char style="add">decorated with</char> silver and gold. <verse eid="DEU 29:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 29:18"/>So be sure that no man or woman or family or tribe that is here <char style="add">today</char> turns away from Yahweh our God, to worship/serve the gods of those nations. Doing that would be like a root <char style="add">of a plant that would grow</char> among you and bear poisonous and bitter fruit [MET].<verse eid="DEU 29:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 29:19"/>“Be sure that no one here today who hears this agreement thinks, ‘Everything will go well with me, even if I stubbornly do what I want to.’ If you are stubborn like that, the result will be that Yahweh will eventually get rid of all of you, both good people and evil people [MET]. <verse eid="DEU 29:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 29:20"/>Yahweh will not forgive anyone who is <char style="add">stubborn</char> like that. Instead, he will be extremely angry [DOU] with that person, and that person will experience all the curses that I have told you about, until Yahweh gets rid of that person and his family [IDM]. <verse eid="DEU 29:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 29:21"/>From all the tribes of Israel, Yahweh will separate that individual. Yahweh will cause him to experience all the disasters that I have listed in the agreement that states the things that Yahweh will do to curse <char style="add">those who disobey</char> the laws <char style="add">that I have written</char> in this scroll/book.<verse eid="DEU 29:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 29:22"/>“In the future, your descendants and people from other countries will see the disasters and the illnesses that Yahweh has caused to happen to you. <verse eid="DEU 29:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 29:23"/>They will see that all your land has been ruined by burning sulfur and salt. Nothing will have been planted. Not even weeds will grow there. Your land will resemble Sodom and Gomorrah <char style="add">cities</char>, and Admah and Zeboiim <char style="add">cities</char>, which Yahweh destroyed when he was very angry [DOU] <char style="add">with the people who lived there</char>. <verse eid="DEU 29:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 29:24"/>And the people from those other nations will ask, ‘Why did Yahweh do this to this land? Why was he very angry <char style="add">with the people who lived here</char>?’<verse eid="DEU 29:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 29:25"/>“Then other people will reply, ‘It is because they refused to keep the agreement that Yahweh, the God whom their ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, had made with them when he brought them out of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 29:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 29:26"/>Instead, they served/worshiped other gods that they had never worshiped before, gods that Yahweh had told them not to worship. <verse eid="DEU 29:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 29:27"/>So, Yahweh became very angry with the Israeli people in this land, and he caused them to experience all the disasters that their leader warned them about. <verse eid="DEU 29:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 29:28"/>Yahweh became extremely angry [DOU] with them and took/yanked them [MET] out of their land and banished them into another land, and they are still there.’<verse eid="DEU 29:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 29:29"/>“<char style="add">There are some</char> things that Yahweh our God has ◄kept secret/not revealed►, but he has revealed his laws to us, and <char style="add">he expects</char> us and our descendants to obey them forever.”<verse eid="DEU 29:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="DEU 30"/>
  <para style="s1">Bringing them back to Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 30:1"/>“I have now told you about the ways that Yahweh our God will bless you <char style="add">if you obey him</char> and the ways that he will curse you <char style="add">if you disobey him</char>. I am saying that you must choose which you want. But when <char style="add">you choose not to obey his laws</char>, some day you will be living in the countries to which he will scatter you, and you will remember <char style="add">what I told you</char>. <verse eid="DEU 30:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 30:2"/>Then, if you return to Yahweh our God and faithfully [IDM] obey all that I have today commanded you to do, <verse eid="DEU 30:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 30:3"/>he will be merciful to you. He will bring you back from the nations to which he scattered you, and he will cause you to be prosperous again. <verse eid="DEU 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 30:4"/>Even if you have been scattered to the most distant places on the earth, Yahweh our God will gather you from there and bring you back <char style="add">to your land</char>. <verse eid="DEU 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 30:5"/>He will enable you to possess again the land where your ancestors lived. And he will cause you to be more prosperous and more numerous than you are now. <verse eid="DEU 30:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 30:6"/>Yahweh our God will change [MET] your inner beings, with the result that you will love him more than you love anything else and want to do only what he wants you to do. And then you will continue to live in that land. <verse eid="DEU 30:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 30:7"/>Yahweh our God will cause your enemies and those who oppressed/persecuted you to experience all the disasters that I have told you about. <verse eid="DEU 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 30:8"/>You will do what Yahweh wants you to do, as you did before, and you will obey all the commands that I have given to you today. <verse eid="DEU 30:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 30:9"/>Yahweh our God will cause you to be very successful in all that you do. You will have many children [IDM], and a lot of cattle, and you will have abundant crops. He will again be happy to enable you to prosper, just like he was happy to enable your ancestors to prosper. <verse eid="DEU 30:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 30:10"/><char style="add">But he will do those things only</char> if you do what he has told you to do, and if you obey all his rules and regulations that I have written about <char style="add">in this scroll</char>, and if you will love him more than you love anything else and want to do only what he wants you to do.<verse eid="DEU 30:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Choose life, not death</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 30:11"/>The commands that I am giving to you today are not very difficult for you <char style="add">to obey</char>, and they are not <char style="add">difficult to know</char>. <verse eid="DEU 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 30:12"/>They are not in heaven, with the result that you need to say, ‘◄Who will need to go up to heaven for us to bring them <char style="add">down here to us</char> in order that we can hear them and obey them?/Someone will need to go up to heaven for us to bring them <char style="add">down here to us</char> in order that we can hear them and obey them.►’ [RHQ] <verse eid="DEU 30:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 30:13"/>And they are not on the other side of the sea, with the result that you need to say, ‘◄Who will need to cross the sea for us and bring them back to us, in order that we can hear them and obey them?/Someone will need to cross the sea for us and bring them back to us, in order that we can hear them and obey them.►’ [RHQ] <verse eid="DEU 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 30:14"/><char style="add">You do not need to do that because</char> his commands are here with you. You know them [MTY] and you have ◄memorized them/put them in your minds►. So you can <char style="add">easily</char> obey them.<verse eid="DEU 30:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 30:15"/>So listen! Today I am allowing you to choose between <char style="add">doing what is</char> evil and <char style="add">doing what is</char> good, between what will enable you to live <char style="add">for a long time</char> and <char style="add">what will cause you</char> to die <char style="add">while you are still young</char>. <verse eid="DEU 30:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 30:16"/><char style="add">I say again</char>, if you obey the commands of Yahweh our God that I am giving to you today, and if you love him and conduct your lives as he wants you to do, and if you obey all his rules and regulations, you will prosper and become very numerous, and Yahweh our God will bless you in the land that you are about to enter and possess.<verse eid="DEU 30:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 30:17"/>But if you turn away <char style="add">from Yahweh</char> and refuse to heed what he says, and if you allow yourselves to be led away to worship other gods, <verse eid="DEU 30:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 30:18"/>I am warning you today that you will <char style="add">soon</char> die. You will not live for a long time in the land that you are about to cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to enter and possess.<verse eid="DEU 30:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 30:19"/>I am requesting that <char style="add">everyone in</char> heaven and the earth testify to you, that today I am allowing you to choose whether you <char style="add">want to</char> live for a long time or to soon die, whether <char style="add">you want Yahweh to</char> bless you or to curse you. So choose to live. <verse eid="DEU 30:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 30:20"/><char style="add">Choose to</char> love Yahweh our God, and to obey him [MTY], and to ◄be faithful to/have a close relationship with► him. If you do that, you and your descendants will live for a long time in the land that Yahweh solemnly promised to your ancestors Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, that he would give to them.”<verse eid="DEU 30:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="DEU 31"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses appointed Joshua to succeed him</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 31:1"/>When Moses/I finished saying all that to the Israeli people, <verse eid="DEU 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 31:2"/>he/I said to them, “Now I am 120 years old. I am no longer able to go everywhere <char style="add">that you go</char> (OR, to be your leader). Furthermore, Yahweh has told me that I will not cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="DEU 31:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 31:3"/>But Yahweh our God will go ahead of you. He will <char style="add">enable you to</char> destroy the nations that are living there, in order that you can occupy their land. Joshua will be your leader, which is what Yahweh already told me. <verse eid="DEU 31:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 31:4"/>Yahweh will do to those nations what he did to Sihon and Og, the two kings of the Amor people-group when he destroyed their armies [MTY]. <verse eid="DEU 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 31:5"/>Yahweh will enable you to conquer those nations, but you must <char style="add">kill all of the people of those nations, which is</char> what I have commanded you to do. <verse eid="DEU 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 31:6"/>Be brave and confident. Do not be afraid of those people. <char style="add">Do not forget that</char> it is Yahweh our God who will go with you. He will always help [LIT] you and never abandon you.”<verse eid="DEU 31:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 31:7"/>Then Moses/I summoned Joshua, and while all the Israeli people were listening, he/I said to him, “Be brave and confident. You are the one who will lead these people into the land that Yahweh promised to our ancestors that he would give to them, and you will enable them to occupy it. <verse eid="DEU 31:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 31:8"/>It is Yahweh who will go ahead of you. He will be with you. He will always help [LIT] you. He will never abandon you. So do not be afraid or dismayed.”<verse eid="DEU 31:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The laws are to be read periodically</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 31:9"/>Moses/I wrote down all these laws <char style="add">on two scrolls</char> and gave <char style="add">one scroll</char> to the priests, who carried the chest containing the Ten Commandments, and <char style="add">gave the other scroll</char> to the Israeli elders. <verse eid="DEU 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 31:10"/>Moses/I told them, “At the end of every seven years, at the time that all debts are canceled, <char style="add">read this to the people</char> during the Festival of <char style="add">Living in Temporary</char> Shelters. <verse eid="DEU 31:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 31:11"/>Read it to all the Israeli people when they gather at the place that Yahweh chooses for them to worship him. <verse eid="DEU 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 31:12"/>Gather together everyone—men, women, children, even the foreigners <char style="add">who are living</char> in your towns—in order that they may hear <char style="add">these laws</char> and learn to revere Yahweh our God, and to faithfully obey everything that is written in these laws. <verse eid="DEU 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 31:13"/><char style="add">If they do that</char>, your descendants who have never known these laws will hear them and will also learn to revere Yahweh our God, during all the years that they live in the land that you are about to cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to occupy.”<verse eid="DEU 31:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Moses predicted their disobedience</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 31:14"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Listen carefully. You will soon die. Summon Joshua, and you go to the Sacred Tent with him, in order that I may appoint him <char style="add">to be the new leader</char>.” So Joshua and Moses/I went to the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="DEU 31:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 31:15"/>There Yahweh appeared to them/us in a pillar of cloud, and that cloud was close to the door of the tent. <verse eid="DEU 31:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 31:16"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, “You will soon die [EUP]. Then these people will become unfaithful [MET] to me. They will abandon me and ◄break/stop obeying► the agreement that I made with them. They will begin to worship the foreign/pagan gods <char style="add">that are worshiped by the people</char> of the land that they will enter. <verse eid="DEU 31:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 31:17"/>When that happens, I will become very angry with them. I will abandon them [DOU] and I will no longer help them [IDM], and I will destroy them {they will be destroyed}. Many terrible things will happen to them, with the result that they will say, ‘<char style="add">We are certain that</char> [RHQ] these things are happening to us because our God is no longer with us.’ <verse eid="DEU 31:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 31:18"/>And because of all the evil things that they will have done, and <char style="add">especially because</char> they will have started to worship other gods, I will refuse to help [IDM] them.<verse eid="DEU 31:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 31:19"/>“So, <char style="add">I am going to give you</char> a song. Write it <char style="add">on a scroll</char> and teach it to the Israeli people and cause them to memorize it. It will be like a witness that accuses them. <verse eid="DEU 31:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 31:20"/>I am about to take them into a very fertile [IDM] land, a land that I solemnly promised their ancestors that I would give to them. There they will have plenty to eat, with the result that their <char style="add">stomachs</char> will <char style="add">always</char> be full and they will become fat. But then they will turn to other gods and start to worship them, and they will despise me and ◄break/stop obeying► the agreement that I made with them. <verse eid="DEU 31:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 31:21"/>And they will experience many terrible disasters. After that happens, their descendants will never forget this song, and it will be like a witness <char style="add">that says, ‘Now you know why Yahweh punished your ancestors</char>.’ I will soon take them into the land that I vowed that I would give to them; but now, before I do that, I know what they are thinking <char style="add">that they will do when they are living there</char>.” <verse eid="DEU 31:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 31:22"/>So on the day that <char style="add">Yahweh gave Moses/me this song</char>, he/I wrote it down, and he/I taught it to the Israeli people.<verse eid="DEU 31:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 31:23"/>Then Yahweh ◄appointed/set apart► Joshua and said to him, “Be brave and confident, because you will lead the Israeli people into the land that I vowed that I would give to them. And I will be with you.”<verse eid="DEU 31:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 31:24"/>Then Moses/I finished writing on a scroll all the laws that Yahweh had told to him/me. <verse eid="DEU 31:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 31:25"/>Then Moses/I told the descendants of Levi, who were carrying the Sacred Chest that contained the Ten Commandments, <verse eid="DEU 31:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 31:26"/>“Take this scroll on which these laws <char style="add">are written</char>, and place it beside the Sacred Chest that contains the agreement that Yahweh our God made with you, in order that it may remain there to testify <char style="add">about what Yahweh will do</char> to the people <char style="add">if they disobey him</char>. <verse eid="DEU 31:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 31:27"/><char style="add">I say this</char> because I know that these people are very stubborn [DOU]. They have rebelled against Yahweh all during the time that I have been <char style="add">with them</char>, and they will rebel much more after I die! <verse eid="DEU 31:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 31:28"/>So gather all the elders of the tribes and your officials, in order that I can tell them the words <char style="add">of this song</char>, and request all those who are in heaven and on the earth to be witnesses to testify against these people. <verse eid="DEU 31:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 31:29"/>I say that because I know that after I die, the people will become very wicked. They will turn away from doing everything that I have commanded them to do. And in the future, because of all the evil things that they will do, they will cause Yahweh to become angry with them. And he will cause them to experience disasters.”<verse eid="DEU 31:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The song that Moses sang to them</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 31:30"/>Then, while all the Israeli people listened, Moses/I sang/recited this entire song to them:<verse eid="DEU 31:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 31"/>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="DEU 32"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 32:1"/>“Listen to me, <char style="add">all you who are in the</char> heavens,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:1">and <char style="add">all you who are on the</char> earth, listen to what I say [MTY].<verse eid="DEU 32:1"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 32:2"/>I wish/desire that my teaching will fall on you like rain drops</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:2">or be like dew on the ground,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:2">and be like a gentle rain on the young plants,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:2">like showers on the grass.<verse eid="DEU 32:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 32:3"/>I will praise Yahweh [MTY].</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:3">And <char style="add">all you people should</char> tell others that our God is very great.<verse eid="DEU 32:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 32:4"/>He is like a rock [MET] <char style="add">under which we are protected</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:4">
    <char style="add">everything</char> that he does is perfect and completely just/fair [DOU].</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:4">He always does what he says that he will do;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:4">he never does anything that is wrong.<verse eid="DEU 32:4"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 32:5"/>“But <char style="add">you Israeli people</char> have been very unfaithful to him;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:5">because of your sins, you no longer <char style="add">deserve to</char> be his children.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:5">You are extremely wicked and deceitful [DOU].<verse eid="DEU 32:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 32:6"/>You foolish and senseless [DOU] people,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:6">◄is this the way that you should repay Yahweh <char style="add">for all that he has done for you</char>?/this is certainly not the way that you should repay Yahweh <char style="add">for all that he has done for you</char>.► [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:6">He is your father; he created you [RHQ];</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:6">he caused you to become a nation.<verse eid="DEU 32:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 32:7"/>“Think about <char style="add">what happened</char> long ago;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:7">consider what happened to your ancestors.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:7">Ask your parents, and they will inform you;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:7">ask the older people, and they will tell you.<verse eid="DEU 32:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 32:8"/>When God, who is greater than any other god, long ago divided the people into groups,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:8">he assigned to the nations their land.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:8">He determined where each people-group should live</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:8">and ◄assigned to/chose for► each people-group a god/angel.<verse eid="DEU 32:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 32:9"/>But Yahweh decided that we would be his people;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:9">he chose <char style="add">us, the descendants of</char> Jacob, to belong to him.<verse eid="DEU 32:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 32:10"/>“He saw <char style="add">our ancestors</char> when they were in a desert,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:10">wandering in a land ◄that was desolate/where no people lived►.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:10">He protected them and took care of them,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:10">as every person takes good care of his own eyes. [SIM, IDM]<verse eid="DEU 32:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 32:11"/>
    <char style="add">Yahweh protected his people</char> just like an eagle encourages its babies <char style="add">to fly</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:11">and flutters over them [MET],</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:11">spreading its wings and catching them <char style="add">if they start to fall</char>.<verse eid="DEU 32:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 32:12"/>Yahweh was the only one who led them;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:12">no other foreign god helped him.<verse eid="DEU 32:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 32:13"/>“<char style="add">After they entered the land that Yahweh promised to give to them</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:13">Yahweh enabled them to rule the hilly areas;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:13">they ate the crops that grew in the fields.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:13">They found honey in the rocks,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:13">and their olive trees [MTY] grew <char style="add">even</char> in stony ground.<verse eid="DEU 32:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 32:14"/>The cows gave them plenty of curds/yogurt, the goats gave them plenty of milk,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:14">they had well-fed sheep and cattle,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:14">they had very good wheat,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:14">and they made delicious wine from their grapes.<verse eid="DEU 32:14"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 32:15"/>“The Israeli people became rich and prosperous,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:15">but then they rebelled against God;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:15">they abandoned him, the one who created them,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:15">the one who powerfully saves them.<verse eid="DEU 32:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 32:16"/>So he abandoned them because they started to worship other/strange gods.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:16">Because of their worshiping disgusting idols,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:16">he became angry.<verse eid="DEU 32:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 32:17"/>They offered sacrifices to gods who were <char style="add">really</char> demons,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:17">gods that their ancestors had never known;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:17">they offered sacrifices to gods that they had recently found out about,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:17">gods whom your ancestors had never revered.<verse eid="DEU 32:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 32:18"/>They forgot <char style="add">the true</char> God, the one who protects them [MET],</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:18">the one who created them and caused them to live.<verse eid="DEU 32:18"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 32:19"/>“When Yahweh saw that <char style="add">they had abandoned him</char>, he became angry,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:19">so he rejected <char style="add">the Israeli people, who are like</char> his sons and daughters.<verse eid="DEU 32:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 32:20"/>He said, ‘They are very wicked/stubborn people,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:20">very unfaithful;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:20">so I will no longer help them,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:20">and then I will watch and see what happens to them.<verse eid="DEU 32:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 32:21"/>They <note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">32:21 </char><char style="fq" closed="false">Because they </char><char style="ft" closed="false">hey</char></note>made me very angry because of their worshiping idols, which are not really gods;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:21">they have caused me to be <char style="add">jealous [MET] because I want them to worship only me</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:21">So now, in order to cause them to become jealous,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:21">I will send <char style="add">to attack them an army of</char> a nation of worthless and foolish people.<verse eid="DEU 32:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 32:22"/>I will be very angry, and I will destroy them</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:22">like a fire that will burn on the earth and all the way down to the place where dead people are [MET];</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:22">that fire will destroy the earth and everything that grows on it,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:22">and it will even burn what is down under the mountains.<verse eid="DEU 32:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 32:23"/>I will cause them to experience many disasters;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:23">
    <char style="add">they will feel as though</char> [MET] I am shooting all my arrows at them.<verse eid="DEU 32:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 32:24"/>They will die because of being hungry and because of having hot fevers</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:24">and because of terrible diseases;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:24">I will send wild animals to attack [MTY] them,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:24">and poisonous snakes to bite [MTY] them.<verse eid="DEU 32:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 32:25"/>Outside <char style="add">their houses, their enemies</char> will kill them [MTY] with swords,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:25">and in their homes, <char style="add">their enemies will cause</char> them to be terrified.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:25">Their enemies will kill young men and young women,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:25">and they will kill infants and old people with gray hair.<verse eid="DEU 32:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 32:26"/>I wanted to scatter the Israeli people to distant countries</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:26">in order that no one would ever remember them.<verse eid="DEU 32:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 32:27"/>But <char style="add">if I did that</char>, their enemies would wrongly boast</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:27">that they were the ones who had <char style="add">gotten rid of my people</char>;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:27">they would say, “We [SYN] are the ones who defeated them;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:27">it was not Yahweh who has done all these things.”’<verse eid="DEU 32:27"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 32:28"/>You Israelis are a nation of people who do not have any sense.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:28">None of you is wise.<verse eid="DEU 32:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 32:29"/>If you were wise, you would understand <char style="add">why you would be punished</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:29">you would have realized what was going to happen to you.<verse eid="DEU 32:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="DEU 32:30"/>
    <char style="add">You would have realized</char> why 1,000 <char style="add">of your soldiers</char> would be defeated by only one <char style="add">of the enemy soldiers</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:30">and why two of your enemies would chase away 10,000 <char style="add">Israeli soldiers</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:30">
    <char style="add">You would realize that this would happen</char> only if God, the one who always defended you [MET], had allowed your enemies to defeat you,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:30">because he had abandoned you.<verse eid="DEU 32:30"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="DEU 32:31"/>Your enemies know that their gods are not powerful like Yahweh, our God,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:31">
    <char style="add">so their gods could not have defeated us Israelis</char>.<verse eid="DEU 32:31"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="DEU 32:32"/>Your enemies are like [MET] grapevines planted near <char style="add">the ruins of</char> Sodom and Gomorrah <char style="add">cities</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:32">the grapes from those vines are bitter and poisonous;<verse eid="DEU 32:32"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="DEU 32:33"/>the wine <char style="add">from those grapes</char> is like the poison of snakes [DOU].<verse eid="DEU 32:33"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="DEU 32:34"/>
    <char style="add">“Yahweh says</char>, ‘I know [RHQ] <char style="add">what I have planned to do to the Israeli people and to their enemies</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:34">and those plans are so secure <char style="add">that it as though he locked them up</char> [MET].<verse eid="DEU 32:34"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="DEU 32:35"/>I am the one who will get revenge and pay those enemies back for what they have done <char style="add">to my people</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:35">at the right time for them to be punished [IDM];</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:35">they will soon experience disasters,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:35">and I will punish/destroy them quickly.’<verse eid="DEU 32:35"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="DEU 32:36"/>“But Yahweh will see that you who are truly his people, who ◄are innocent/have not done things that are wrong►,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:36">and he will be merciful to you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:36">And he will see that you are helpless,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:36">and that there are very few of you, slaves or free people, who are still alive.<verse eid="DEU 32:36"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="DEU 32:37"/>Then Yahweh will ask his people, ‘Where are the gods</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:37">that you thought would protect you [MET]?<verse eid="DEU 32:37"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="DEU 32:38"/>You gave to those gods the best parts of the animals that you sacrificed,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:38">and you poured out wine for them to drink.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:38">So, they should begin to help you;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:38">they should be the ones who will protect you!<verse eid="DEU 32:38"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="DEU 32:39"/>“But now you will realize that I, only I, am God;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:39">there is no other god who is <char style="add">a real</char> god.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:39">I am the one who can kill people and who can cause people to live;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:39">I can wound people, and I can heal people,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:39">and there is no one who can prevent me from doing those things.<verse eid="DEU 32:39"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="DEU 32:40"/>I raise my hand toward heaven and solemnly declare</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:40">that just as sure as I live forever,<verse eid="DEU 32:40"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="DEU 32:41"/>that when I sharpen my sword,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:41">as I [SYN] prepare to punish people,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:41">I will get revenge on my enemies;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:41">I will pay back those who hate me.<verse eid="DEU 32:41"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="DEU 32:42"/>I will kill all <char style="add">of my enemies</char> with a sword;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:42">it will be as though I had arrows that will be covered with their blood.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:42">I will kill [MTY] all those whom I capture</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:42">and cut off their leaders’ heads.’<verse eid="DEU 32:42"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="DEU 32:43"/>“You people of all nations, you as well as his people should praise Yahweh,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:43">because Yahweh gets revenge on those who kill the people who serve him;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 32:43">and he cleanses his people’s land</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 32:43">which has become defiled because of their sins.”<verse eid="DEU 32:43"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="DEU 32:44"/>Joshua and Moses/I recited the words of that song while the Israeli people were listening. <verse eid="DEU 32:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="DEU 32:45"/>When they/we finished reciting to the Israeli people the words of this song, <verse eid="DEU 32:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="DEU 32:46"/>Moses/I said, “Never forget all these commands that I have been giving you today. Teach these laws to your children, in order that they will faithfully obey all of them. <verse eid="DEU 32:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="DEU 32:47"/>These instructions are very important [LIT]. If <char style="add">you obey</char> them, you will live a long time in the land that you are about to cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to occupy.”<verse eid="DEU 32:47"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God told Moses that he would see the land from far away</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="DEU 32:48"/>On that same day, Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="DEU 32:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="DEU 32:49"/>“Go to the Abarim Mountain range <char style="add">here</char> in the Moab region, across from Jericho. Climb Nebo Mountain, and look <char style="add">toward the west</char> to see Canaan land, the land that I am about to give to the Israeli people. <verse eid="DEU 32:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="DEU 32:50"/>You will die on that mountain [EUP, DOU], like your <char style="add">older</char> brother Aaron died on Hor Mountain. <verse eid="DEU 32:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="DEU 32:51"/>You will die because both of you disobeyed me in the presence of the Israeli people, when you all were at Meribah Springs near Kadesh <char style="add">town</char> in the Zin Desert. You did not honor and respect me in the presence of the Israeli people in the way that I deserve because I am God. <verse eid="DEU 32:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="DEU 32:52"/><char style="add">When you are on that mountain where I told you to go</char>, you will see in the distance in front of you the land that I am about to give to the Israeli people, but you will not enter it.”<verse eid="DEU 32:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 32"/>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="DEU 33"/>
  <para style="s1">Moses blessed the Israeli tribes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 33:1"/>Before God’s prophet Moses died, he <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless the Israeli people. <verse eid="DEU 33:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 33:2"/>This is what he said:</para>
  <para style="b" vid="DEU 33:2"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:2">“Yahweh came <char style="add">and spoke</char> to us at Sinai <char style="add">Mountain</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:2">he <char style="add">came like</char> [MET] the sun rises in the Edom <char style="add">region</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:2">and like his light shone on us when we were <char style="add">in the desert</char> near Paran Mountain <char style="add">after we left Sinai Mountain</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:2">He came with 10,000 angels,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:2">and there was a flaming fire at his right side.<verse eid="DEU 33:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 33:3"/>Yahweh truly loves his people,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:3">and protects [MTY] all those who belong to him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:3">So they prostrate themselves in front of him,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:3">and they listen to his instructions.<verse eid="DEU 33:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 33:4"/>I gave them laws to obey,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:4">laws that would be the most precious thing that <char style="add">the descendants of</char> Jacob owned.<verse eid="DEU 33:4"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 33:5"/>So Yahweh became the king of his Israeli people</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:5">when all the tribes and their leaders were gathered together.<verse eid="DEU 33:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 33:6"/>
    <char style="add">I say this about the tribe of</char> Reuben:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:6">I desire/hope that their tribe will never disappear,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:6">but they will never become numerous.<verse eid="DEU 33:6"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 33:7"/>“ say this about <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Judah:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:7">Yahweh, listen to them when they call out <char style="add">for help</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:7">and unite them with the other tribes again.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:7">Fight for them,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:7">and help them to fight against their enemies.<verse eid="DEU 33:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 33:8"/>I say this about <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Levi:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:8">Yahweh, give to those who are dedicated to you the sacred stones <char style="add">that they will use to find out what you want to be done</char>;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:8">You tested them at a spring in the desert, a spring that they named Massah and also named Meribah</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:8">
    <char style="add">to find out if they would ◄remain loyal to/continue to obey► you</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 33:9"/>The tribe of Levi did what you told them to do</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:9">and obeyed the agreement that you <char style="add">made with the Israeli people</char>;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:9">those laws were more important to them [HYP]</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:9">than their siblings and parents and children.<verse eid="DEU 33:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 33:10"/>The tribe of Levi will teach the Israeli people [DOU] your rules and regulations,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:10">and they are the ones who will burn incense and who will completely burn on the altar the offerings <char style="add">that the people bring</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 33:11"/>Yahweh, bless their work</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:11">and ◄accept/be pleased with► all that they do.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:11">Crush/Destroy all their enemies;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:11">do not enable their enemies to be able to fight against them again.<verse eid="DEU 33:11"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 33:12"/>I say this about <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Benjamin:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:12">They are the tribe that Yahweh loves;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:12">he keeps them safe.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:12">He protects them continually,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:12">and he lives among their hills [MET].<verse eid="DEU 33:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="DEU 33:13"/>“ say this about <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Joseph:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:13">I desire/hope that Yahweh will bless their land</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:13">by giving them rain/dew from the sky</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:13">and water from deep <char style="add">in the ground</char>,<verse eid="DEU 33:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="DEU 33:14"/>by giving them good fruit <char style="add">ripened </char> by the sun</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:14">and good crops at harvest time.<verse eid="DEU 33:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="DEU 33:15"/>I desire/hope that very nice fruit will grow on trees in their ancient mountains/hills [DOU],<verse eid="DEU 33:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="DEU 33:16"/>and that their land will be have many good crops,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:16">blessed by <char style="add">Yahweh</char>, the one who appeared to me in a burning bush.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:16">I desire/hope that Yahweh will bless the tribes of Joseph in all those ways,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:16">because he was the leaders of his <char style="add">older</char> brothers <char style="add">when they were in Egypt</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="DEU 33:17"/>The descendants of Joseph will be as strong as [SIM] a bull;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:17">
    <char style="add">with their weapons they will wound their enemies, like</char> [MET] a wild ox <char style="add">gores other animals</char> with its horns.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:17">They will force other people-groups,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:17">all of them, to be exiled to the most distant places on the earth.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:17">That is what <char style="add">the descendants of the two sons of Joseph</char> will do,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:17">the ten thousands <char style="add">of the tribe</char> of Ephraim and the thousands <char style="add">of the tribe</char> of Manasseh.<verse eid="DEU 33:17"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="DEU 33:18"/>“ say this about <char style="add">the tribes of</char> Zebulun <char style="add">and Issachar</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:18">I desire/hope that the people of Zebulun will prosper in their travels <char style="add">across the seas</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:18">and that the people of Issachar will prosper while they stay at home <char style="add">and take care of their cattle and crops</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="DEU 33:19"/>They will invite people <char style="add">from the other Israeli tribes</char> to the mountain <char style="add">where they worship Yahweh</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:19">and they will offer the correct/proper sacrifices to him.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:19">They will become rich from <char style="add">the work that they do on</char> the seas</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:19">and from <char style="add">the things that they make from</char> (OR, <char style="add">find in</char>) the sand <char style="add">on the beaches</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="DEU 33:20"/>“ say this about <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Gad:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:20">Praise <char style="add">Yahweh</char>, the one who made their <char style="add">territory</char> large.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:20">The people of their tribe <char style="add">will attack their enemies fiercely</char> [SIM] like a lion that crouches,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:20">waiting to tear off the arm or the scalp <char style="add">of some animal</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="DEU 33:21"/>They chose the best part of the land for themselves;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:21">
    <char style="add">a large share of the land</char>, a share that should be given to a leader was allotted to them.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:21">When the leaders of the tribes of Israel <char style="add">gathered together</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:21">they decided that the tribe of Gad should have a large share of the land.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:21">The tribe of Gad obeyed the commands of Yahweh and the things that he decided that they should do.<verse eid="DEU 33:21"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="DEU 33:22"/>“ say this about <char style="add">the tribe</char> of Dan:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:22">The people of the tribe of Dan are like [SIM] a young lion;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:22">they leap from <char style="add">their caves in the</char> Bashan <char style="add">region to attack their enemies</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:22"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="DEU 33:23"/>“ say this about <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Naphtali:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:23">
    <char style="add">The people of the tribe of</char> Naphtali have been blessed by Yahweh, who has been very kind to them;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:23">their land extends far south from Lake <char style="add">Galilee</char>.<verse eid="DEU 33:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="DEU 33:24"/>“ say this about <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Asher:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:24">May Yahweh bless the descendants of Asher more than he will bless the other tribes.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:24">May he favor Asher’s descendants most of all.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:24">I desire/hope that their land will <char style="add">be filled with olive trees that will</char> produce a lot of [IDM] <char style="add">olives to make olive</char> oil.<verse eid="DEU 33:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="DEU 33:25"/>Their <char style="add">towns will be protected by high walls with gates that have</char> bronze and iron bars;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:25">I desire/hope that they will be strong and secure/protected all the time that they are alive.<verse eid="DEU 33:25"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="DEU 33:26"/>“You people of Israel, there is no god like your God,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:26">who rides majestically across the sky to help you.<verse eid="DEU 33:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="DEU 33:27"/>God, who lives forever, is the one who ◄gives you refuge/protects you►;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:27">
    <char style="add">it is as though</char> he puts his everlasting arms under you <char style="add">to support you</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:27">He will expel your enemies while you advance;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:27">he has told you to destroy all of them.<verse eid="DEU 33:27"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="DEU 33:28"/>So, you Israeli people will live safely;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:28">you descendants of Jacob will not be disturbed by others;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:28">in the land where <char style="add">you will live</char>, there will be plenty of grain and wine,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:28">and there will be plenty of rain.<verse eid="DEU 33:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="DEU 33:29"/>You people of Israel, Yahweh ◄has blessed/is pleased with► you.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">There is certainly [RHQ] no nation like your nation,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">whom Yahweh has rescued <char style="add">from being slaves in Egypt</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:29">
    <char style="add">He will be like</char> [MET] a shield to protect you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">and like [MET] a sword to enable you to defeat <char style="add">your enemies</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="DEU 33:29">Your enemies will come to you begging for you <char style="add">to act mercifully toward them</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="DEU 33:29">but you will trample on their backs/necks.”<verse eid="DEU 33:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 33"/>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="DEU 34"/>
  <para style="s1">How Moses died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="DEU 34:1"/>Then Moses climbed up from the plains in the Moab <char style="add">region</char> to the top of Pisgah Peak on Nebo Mountain, across <char style="add">the Jordan River</char> from Jericho. There Yahweh showed him all the land <char style="add">that the Israelis would occupy</char>. He showed him the Gilead <char style="add">region</char> as far north as Dan <char style="add">city</char>; <verse eid="DEU 34:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="DEU 34:2"/>all <char style="add">the land that the tribe of</char> Naphtali would occupy; all the land <char style="add">that the tribes</char> of Ephraim and Manasseh <char style="add">had occupied</char>; all the land <char style="add">that the tribe of</char> Judah would occupy as far west as the Mediterranean sea; <verse eid="DEU 34:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="DEU 34:3"/>the desert <char style="add">area in the south part of Judah</char>; and the <char style="add">Jordan</char> Valley that extends from Jericho <char style="add">in the north</char> to Zoar <char style="add">city in the south</char>. <verse eid="DEU 34:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="DEU 34:4"/>Then Yahweh said to him, “You have now seen this land that I solemnly promised to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, saying ‘I will give it to your descendants.’ I have allowed you to see it <char style="add">from a distance</char>, but you will not go there.”<verse eid="DEU 34:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="DEU 34:5"/>So Moses, who <char style="add">always</char> served Yahweh <char style="add">faithfully</char>, died there <char style="add">on that mountain</char> in the Moab <char style="add">region</char>, which is what Yahweh said would happen. <verse eid="DEU 34:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="DEU 34:6"/>Yahweh buried Moses’ body in a valley in the Moab <char style="add">region</char>, opposite/near Beth-Peor <char style="add">town</char>, but no one to this day knows where Yahweh buried him. <verse eid="DEU 34:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="DEU 34:7"/>Moses was 120 years old when he died, but he was still very strong, and he could still see [MTY] very well. <verse eid="DEU 34:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="DEU 34:8"/>The Israeli people mourned for him in the plains of the Moab <char style="add">region</char> for 30 days.<verse eid="DEU 34:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="DEU 34:9"/>God caused Joshua to be very wise, because Moses had put his hands on Joshua <char style="add">to appoint him to be their new leader</char>. The Israeli people obeyed Joshua, and they obeyed all the commands that Yahweh had given to Moses to tell to the Israeli people.<verse eid="DEU 34:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="DEU 34:10"/>Since the time that Moses <char style="add">lived</char>, there has never been a prophet in Israel like him. Yahweh spoke to him face-to-face/directly. <verse eid="DEU 34:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="DEU 34:11"/>No other prophet has performed all the kinds of [DOU] miracles that Yahweh sent Moses to perform in front of the king of Egypt, his officials, and all [HYP] the people of Egypt. <verse eid="DEU 34:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="DEU 34:12"/>No other prophet has been able to do all the great and terrifying things that Moses did while all the Israelis watched.<verse eid="DEU 34:12"/></para>
  <chapter eid="DEU 34"/>
</usx>
