<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="HEB" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">HEBREWS</para>
  <para style="toc1">Hebrews</para>
  <para style="toc2">Hebrews</para>
  <para style="toc3">Heb</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book is a letter that was written to Jewish believers. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Hebrews</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="HEB 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Hebrews 1:1-3</para>
  <para style="s1">God formerly communicated with us through the prophets, but now he has communicated with us through his son, who is just like God.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 1:1"/>Long ago God communicated frequently to our ancestors in various ways by what the prophets <char style="add">said and wrote</char>. <verse eid="HEB 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 1:2"/>But now when this final age <char style="add">is beginning</char>, God has communicated to us <char style="add">just once</char> by means of what ◄his Son/the man who was also God► <char style="add">said and did. God</char> appointed him in order that he would possess everything <char style="add">that truly belongs to God. God also appointed</char> him in order that he would create the universe. <verse eid="HEB 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 1:3"/>He manifests God’s glory. He exactly represents <char style="add">what God is like</char>. He ◄sustains everything by means of his powerful words. When he had <char style="add">enabled people to be</char> freed from the <char style="add">guilt of</char> their sins [MET], he sat down in heaven [EUP] <char style="add">to rule</char> at the place of greatest honor [MTY] with God [MTY].<verse eid="HEB 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s son is greater than the angels.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 1:4-14">Hebrews 1:4-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 1:4"/>By doing that, he <char style="add">showed that he</char> was very much greater than the angels, to the extent that his relationship [MTY] <char style="add">to God, as his Son</char>, is more excellent than the relationship the angels <char style="add">have to God</char>. <verse eid="HEB 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 1:5"/><char style="add">We know that</char> because <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char> no one [RHQ] ever reported that God said to any angel <char style="add">what he said to his Son</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:5">You <char style="add">(sg)</char> are my Son!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:5">Today I have declared to all that I am your Father [DOU]!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:5">And he said in another Scripture passage,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:5">I will be his Father,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:5">and he will be my Son [DOU].<verse eid="HEB 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 1:6"/>And <char style="add">we know his Son is greater than the angels because in</char> another <char style="add">Scripture passage someone wrote this about God’s esteemed Son</char>, when God was about to send him into the world:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:6">All God’s angels must worship him.<verse eid="HEB 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 1:7"/>
    <char style="add">And in the Scriptures it is written that</char> someone said this about the angels:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:7">
    <char style="add">God</char> makes the <char style="add">angels</char> who serve him <char style="add">to be changeable like</char> [MET] winds and flames of fire.<verse eid="HEB 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 1:8"/>But on the other hand, <char style="add">in the Scriptures it is written that God said</char> this to his Son:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:8">You <char style="add">(sg)</char> who are <char style="add">also</char> God will rule forever [MTY],</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:8">and you will reign righteously over your kingdom [MTY].<verse eid="HEB 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 1:9"/>You have loved <char style="add">people’s</char> righteous <char style="add">deeds</char> and you have hated <char style="add">people’s</char> lawless <char style="add">deeds</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:9">So I, your God, have caused you to be more joyful [MTY] than anyone else.<verse eid="HEB 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 1:10"/>And <char style="add">we also know that his Son is superior to angels because in the Scriptures the Psalmist wrote that</char> someone said to God’s Son,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:10">Lord, it was you who created the earth in the beginning.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:10">You also made <char style="add">the rest of</char> the universe (OR, the <char style="add">things in</char> the sky) [MTY].<verse eid="HEB 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 1:11"/>Everything in the universe will disappear, but you will keep on living <char style="add">forever</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:11">They will wear out as clothing <char style="add">wears out</char>.<verse eid="HEB 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 1:12"/>You will dispose of them as one rolls up an <char style="add">old</char> coat <char style="add">before getting rid of it</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:12">
    <char style="add">Then</char>, you will exchange <char style="add">everything that is in the universe for what is new</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:12">as someone puts on a new garment <char style="add">in exchange for an old garment</char> [SIM].</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:12">But you <char style="add">are not like what you created</char>;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:12">You stay the same, and you live forever [LIT]!<verse eid="HEB 1:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 1:13"/>
    <char style="add">We also know that his Son is superior to angels because no one ever stated</char> [RHQ] <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char> that God said to any angel <char style="add">what he said to his Son</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:13">Sit <char style="add">in the place of honor</char> next to me and rule with me [MTY]</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 1:13">while I put all of your enemies completely under your control [MET]!<verse eid="HEB 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 1:14"/>The angels are <char style="add">only</char> spirits who serve <char style="add">God</char> [RHQ]. <char style="add">God</char> sends them <char style="add">to earth</char> in order to help those he has saved (OR, those whom he will save).<verse eid="HEB 1:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="HEB 2"/>
  <para style="s1">We will not escape God’s punishment if we ignore such a great message of salvation.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 2:1-4">Hebrews 2:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 2:1"/>So, <char style="add">since that is true</char>, we must pay very careful attention to what we have heard <char style="add">about God’s Son</char>, in order that we do not drift away from it, <char style="add">as a boat drifts off its course when people do not guide it</char> [MET]. <verse eid="HEB 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 2:2"/><char style="add">God’s laws that</char> were given by angels were valid, and God justly punished all who rejected them and all who disobeyed [DOU] them. <verse eid="HEB 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 2:3"/>So, we will certainly not escape <char style="add">God punishing us</char> if we ignore such a great <char style="add">message about how God</char> [MTY] saves us! [RHQ] This <char style="add">new message</char> was first spoken by the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> {The Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> first spoke this <char style="add">message</char>}. Then it was confirmed to us by those who heard <char style="add">what the Lord told them</char> {those who heard <char style="add">what the Lord told them</char> confirmed it to us}. <verse eid="HEB 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 2:4"/>God also confirmed to us <char style="add">that this message was true</char> by <char style="add">enabling believers to do</char> many things that showed God’s power, to do other miraculous things [DOU], and <char style="add">to do other things</char> by the gifts that the Holy Spirit distributed to them according to what <char style="add">God</char> desired.<verse eid="HEB 2:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God has determined that Christ, not angels or people, will rule everything.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 2:5-9a">Hebrews 2:5-9a</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 2:5"/>God has determined that the angels will not rule over everything. <char style="add">Instead, he has determined that Christ</char> will rule in the new world that <char style="add">God</char> will <char style="add">create</char>. <char style="add">That is the new world</char> about which I am writing. <verse eid="HEB 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 2:6"/>Someone spoke to <char style="add">God about this</char> somewhere <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>, saying,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 2:6">◄No one is worthy enough for you to think about him!/Who is <char style="add">worthy enough</char> for you to think about him?► [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 2:6">◄No human is <char style="add">worthy enough</char> for you to care for him!/Is any human <char style="add">worthy enough</char> for you to care for him?► [RHQ]<verse eid="HEB 2:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 2:7"/>
    <char style="add">So it is surprising that</char> you have caused people to be for a little while inferior in rank to angels.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 2:7">You have greatly honored [DOU] them [MET], as <char style="add">kings are honored with</char> a crown.<verse eid="HEB 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 2:8"/>You have put everything under people’s control [MET].</para>
  <para style="p" vid="HEB 2:8">God has determined that people will rule over absolutely everything [LIT]. But now, at this present time, we perceive that people do not yet have authority over everything. <verse eid="HEB 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 2:9"/>But we do know about Jesus, <char style="add">who truly has authority over everything</char>!</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="HEB 2:9">Jesus, the creator of everything, is the one who died for us, makes us holy, and proclaims us to be his brothers and sisters.</para>
  <para style="sr" vid="HEB 2:9">
    <ref loc="HEB 2:9b-13">Hebrews 2:9b-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p" vid="HEB 2:9">Jesus, for a little while, became inferior <char style="add">in rank</char> to angels in order to die on behalf of [MET] everyone. He became inferior when he suffered <char style="add">and</char> died, as God kindly <char style="add">planned</char>. But now he has been greatly <char style="add">honored</char> [DOU] <char style="add">by being</char> crowned <char style="add">as kings are</char>. <verse eid="HEB 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 2:10"/>It was fitting that <char style="add">God</char> make <char style="add">Jesus</char> ◄perfect/all that God intended him to be►. God was enabling many people who would belong to him [MET] to share his glory. God <char style="add">is the one who</char> created all things, and <char style="add">he is the one</char> for whom all things <char style="add">exist</char>. <char style="add">He perfected Jesus</char> by causing him to suffer <char style="add">and die</char>. <char style="add">Jesus</char> is the one whom <char style="add">God</char> uses to save people. <verse eid="HEB 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 2:11"/><char style="add">Jesus</char> is the one who ◄makes people holy/sets people apart for God►, and they all belong to God’s family. <char style="add">As a result, Christ</char> gladly [LIT] proclaims them to be <char style="add">like</char> his own brothers <char style="add">and sisters</char>. <verse eid="HEB 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 2:12"/><char style="add">The Psalmist wrote what Christ said to God about us becoming</char> his brothers, in these words:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 2:12">I will proclaim to my brothers how awesome you are (OR, what you ◄<char style="add">are like/have done</char>►) [MTY].</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 2:12">I will sing praise to you in the presence of the congregation!<verse eid="HEB 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 2:13"/>And a prophet wrote <char style="add">in</char> another <char style="add">Scripture passage what Christ said about God</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 2:13">I will trust him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="HEB 2:13">And in another <char style="add">Scripture passage, Christ said about those who are like his</char> children,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 2:13">I and the ones that God has given me are here.<verse eid="HEB 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is Jesus, not angels, who became a human to help us as our Supreme Priest.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 2:14-18">Hebrews 2:14-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 2:14"/>So, since those <char style="add">whom God calls his</char> children are all human beings [MTY], Jesus also became a human being <char style="add">just like them</char>. The devil has the power to cause people <char style="add">to be afraid</char> to die, but Christ became human in order that by his dying he might make the devil powerless. <verse eid="HEB 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 2:15"/><char style="add">Jesus did that</char> to free all of us who are like slaves [MET] all the time we live, because we are <char style="add">forced to</char> be afraid to die. <verse eid="HEB 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 2:16"/>Because <char style="add">Jesus became a human being</char>, it is not angels whom he wants to help. No, it is we who trust God as Abraham did whom he wants to help. <verse eid="HEB 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 2:17"/>So, <char style="add">since he came to help humans, not angels</char>, he had to be made exactly like <char style="add">us whom he calls</char> his own brothers <char style="add">and sisters</char>. He wants to be a Supreme Priest who <char style="add">acts</char> mercifully <char style="add">to all people</char> and who faithfully does what God wants, so that people who had sinned would be declared no longer guilty. <verse eid="HEB 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 2:18"/><char style="add">Specifically</char>, he is able to help those/us who are tempted <char style="add">to sin</char>. He can do that because he suffered, and he was also tempted <char style="add">to sin like we are tempted to sin</char>.<verse eid="HEB 2:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="HEB 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Our Supreme Priest, Jesus, deserves more honor than Moses does.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 3:1-6">Hebrews 3:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 3:1"/>My fellow believers, <char style="add">God</char> has set you apart and has chosen you, just like he chose me. So consider Jesus. <char style="add">He is God’s</char> messenger to us. He is also the Supreme Priest whom we say we believe in. <verse eid="HEB 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 3:2"/>He faithfully <char style="add">served God</char>, who appointed him, just like Moses faithfully <char style="add">served</char> God’s people [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 3:2"/><verse number="3-4" style="v" sid="HEB 3:3-4"/>Just like every house is made by someone {as someone makes every house}, Jesus made everything, and he is God/Divine. So God has considered that Jesus is worthy <char style="add">that people honor</char> him more than they honor Moses, just like the one who builds a house deserves that people honor him more than they should honor the house <char style="add">he built</char>. <verse eid="HEB 3:3-4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 3:5"/>Moses very faithfully <char style="add">served God as he</char> ◄<char style="add">helped/cared for</char>► [MET] God’s people, just like a servant <char style="add">faithfully serves his master</char>. The result was that Moses testified about what Jesus would say later. <verse eid="HEB 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 3:6"/>But Christ <char style="add">faithfully serves God as he</char> ◄<char style="add">helps/cares for</char>► his own people [MTY, MET], just like a <char style="add">son helps/cares for his own family</char>. And we are God’s people [MTY] if we continue to confidently <char style="add">believe in Christ</char> and if we continue to confidently wait for <char style="add">what God will do for us</char>.<verse eid="HEB 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not stubbornly rebel against God as their Jewish ancestors did.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 3:7-11">Hebrews 3:7-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 3:7"/>The Holy Spirit <char style="add">caused the Psalmist to write these words in the Scriptures to the Israelites</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 3:7">Now, when you <char style="add">(pl)</char> hear God speaking to you [MTY], <verse eid="HEB 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 3:8"/>do not stubbornly ◄<char style="add">disobey/refuse to</char> obey <char style="add">him</char>► [IDM], <char style="add">as your Jewish ancestors stubbornly disobeyed him</char> when they rebelled against <char style="add">him</char> in the desert.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="HEB 3:8">
    <char style="add">At that time, God said to your ancestors</char>, “They tried to determine how many <char style="add">things that displeased me they could do</char> in the desert <char style="add">without me punishing them</char>. <verse eid="HEB 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 3:9"/>Your ancestors repeatedly tested <char style="add">whether I would be patient with them, even though</char> for 40 years they saw all the amazing things I did.<verse eid="HEB 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 3:10"/>So, I became disgusted with those people who saw those things, and I said <char style="add">about them</char>, ‘They are constantly disloyal to me, and they do not understand how I <char style="add">wanted them</char> to conduct their lives.’<verse eid="HEB 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 3:11"/>As a result, because I was angry with them, I solemnly declared, ‘They will not enter <char style="add">the land of Canaan</char> where I would let them rest [MTY]!’ ”<verse eid="HEB 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Beware that you do not stop trusting in Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 3:12-15">Hebrews 3:12-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 3:12"/>So, my fellow believers, be careful that none of you is so evil that you stop trusting <char style="add">in Christ</char>. That would cause you to reject God who is all-powerful. <verse eid="HEB 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 3:13"/>Instead, each of you must encourage each other every day, while <char style="add">you still have</char> the opportunity [IDM], in order that none of you may stubbornly <char style="add">reject God</char> by <char style="add">letting others</char> deceive you (OR, as you deceive yourselves), <char style="add">with the result that</char> you <char style="add">(sg)</char> sin [PRS]. <verse eid="HEB 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 3:14"/><char style="add">We must encourage one another</char>, because we <char style="add">(inc)</char> benefit from <char style="add">all</char> Christ <char style="add">has done</char> only if we firmly keep trusting <char style="add">in him</char> from the time when we first confidently <char style="add">trusted in him</char> until <char style="add">the time when</char> we die [EUP]. <verse eid="HEB 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 3:15"/><char style="add">We can do this</char> by paying attention to <char style="add">what the Psalmist wrote in that Scripture passage in which</char> God said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 3:15">Now, when you hear me speaking <char style="add">to you(pl)</char> [MTY], do not stubbornly disobey me as <char style="add">your ancestors stubbornly disobeyed me</char> when they rebelled <char style="add">against me</char>.<verse eid="HEB 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It was your ancestors, ones for whom God did great things, who rebelled against God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 3:16-19">Hebrews 3:16-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 3:16"/>◄<char style="add">You must keep trusting in God</char> because you must remember who it was who rebelled against God although they heard him speaking to them./Do you remember who it was who rebelled against God although they heard <char style="add">him speaking to them</char>?► [RHQ] It was people who had certainly experienced [LIT] God’s power. It was all those people whom Moses led miraculously out of Egypt. [RHQ] <verse eid="HEB 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 3:17"/>And ◄<char style="add">you must remember</char> who it was that God was disgusted with for 40 years./do you <char style="add">remember</char> who it was that God was disgusted with for 40years?► [RHQ] It was those same people who had sinned like that, and who as a result died in the desert! [RHQ] <verse eid="HEB 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 3:18"/>And ◄<char style="add">you must remember</char> about whom God solemnly declared, “They will not enter the land where I would let them rest.”/do you <char style="add">remember</char> about whom <char style="add">God</char> solemnly declared, “They will not enter the land where I <char style="add">would let them</char> rest”?► [RHQ] It was those Israelites who disobeyed God. <verse eid="HEB 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 3:19"/>So, from that example we <char style="add">(inc)</char> realize that it was because they did not keep trusting <char style="add">in God</char> that they were unable to enter <char style="add">the land where they would rest</char>.<verse eid="HEB 3:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="HEB 4"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelites failed to enter the place where they would rest; we must be careful not to act like them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 4:1-5">Hebrews 4:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 4:1"/>
    <char style="add">The Israelites did not enter the place where they would rest</char>. But <char style="add">God</char> has still promised us that we can enter the place of resting <char style="add">in heaven eternally</char>. So we must beware <char style="add">of the possibility</char> that <char style="add">God</char> may consider that some of you have failed to enter the <char style="add">place of</char> resting <char style="add">eternally as the Israelites did not enter the place where they would rest</char>. <verse eid="HEB 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 4:2"/>We have heard the message <char style="add">about Christ</char>, just like <char style="add">the Israelites</char> heard <char style="add">what God promised</char>. But <char style="add">just like</char> the message did not benefit <char style="add">most of</char> those who heard it because they did not believe it as <char style="add">Joshua and Caleb did, it</char> will not <char style="add">benefit us eternally if we do not keep believing it</char>. <verse eid="HEB 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 4:3"/>We who have believed <char style="add">in Christ</char> are able to enter the place of resting <char style="add">eternally. We know there is a place where we will rest eternally</char> because God said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 4:3">Because I was angry with them, I solemnly declared, “They will not enter <char style="add">the land where</char> I would let them rest.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="HEB 4:3">
    <char style="add">God said that</char> even though he ceased his work <char style="add">of creating things</char> after he created the world. <verse eid="HEB 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 4:4"/>What someone wrote somewhere <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char> about the seventh day <char style="add">after he had spent six days creating the world</char>, supports that:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 4:4">Then, on the seventh day, God rested from his work <char style="add">of creating everything</char>.<verse eid="HEB 4:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 4:5"/>But note again what God said about the Israelites <char style="add">in the</char> passage that I quoted previously:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 4:5">They will not enter <char style="add">the land where</char> I would let them rest.<verse eid="HEB 4:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Scriptures support the claim that there is a time when God’s people will rest eternally.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 4:6-10">Hebrews 4:6-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 4:6"/>Some people experience entering that <char style="add">place of resting eternally. But</char> those <char style="add">Israelites</char> who first had the good message preached to them {first heard the good message} <char style="add">about what God promised them</char> did not enter <char style="add">that place of resting</char>, because they refused to believe <char style="add">God</char>. <verse eid="HEB 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 4:7"/><char style="add">But God</char> appointed another time <char style="add">when we may enter that place of resting</char>. That time is now! <char style="add">We know that is true because</char> much later than when <char style="add">the Israelites rebelled against God in the desert</char>, he caused <char style="add">King</char> David to write what I have already quoted,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 4:7">Now, when you understand what God is saying <char style="add">to you</char>, do not stubbornly disobey him.<verse eid="HEB 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 4:8"/>If Joshua had led the Israelites to enter the place of resting, God would not have spoken later about another <char style="add">time when we could rest</char> [MET]. <char style="add">So we know God was speaking about another time when some people would enter that place of resting eternally</char>. <verse eid="HEB 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 4:9"/>So, just like <char style="add">God rested on</char> the seventh day <char style="add">after he finished making everything</char>, there remains a time when God’s people will rest eternally. <verse eid="HEB 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 4:10"/>Specifically, whoever enters God’s place of resting has ceased doing things <char style="add">to gain God’s favor</char>, just like God ceased doing his work <char style="add">of creating everything</char>.<verse eid="HEB 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We must be careful not to be insincere about trying to enter the place of eternal rest.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 4:11-13">Hebrews 4:11-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 4:11"/>God severely punished the <char style="add">Israelites because they disbelieved his message</char>. So we must strive to experience entering that <char style="add">place of</char> resting <char style="add">eternally</char>, in order that he will not severely punish any of us for not believing <char style="add">his message</char>. <verse eid="HEB 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 4:12"/><char style="add">Beware of being insincere about doing this</char>, because the message God <char style="add">has given us</char> very powerfully penetrates our thinking more than a two-edged sword <char style="add">penetrates flesh</char> [MET]. It penetrates <char style="add">deeply</char> into our souls and spirits, as <char style="add">a sharp sword can penetrate</char> into our joints and marrow. That <char style="add">is, by his message God</char> [PRS] discerns all that we think about, and he discerns all that we desire <char style="add">to do</char> [MTY] (OR, <char style="add">His message</char> exposes <char style="add">to us</char> all our thoughts and all our desires). <verse eid="HEB 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 4:13"/>God knows everything about everyone. Everything is completely exposed [DOU] to him, <char style="add">and he is</char> the one [SYN] who will say whether he approves of what we have done.<verse eid="HEB 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Let us come boldly to Christ, our Supreme Priest, to receive his gracious help.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 4:14-16">Hebrews 4:14-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 4:14"/>We have a great Supreme Priest who ascended through the heavens <char style="add">when he returned to God’s presence</char>. He is Jesus, ◄God’s Son/the man who is also God►. So let us firmly profess <char style="add">what we believe about him</char>. <verse eid="HEB 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 4:15"/>Our Supreme Priest can indeed [LIT] compassionately deal with us who tend to sin easily, because he also was tempted <char style="add">to sin</char> in every way that we are <char style="add">tempted to sin</char>, and yet he did not sin. <verse eid="HEB 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 4:16"/>So, let us come boldly to <char style="add">Christ</char> [MTY], who rules [MET] <char style="add">from heaven</char> and does for us what we do not deserve, in order that we might experience <char style="add">his acting</char> mercifully <char style="add">toward us</char>, and in order that we might experience his helping us in a kind way whenever we need <char style="add">help</char>.<verse eid="HEB 4:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="HEB 5"/>
  <para style="s1">As Christ suffered, he learned to be a compassionate Supreme Priest by obeying God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 5:1-10">Hebrews 5:1-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 5:1"/>Every <char style="add">Jewish</char> Supreme Priest was chosen by <char style="add">God</char> {<char style="add">God</char> chose every <char style="add">Jewish</char> Supreme Priest} from among <char style="add">ordinary</char> men. They were appointed {<char style="add">He</char> appointed them} in order that they would come before him on behalf of the people. <char style="add">Specifically, God appointed them</char> in order that they would bring gifts <char style="add">to him on behalf of the people</char>, and in order to sacrifice <char style="add">animals to him</char> for people who sinned. <verse eid="HEB 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 5:2"/>The Supreme Priests could deal gently with those who ignorantly sinned, since the Supreme Priests themselves tended to sin easily. <verse eid="HEB 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 5:3"/>As a result, they had to offer something to God for their own sins, just like <char style="add">they had to offer something to God</char> for <char style="add">other</char> people who sinned. <verse eid="HEB 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 5:4"/>Furthermore, <char style="add">it is an honor to be a Supreme Priest</char> so no one honors himself <char style="add">by appointing himself to become a Supreme Priest</char>. Instead, God chose each man <char style="add">to become a Supreme Priest</char>, as he chose Aaron <char style="add">to be the first Supreme Priest</char>. <verse eid="HEB 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 5:5"/>Similarly, Christ also did not honor himself by appointing himself to become a Supreme Priest. Instead, God <char style="add">appointed him by</char> saying to <char style="add">him what he never said to any other priest, what the</char> Psalmist wrote in the Scriptures,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 5:5">You <char style="add">(sg)</char> are my Son! Today I have declared that I am your Father!<verse eid="HEB 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 5:6"/>And he also said <char style="add">to Christ what the Psalmist wrote</char> in another Scripture passage,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 5:6">You are a priest eternally just like Melchizedek was a priest.<verse eid="HEB 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 5:7"/>When Christ lived on the earth [MTY], he prayed [DOU] to God and tearfully cried out loudly to him. <char style="add">Specifically</char>, he asked <char style="add">God</char>, who was able to help him, that he would not <char style="add">fear the sufferings just before</char> he died. As a result, God listened to him, because Christ reverently submitted <char style="add">to what God wanted him to do</char>. <verse eid="HEB 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 5:8"/>Although Christ is <char style="add">God’s own Son</char>, he learned to obey <char style="add">God</char> by suffering <char style="add">before he died</char>. <verse eid="HEB 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 5:9"/>By becoming ◄all <char style="add">that</char> God intended him to be/perfect►, <char style="add">he has now</char> become fully qualified <char style="add">to be our Supreme Priest. As a result, he is the one who saves</char> eternally all who obey him. <verse eid="HEB 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 5:10"/>Furthermore, God has designated him to be <char style="add">our</char> Supreme Priest in the way that Melchizedek was a Supreme Priest.<verse eid="HEB 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">You are not ready for more advanced spiritual truth.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 5:11-14">Hebrews 5:11-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 5:11"/>Although there is much to say <char style="add">to you(pl)</char> about <char style="add">how Christ resembles Melchizedek</char>, this is hard <char style="add">for me</char> to explain <char style="add">to you</char> because you now understand things so slowly. <verse eid="HEB 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 5:12"/><char style="add">You became Christians long ago. So</char> by now you should be teaching <char style="add">spiritual truths to others</char>. But you still need someone to teach you again the truths that God has revealed. <char style="add">I am talking about</char> the truths that we teach people <char style="add">when they</char> first <char style="add">believe in Christ</char>. You need <char style="add">those elementary truths</char> like babies need milk [MET]. You are not <char style="add">ready for advanced teaching, which is like</char> the solid food <char style="add">which mature people need</char> [MET]. <verse eid="HEB 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 5:13"/>Remember that those <char style="add">who are still learning these elementary truths</char> [MET] have not become familiar with <char style="add">what God</char> says concerning becoming/being righteous. They are <char style="add">just like</char> [MET] babies <char style="add">who need</char> milk! <verse eid="HEB 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 5:14"/>But <char style="add">the more advanced spiritual truth</char> is for people who are <char style="add">spiritually</char> mature, just like [MET] solid food is for <char style="add">people who are physically</char> mature. They can tell the difference between what is good and what is evil, because they have trained themselves <char style="add">to keep doing that</char>.<verse eid="HEB 5:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="HEB 6"/>
  <para style="s1">If you believers later reject the message about Christ, God will reject you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 6:1-8">Hebrews 6:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 6:1"/>So, we <char style="add">(inc)</char> must not keep <char style="add">discussing</char> the elementary principles about Christ. Instead, we must proceed <char style="add">to the teaching that will make us spiritually</char> mature [MTY]. We must not <char style="add">be people who always need someone to teach them</char> the elementary truths <char style="add">about Christ that are like</char> [MET] a foundation. <char style="add">I am referring to the teaching that people who do sinful</char> things must turn away from their sinful behavior, things that <char style="add">those who are spiritually</char> [MET] dead do. <char style="add">I am referring to the teaching</char> that people must believe in God. <verse eid="HEB 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 6:2"/><char style="add">I am referring to the teaching about what</char> various <char style="add">Jewish and Christian</char> rituals for purifying people <char style="add">signify. I am referring to the teaching about how elders enable people to receive spiritual gifts by</char> laying hands <char style="add">on them</char> [MTY]. <char style="add">I am referring to the teaching that God will</char> ◄<char style="add">cause</char> those who have died to live again/raise people from the dead►. And <char style="add">I am referring to the teaching that God</char> will judge <char style="add">some people and punish them</char> eternally. <verse eid="HEB 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 6:3"/><char style="add">Instead of continuing to discuss these elementary truths</char>, we <char style="add">(inc)</char> (OR, I) will <char style="add">go on to give people mature teaching</char>, if God allows it. <verse eid="HEB 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 6:4"/><char style="add">I will explain why it is important to do that. Some</char> people have at one time fully understood <char style="add">the message about Christ</char> [MET]. They have experienced <char style="add">a relationship with Jesus Christ</char> that God [EUP/MTY] gave <char style="add">to them</char>. They have received the Holy Spirit the same as <char style="add">others have</char>. <verse eid="HEB 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 6:5"/>They have experienced that God’s message is good. And by what they have experienced <char style="add">now</char>, they know how <char style="add">God will work</char> powerfully in the future. If those people reject <char style="add">the message about Christ</char>, it will not be possible for anyone to persuade them to turn away from their sinful behavior again! <verse eid="HEB 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 6:6"/>What those <char style="add">believers who later renounce the message about Christ do is as though</char> [MET] they themselves are nailing the Son of God to a cross again! They are causing others to publicly despise Christ. <verse eid="HEB 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 6:7"/>Think about this: It is land on which rain has frequently fallen [PRS] and on which plants grow [PRS] that is useful for the people who prepare the land that God has blessed. <char style="add">Similarly, it is those believers who have received many good things from God and who do good deeds/things that please God, whom God will bless</char> [MET]. <verse eid="HEB 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 6:8"/>But <char style="add">what will happen to believers who do deeds/things that do not please God will be like what happens to land</char> on which <char style="add">only</char> thorns and thistles grow [MET]. <char style="add">Such land</char> is worthless. It has almost become land that God will curse, and eventually he will burn <char style="add">its vegetation</char> [MTY].<verse eid="HEB 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">But God will not overlook all you have done for him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 6:9-12">Hebrews 6:9-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 6:9"/>Although I am writing <char style="add">to you</char> like this as a <char style="add">warning</char>, I am certain concerning you whom I love that <char style="add">you are doing</char> better than that. Specifically, I am sure that <char style="add">you are doing</char> the things that are appropriate <char style="add">for those whom God</char> has saved. <verse eid="HEB 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 6:10"/>Since God always acts justly [LIT], he will not overlook all you have done <char style="add">for him. He will also not overlook</char> [MTY] <char style="add">your showing that you love</char> him by the way you helped your fellow believers and <char style="add">by the way you still</char> help them. <char style="add">Instead, God will reward you for doing good deeds</char>. <verse eid="HEB 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 6:11"/>I very much want each of you to diligently continue to fully expect to receive <char style="add">what God has provided for you</char>, until you finally <char style="add">receive everything that you have confidently expected to receive</char>. <verse eid="HEB 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 6:12"/>I do not want you to be lazy. <char style="add">Instead, I want</char> you to imitate those who, because they patiently continued to trust in <char style="add">God</char>, are receiving what he promised them.<verse eid="HEB 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We are confident that God will bless us as he promised; he made an oath to confirm that he would do that.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 6:13-20">Hebrews 6:13-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 6:13"/>When God promised to <char style="add">do things for</char> Abraham, he said that he would punish himself <char style="add">if he did not do that</char>, because there was no one of greater importance to ask to punish him <char style="add">if he did not do it</char>. <verse eid="HEB 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 6:14"/>He said <char style="add">to Abraham</char>, “I will certainly bless you <char style="add">(sg)</char>, and I will certainly increase <char style="add">the number of</char> your <char style="add">descendants</char> [SYN].” <verse eid="HEB 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 6:15"/>As a result, after Abraham patiently waited <char style="add">for God to do what he promised</char>, he received what <char style="add">God</char> promised him. <verse eid="HEB 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 6:16"/><char style="add">Keep in mind that when people promise something</char>, they ask a more important person to punish them if they do not do what they promise. Furthermore, when people ask God to punish them <char style="add">if they do not tell the truth</char>, that causes people who are disputing to stop disputing. <verse eid="HEB 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 6:17"/>So, when God wanted to demonstrate very clearly ◄to us/to those people► who would receive what he had promised that he would not change what he had purposed <char style="add">to do</char>, he solemnly guaranteed that he would declare himself guilty if he did not do what he promised. <verse eid="HEB 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 6:18"/>He did that to strongly encourage us as a result of our <char style="add">knowing</char> that <char style="add">God has done</char> two things that cannot change. <char style="add">Namely, he promised to bless us, and he solemnly declared that he would declare himself guilty if he did not bless us</char>. We <char style="add">know</char> that God, who did those things, cannot lie. We have fled <char style="add">to him</char> in order that we might continue confidently to expect to receive what he promised us. <verse eid="HEB 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 6:19"/><char style="add">Our confidently expecting</char> [SYN] <char style="add">to receive what he has promised is like</char> an anchor [MET] that very firmly [DOU] <char style="add">holds us fast. The one we confidently expect to help us</char> [SYN] <char style="add">is Jesus, who</char> goes into <char style="add">God’s very presence, just like the Supreme Priests went</char> behind the curtain into the innermost <char style="add">part of the tent in the barren area</char> [MET]. <verse eid="HEB 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="HEB 6:20"/>Jesus went <char style="add">into God’s presence</char> ahead of us <char style="add">(inc)</char> to <char style="add">help</char> us when he became a Supreme Priest eternally in the way that Melchizedek was a Supreme Priest.<verse eid="HEB 6:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="HEB 7"/>
  <para style="s1">There are ways in which Melchizedek was like God’s Son.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 7:1-3">Hebrews 7:1-3</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 7:1"/>
    <char style="add">Now I will say more about</char> this <char style="add">man</char> Melchizedek. He was the king of Salem <char style="add">city and was</char> a priest of God, the one who is greater <char style="add">than anyone else</char>. He met Abraham who was returning <char style="add">home</char> after <char style="add">he and his men</char> had defeated the <char style="add">armies of four</char> kings [SYN]. Melchizedek <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless Abraham. <verse eid="HEB 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 7:2"/>Then Abraham gave to him one tenth of all <char style="add">the spoils he</char> took after winning <char style="add">the battle. Melchizedek’s name</char> means firstly ‘king <char style="add">who rules</char> righteously’, and since Salem means ‘peace’, he was the ‘king <char style="add">who rules</char> peacefully’. <verse eid="HEB 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 7:3"/><char style="add">In the Scriptures there is</char> no <char style="add">record of who his</char> father <char style="add">was</char>, nor <char style="add">is there any record of who his</char> mother <char style="add">was</char>, nor <char style="add">is there any record of who his</char> ancestors <char style="add">were</char>. There is no <char style="add">record of when he was</char> born, nor <char style="add">is there any record of when he</char> died. <char style="add">For these reasons</char>, <char style="add">it is as though</char> he continues to be a priest forever, and for this reason he is like God’s Son.<verse eid="HEB 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Melchizedek was greater than Abraham.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 7:4-10">Hebrews 7:4-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 7:4"/>You can realize how great this <char style="add">man Melchizedek was</char> from the fact that Abraham, <char style="add">our famous</char> ancestor, gave him ◄a tithe/one tenth► of the spoils <char style="add">from the battle</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 7:5"/>According to the laws <char style="add">God gave Moses</char>, the descendants of <char style="add">Abraham’s great-grandson</char> Levi, who were priests, should take tithes from <char style="add">God’s</char> people who were their relatives, even though those people also were Abraham’s descendants. <verse eid="HEB 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 7:6"/>But this man <char style="add">Melchizedek</char>, who was not among the descendants <char style="add">of Levi</char>, took tithes from Abraham. He also <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless Abraham, the man to whom <char style="add">God</char> promised <char style="add">many descendants</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 7:7"/>We know for certain that it is the more <char style="add">important people</char> who <char style="add">ask God to</char> bless the less important people. <char style="add">And Melchizedek blessed Abraham. So we conclude that Melchizedek was greater than Abraham</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 7:8"/>In the case of <char style="add">the priests who are descendants of Levi</char>, men who some day will die receive tithes. But in the case of <char style="add">Melchizedek it is as if God</char> testifies that he was still living, <char style="add">since there is no record in Scriptures about his death</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 7:9"/>And it was as though Levi himself, and <char style="add">all the priests descended from him</char>—who received tithes <char style="add">from the people</char>—paid tithes <char style="add">to Melchizedek</char>. And when Abraham paid tithes, it <char style="add">was as though Levi and all the priests descended from him acknowledged that the work Melchizedek did as a priest was greater than the work Levi did</char>, <verse eid="HEB 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 7:10"/>since <char style="add">the sperm from which all those priests were eventually born</char> was still in Abraham’s body [EUP] when Melchizedek met Abraham.<verse eid="HEB 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The former Jewish priests were not adequate, so a new one like Melchizedek had to come.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 7:11-19">Hebrews 7:11-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 7:11"/>
    <char style="add">God</char> gave his laws to his people at the same time he gave regulations about the priests. So, if what the priests who were descended from Levi did could have provided a way for God to completely <char style="add">forgive</char> people <char style="add">for disobeying those laws</char>, certainly no other priest like Melchizedek would have been necessary. [RHQ] Instead, priests who were descended from Aaron, <char style="add">Levi’s descendant, would have been adequate</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 7:12"/><char style="add">But we know they were not adequate, because a new type of priest like Melchizedek has come</char>. And since <char style="add">God</char> has appointed a new type of priest, he also had to change the regulations <char style="add">concerning how priests were appointed</char> {<char style="add">he appointed priests</char>}. <verse eid="HEB 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 7:13"/><char style="add">Jesus</char>, the one about whom I am saying these things, is a descendant of someone else, <char style="add">not a descendant of Levi</char>. None of the men from whom Jesus descended ever served as priests [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 7:14"/><char style="add">We know that</char> since it is obvious that it is from <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Judah that our Lord was descended. Moses never said that any of Judah’s descendants would <char style="add">become</char> priests. <verse eid="HEB 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 7:15"/>Furthermore, <char style="add">we know that the priests who were descended from Levi were inadequate, since</char> it is even more obvious that another priest has appeared who is like Melchizedek. <verse eid="HEB 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 7:16"/>Jesus became a priest, but not because <char style="add">he fulfilled</char> what <char style="add">God’s</char> law required <char style="add">about being a descendant of Levi</char>. Instead, he has the kind of power that <char style="add">came from a</char> life that nothing can destroy (OR, <char style="add">enabled him to</char> live <char style="add">again after he was</char> killed). <verse eid="HEB 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 7:17"/><char style="add">We know this</char> since <char style="add">God</char> confirmed it in <char style="add">the Scripture passage in which he said to his Son</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 7:17">You <char style="add">(sg)</char> are a priest eternally just like Melchizedek was a priest.<verse eid="HEB 7:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 7:18"/>On the one hand, God canceled what he commanded previously <char style="add">concerning the priests</char> because it failed in every way to enable anyone <char style="add">to become all that God intended</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 7:19"/>Remember that no one was able to become all that God intended <char style="add">by obeying</char> the laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char>. On the other hand, <char style="add">God caused that we could</char> confidently expect better things <char style="add">than we could expect by obeying God’s laws</char>. <char style="add">He did that by his establishing Christ as priest</char>. Now by means of <char style="add">Christ sacrificing himself for us</char> we can come near to God.<verse eid="HEB 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus lives eternally as a Supreme Priest to plead with God for us.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 7:20-25">Hebrews 7:20-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="HEB 7:20"/>Furthermore, <char style="add">when God appointed Christ, it was when God</char> solemnly declared <char style="add">that Christ would be a priest</char> [LIT]. When <char style="add">God appointed former</char> priests, it was not by his solemnly declaring <char style="add">that they would be priests</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="HEB 7:21"/>However, when he <char style="add">appointed Christ to be a priest</char>, it was by these words that <char style="add">the Psalmist wrote in Scripture</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 7:21">The Lord has solemnly declared <char style="add">to the Messiah</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 7:21">—and he will not change his mind—</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 7:21">“You will be a priest forever!”<verse eid="HEB 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="HEB 7:22"/>Because of that, Jesus guarantees that <char style="add">the new</char> covenant will be better <char style="add">than the old one</char>.<verse eid="HEB 7:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="HEB 7:23"/>And formerly, the priests could not keep serving <char style="add">as priests</char>, because they all died [PRS]. So there were many priests <char style="add">to take the place of the ones who died</char>. <verse eid="HEB 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="HEB 7:24"/>But because <char style="add">Jesus</char> lives eternally, he will continue to be a Supreme Priest forever. <verse eid="HEB 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="HEB 7:25"/>So, he can completely and eternally save those who come to God by <char style="add">trusting in what Jesus has done for them</char>, since he lives forever to plead <char style="add">with God</char> to help them.<verse eid="HEB 7:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus is the kind of Supreme Priest we need, because he was sinless.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 7:26-28">Hebrews 7:26-28</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="HEB 7:26"/>Jesus is the kind of Supreme Priest that we need. He was holy; he did no wrong; he was completely innocent. <char style="add">God</char> has now taken him up to the highest heaven separated from <char style="add">living among</char> sinners. <verse eid="HEB 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="HEB 7:27"/><char style="add">The other</char> Supreme Priests need to sacrifice <char style="add">animals</char> day by day <char style="add">as well as year by year</char>. They do this, firstly, <char style="add">to atone</char> for their own sins, and then <char style="add">to atone for other</char> people <char style="add">who have sinned</char>. <char style="add">But because Jesus never sinned</char>, he does not need to atone for his own sin. The only thing <char style="add">he needed to do to save people</char> was to sacrifice himself once! <verse eid="HEB 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="HEB 7:28"/><char style="add">We need a Supreme Priest like</char> him, because in the laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char> [PRS] the ones who would be appointed to be priests would be men who tended <char style="add">to sin easily</char>. But <char style="add">God</char> solemnly <char style="add">declared</char> [PRS] after <char style="add">he had given</char> his laws <char style="add">to Moses</char> that <char style="add">he would appoint</char> ◄his Son/the man who is also God► <char style="add">to be a Supreme Priest. Now</char> ◄<char style="add">his Son/the man who is also God</char>► has forever become all that God intends him to be.<verse eid="HEB 7:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="HEB 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The rituals that were performed by the Jewish high priests were only a model of what Jesus our high priest does in heaven.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 8:1-6">Hebrews 8:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 8:1"/>The main point of <char style="add">all</char> that <char style="add">I</char> have written is that we have a Supreme Priest like that. He has sat down to rule [MTY] with God [EUP] at the place of greatest honor in heaven. <verse eid="HEB 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 8:2"/>He ministers in the Most Holy Place, that is, in the true place <char style="add">of worship in heaven</char>. That is a place that <char style="add">Moses’</char> tent <char style="add">represented</char>. The Lord set up the true place of worship. No human <char style="add">set it up</char>.<verse eid="HEB 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 8:3"/>Every Supreme Priest was appointed {<char style="add">God</char> appointed every Supreme Priest} to offer <char style="add">to God</char> gifts and sacrifices <char style="add">for people who sinned</char>. So, since <char style="add">Christ became a Supreme Priest</char>, he also had to offer something. <verse eid="HEB 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 8:4"/>Since there are already <char style="add">Jewish</char> priests who offer gifts as God’s laws <char style="add">require</char>, if Christ were <char style="add">now living</char> on the earth, he would not be a Supreme Priest. <verse eid="HEB 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 8:5"/>The <char style="add">Jewish</char> priests perform rituals which are only a model [DOU] of <char style="add">what Christ would do in heaven</char> [MTY]. What <char style="add">God</char> told Moses when Moses was about to set up the tent <char style="add">for worshipping him supports the idea that those rituals were only a model. God said</char>, “Be sure that you <char style="add">(sg)</char> make everything according to the model that I showed you on <char style="add">Sinai</char> Mountain!” <verse eid="HEB 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 8:6"/>But now as it is, <char style="add">Christ</char> ministers in a more excellent way <char style="add">than the Jewish priests do</char>. Likewise, the <char style="add">new</char> covenant that he established <char style="add">between God and people</char> is better <char style="add">than the old one. When the new covenant was established</char> {<char style="add">God established the new covenant</char>}, he promised us better things <char style="add">than the laws that God gave Moses did</char>.<verse eid="HEB 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The first covenant was not adequate, so God needed a new one.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 8:7-13">Hebrews 8:7-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 8:7"/>If that first covenant had been perfectly adequate [LIT], God would not have thought that he needed another <char style="add">covenant/agreement to replace it</char>. But <char style="add">it was not adequate, so he needed a new one</char>. <verse eid="HEB 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 8:8"/>Because God declared <char style="add">that the Israelites</char> were guilty <char style="add">of not obeying the first covenant, he wanted a new covenant. This is what</char> ◄<char style="add">a prophet/Jeremiah</char>► <char style="add">wrote about that</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:8">The Lord says, “Listen! There will soon be a time</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:8">when I will make a new covenant with the people [MTY] of Israel and the people [MTY] of Judah.<verse eid="HEB 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 8:9"/>That covenant will not be like the covenant that I made with their ancestors</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:9">when I led them out of Egypt [MET] <char style="add">like a father leads a child</char> by the hand.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:9">They did not continue to <char style="add">obey</char> my covenant,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:9">so I rejected them,” says the Lord.<verse eid="HEB 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 8:10"/>“This is the covenant that I will make with the Israelites [MTY],</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:10">after <char style="add">the first covenant has ended</char> [MTY],” says the Lord:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:10">“I will enable them to understand my laws [MTY],</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:10">and I will enable them to obey them (OR, truly know them) [MTY] sincerely.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:10">I will be their God, and they will be my people [DOU].<verse eid="HEB 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 8:11"/>
    <char style="add">As a result</char>, no one will <char style="add">need to</char> teach a fellow citizen</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:11">or tell his fellow kinsmen, ‘<char style="add">You need to</char> know the Lord,’</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:11">because all <char style="add">my people</char> will know me:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:11">
    <char style="add">My people</char> of every status <char style="add">will know me</char>.<verse eid="HEB 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 8:12"/>I will mercifully <char style="add">forgive them for</char> the wicked things they have done.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 8:12">I will no longer <char style="add">consider</char> that <char style="add">they are guilty for</char> [DOU] <char style="add">their</char> sins.”<verse eid="HEB 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 8:13"/>Since God spoke about a new <char style="add">covenant</char>, he considered that the first <char style="add">covenant</char> was no longer in use, and that it would soon disappear, just like <char style="add">anything that</char> gets old <char style="add">will disappear</char> [MET, DOU].<verse eid="HEB 8:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="HEB 9"/>
  <para style="s1">A description of the man-made sanctuary that accompanied the first covenant.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 9:1-5">Hebrews 9:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 9:1"/>
    <char style="add">To continue</char>: In the first <char style="add">covenant, God</char> regulated how people <char style="add">should perform</char> rituals, and <char style="add">he told them to make</char> [MTY] a sanctuary. <verse eid="HEB 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 9:2"/><char style="add">That sanctuary</char> was a tent that <char style="add">the Israelites</char> set up. In its outer room there was the lampstand and the table <char style="add">on which they put</char> the bread that <char style="add">the priests</char> presented <char style="add">to God. That room</char> was called ‘the holy place’. <verse eid="HEB 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 9:3"/>Behind the curtain inside <char style="add">the holy place</char> there was <char style="add">another</char> room. That was called ‘the very holy place’. <verse eid="HEB 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 9:4"/>It had an altar, <char style="add">made from</char> gold, <char style="add">for burning</char> incense. <char style="add">It also had the chest which they called</char> the chest of the covenant. All its sides were covered with gold. In it was the golden pot which contained <char style="add">pieces of the food they called</char> manna. <char style="add">That was the food with which God miraculously fed the people before they entered the promised land</char>. In the chest there was also Aaron’s walking stick that budded <char style="add">to prove that he was God’s true priest</char>. In the chest were also the stone tablets <char style="add">on which God had written</char> the Ten Commandments. <verse eid="HEB 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 9:5"/>On top of <char style="add">the chest</char> were <char style="add">figures of</char> winged creatures <char style="add">that symbolized God’s</char> glory. Their <char style="add">wings</char> overshadowed the chest’s lid where <char style="add">the high priest sprinkled the blood</char> ◄to <char style="add">atone for/to forgive</char>► <char style="add">those who had sinned. I</char> do not <char style="add">need</char> to write about these things in detail now.<verse eid="HEB 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Offerings that were made under the first covenant were not able to remove a sense of guilt for sin.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 9:6-10">Hebrews 9:6-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 9:6"/>After all those things were prepared {After they had prepared all those things like that} <char style="add">in the two rooms of the tent</char>, the <char style="add">Jewish</char> priests habitually went into the outer <char style="add">room of the</char> tent to perform their rituals. <verse eid="HEB 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 9:7"/>But into the inner room, only the Supreme Priest <char style="add">went</char>, once a year. He always took [LIT] the blood <char style="add">of animals that they had slaughtered</char>. He offered them <char style="add">to God</char> for his own <char style="add">sins</char> and for the sins that other people had committed. They included sins that they did not realize <char style="add">were sinful</char>. <verse eid="HEB 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 9:8"/>By those things the Holy Spirit indicated that <char style="add">just like God</char> did not reveal the way <char style="add">for ordinary people</char> to enter into the inner room while the outer room still existed [MET], <char style="add">similarly he did not reveal the way for ordinary people to enter the presence of God while the Jewish system of offering sacrifices was in effect</char>. <verse eid="HEB 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 9:9"/><char style="add">The things that the priests did inside the outer room</char> [MTY] symbolized <char style="add">what was true</char> during the time <char style="add">when the first covenant was in effect</char>. According to <char style="add">the first covenant</char> (OR, <char style="add">In that outer room</char>), <char style="add">priests</char> offered gifts and other sacrifices to God. But <char style="add">by offering them</char>, the people who brought them were unable to make themselves feel that they were no longer guilty for having sinned. <verse eid="HEB 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 9:10"/><char style="add">They brought those gifts and made those sacrifices</char> according to <char style="add">regulations concerning</char> things to eat and drink, and <char style="add">according to rules that required people to</char> wash various things. <char style="add">God</char> declared that those regulations about our bodies were to be in effect until <char style="add">he put into effect the new covenant</char>; that was a better system.<verse eid="HEB 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ redeemed us by offering his own blood as a sacrifice.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 9:11-14">Hebrews 9:11-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 9:11"/>But when Christ came as our Supreme Priest, <char style="add">he brought</char> the good things that are now available. When he appeared, <char style="add">he went into God’s presence in heaven. That is like a</char> [MET] very great and perfect tent not made by humans {which no human made} [SYN]; that is, it is not part of the world <char style="add">God</char> created. It was better <char style="add">than the tent Moses set up here on earth</char>. <verse eid="HEB 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 9:12"/><char style="add">When a Supreme Priest goes into the inner room in the tent each year, he takes</char> goats’ blood and calves’ blood <char style="add">to offer as a sacrifice</char>. But Christ did not <char style="add">do that. It was as though</char> he went into that very holy place only once, taking his own blood with him. By doing that, he eternally redeemed us. <verse eid="HEB 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 9:13"/>The priests sprinkle on people goats’ blood and bulls’ blood and <char style="add">the water that has been filtered through</char> the ashes of a <char style="add">red</char> heifer that has been <char style="add">completely burned. By performing that ritual, they can ritually</char> cleanse the bodies of those who are <char style="add">ceremonially</char> unclean. Furthermore, performing those rituals enabled people to have fellowship with God again. <verse eid="HEB 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 9:14"/><char style="add">So, because we know what</char> Christ <char style="add">accomplished when</char> his blood flowed <char style="add">when he died for us</char> [PRS, MTY], we will be very certain that we are not guilty <char style="add">of having</char> done those things <char style="add">that those who are spiritually</char> dead do. <char style="add">As a result</char>, we can serve God, who is all-powerful. <char style="add">The priests always offer to God animals</char> with no defects. Similarly, when Christ offered himself <char style="add">as a sacrifice</char> to God, he was sinless [MET]. He did that as a result of <char style="add">God’s</char> eternal Spirit <char style="add">helping him</char>.<verse eid="HEB 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ has put the new covenant into effect with his own blood.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 9:15-22">Hebrews 9:15-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 9:15"/>
    <char style="add">By</char> dying <char style="add">for us</char>, <char style="add">Christ</char> ◄<char style="add">redeemed/</char>set free from the penalty for their sins► even those who disobeyed the <char style="add">conditions of</char> (OR, <char style="add">during the time of</char>) the first covenant. So, <char style="add">because</char> no <char style="add">one could be made perfect by obeying the old covenant</char>, now Christ establishes <char style="add">between God and people</char> a new covenant. He does that in order that those whom God has chosen may eternally have <char style="add">the blessings that God</char> has promised them. <verse eid="HEB 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 9:16"/>A covenant <char style="add">is like a will. In the case of a will</char>, <char style="add">in order to put its provisions into effect</char>, someone must prove that the one who made it has died. <verse eid="HEB 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 9:17"/>A will goes into effect <char style="add">only when the one who makes the will</char> has died. It is not in effect when the one who made it is still alive. <verse eid="HEB 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 9:18"/>And so <char style="add">God</char> put the first covenant into effect only [LIT] by means of <char style="add">animals’</char> blood that was shed <char style="add">when they were slaughtered</char>. <verse eid="HEB 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 9:19"/>After Moses had declared to all the Israelites everything that God commanded in the laws <char style="add">that God gave him</char>, he took calves’ and goats’ blood <char style="add">mixed</char> with water. He <char style="add">dipped into it</char> scarlet wool <char style="add">that he tied around</char> a sprig of hyssop. Then he sprinkled <char style="add">with some of the blood</char> the scroll itself containing God’s laws. Then he sprinkled <char style="add">more of that blood on all the</char> people, <verse eid="HEB 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="HEB 9:20"/>saying to them, “This is the blood <char style="add">which brings into effect</char> the covenant that God commanded that you <char style="add">obey</char>.” <verse eid="HEB 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="HEB 9:21"/>Likewise, he sprinkled with that blood the tent and every object that they used in performing rituals. <verse eid="HEB 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="HEB 9:22"/>It was by <char style="add">sprinkling</char> blood that they <char style="add">ritually</char> cleansed almost everything. That was what <char style="add">was stated in</char> God’s laws. If blood is not shed <char style="add">when people offer a sacrifice, God</char> cannot forgive <char style="add">the person who is making the sacrifice</char>.<verse eid="HEB 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish priests kept offering the blood of animal sacrifices every year, but Christ sacrificed himself once to take away our guilt.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 9:23-28">Hebrews 9:23-28</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="HEB 9:23"/>So, by rituals like that, it was necessary for <char style="add">the priests</char> to cleanse the things that symbolized what Christ does [MTY] in heaven. But God has to <char style="add">consecrate</char> the <char style="add">people who will enter</char> [MTY] heaven <char style="add">by means of</char> better sacrifices than those. <verse eid="HEB 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="HEB 9:24"/>Christ did not enter a sanctuary that humans made. That one only represented the true <char style="add">sanctuary</char>. Instead, he entered heaven itself, in order to now be in God’s presence <char style="add">to plead with</char> God for us. <verse eid="HEB 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="HEB 9:25"/>The <char style="add">Jewish</char> Supreme Priest enters the very holy place once every year, taking blood that is not his own, <char style="add">to offer it as a sacrifice</char>. But when Christ entered heaven, it was not in order to offer himself repeatedly like that. <verse eid="HEB 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="HEB 9:26"/><char style="add">If that were so</char>, he would have needed to suffer <char style="add">and shed his blood</char> repeatedly since <char style="add">the time when God</char> created the world. But instead, in this final age, <char style="add">Christ</char> has appeared once in order that by sacrificing himself he could cause <char style="add">that people</char> no longer will be <char style="add">punished for their</char> sins. <verse eid="HEB 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="HEB 9:27"/>All people must die once, and after that <char style="add">God</char> will judge them <char style="add">for their sins</char>. <verse eid="HEB 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="HEB 9:28"/>Likewise, when Christ <char style="add">died</char>, <char style="add">God</char> offered him once to be a sacrifice, to punish him instead of the many <char style="add">people who had</char> sinned. He will come <char style="add">to earth</char> a second time, not <char style="add">in order to sacrifice himself again for those who</char> have sinned, but in order to <char style="add">complete</char> his saving those who expectantly wait for him.<verse eid="HEB 9:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="HEB 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The blood of animals can never take away the guilt for sins.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 10:1-4">Hebrews 10:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 10:1"/>Just like a shadow vaguely represents the thing that it is a shadow of, the laws that God <char style="add">gave Moses</char> only poorly represent [MET] the good things that were to come later. Those laws were not all the good things themselves that God has promised. So, by offering the same kinds of sacrifices every year, people [PRS] who approach God can never become ◄perfect/all that God intends them to be►. <verse eid="HEB 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 10:2"/>If God had removed the guilt for having sinned of those who brought the sacrifices, they would not feel that they were still guilty. So they would certainly have stopped offering those sacrifices! [RHQ] <verse eid="HEB 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 10:3"/>But rather, the fact that they offer those sacrifices each year reminds them that they are still guilty for their sins. <verse eid="HEB 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 10:4"/>The principle is that blood of animals such as bulls or goats can never remove the guilt of those who have sinned.<verse eid="HEB 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ set us apart for God by offering his own body once as a sacrifice.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 10:5-10">Hebrews 10:5-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 10:5"/>So, as <char style="add">Christ</char> was coming into the world, he spoke <char style="add">to his Father about offering himself as a sacrifice for people’s sin. The Psalmist wrote this that Christ said</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:5">It is not sacrifices and offerings that you <char style="add">(sg)</char> have wanted,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:5">but you have prepared for me a body <char style="add">to serve you</char>.<verse eid="HEB 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 10:6"/>Animals that are completely burned up as sacrifices have not pleased you,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:6">and <char style="add">other sacrifices that atone</char> for those who have sinned have not pleased you.<verse eid="HEB 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 10:7"/>Then <char style="add">because of this</char>, I said, “My God, ◄listen!/here I am!►</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:7">I have come <char style="add">here</char> in order to do what you want me <char style="add">to do</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:7">
    <char style="add">just like</char> has been written {as they have written} about me in the Scriptures.”<verse eid="HEB 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 10:8"/>First, <char style="add">Christ</char> said, “It is not sacrifices and offerings and animals that <char style="add">the priests</char> have completely burned up and other <char style="add">offerings to atone for</char> those who have sinned that you have really wanted. They have not pleased you.” <char style="add">Christ said that even though</char> those things were offered {they offered all those things} according to the laws <char style="add">God gave Moses</char>! <verse eid="HEB 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 10:9"/>Then, <char style="add">concerning his offering himself as a sacrifice to atone for people’s sin</char>, he said, “Listen! I have come <char style="add">here</char> to do what you want me <char style="add">to do</char>!” In that way Christ got rid of the first <char style="add">way of atoning for sin</char>, in order to establish the second <char style="add">way of atoning for</char> sin. <verse eid="HEB 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 10:10"/>Because of Jesus Christ <char style="add">doing what God</char> wanted him to do, we have been dedicated to {<char style="add">he</char> has set us apart for} God by his offering his own body only once <char style="add">as a sacrifice, a sacrifice that will not need to be repeated</char>.<verse eid="HEB 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Scripture supports the claim that Christ made one sacrifice that will be adequate forever.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 10:11-18">Hebrews 10:11-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 10:11"/>As every <char style="add">Jewish</char> priest stands daily <char style="add">in front of the altar</char>, he performs rituals and offers the same kind of sacrifices that could never remove <char style="add">the guilt from anyone who</char> sinned [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 10:12"/>But <char style="add">Christ</char> offered a sacrifice that <char style="add">will be adequate</char> forever, and he offered it only one time! Then he sat down <char style="add">to rule</char> with God at the place of highest honor [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 10:13"/>From now on, he is waiting for <char style="add">God</char> to completely subdue <char style="add">all</char> Christ’s enemies [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 10:14"/>By offering himself once, he has provided that those whom <char style="add">God</char> has set apart will be eternally made ◄perfect/all that God intends them to be►. <verse eid="HEB 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 10:15"/>The Holy Spirit also confirms to us <char style="add">that this is true</char>. First the Lord says:<verse eid="HEB 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 10:16"/>When the time [MTY] <char style="add">when the first covenant that God made</char> with my people has ended,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:16">I will make a new covenant with them [MTY].</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:16">I will do like this for them:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:16">I will cause them to understand my laws</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:16">and I will cause them to obey them (OR, enable them to know them sincerely).<verse eid="HEB 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 10:17"/>Then <char style="add">the Lord said</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:17">
    <char style="add">I will forgive them for</char> their [DOU] sins,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:17">and I will <char style="add">consider</char> that they are no longer <char style="add">guilty for</char> having sinned.<verse eid="HEB 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 10:18"/>When <char style="add">God</char> has forgiven someone’s sins, that person does not <char style="add">need to make</char> any more offerings <char style="add">to atone for his sin</char>!<verse eid="HEB 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Let us come to God and let him make us pure and help us to keep believing his truth and do things that please him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 10:19-25">Hebrews 10:19-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 10:19"/>So, my fellow believers, because we <char style="add">trust in what Jesus accomplished when</char> his own blood <char style="add">flowed for us</char>, we can confidently go into <char style="add">God’s very presence</char> that was <char style="add">symbolized</char> by the very holy place <char style="add">in the tent</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="HEB 10:20"/>Jesus enabled us to go into <char style="add">God’s presence</char> by making a new and effective way. <char style="add">Specifically</char>, he <char style="add">offered</char> his body <char style="add">as a sacrifice</char> for us <char style="add">in order that nothing would stop us</char> from entering <char style="add">God’s presence, just like</char> [MET] the curtain <char style="add">of the very holy place prevented people from entering God’s presence</char>. <verse eid="HEB 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="HEB 10:21"/>Christ is a great priest <char style="add">who rules over us, who are</char> God’s people [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="HEB 10:22"/><char style="add">Just like the priests</char> were sprinkled {<char style="add">as Moses</char> sprinkled <char style="add">the priests</char>} <char style="add">with blood</char> [MET] to symbolize that they were no longer guilty for having sinned, we also no longer are <char style="add">guilty for having done</char> evil. <char style="add">Just like the priests ceremonially</char> washed their bodies with pure water <char style="add">to prepare themselves to serve God</char>, we are allowing <char style="add">God</char> to continually make us pure. So, we <char style="add">(inc)</char> must approach <char style="add">God</char> sincerely by confidently trusting <char style="add">in him</char>. <verse eid="HEB 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="HEB 10:23"/>We must unwaveringly keep holding tight <char style="add">to what we believe. Since God</char> faithfully <char style="add">does all</char> he promised <char style="add">to do</char>, we must confidently expect <char style="add">him to keep doing that</char>. <verse eid="HEB 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="HEB 10:24"/><char style="add">Since God</char> faithfully <char style="add">does all that</char> he promised <char style="add">to do</char>, let us consider how each of us can motivate other believers, in order that <char style="add">believers </char> will love each other, and in order that each one will do good things. <verse eid="HEB 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="HEB 10:25"/>We must not stop assembling ourselves <char style="add">to worship the Lord</char>, as some people have done. Instead, each one of us must encourage/exhort other believers. <char style="add">Let us do that</char> even more since we know that the day <char style="add">that the Lord will return</char> [MTY] is near.<verse eid="HEB 10:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">If we have known and then rejected the message about Christ, God will surely punish us.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 10:26-31">Hebrews 10:26-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="HEB 10:26"/>
    <char style="add">We(inc) must do those things</char>, because if we deliberately and habitually sin after we have known the true <char style="add">message about Christ</char>, no other sacrifice will remove our guilt for having sinned in that way. <verse eid="HEB 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="HEB 10:27"/>Instead, we must fearfully expect that <char style="add">God will</char> judge and angrily <char style="add">punish</char> his enemies in a furious fire [MET]. <verse eid="HEB 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="HEB 10:28"/>Everyone who rejected the laws <char style="add">that God gave</char> Moses was mercilessly killed when <char style="add">at least</char> two or three people testified that they had done that. <verse eid="HEB 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="HEB 10:29"/><char style="add">That was severe punishment</char>. But <char style="add">Christ</char> is ◄God’s Son/the man who is also God►. His blood, by means of which <char style="add">he put into effect</char> the new covenant, is sacred. Because of <char style="add">Christ’s</char> [MTY] blood <char style="add">flowing for us when he died</char>, <char style="add">God</char> freed us from our guilt. So, you can be sure [RHQ] that anyone who shows contempt for <char style="add">those truths</char> and who insults the Spirit of God, the one who acts with kindness toward us in a way we do not deserve, deserves to be punished even worse than <char style="add">those Israelis were punished</char> [MET]! <verse eid="HEB 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="HEB 10:30"/><char style="add">We can be sure of that</char> (OR, <char style="add">need to think about that carefully</char>) since we know that God said, “I myself will get revenge on those who sinned, and I will punish them as they deserve [DOU].” <char style="add">Moses wrote</char>, “The Lord will judge his people.” <verse eid="HEB 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="HEB 10:31"/>It will be a terrible thing if God who is all-powerful [MTY] seizes and punishes you [IDM]!<verse eid="HEB 10:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Remember how you accepted persecution because of your faith in Christ, and do not be discouraged if you are persecuted now.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 10:32-39">Hebrews 10:32-39</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="HEB 10:32"/>Recall previous times when you <char style="add">first</char> understood [MET] <char style="add">the message about Christ</char>. You endured a hard struggle, but you <char style="add">continued to trust him</char> when you suffered <char style="add">because you believed in Christ</char>. <verse eid="HEB 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="HEB 10:33"/>At times you were publicly insulted {people publicly insulted you} and you suffered {people persecuted you}. But you showed great concern for those who were treated like that. <verse eid="HEB 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="HEB 10:34"/>You not only were kind to those who were in prison <char style="add">because they believed in Christ</char>, but you also accepted it joyfully when <char style="add">unbelievers</char> took away your possessions. You accepted it because you yourselves knew very well that you have eternal possessions <char style="add">in heaven</char> that are much better <char style="add">than those that they took from you</char>! <verse eid="HEB 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="HEB 10:35"/>So, do not become discouraged <char style="add">when they cause you to suffer</char> {<char style="add">you are persecuted</char>}, because <char style="add">if you continue to trust in God</char>, he will greatly reward you. <verse eid="HEB 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="HEB 10:36"/>You must patiently continue <char style="add">to trust in him</char> in order that, because of your doing what God wants you to do, he will give you what he has promised. <verse eid="HEB 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="HEB 10:37"/><char style="add">You must do that</char> since <char style="add">a prophet wrote</char> in the Scriptures <char style="add">that God said about the Messiah</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:37">In just a short time the one <char style="add">I promised</char> would come will surely come;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:37">he will not delay coming.<verse eid="HEB 10:37"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="HEB 10:38"/>But those whom I have summoned, who <char style="add">act</char> righteously, must continually live trusting in me,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:38">because if they, in a cowardly manner, cease <char style="add">to trust in me</char>, I</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 10:38">◄will not be pleased/will be angry► with them.<verse eid="HEB 10:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="HEB 10:39"/>But we are not ones who in a cowardly manner stop <char style="add">trusting in God</char>, with the result that God will severely punish us. Instead, we are ones who trust in him, with the result that <char style="add">God</char> will save us [SYN] eternally.<verse eid="HEB 10:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="HEB 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Because of our faith, we confidently expect to receive God’s promises.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 11:1-3">Hebrews 11:1-3</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 11:1"/>It is because people trust <char style="add">God</char> that they are sure that they will receive the things that they confidently expect <char style="add">God to give them</char>. They are also certain <char style="add">that they will see those things</char>, though no one sees them yet. <verse eid="HEB 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 11:2"/>It was because our ancestors trusted in God that they pleased him. <verse eid="HEB 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 11:3"/>It is because we trust in God that we understand that he formed the universe by commanding <char style="add">it to exist</char>. The result is that the things that we see were not made from things that already existed.<verse eid="HEB 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because of his faith, Abel offered a better sacrifice than his brother Cain did.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 11:4">Hebrews 11:4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 11:4"/>It was because <char style="add">Adam’s son</char> Abel trusted God that he sacrificed something better to God than what <char style="add">his older brother</char> Cain offered to God. Because Abel did that, when God spoke well about what Abel sacrificed, God declared that Abel was righteous. And although Abel is dead, we still learn from him <char style="add">about trusting God</char>.<verse eid="HEB 11:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because of their faith, God blessed Enoch, Noah, and Abraham.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 11:5-12">Hebrews 11:5-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 11:5"/>It was because Enoch believed <char style="add">God that God</char> took him <char style="add">up to heaven</char>. The result was that he did not die. No one found him, because he was taken up {<char style="add">God</char> had removed him} from the earth <char style="add">to heaven</char>. Before <char style="add">God</char> took him away, <char style="add">he</char> testified that Enoch pleased him well. <verse eid="HEB 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 11:6"/>It is possible for people to please God only if they trust God, because anyone who wants to come to God must first believe that God exists and that he rewards those who seek <char style="add">to know</char> him.<verse eid="HEB 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 11:7"/>It was because Noah trusted <char style="add">God</char> that after he was warned by God {after <char style="add">God</char> warned him} about <char style="add">a flood that</char> had not yet happened, Noah <char style="add">showed that he</char> revered God by building a huge ship to save his family. By doing that, he <char style="add">showed all the people who did not believe him</char> [MTY] <char style="add">that they deserved to be condemned</char> {<char style="add">that God would</char> condemn them}. He was someone whom God declared to be righteous because of his trusting in God.<verse eid="HEB 11:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 11:8"/>It was because Abraham trusted God that when he was told to go {when <char style="add">God</char> told him to go}, he obeyed <char style="add">God</char>, he left <char style="add">his own country</char>, and went to a place that God would give him. Abraham left his own country, even though he did not know where he would be going. <verse eid="HEB 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 11:9"/>It was because Abraham trusted God that he lived as though he was a foreigner in the land that <char style="add">God</char> had promised to him. Abraham lived in tents, and his son Isaac and his grandson Jacob did also. God promised to give to Isaac and Jacob the same things that he promised to give Abraham. <verse eid="HEB 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 11:10"/>Abraham was waiting to live in a city <char style="add">in heaven</char> that would exist forever [MET]. It was a city that God is building [DOU]. <verse eid="HEB 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 11:11"/>It was because Abraham trusted God that God gave Abraham strength so that he <char style="add">was</char> able to produce a son. Even though his wife Sarah was past the age <char style="add">when women bear children</char>, <char style="add">God</char> promised <char style="add">that he would give her a son</char>, and Abraham considered that God would do what he promised to do. <verse eid="HEB 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 11:12"/>So, although Abraham was also too old to have children, so many people descended from that one man that they were as numerous as the stars in the sky and are as countless as the grains of sand along the seashore, <char style="add">just like God promised him</char>.<verse eid="HEB 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">All those people who trusted in God died without receiving what God promised.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 11:13-16">Hebrews 11:13-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 11:13"/>It was while they still trusted in God that all those people died. Even though they had not yet received the things that God had promised to give them, <char style="add">it was as though</char> they saw those things in a distance. They were glad <char style="add">to know</char> about what God promised. It was as though they admitted that they were not from this earth, but that they were only here temporarily. <verse eid="HEB 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 11:14"/>As for those people who talk like that, they clearly show that they long for <char style="add">a place that will become</char> their true native land. <verse eid="HEB 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 11:15"/>If they had been thinking about <char style="add">that place being</char> the place from which they had come, they would have taken the opportunity to return there. <verse eid="HEB 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 11:16"/>But, instead, they desired a better <char style="add">place in which to live</char>; that is, they desired <char style="add">a home</char> in heaven. So God has prepared a city for them to live <char style="add">with him</char>, and he is pleased [LIT] for them to say that he is their God.<verse eid="HEB 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It was because Abraham, Isaac, Joseph, Moses, the Israelite people, and Rahab trusted God that he blessed them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 11:17-31">Hebrews 11:17-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 11:17"/>It was because Abraham trusted <char style="add">God</char> that he <char style="add">was ready to</char> kill his son Isaac as a sacrifice when <char style="add">God</char> tested him. This same man to whom <char style="add">God</char> promised <char style="add">to give</char> ◄<char style="add">a son/many descendants</char>► was going to sacrifice <char style="add">that same son</char>, the only son <char style="add">whom his own wife had borne</char>! <verse eid="HEB 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 11:18"/>It was to Abraham that God said, “It is <char style="add">only</char> from Isaac that I will consider your family to descend.” <verse eid="HEB 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 11:19"/>Abraham considered that <char style="add">to fulfill that promise</char>, God could make <char style="add">Isaac</char> live again <char style="add">even if</char> he had died <char style="add">after Abraham sacrificed him</char>! The result was that when Abraham did receive Isaac back <char style="add">after God told him not to harm Isaac</char>, it was as though he received him back even after he died.<verse eid="HEB 11:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="HEB 11:20"/>It was because Isaac trusted God that he <char style="add">prayed that after he died, God would</char> bless <char style="add">his</char> sons Jacob and Esau.<verse eid="HEB 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="HEB 11:21"/>It was because Jacob trusted God that, as he was dying, he <char style="add">prayed that God would</char> bless each of the sons of <char style="add">his own son Joseph</char>. He worshipped God as he leaned upon his walking stick <char style="add">before he died</char>. <verse eid="HEB 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="HEB 11:22"/>It was because Joseph trusted God that, when he was about to die <char style="add">in Egypt</char>, he anticipated the time when the Israelis would leave Egypt; and he instructed <char style="add">that</char> his people <char style="add">should carry</char> his bones <char style="add">with them when they</char> ◄<char style="add">left Egypt/returned to Canaan</char>►.<verse eid="HEB 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="HEB 11:23"/>It was because Moses’ father and mother trusted God that they hid <char style="add">their son</char> for three months shortly after he was born, because they saw that he was so beautiful. They were not afraid of <char style="add">disobeying</char> what the king of Egypt had commanded, <char style="add">namely, that all the Jewish male babies must be killed</char>. <verse eid="HEB 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="HEB 11:24"/>The daughter of the <char style="add">king, whom they called</char> Pharaoh, <char style="add">raised</char> Moses, but when he had grown up, it was because he trusted God that he refused to <char style="add">accept the privileges that would have been his if people</char> considered that he was ◄the son of the king’s daughter/the king’s own grandson►. <verse eid="HEB 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="HEB 11:25"/>He decided that it was better for others to mistreat him for a time along with the Israeli people, than to temporarily enjoy living sinfully <char style="add">in the King’s palace</char>. <verse eid="HEB 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="HEB 11:26"/>This is because he decided that if he suffered for the Messiah, it would be worth far more <char style="add">in God’s sight</char> than his owning all the treasures of Egypt <char style="add">that he would receive as Pharaoh’s heir. He decided that</char> because he looked forward to the time when <char style="add">God would give him</char> an <char style="add">eternal</char> reward. <verse eid="HEB 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="HEB 11:27"/>It was because he trusted God that he left Egypt. He was not afraid that the king would be angry <char style="add">because of his doing that</char>. He ◄kept going/did not turn back► because <char style="add">it was as though</char> he kept seeing <char style="add">God</char>, whom no one can see. <verse eid="HEB 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="HEB 11:28"/>It was because Moses believed <char style="add">that God would save his own people</char> that he instituted the <char style="add">festival called</char> Passover. He did that <char style="add">by commanding that the people should kill lambs and</char> sprinkle their blood <char style="add">on their</char> doorposts. They did that in order that <char style="add">the angel who</char> causes people to die would not kill [EUP] the oldest male Israelites <char style="add">when he killed the oldest sons in each Egyptian family</char>.<verse eid="HEB 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="HEB 11:29"/>It was because they trusted God that <char style="add">when </char> the <char style="add">Israelite</char> people walked through <char style="add">where</char> the Red Sea <char style="add">had been, it was</char> as <char style="add">though they walked</char> on dry land! But, when the <char style="add">army of</char> Egypt also attempted to <char style="add">cross that same water</char>, they drowned, because <char style="add">the sea came back and flooded them</char>!<verse eid="HEB 11:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="HEB 11:30"/>It was because the <char style="add">Israeli</char> people trusted God that the walls around Jericho <char style="add">city</char> collapsed, after the Israelis marched around the walls for seven days.<verse eid="HEB 11:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="HEB 11:31"/>Rahab <char style="add">had been</char> a prostitute, but because she trusted God, she did not perish with those <char style="add">inside Jericho</char> who disobeyed <char style="add">God. Joshua sent some spies</char> into the city <char style="add">in order</char> to find ways to destroy it, but God saved her because she welcomed those spies <char style="add">peaceably</char>.<verse eid="HEB 11:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Some who trusted God gained great victories and others were tortured and killed.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 11:32-38">Hebrews 11:32-38</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="HEB 11:32"/>I do not know what more I should say [RHQ] <char style="add">about others who trusted in God</char>. It would take too much time to tell about Gideon, Barak, Samson, Jephthah, David, Samuel, and the <char style="add">other</char> prophets. <verse eid="HEB 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="HEB 11:33"/>It was because they trusted God that some of them <char style="add">did great things for him</char>. Some conquered lands ruled by powerful men. Some ruled <char style="add">Israel</char> and justly <char style="add">punished those men and nations who rebelled against God</char>. Some obtained <char style="add">from God</char> the things that he promised to give them [MTY]. <verse eid="HEB 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="HEB 11:34"/>Some forced lions to keep their mouths shut. Some escaped from being destroyed by fire. Some of those people escaped from <char style="add">being killed with</char> a sword [MTY]. Some of those <char style="add">people who trusted God</char> were made strong {became mighty} again after they had once been weak. Some became powerful when they fought wars. Some caused armies <char style="add">that came from foreign lands</char> to run away from them. <verse eid="HEB 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="HEB 11:35"/>Some women <char style="add">who trusted God</char> received <char style="add">their relatives</char> back again when <char style="add">God</char> ◄<char style="add">made them live again after they had died/raised them from the dead</char>►. But <char style="add">others who trusted God</char> were tortured until they died. They were tortured because they refused to agree when <char style="add">their captors said, “We will</char> release you <char style="add">if you deny that you believe in God.” They refused to do that</char>, because they wanted to live with God forever, which is better than <char style="add">continuing to live on earth</char> after having almost died. <verse eid="HEB 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="HEB 11:36"/>Other <char style="add">people who trusted God</char> were mocked; <char style="add">some had their backs</char> cut <char style="add">open by being struck</char> with leaded whips. Some were chained and put in prison. <verse eid="HEB 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="HEB 11:37"/><char style="add">Some of</char> those believers were stoned to death {People <char style="add">killed some of those believers by</char> throwing stones at them}. Others were cut completely in two. Others were killed with swords. Others of these people who trusted God wandered around the land <char style="add">wearing garments made only of</char> skins from sheep and goats. They did not have any money. They were continually oppressed and tormented {People continuously oppressed them and tormented them}. <verse eid="HEB 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="HEB 11:38"/><char style="add">The people on earth who caused those who trusted in God to suffer were so bad that</char> they did not deserve <char style="add">to live with people who trusted God. Some who trusted God</char> wandered in deserts and on mountains. Some lived in caves and in other <char style="add">large</char> holes in the ground.<verse eid="HEB 11:38"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Only when we are together with all these people who trusted God will we receive all God has promised.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 11:39-40">Hebrews 11:39-40</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="HEB 11:39"/>Although all these people were commended <char style="add">by God</char> {<char style="add">God</char> commended all these people} because they trusted him, God did not give them all that he promised them <char style="add">while they were alive</char>. <verse eid="HEB 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="HEB 11:40"/>God knew ahead of time that what he would give us and them <char style="add">later</char> would be better than giving <char style="add">them immediately what he promised</char>. What God intends is that only when they and we are together will we have all that God intends us to have.<verse eid="HEB 11:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="HEB 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Since we know so many people with faith like that, we must put aside anything, especially sin, which hinders us, and we must strive to achieve God’s will and concentrate on Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 12:1-2">Hebrews 12:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 12:1"/>We <char style="add">know about</char> many people like that <char style="add">who showed they trusted in God</char>. They are like a crowd of spectators <char style="add">who are cheering for us inside a stadium</char> [MET]. Knowing that, we must put away all the things that hinder us, <char style="add">as a runner puts aside everything that would hinder him because they are heavy</char> [MET]. Especially we must put away sinful actions that <char style="add">hinder us, as a runner</char> sets aside clothes he does not need, clothes that would entangle him [MET]. Let us <char style="add">wholeheartedly strive to achieve what God has planned for us, as someone</char> in a race wholeheartedly runs the course that is before him [MET]. <verse eid="HEB 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 12:2"/>And let us <char style="add">keep our minds on</char> Jesus, <char style="add">as a runner</char> keeps his eyes on <char style="add">the goal</char> [MET]. Jesus is the one we should imitate in the way he perfectly trusted <char style="add">God. When he died on</char> the cross he endured it as he suffered greatly [MTY], instead of <char style="add">thinking about the things he would</char> rejoice about <char style="add">later</char>. He disregarded being disgraced by <char style="add">dying that way</char>. He is now sitting at the place of highest honor [MTY] at the throne <char style="add">where God rules</char>.<verse eid="HEB 12:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not become discouraged when you are suffering as you struggle against evil.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 12:3-6">Hebrews 12:3-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 12:3"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus</char> patiently endured it when sinful people acted so hostilely against him. Try to act the way he did, so that you do not give up <char style="add">trusting</char> God or become discouraged. <verse eid="HEB 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 12:4"/>While you have struggled against <char style="add">being tempted to</char> sin, you have not yet bled <char style="add">and died because of resisting evil, as Jesus did</char>. <verse eid="HEB 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 12:5"/>Do not forget [RHQ] these words <char style="add">that Solomon spoke to his son, that are the same as God</char> would exhort you as his children:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 12:5">My child, pay attention [LIT] when the Lord is disciplining you,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 12:5">and do not be discouraged when the Lord punishes you [DOU],<verse eid="HEB 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 12:6"/>because it is everyone whom he loves whom the Lord disciplines,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 12:6">and he punishes everyone whom he accepts as his child.<verse eid="HEB 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Since our sufferings are to discipline us, if we have not experienced God’s discipline we are not his true children. We should accept God’s discipline, because it is always to help us.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 12:7-11">Hebrews 12:7-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 12:7"/>It is in order that God may discipline you that he requires you to endure the disagreeable things <char style="add">that happen to you</char>. <char style="add">When God disciplines you</char> he is treating you as a father treats his children. All fathers [RHQ] discipline their children [LIT]. <verse eid="HEB 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 12:8"/>So, if you have not experienced God disciplining you just like he disciplines all his other children, you are <char style="add">not true children of God</char> [MET]. <char style="add">You are like</char> illegitimate children; <char style="add">no father disciplines them</char>. <verse eid="HEB 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 12:9"/>Furthermore, our natural fathers disciplined us <char style="add">when we were young</char>, and we respected them for doing that. So we should certainly more readily accept God our spiritual Father disciplining us, with the result that we live eternally [RHQ]! <verse eid="HEB 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 12:10"/>Our natural fathers disciplined us for a short time in a way that they considered right, <char style="add">but it wasn’t always right</char>, but God always disciplines us <char style="add">in a right way</char>, to help us. He does it so that we may be holy as he is. <verse eid="HEB 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 12:11"/>During the time that God is disciplining us, that does not seem to be something about which we should rejoice. Instead, it is something that pains us. But later it causes those who have learned from it to be peaceful and to <char style="add">live</char> righteously.<verse eid="HEB 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Renew yourselves spiritually; go forward in your Christian life; try to live peacefully with everyone; seek to be holy; guard against bitterness; do not be immoral; and do not refuse to listen to God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 12:12-17">Hebrews 12:12-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 12:12"/>So, <char style="add">instead of acting as though you were spiritually exhausted</char>, renew yourselves [MET] spiritually. <verse eid="HEB 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 12:13"/>Go straight forward <char style="add">in your Christian life</char> [MET], in order that believers who are uncertain about their faith <char style="add">will imitate you</char> and not ◄<char style="add">leave God’s way/</char>become useless <char style="add">to God</char>► [MET]. Instead, they will be spiritually restored [MET] as an injured and useless limb is restored. <verse eid="HEB 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 12:14"/>Try to live peacefully with all people. Seek to be holy, since no one will see the Lord if he is not holy. <verse eid="HEB 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 12:15"/>Beware that none of you stops <char style="add">trusting in</char> God, <char style="add">who has done kind things for us that we did not deserve</char> (OR, Beware that you have never <char style="add">experienced</char> God kindly <char style="add">saving you</char>). Be on guard lest any of you <char style="add">act in an evil way towards others</char>, because your doing that will <char style="add">grow like</char> [MET] a root <char style="add">grows into a big plant</char>, and the result <char style="add">of your</char> doing that will be that many believers will sin and become unacceptable to God. <verse eid="HEB 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 12:16"/>Do not let anyone be immoral, or be irreligious as Esau was. He exchanged the rights he had as a firstborn son for only one meal. <verse eid="HEB 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 12:17"/>You know that after he did that, he wanted to receive <char style="add">what his father would promise to give him if</char> he blessed him. But <char style="add">his father</char> was unable <char style="add">to change what he had already done</char>. And Esau found no way to change things, even though he sought tearfully to do that.<verse eid="HEB 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">You have not experienced the terrifying things your ancestors did; you have come to Christ and benefited from his blood flowing for you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 12:18-24">Hebrews 12:18-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 12:18"/>In coming <char style="add">to God</char> you have not <char style="add">experienced things like what the Israeli people experienced</char> at <char style="add">Sinai</char> Mountain. <char style="add">They</char> approached <char style="add">a mountain that God told them they</char> should not touch. <char style="add">They approached</char> a blazing fire, and it was gloomy and dark [DOU], and there was a hurricane/cyclone. <verse eid="HEB 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 12:19"/>They heard a trumpet sounding and they heard <char style="add">God</char> speak. The result was that those who heard it pleaded for God not to speak to them like that again. <verse eid="HEB 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="HEB 12:20"/>When <char style="add">God</char> commanded them saying, “If <char style="add">a person or</char> even an animal touches this mountain, <char style="add">you</char> must <char style="add">kill him/it by</char> throwing stones at him/it,” they were terrified. <verse eid="HEB 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="HEB 12:21"/>Truly, because Moses was terrified after seeing what happened <char style="add">on the mountain</char>, he said, “I am trembling because I am very afraid!” <verse eid="HEB 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="HEB 12:22"/>Instead, <char style="add">it is as though</char> you have come to <char style="add">the presence of God in heaven</char> [MET]. <char style="add">That is like what your ancestors did when they came to worship</char> God on Zion Hill, in Jerusalem, in the city of God who is all-powerful. You have come (OR, you are coming) to where there are countless angels, who are rejoicing as they have gathered together. <verse eid="HEB 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="HEB 12:23"/>You have joined all the believers <char style="add">who have privileges like</char> firstborn sons, whose names <char style="add">God</char> has written down in heaven. You have come to God, who will judge everyone. You have come to where the spirits of God’s people are, people who lived righteously <char style="add">before they died</char>, and who now have been made perfect <char style="add">in heaven</char>. <verse eid="HEB 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="HEB 12:24"/>You have come to Jesus, who arranged a new covenant <char style="add">between us and God</char>. You have accepted <char style="add">what he accomplished when</char> his blood flowed <char style="add">when he died on the cross. His doing that made it possible for God to forgive us</char>. That is better than the blood of Abel, <char style="add">who just</char> wanted revenge because his brother Cain murdered him.<verse eid="HEB 12:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We should be in awe before God, who will punish us if we reject him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 12:25-29">Hebrews 12:25-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="HEB 12:25"/>Beware that you do not refuse to listen to <char style="add">God</char> who is speaking to you. The Israeli people did not escape <char style="add">God punishing them</char> when <char style="add">Moses</char> (OR, <char style="add">God</char>) warned them here on earth. So we shall surely not escape <char style="add">God punishing us</char> if we reject him when he warns us from heaven! [RHQ] <verse eid="HEB 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="HEB 12:26"/>The earth shook [PRS] then when he spoke [MTY] <char style="add">at Sinai Mountain</char>. But now he has promised, “I will shake the earth again, one more time, but I will shake heaven too.” <verse eid="HEB 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="HEB 12:27"/>The words “again, one more time” indicate that things <char style="add">on earth</char> will be shaken {that <char style="add">he</char> will shake things <char style="add">on earth</char>}, meaning that he will set aside all that <char style="add">he</char> has created, in order that the things <char style="add">in heaven</char> that cannot be shaken {that nothing can shake} may remain forever. <verse eid="HEB 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="HEB 12:28"/>So, let us thank God that we are becoming members of a kingdom that nothing can shake. Let us worship/serve God in a way that pleases him by being greatly in awe [DOU] before him. <verse eid="HEB 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="HEB 12:29"/>Remember that the God we <char style="add">worship/serve</char> is like a fire that burns up everything <char style="add">that is impure</char> [MET]!<verse eid="HEB 12:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="HEB 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Love one another, be hospitable, and help imprisoned and other mistreated believers.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:1-3">Hebrews 13:1-3</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="HEB 13:1"/>Continue to love your fellow believers. <verse eid="HEB 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="HEB 13:2"/>Do not forget to be hospitable to needy travelers [LIT]. You need to know that by being hospitable, some people have entertained angels without knowing it. <verse eid="HEB 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="HEB 13:3"/>Remember <char style="add">to help</char> those who are in prison <char style="add">because they are Christians</char>, as though you were in prison with them. Remember those who are being mistreated {whom people are mistreating} <char style="add">because they are believers. As you do that</char>, consider that you you could suffer as they do.<verse eid="HEB 13:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Respect the marriage relationship, and avoid covetousness.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:4-6">Hebrews 13:4-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="HEB 13:4"/>You must ◄respect/keep sacred► the marriage relationship in every way, and you must keep sexual relations [EUP] pure, because God will surely condemn those who act immorally and those who act adulterously. <verse eid="HEB 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="HEB 13:5"/>Live without constantly coveting money, and be content with the things you possess, remembering what <char style="add">Moses</char> wrote <char style="add">that God</char> has said <char style="add">about supplying what you need</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 13:5">I will never leave you,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 13:5">I will never stop providing for you [DOU].<verse eid="HEB 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="HEB 13:6"/>So we can say confidently <char style="add">as the Psalmist said</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="HEB 13:6">Since the Lord is the one who helps me, I will not be afraid! People can do nothing to me <char style="add">that will deprive me of God’s blessings</char> [RHQ].<verse eid="HEB 13:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Remember how your former spiritual leaders lived and imitate their faith; since Christ never changes, do not be diverted to strange teachings.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:7-9">Hebrews 13:7-9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="HEB 13:7"/>Your spiritual leaders used to tell you the message from God <char style="add">before they died</char>. Remember how they conducted their lives. By considering ◄how they died/what resulted from how they lived►, imitate how they believed <char style="add">in Christ/God</char>. <verse eid="HEB 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="HEB 13:8"/>Jesus Christ <char style="add">is</char> the same now as he was previously, and he will be the same forever. <verse eid="HEB 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="HEB 13:9"/><char style="add">So</char>, do not let yourselves be diverted {let anything divert you} so that you believe various teachings <char style="add">that are contrary to God’s truth</char>. It is good that God acts kindly toward us so that we may be strengthened spiritually. <char style="add">Obeying rules about</char> various foods, rules that have not benefited those who obeyed them, will not benefit us.<verse eid="HEB 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We must stop practicing Jewish sacrifices and rituals, and go to Jesus to be saved, since we do not have a city like Jerusalem where we must offer sacrifices, but instead we wait for a future everlasting heavenly city.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:10-14">Hebrews 13:10-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="HEB 13:10"/>We have <char style="add">Jesus</char> [MTY]. All those who continue to observe the Jewish rituals [MTY] of sacrifice have no right to obtain the benefits of his sacrifice [MET]. <verse eid="HEB 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="HEB 13:11"/>After the high priest brings into the most holy place the blood of animals <char style="add">that they have sacrificed to atone</char> for sins, the bodies of those animals are burned {they burn the bodies of those animals} outside the camp. <verse eid="HEB 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="HEB 13:12"/>Similarly, Jesus suffered <char style="add">and died</char> outside the gate <char style="add">of Jerusalem</char> in order that he might make <char style="add">us</char>, his people, holy by <char style="add">offering</char> his own blood <char style="add">as a sacrifice to atone for our sins</char>.<verse eid="HEB 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="HEB 13:13"/>So, we must abandon <char style="add">performing Jewish</char> sacrifices and rituals [MET] <char style="add">in order to be saved</char>, and let us go to Jesus <char style="add">to be saved</char>. As we do that, we must <char style="add">be willing to</char> let others reproach us just like people reproached Jesus. <verse eid="HEB 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="HEB 13:14"/>Here on earth, we believers do not have a city <char style="add">such as Jerusalem where we must</char> continually <char style="add">offer sacrifices</char> [MET]. Instead, we are waiting for a future <char style="add">heavenly</char> city <char style="add">that will last forever</char>.<verse eid="HEB 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Since Christ sacrificed himself for us, let our continual praise of God be our sacrifice.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:15">Hebrews 13:15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="HEB 13:15"/>With <char style="add">the help of</char> Jesus, we must continually praise God. That will be something we can sacrifice <char style="add">to him</char> [MET] <char style="add">instead of our sacrificing animals only at specific times</char>. Specifically, we must say openly [MTY] <char style="add">that we have trusted</char> in Christ [MTY].<verse eid="HEB 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Continually do good deeds and share with others, because this too will be a sacrifice pleasing to God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:16">Hebrews 13:16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="HEB 13:16"/>Be continually [LIT] doing good deeds <char style="add">for others</char>, and be continually sharing <char style="add">with others the things you have</char>, because doing things like that will <char style="add">also</char> be <char style="add">as though you are offering</char> sacrifices that will please God.<verse eid="HEB 13:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Obey your spiritual leaders.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:17">Hebrews 13:17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="HEB 13:17"/>Obey your <char style="add">spiritual</char> leaders; do what they tell you, since they are the ones who are looking out for your spiritual welfare [SYN]. <char style="add">Some day</char> they will have to stand before God so that he can say if he approves of what they have done. Obey them in order that they can do the work of guarding you joyfully, and not have to do it sadly, because if you cause them to do it sadly, that will certainly not help you at all (OR, they will not be able to help you at all).<verse eid="HEB 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Pray for me that God will quickly remove the things that hinder my coming to you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:18-19">Hebrews 13:18-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="HEB 13:18"/>Pray for me. I am certain that I have not done anything that displeases God. I have tried to act honorably <char style="add">toward you</char> in every way. <verse eid="HEB 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="HEB 13:19"/>I urge you earnestly to pray that <char style="add">God</char> will quickly remove the things that hinder my coming to you.<verse eid="HEB 13:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">May God equip you with everything good that you need, and may Christ be praised forever.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:20-21">Hebrews 13:20-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="HEB 13:20"/>Jesus <char style="add">provides for us</char>, <char style="add">protects us, and guides us as</char> a great shepherd does for his sheep [MET]. And God, who gives us <char style="add">inner</char> peace, brought our Lord Jesus back to life. By doing that, God ratified his eternal covenant with us by the blood <char style="add">that flowed from Jesus when he died on the</char> cross. <verse eid="HEB 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="HEB 13:21"/>So I pray that God will equip you with everything good <char style="add">that you need in order</char> that you may do the things that he desires. May he accomplish in our lives whatever he considers pleasing as a result of Jesus Christ <char style="add">equipping us</char>. May Jesus Christ be praised forever. ◄Amen!/May it be so!►<verse eid="HEB 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Patiently consider what I have written in this short exhortation.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:22">Hebrews 13:22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="HEB 13:22"/>My fellow believers, I appeal to you that you patiently consider <char style="add">what</char> I have written in this short letter, to exhort you.<verse eid="HEB 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Since Timothy has been released from prison, he will accompany me when I go to see you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:23">Hebrews 13:23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="HEB 13:23"/>I want you to know that our fellow believer Timothy has been released {<char style="add">the authorities</char> have released our fellow believer Timothy} <char style="add">from prison</char>. If he comes here soon, he will accompany me when I go to see you.<verse eid="HEB 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Greet your spiritual leaders and all other believers; the believers who are from Italy send you their greetings.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:24">Hebrews 13:24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="HEB 13:24"/>Tell all your <char style="add">spiritual</char> leaders and all the <char style="add">other</char> fellow believers <char style="add">in your city</char> that ◄I am thinking fondly about them/I am sending them my greetings►. The believers <char style="add">in this area who have come</char> from Italy <char style="add">want you to know they</char> are ◄thinking about you/sending you their greetings►.<verse eid="HEB 13:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">May God act graciously to you all.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="HEB 13:25">Hebrews 13:25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="HEB 13:25"/>
    <char style="add">I pray that</char> you will continue to experience God’s acting kindly toward you all.<verse eid="HEB 13:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="HEB 13"/>
</usx>
