<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JDG" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">JUDGES</para>
  <para style="toc1">Judges</para>
  <para style="toc2">Judges</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jdg</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of people who delivered Israel from their enemies. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Judges</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JDG 1"/>
  <para style="s1">The tribes of Judah and Simeon defeated the Canaanites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 1:1"/>After Joshua died, the Israeli people asked Yahweh, “Which <char style="add">of our tribes</char> should attack the Canaan people-group first?”<verse eid="JDG 1:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 1:2"/>Yahweh replied, “I will enable the tribe of Judah to defeat [IDM] the Canaan people-group.”<verse eid="JDG 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 1:3"/>The men of Judah went to their fellow Israelis, <char style="add">the men</char> from the tribe of Simeon, and said to them, “Come and help us to fight the Canaan people-group <char style="add">in order that we can take from them</char> the land <char style="add">that Yahweh</char> allotted to us. If you do that, we will go with you <char style="add">and help you</char> conquer the people in the land <char style="add">that Yahweh promised to give to</char> you.” So the men from the tribe of Simeon went with the men of the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="JDG 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 1:4"/>When the men of those two tribes attacked, Yahweh enabled them to defeat 10,000 men of the Canaan people-group and the Periz people-group [DOU] at Bezek <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="JDG 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 1:5"/>During the battle they found Adoni-Bezek, the leader of the city, <verse eid="JDG 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 1:6"/>but he <char style="add">tried to</char> run away. The Israelis pursued him and caught him. Then they cut off his thumbs and his big toes.<verse eid="JDG 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 1:7"/>Adoni-Bezek said, “<char style="add">My army captured</char> 70 kings. We cut off their thumbs and big toes. After that, <char style="add">we forced</char> those kings to eat scraps that fell from our table. Now God has ◄paid me back for/done to me like► <char style="add">what we did to them</char>.” Then the men of Judah took Adoni-Bezek to Jerusalem, and he died there.<verse eid="JDG 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 1:8"/>The army of Judah fought against the men of Jerusalem, and they captured the city. With their swords they killed <char style="add">the people who lived there</char> and they burned <char style="add">the houses in</char> the city.<verse eid="JDG 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 1:9"/>Later, the men of Judah went down to fight the Canaan people-group who lived in the hilly area, in the desert to the south, and in the foothills <char style="add">to the west</char>. <verse eid="JDG 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 1:10"/>The men of Judah also went to fight against the Canaan people-group who lived in Hebron <char style="add">city</char>, which at that time was named Kiriath-Arba. They defeated <char style="add">the armies of kings</char> Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai.<verse eid="JDG 1:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Springs for Caleb’s daughter</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 1:11"/>Then they left that area and went to fight against the people living in Debir <char style="add">city</char>, which was previously named Kiriath-Sepher. <verse eid="JDG 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 1:12"/><char style="add">Before they attacked the city</char>, Caleb said to them, “If one of you attacks and captures Kiriath-Sepher, I will allow him to marry my daughter.” <verse eid="JDG 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 1:13"/>Othniel, who was the son of Caleb’s younger brother Kenaz, captured the city. So Caleb gave his daughter Acsah to him, to become his wife.<verse eid="JDG 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 1:14"/>When Acsah married Othniel, she told him to ask her father to give him a field. <char style="add">But she decided to ask him herself. She rode to Caleb’s house on her donkey</char>, and when she got off the donkey, Caleb <char style="add">could see that something was troubling her. So he</char> asked her, “What do you want?”<verse eid="JDG 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 1:15"/>She replied, “I want you to do a favor for me. You have given me some land in the southern desert, <char style="add">but it is very dry there</char>. So please also give me some <char style="add">land that has</char> springs of water.” So Caleb gave her some land on higher ground that had a spring, and some land on lower ground that also had a spring.<verse eid="JDG 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">More fights against the Canaanites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 1:16"/>The people of the Ken people-group who were descendants of Moses’ father-in-law left Jericho, which was called ‘The City of Palm Trees’. They went with some of the men of Judah to live with them in the southern desert area, near Arad <char style="add">city</char>.<verse eid="JDG 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 1:17"/>The men of Judah and their fellow Israelis from the tribe of Simeon defeated the people of the Canaan people-group who lived in Zephath <char style="add">city</char>. They completely destroyed the city and gave it a new name, Hormah, <char style="add">which means ‘complete destruction’</char>. <verse eid="JDG 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 1:18"/>The men of Judah also captured Gaza, Ashkelon, and Ekron <char style="add">cities</char> and all the land that is near those cities. <verse eid="JDG 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 1:19"/>Yahweh helped the men of Judah to capture the hilly area, but they could not force the people who were living in the plains to leave, because <char style="add">those people had better weapons—</char>they had iron chariots.<verse eid="JDG 1:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 1:20"/>Hebron <char style="add">city</char> was given to Caleb because Moses had promised him that he could have that city. And Caleb forced the three clans descended from Anak to leave that area. <verse eid="JDG 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 1:21"/>But the people of the tribe of Benjamin could not force the people of the Jebus people-group to leave Jerusalem. So, since that time the people of the Jebus people-group have lived in Jerusalem with the people of the tribe of Benjamin.<verse eid="JDG 1:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 1:22"/>The men of the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh went to fight against <char style="add">the men of</char> Bethel <char style="add">city</char>, and Yahweh helped them. <verse eid="JDG 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 1:23"/>They sent some spies to <char style="add">find out everything that they could find out about</char> Bethel, which was previously called Luz. <verse eid="JDG 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 1:24"/>The spies saw a man who was coming out of the city. They said to him, “If you show us a way to get into the city, we will be kind to you <char style="add">and we will not kill you</char>.” <verse eid="JDG 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 1:25"/>So the man showed them a way to enter the city. The men of the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh entered the city and killed all the people with their swords, but they did not kill the man <char style="add">who showed them how to get into the city</char>, and they did not kill his family. <verse eid="JDG 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 1:26"/>That man went to the area where the descendants of Heth lived, and built a city. He named the city Luz, and that is still the name of that city.<verse eid="JDG 1:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 1:27"/>There were people of the Canaan people-group who lived in Beth-Shan, Taanach, Dor, Ibleam, and Megiddo <char style="add">cities</char> and in the surrounding villages. <char style="add">The men of</char> the tribe of Manasseh did not force those people to leave those towns, because the people of the Canaan people-group were determined to stay there. <verse eid="JDG 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 1:28"/>Later, the Israelis became ◄stronger/more numerous►, and they forced the people of the Canaan people-group to work for them <char style="add">as their slaves</char>, but they did not force all the people of the Canaan people-group to leave their land. <verse eid="JDG 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 1:29"/><char style="add">The men of</char> the tribe of Ephraim did not force the people of the Canaan people-group to leave Gezer <char style="add">city</char>. So the people of the Canaan people-group continued to live with the people of the tribe of Ephraim. <verse eid="JDG 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 1:30"/><char style="add">The men of</char> the tribe of Zebulun did nor compel the people of the Canaan people-group who were living in Kitron and Nahalol <char style="add">cities</char> to leave. They stayed there and lived among the people of the tribe of Zebulun, but the people of Zebulun forced them to work for them as their slaves. <verse eid="JDG 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 1:31"/><char style="add">The men of</char> the tribe of Asher did not force the people of the Canaan people-group who lived in Acco, Sidon, Ahlab, Aczib, Helbah, Aphek and Rehob <char style="add">cities</char> to leave. <verse eid="JDG 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 1:32"/>So the people of the tribe of Asher lived among them. <verse eid="JDG 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 1:33"/><char style="add">The men of</char> the tribe of Naphtali did not compel the people who lived in Beth-Shemesh and Beth-Anath <char style="add">cities</char> to leave, so the people in those two cities continued to live there, but the people of the Canaan people-group were forced to work as the slaves of the people of the tribe of Naphtali. <verse eid="JDG 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 1:34"/>The people of the Amor people-group forced the people of the tribe of Dan to live in the hills. They did not allow them to come down <char style="add">and live</char> on the plain. <verse eid="JDG 1:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 1:35"/>The people of the Amor people-group were determined to stay in Heres Mountain and in Aijalon and Shaalbim <char style="add">cities</char>. But when the Israelis became ◄stronger/more numerous►, they forced the people of the Amor people-group to work as their slaves. <verse eid="JDG 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 1:36"/>The land where the Amor people-group lived extended from Scorpion Pass <char style="add">toward the west</char> beyond Sela <char style="add">town</char>, up into the hilly area.<verse eid="JDG 1:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JDG 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh’s message to Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 2:1"/>Yahweh <char style="add">appeared in the form of</char> an angel <char style="add">and </char> went up from Gilgal to <char style="add">a place that was later called</char> Bokim. He said <char style="add">to the Israeli people</char>, “I brought your <char style="add">ancestors</char> up here from Egypt. I led them into this land that I solemnly promised to give to your ancestors. I said to them, ‘The agreement that I made with you, as for me, I will never ◄break it/say that it is ended►. <verse eid="JDG 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 2:2"/>But as for you, you must never make a peace agreement with the people who live in this land. You must tear down the altars <char style="add">where they make sacrifices to idols</char>.’ But you have not obeyed me. <verse eid="JDG 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 2:3"/>So now, I am telling you that I will not expel <char style="add">your enemies</char> as you advance. They will be like thorns in your sides. And <char style="add">they</char> will try to trap you <char style="add">by making you worship</char> their idols.”<verse eid="JDG 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 2:4"/>After he told that to all the Israelis, the people cried loudly. <verse eid="JDG 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 2:5"/>They called that place Bokim, <char style="add">which means ‘weeping’</char>. There they offered sacrifices to Yahweh.<verse eid="JDG 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 2:6"/>After Joshua sent the Israeli people away, each group went to possess the land that had been allotted to them. <verse eid="JDG 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 2:7"/>They served Yahweh as long as Joshua was alive, and as long as the elders, those who had seen all the great things that Yahweh had done for Israel, were alive.<verse eid="JDG 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 2:8"/>Then Yahweh’s servant Joshua died. He was 110 years old when he died. <verse eid="JDG 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 2:9"/>They buried his body in the area he had received <char style="add">from Moses</char>, at Timnath-Serah, in the area where the descendants of Ephraim lived, north of Gaash Mountain.<verse eid="JDG 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis were punished for doing evil things</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 2:10"/>After all the people died who lived at the same time as Joshua [EUP], a group of people grew up who did not know Yahweh, and did not know what great things he had done for the Israeli people. <verse eid="JDG 2:10"/><verse number="11-13" style="v" sid="JDG 2:11-13"/>They did things that Yahweh said were very evil. They worshiped <char style="add">idols that represented the god</char> Baal and the goddess Astarte. They worshiped [DOU] the various gods that the people-groups around them worshiped. They stopped worshiping Yahweh, the God their ancestors worshiped, the one who had brought their ancestors out of Egypt. That caused Yahweh to be very angry. <verse eid="JDG 2:11-13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 2:14"/>So he allowed people from other groups to raid them and steal their crops and animals. They were no longer able to resist their enemies, and Yahweh allowed all their enemies around them to defeat them. <verse eid="JDG 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 2:15"/>Whenever the Israelis went to fight <char style="add">their enemies</char>, Yahweh [MTY] was opposing them, and allowed their enemies to defeat them, just as he had promised he would do. So the Israelis were greatly distressed.<verse eid="JDG 2:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 2:16"/>Then Yahweh gave leaders to them. These leaders rescued the Israelis from the people who were raiding them. <verse eid="JDG 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 2:17"/>But the Israelis still would not pay attention to their leaders. Instead, they went to the idols, <char style="add">acting like</char> prostitutes <char style="add">who gave themselves to men who were not their husbands</char> [MET], and they worshiped those idols. They were not like their ancestors. Their ancestors obeyed what Yahweh commanded, but their descendants quickly stopped behaving as their ancestors had behaved. <verse eid="JDG 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 2:18"/>Whenever Yahweh gave a leader to them, he helped that leader and enabled him to rescue the people from their enemies. He helped them like that as long as that leader was alive. Yahweh pitied them as they groaned because they were being oppressed and caused to suffer. <verse eid="JDG 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 2:19"/>But after that leader died, the people went back to behaving in ways even more evil than their ancestors had behaved. They worshiped other gods and bowed down to them and did all [LIT] the things that they thought those gods wanted them to do.<verse eid="JDG 2:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 2:20"/>So Yahweh was very angry with the Israeli people. He said, “These people have disobeyed the agreement I made with their ancestors. They have not done what I told them to do. <verse eid="JDG 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 2:21"/>So I will no longer expel the people-groups that Joshua left in this land when he died. <verse eid="JDG 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 2:22"/>I will use them to test the Israeli people to see whether they will do what I want them to do, as their ancestors did.” <verse eid="JDG 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 2:23"/>Yahweh had allowed those people-groups to stay in that land. He did not expel them by allowing Joshua <char style="add">and his men</char> to defeat them.<verse eid="JDG 2:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JDG 3"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-2" style="v" sid="JDG 3:1-2"/>At that time there were still many people-groups in Canaan. Yahweh left them there to test the Israeli people. But many of the Israelis in Canaan were ones who had not fought in any of the wars in Canaan. So Yahweh also left those people-groups in Canaan so that the descendants of those who had not fought in any of the wars might learn how to fight. <verse eid="JDG 3:1-2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 3:3"/><char style="add">This is a list of</char> the people-groups that Yahweh left there: The Philistines and their five leaders, the people living in the area near Sidon <char style="add">city</char>, the descendants of Canaan, and the descendants of Hiv who were living in the mountains of Lebanon between Baal-Hermon Mountain and Lebo-Hamath. <verse eid="JDG 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 3:4"/>Yahweh left these people-groups there to test the Israelis, to see if they would obey his commands which he had told Moses to give them. <verse eid="JDG 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 3:5"/>The Israelis lived among the Canaan people-group, the Hiv people-group, the Amor people-group, the Periz people-group, the Hiv people-group, and the Jebus people-group. <verse eid="JDG 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 3:6"/><char style="add">Moses had told the people not to associate with any of those people</char>. But the Israelis took daughters of people from those people-groups <char style="add">to be their own wives</char>, and gave their own daughters to men of those groups, to marry them. And <char style="add">as a result</char> they started to worship the gods of those people-groups.<verse eid="JDG 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Othniel became their leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 3:7"/>The Israelis did things that Yahweh said were very evil. They forgot about Yahweh, their God, and they started to worship <char style="add">the idols that represented</char> the god Baal and the goddess Asherah. <verse eid="JDG 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 3:8"/>Yahweh became very angry with the Israelis. So he allowed king Cushan from Mesopotamia to conquer them and rule them for eight years. <verse eid="JDG 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 3:9"/>But when they pleaded to Yahweh <char style="add">to help them</char>, he gave them a leader to rescue them. He was Othniel, the son of Caleb’s younger brother Kenaz. <verse eid="JDG 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 3:10"/>Yahweh’s Spirit came upon him, and he became their leader. He <char style="add">led an army that</char> fought against <char style="add">the army of</char> Cushan, and defeated them. <verse eid="JDG 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 3:11"/>After that, there was peace in the land for 40 years, until Othniel died.<verse eid="JDG 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ehud became their next leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 3:12"/>After that, the Israelis again did things that Yahweh said were very evil. As a result, he allowed the army of King Eglon, who ruled <char style="add">the </char> Moab <char style="add">area</char>, to defeat the Israelis. <verse eid="JDG 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 3:13"/>Eglon persuaded the leaders of the Ammon and Amalek people-groups to join their armies with his army to attack Israel. They captured <char style="add">Jericho, which was called</char> ‘The City of Palm Trees’. <verse eid="JDG 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 3:14"/>Then King Eglon ruled the Israelis for eighteen years.<verse eid="JDG 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 3:15"/>But then the Israelis again pleaded to Yahweh <char style="add">to help them</char>. So he gave them another leader to rescue them. He was Ehud, a left-handed man, the son of Gera, from the descendants of Benjamin. The Israelis sent him to King Eglon to give him their yearly protection money. <verse eid="JDG 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 3:16"/>Ehud had with him a double-edged dagger, about a foot and a half long. He strapped it to his right thigh, under his clothes. <verse eid="JDG 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 3:17"/>He gave the money to King Eglon, who was a very fat man. <verse eid="JDG 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 3:18"/>Then Ehud started to go back home with the men who had carried the money. <verse eid="JDG 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 3:19"/>When they arrived at the stone carvings near Gilgal, <char style="add">he told the other men to go on, but</char> he himself turned around and went back <char style="add">to the king of Moab. When he arrived at the palace</char>, he said to the king, “Your majesty, I have a secret message for you.” So the king told all his servants to be quiet, and sent them out of the room.<verse eid="JDG 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 3:20"/>Then, as Eglon was sitting alone in the upstairs room of his summer palace, Ehud came close to him and said, “I have a message for you from God.” As the king got up from his chair, <verse eid="JDG 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 3:21"/>Ehud reached with his left hand and pulled the dagger from his right thigh, and plunged it into the king’s belly. <verse eid="JDG 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 3:22"/>He thrust it in so far that the handle went into the king’s belly, and the blade came out the king’s back. Ehud did not pull the dagger out. <char style="add">He left it there, with</char> the handle buried in the king’s fat. <verse eid="JDG 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 3:23"/>Then Ehud left the room. He went out to the porch. He shut the doors to the room and locked them.<verse eid="JDG 3:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 3:24"/>After he had gone, King Eglon’s servants came back, but they saw that the doors of the room were locked. They said, “The king must be defecating in the inner room.” <verse eid="JDG 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 3:25"/>So they waited, but when the king did not open the doors of the room, after a while they were worried. They got a key and unlocked the doors. And they saw that their king was lying on the floor, dead.<verse eid="JDG 3:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 3:26"/>Meanwhile, Ehud escaped. He passed by the stone carvings and arrived at Seirah, in the hilly area where the descendants of Ephraim lived. <verse eid="JDG 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 3:27"/>There he blew a trumpet <char style="add">to signal that the people should join him to fight the people of Moab</char>. So the Israelis went with him from the hills. They went down <char style="add">toward the Jordan river</char>, with Ehud leading them.<verse eid="JDG 3:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 3:28"/>He said to the men, “Yahweh is going to allow us to defeat your enemies, the people of Moab. So follow me!” So they followed him down to the river, and they stationed some of their men at the place where people can walk across the river, in order that they could <char style="add">kill any people from Moab who tried to</char> cross the river <char style="add">to escape</char>. <verse eid="JDG 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 3:29"/>At that time, the Israelis killed about 10,000 people from Moab. They were all strong and capable men, but not one of them escaped. <verse eid="JDG 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 3:30"/>On that day, the Israelis conquered the people of Moab. Then there was peace in their land for 80 years.<verse eid="JDG 3:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Shamgar became their next leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 3:31"/>After Ehud <char style="add">died</char>, Shamgar became their leader. He rescued the Israelis <char style="add">from the Philistines. In one battle</char> he killed 600 Philistines with an ◄ox goad/sharp wooden pole►.<verse eid="JDG 3:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JDG 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Deborah became the next leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 4:1"/>After Ehud died, the Israelis again started doing things Yahweh said were very evil. <verse eid="JDG 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 4:2"/>So he allowed the army of Jabin, one of the kings of Canaan land, who ruled in Hazor <char style="add">city</char>, to conquer the Israelis. The commander of his army was Sisera, who lived in Harosheth-Haggoyim. <verse eid="JDG 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 4:3"/>Sisera’s <char style="add">army</char> had 900 chariots. For 20 years he oppressed the Israelis. Then they pleaded to Yahweh to help them.<verse eid="JDG 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 4:4"/>At that time Deborah, who was the wife of Lappidoth, was a prophetess who had become the leader in Israel. <verse eid="JDG 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 4:5"/>She would sit under her palm tree at a place between Ramah and Bethel, in the hilly area where the descendants of Ephraim lived, and people would come to her and ask her to settle disputes between them. <verse eid="JDG 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 4:6"/>One day she summoned Barak, the son of Abinoam, when he was in Kedesh, in the area where the descendants of Naphtali lived. She said to him, “This is what Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis worship, is commanding you to do: ‘Take with you 1,000 men, some from the descendants of Naphtali and some from the descendants of Zebulun, and lead them to Tabor Mountain. <verse eid="JDG 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 4:7"/>Yahweh will lure Sisera, the commander of King Jabin’s army, to come with his chariots and his army, to the Kishon River, <char style="add">a few miles away</char>. I will enable your men to defeat them there.’ ”<verse eid="JDG 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 4:8"/>Barak replied, “I will go only if you go with me.”<verse eid="JDG 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 4:9"/>She replied, “Okay, I will go with you. But because that is what you have decided to do, Yahweh will enable a woman to defeat Sisera, and the result will be that ◄you will not be honored/people will not honor you► <char style="add">for doing that</char>.” <verse eid="JDG 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 4:10"/>So Deborah went with Barak to Kedesh. There he summoned men from Zebulun and Naphtali. Ten thousand men came to him, and then they went together with Deborah <char style="add">to Tabor Mountain</char>.<verse eid="JDG 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 4:11"/>At that time Heber, one of the descendants of the Ken people-group, had moved <char style="add">with his wife Jael</char> from the area where that group lived, and set up his tent near the big oak tree at Zaanannim, near Kedesh. Heber was a descendant of Moses’ brother-in-law Hobab.<verse eid="JDG 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 4:12"/>Someone told Sisera that Barak had gone up on Tabor Mountain <char style="add">with an army</char>. <verse eid="JDG 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 4:13"/>So he gathered his troops with their 900 chariots, and they marched from Harosheth-Haggoyim to the Kishon River.<verse eid="JDG 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 4:14"/>Then Deborah said to Barak, “Get ready! This is the day that Yahweh will enable your <char style="add">army</char> to defeat the army of Sisera. Yahweh is going ahead of you!” So Barak led his men as they descended from Tabor Mountain. <verse eid="JDG 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 4:15"/>As they advanced, Yahweh caused Sisera and all his chariots and his army to have great difficulty maneuvering/moving around. So Sisera jumped down from his chariot and ran away. <verse eid="JDG 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 4:16"/>But Barak and his men pursued the other chariots and the enemy soldiers as far as Harosheth-Haggoyim. They killed all of the men in Sisera’s army. Not one man survived.<verse eid="JDG 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 4:17"/>But Sisera ran to Jael’s tent. He did that because <char style="add">his boss</char>, King Jabin of Hazor <char style="add">city</char>, was a good friend of <char style="add">Jael’s husband</char> Heber.<verse eid="JDG 4:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 4:18"/>Jael went out to greet Sisera. She said to him, “Sir, come into my tent! Do not be afraid!” So he went into the tent <char style="add">and lay down</char>, and she covered him with a blanket.<verse eid="JDG 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 4:19"/>He said to her, “I’m thirsty; can you give me some water?” So she opened a leather container of milk, and gave him a drink. Then she covered him with the blanket again.<verse eid="JDG 4:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 4:20"/>He said to her, “Stand in the entrance of the tent. If someone comes and asks ‘Is anyone else here?’, say ‘No.’”<verse eid="JDG 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 4:21"/>Sisera was very exhausted, so he soon was asleep. While he was sleeping, Jael crept quietly to him, holding a hammer and a tent peg. She pounded the peg into his skull, and all the way through his head into the ground, and he died.<verse eid="JDG 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 4:22"/>When Barak passed by Jael’s tent to look for Sisera, she went out to greet him. She said, “Come in, and I will show you the man you are searching for!” So he followed her into the tent, and he saw Sisera lying there, dead, with the tent peg through his head.<verse eid="JDG 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 4:23"/>On that day God enabled the Israelis to defeat <char style="add">the army of</char> Jabin, the king of the people of Canaan. <verse eid="JDG 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 4:24"/>From that time, the Israeli people continued to become stronger, and <char style="add">the army of</char> King Jabin continued to become weaker. Finally the Israelis were able to completely subdue the people ruled by the king of Canaan.<verse eid="JDG 4:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JDG 5"/>
  <para style="s1">The song that Deborah sang</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 5:1"/>On that day, Deborah sang this song, along with Barak:<verse eid="JDG 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 5:2"/>“When the leaders of the Israeli people really lead them, and the people follow them, <char style="add">it is time to</char> praise Yahweh!<verse eid="JDG 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 5:3"/>Listen, you kings! Pay attention, you leaders!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:3">I will sing to Yahweh. With this song I will praise Yahweh, the God we Israelis worship.<verse eid="JDG 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 5:4"/>O Yahweh, when you came from Seir, when you marched from that land <char style="add">better known as</char> Edom,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:4">the earth shook,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:4">and rain poured down from the skies.<verse eid="JDG 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 5:5"/>The mountains shook when you came,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:5">just like Sinai Mountain shook when you appeared there,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:5">because you are Yahweh,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:5">the God whom we Israelis worship.<verse eid="JDG 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 5:6"/>“When Shamgar was our leader and when Jael ruled us,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:6">
    <char style="add">we were afraid to walk on</char> the main roads;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:6">instead, caravans of travelers walked on winding <char style="add">less traveled</char> roads</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:6">
    <char style="add">to avoid being molested</char>.<verse eid="JDG 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 5:7"/>People left their small villages, <char style="add">and moved into the walled cities</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:7">until I, Deborah, became their leader.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:7">
    <char style="add">I became like</char> a mother to the Israeli people.<verse eid="JDG 5:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 5:8"/>When the Israeli people <char style="add">abandoned Yahweh and</char> chose new gods,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:8">enemies attacked the gates of the cities,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:8">and then <char style="add">they took away</char> the shields and spears from 40,000 Israeli soldiers.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:8">Not one shield or spear was left.<verse eid="JDG 5:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 5:9"/>I am thankful for the leaders and soldiers who volunteered <char style="add">to fight</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:9">Praise Yahweh <char style="add">for them!</char><verse eid="JDG 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 5:10"/>“You wealthy people who ride on donkeys,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:10">sitting on nice padded saddles,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:10">and you people who just walk on the road,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:10">you all listen!<verse eid="JDG 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 5:11"/>Listen to the voices of the singers who gather at the places where <char style="add">the animals drink</char> water.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:11">They tell about how Yahweh acted righteously</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:11">when he enabled the Israeli warriors to conquer <char style="add">their enemies</char>.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="JDG 5:11"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:11">“Yahweh’s people marched down to the gates of our city.<verse eid="JDG 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 5:12"/>The people came to my house and shouted,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:12">‘Deborah, wake up! Wake up and start singing!’</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:12">They also shouted,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:12">‘Barak, son of Abinoam, get up, and capture our enemies!’<verse eid="JDG 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 5:13"/>Later, some of the Israeli people came down <char style="add">from Tabor Mountain</char></para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:13">with us, their leaders.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:13">These men who belonged to Yahweh came with me</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:13">to fight their strong enemies.<verse eid="JDG 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 5:14"/>Some came from the tribe descended from Ephraim.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:14">They came from land that once belonged to the descendants of Amalek.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:14">And men from the tribe descended from Benjamin followed them.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:14">Troops from the group descended from Makir also came down,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:14">and officers from the tribe descended from Zebulun came down, carrying staffs.<verse eid="JDG 5:14"/></para>
  <para style="q2">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 5:15"/>Leaders from the tribes descended from Issachar joined Barak and me.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:15">They followed Barak, rushing down into the valley.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:15">But men from the tribe descended from Reuben could not decide whether or not to join us.<verse eid="JDG 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 5:16"/>Why did you men stay at your sheep pens,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:16">waiting to hear the shepherds whistle for their flocks of sheep to come to the pens?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:16">Men in the tribe descended from Reuben could not decide</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:16">whether they would join us to fight our enemies, or not.<verse eid="JDG 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 5:17"/>Similarly, the men living in the Gilead area stayed at home, east of the Jordan River.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:17">And the men from the tribe descended from Dan,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:17">why did they stay home?</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:17">The tribe descended from Asher sat by the seashore.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:17">They stayed in their coves.<verse eid="JDG 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 5:18"/>But men from the tribe descended from Zebulun risked ◄their lives/were ready to die fighting► on the battlefield,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:18">and men descended from Naphtali were ready to do that, also.<verse eid="JDG 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 5:19"/>“The kings of Canaan fought us at Taanach, near the springs in Megiddo <char style="add">Valley</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:19">
    <char style="add">But since they did not defeat us</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:19">they did not carry away any silver or other treasures from the battle.<verse eid="JDG 5:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 5:20"/>
    <char style="add">It was as though</char> the stars in the sky fought for us</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:20">
    <char style="add">and as though</char> those stars in their paths fought against Sisera.<verse eid="JDG 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 5:21"/>The Kishon River swept them away—</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:21">that river that has been there for ages.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:21">I will tell myself to be brave and continue marching on.<verse eid="JDG 5:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 5:22"/>The hooves of the horses of Sisera’s <char style="add">army</char> pounded the ground.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:22">Those powerful horses kept galloping along.<verse eid="JDG 5:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 5:23"/>The angel sent by Yahweh said,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:23">‘Curse the people of Meroz <char style="add">town</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:23">because they did not come to help Yahweh</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:23">to defeat the mighty warriors <char style="add">of Canaan</char>.’<verse eid="JDG 5:23"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 5:24"/>“But God is very pleased with Jael,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:24">the wife of Heber from the Ken people-group.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:24">He is more pleased with her than with all the other women who live in tents.<verse eid="JDG 5:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 5:25"/>Sisera asked for some water,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:25">but Jael gave him some milk.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:25">She brought him some yogurt/curds in a bowl that was suitable for kings.<verse eid="JDG 5:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 5:26"/>Then, <char style="add">when he was asleep</char>, she reached for a tent peg with her left hand,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:26">and she reached for a hammer with her right hand.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:26">She hit Sisera hard with it and crushed his head.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:26">She pounded the tent peg right through his head.<verse eid="JDG 5:26"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 5:27"/>He collapsed</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:27">and fell dead at her feet.<verse eid="JDG 5:27"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 5:28"/>“Sisera’s mother looked out from her window.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:28">She waited for him to return.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 5:28">She said, ‘Why is he taking so long to come home in his chariot?</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:28">Why don’t I hear the sound of the wheels of his chariot?’<verse eid="JDG 5:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 5:29"/>One wise woman replied to her,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:29">and she <char style="add">kept consoling herself by</char> repeating those words:<verse eid="JDG 5:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 5:30"/>‘Perhaps they are dividing up the things and the people they captured after the battle.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:30">Each soldier will get one or two women.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:30">Sisera will get some beautiful robes,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:30">and some beautiful embroidered robes for me.’<verse eid="JDG 5:30"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 5:31"/>But <char style="add">that is not what happened</char>! Yahweh, I hope that all your enemies will die as Sisera did!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 5:31">And I desire that all those who love you will be as strong as the sun when it rises!<verse eid="JDG 5:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JDG 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Gideon became the next leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 6:1"/>Again the Israelis did things that Yahweh said were very evil. So he allowed the people of Midian to conquer them and rule them for seven years. <verse eid="JDG 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 6:2"/>The people of Midian treated the Israelis so cruelly that the Israelis fled to the mountains. There they made places to live in caves and animal dens. <verse eid="JDG 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 6:3"/>Whenever the Israelis planted things in their fields, the people of Midian and Amalek and other groups from the east invaded Israel. <verse eid="JDG 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 6:4"/>They set up tents in the area, and then destroyed the crops as far south as Gaza. They did not leave anything for the Israelis’ sheep or cattle or donkeys to eat. <verse eid="JDG 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 6:5"/>They came into Israel with their tents and their livestock like a swarm of locusts. There were <char style="add">so many of them that</char> arrived riding on their camels that no one could count them. They stayed and ruined the Israelis’ crops. <verse eid="JDG 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 6:6"/>The people of Midian took almost everything the Israelis owned. So finally the Israelis pleaded for Yahweh to help them.<verse eid="JDG 6:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 6:7"/>When the Israelis pleaded with Yahweh to help them because of <char style="add">what</char> the people from Midian <char style="add">were doing to them</char>, <verse eid="JDG 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 6:8"/>he sent to them a prophet, who said, “Yahweh, the God we Israelis worship, says this: ‘Your ancestors were slaves in Egypt. <verse eid="JDG 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 6:9"/>But I rescued them from the leaders of Egypt and from all the others who oppressed them. I expelled their enemies from this land, and gave it to your ancestors. <verse eid="JDG 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 6:10"/>I told you all, “I am Yahweh, your God. You are now in the land where the descendants of Amor live, but you must not worship the gods whom they worship.” But you did not pay attention to me.’”<verse eid="JDG 6:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 6:11"/>One day Yahweh appeared <char style="add">in the form of</char> an angel and sat underneath a big oak tree at Ophrah <char style="add">town</char>. That tree belonged to Joash, who was from the clan of Abiezer. Joash’s son Gideon was threshing wheat in the pit where they pressed <char style="add">grapes to make</char> wine. He was threshing the grain there in order to hide it from the people of Midian. <verse eid="JDG 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 6:12"/>Yahweh <char style="add">went over</char> to Gideon and said to him, “You mighty warrior, Yahweh is helping you!”<verse eid="JDG 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 6:13"/>Gideon replied, “Sir, if Yahweh is helping us, why have all these <char style="add">bad things</char> happened to us? We heard about [RHQ] all the miracles that Yahweh performed for our ancestors. We heard people tell us about how he rescued them from <char style="add">being slaves in</char> Egypt. But now Yahweh has abandoned us, and we are ruled by the people from Midian.”<verse eid="JDG 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 6:14"/>Then Yahweh turned toward him and said, “I will give you strength to enable you to rescue the Israelis from the people of Midian. I am sending you <char style="add">to do that</char>!”<verse eid="JDG 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 6:15"/>Gideon replied, “But Yahweh, how can I rescue the Israelis? My clan is the least significant in the whole tribe descended from Manasseh, and I am the least significant person in my whole family!”<verse eid="JDG 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 6:16"/>Yahweh said to him, “I will help you. So you will defeat the army of Midian <char style="add">as easily</char> as if you were fighting only one man!”<verse eid="JDG 6:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 6:17"/>Gideon replied, “If you are truly pleased with me, do something which will prove that you who are speaking to me are really Yahweh. <verse eid="JDG 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 6:18"/>But do not go away until I go and bring back an offering to you.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 6:18">Yahweh answered, “Okay, I will stay here until you return.”<verse eid="JDG 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 6:19"/>Gideon hurried to his home. He <char style="add">killed</char> a young goat <char style="add">and</char> cooked <char style="add">it</char>. Then he took ◄a half a bushel/18 liters► of flour and baked some bread without yeast. Then he put the cooked meat in a basket, and put the broth <char style="add">from the meat</char> in a pot, and took it to Yahweh, who was sitting under the tree.<verse eid="JDG 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 6:20"/>Then Yahweh said to him, “Put the meat and the bread on this rock. Then pour the broth on top of it.” So Gideon did that. <verse eid="JDG 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 6:21"/>Then Yahweh touched the meat and bread with the walking stick that was in his hand. A fire flamed up from the rock and burned up everything that Gideon had brought! And then Yahweh disappeared. <verse eid="JDG 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 6:22"/>When Gideon realized that it was really Yahweh <char style="add">who had appeared in the form of an angel and talked with him</char>, he exclaimed, “O, Yahweh, I have seen you face-to-face <char style="add">when you had the form of</char> an angel! <char style="add">So I will surely die</char>!”<verse eid="JDG 6:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 6:23"/>But Yahweh called to him and said, “Do not be afraid! You will not die <char style="add">because of seeing me</char>!”<verse eid="JDG 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 6:24"/>Then Gideon built an altar to <char style="add">worship</char> Yahweh there. He named it ‘Yahweh gives us peace’. That altar is still there in Ophrah <char style="add">town</char>, in the land that belongs to the descendants of Abiezer.<verse eid="JDG 6:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 6:25"/>That night Yahweh said to Gideon, “Take the second-best/oldest bull from your father’s herd, the bull that is seven years old. <char style="add">Kill it</char>. Then tear down the altar that your father built to <char style="add">worship</char> the god Baal. Also cut down the pole for worshipping <char style="add">the goddess</char> Astarte that is there beside it. <verse eid="JDG 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 6:26"/>Then build a <char style="add">stone</char> altar to worship me, your God Yahweh, here on this hill. Take the wood from the pole you cut down and make a fire <char style="add">to cook the meat of the bull</char> as a burnt offering to me.”<verse eid="JDG 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 6:27"/>So Gideon and his servants did what Yahweh commanded. But they did it at night, because he was afraid what the other members of his family and the other men in town would do to him if they found out that he had done that.<verse eid="JDG 6:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 6:28"/>Early the next morning, as soon as the men got up, they saw that the altar to Baal had been torn down, and the pole for worshiping Astarte was gone. They saw that there was a new altar there, and on it was what remained from the bull they had sacrificed.<verse eid="JDG 6:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 6:29"/>The people asked each other, “Who did this?” After they investigated, someone told them that it was Gideon, the son of Joash, <char style="add">who had done it</char>.<verse eid="JDG 6:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 6:30"/>They went to Joash and said to him, “Bring your son out here! ◄He must be executed/We must kill him►, because he destroyed our god Baal’s altar and cut down the pole for our goddess Astarte!”<verse eid="JDG 6:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 6:31"/>But Joash replied, “Are you trying to defend Baal? Are you trying to argue his case? Anyone who tries to defend Baal should be executed by tomorrow morning! If Baal is truly a god, he ought to be able to defend himself, and to get rid of the person who tore down his altar!” <verse eid="JDG 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 6:32"/>From that time, people called Gideon Jerub-Baal, which means ‘Baal should defend himself’, because he tore down Baal’s altar.<verse eid="JDG 6:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 6:33"/>Soon after that, the armies of the people of Midian and of Amalek and the people from the east gathered together. They crossed the Jordan River <char style="add">to attack the Israelis</char>. They set up their tents in Jezreel Valley. <verse eid="JDG 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 6:34"/>Then Yahweh’s Spirit took control of Gideon. He blew a ram’s horn to summon the men to prepare to fight. So the men of the clan of Abiezer came to him. <verse eid="JDG 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 6:35"/>He also sent messengers throughout the tribes descended from <char style="add">the four tribes of</char> Manasseh, Asher, Zebulun, and Naphtali <char style="add">to tell their soldiers to come</char>, and all of them came.<verse eid="JDG 6:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 6:36"/>Then Gideon said to God, “If you are truly going to enable me to rescue the Israeli people as you promised, <verse eid="JDG 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JDG 6:37"/>confirm it by doing this: Tonight I will put a dry wool fleece on the ground where I thresh the grain. Tomorrow morning, if the fleece is wet with dew but the ground is dry, then I will know that I am the one you will enable to rescue the people of Israel as you promised.” <verse eid="JDG 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JDG 6:38"/>And that is what happened. When Gideon got up the next morning, he picked up the fleece, and squeezed out a whole bowlful of water!<verse eid="JDG 6:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 6:39"/>Then Gideon said to God, “Do not be angry with me, but let me ask you to do one more thing. Tonight I will put the fleece out again. This time, let the fleece remain dry, while the ground is wet with the dew.” <verse eid="JDG 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 6:40"/>So that night, God did what Gideon asked him to do. The next morning the fleece was dry, but the ground was covered with dew.<verse eid="JDG 6:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JDG 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Gideon and his men defeated the army from Midian</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 7:1"/>The next morning, Gideon and his men got up early and went as far as Harod Spring. The army of Midian was camped north of them, in the valley near Moreh Hill. <verse eid="JDG 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 7:2"/>Yahweh said to Gideon, “You have too many soldiers with you. If I allow all of you to fight the army of Midian, <char style="add">if your army defeats them</char>, they will boast to me that they defeated their enemies by themselves, <char style="add">without my help</char>. <verse eid="JDG 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 7:3"/>So tell the men, ‘Whoever among you is timid or afraid may leave us and go home.’ ” So <char style="add">after Gideon told that to them</char>, 22,000 of them went home. Only 10,000 men were left there.<verse eid="JDG 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 7:4"/>But Yahweh told Gideon, “There are still too many men! Take them down to the spring, and there I will choose from among them, which ones will go with you and which ones will not go.”.<verse eid="JDG 7:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 7:5"/>When Gideon took the men down to the spring, Yahweh told him, “When they drink, put into one group the ones who scoop the water into their hands, and then lap it up like dogs do. Put into another group the ones who kneel down <char style="add">and bend over</char> and drink with their mouths in the water.” <verse eid="JDG 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 7:6"/>So when they drank, only 300 men drank from their hands. All the others drank with their mouths down in the water.<verse eid="JDG 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 7:7"/>Then Yahweh told Gideon, “The 300 men who lapped the water from their hands will be your army! I will enable them to defeat the Midian army. Let all the others go home!” <verse eid="JDG 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 7:8"/>So Gideon’s 300 men collected the food and rams’ horns from all the other men, and then he sent them home.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 7:8">The men of Midian were camping in the valley below Gideon. <verse eid="JDG 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 7:9"/>That night, Yahweh said to Gideon, “Get up and go down to their camp, <char style="add">and you will hear something that will convince you that</char> I will enable your men to defeat them. <verse eid="JDG 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 7:10"/>But if you are afraid to attack them by yourself, take your servant Purah with you. <verse eid="JDG 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 7:11"/>Go down and listen to what some of the Midian soldiers are saying. Then you will be very encouraged, and you will be ready to attack their camp.” So Gideon took Purah with him, and they went down to the edge of the enemy camp. <verse eid="JDG 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 7:12"/>The armies of the people of Midian and Amalek and from the east had set up their tents and looked like a swarm of locusts. It seemed that their camels were as impossible to count as the grains of sand on the seashore.<verse eid="JDG 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 7:13"/>Gideon crept closer and heard one man telling a friend about a dream. He said, “I just had a dream, and in the dream I saw a round loaf of barley bread tumble down into our Midian camp. It struck a tent so hard that the tent turned upside down and collapsed!”<verse eid="JDG 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 7:14"/>His friend said, “Your dream can mean only one thing. It means that God will enable Gideon, the man of Israel, to defeat all of the armies that are here with us men from Midian.”<verse eid="JDG 7:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 7:15"/>When Gideon heard the <char style="add">man tell about his</char> dream and the meaning of that dream, he thanked God. Then he <char style="add">and Purah</char> returned to the Israeli camp, and he shouted to the men, “Get up! Because God is enabling you to defeat the men from Midian!” <verse eid="JDG 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 7:16"/>He divided his men into three groups. He gave each man a ram’s horn and an empty clay jar. He also gave each of them a torch <char style="add">that they lit</char>.<verse eid="JDG 7:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 7:17"/>Then he said to them, “Watch me. When we come close to the enemy camp, <char style="add">spread out to surround the camp</char>. Then do exactly what I do. <verse eid="JDG 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 7:18"/>As soon as I and the men with me blow our ram’s horns, you men in the other two groups surrounding the camp blow your horns and shout, ‘<char style="add">We are doing this</char> for Yahweh and for Gideon!’”<verse eid="JDG 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 7:19"/>A while before midnight, just after a new group of Israeli guards took the places of the previous group, Gideon and the 100 men with him arrived at the edge of the Midian camp. Suddenly they all blew their horns, and broke their jars. <verse eid="JDG 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 7:20"/>Then the men in all three groups blew their horns and smashed their jars. They held the torches high with their left hands, and held up the horns with their right hands and alternatively blew them and shouted, “<char style="add">We have</char> swords <char style="add">to fight</char> for Yahweh and for Gideon!” <verse eid="JDG 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 7:21"/>Each of Gideon’s men stood in his position around the enemy camp. As they watched, all the Midian men started running around and shouting in a panic.<verse eid="JDG 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 7:22"/>While the 300 Israeli men kept blowing their horns, Yahweh caused their enemies to start fighting each other with their swords/daggers. Some of them killed each other. The rest fled. Some fled south to Beth-Shittah. Some fled to Zerarah <char style="add">village</char>, near Tabbath. <verse eid="JDG 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 7:23"/>Then Gideon sent messages to the soldiers in the areas where the descendants of Naphtali, Asher, and Manasseh lived, to tell them to come and pursue the army of Midian. <verse eid="JDG 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 7:24"/>He also sent messengers throughout the hilly area where the descendants of Ephraim lived, saying, “Come down to attack the army of Midian. Come down to the Jordan River, to the place where people can wade across, to prevent enemy troops from crossing it! Station men as far south as Beth-Barah.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 7:24">So the men of Ephraim did what Gideon told them to do. <verse eid="JDG 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 7:25"/>They also captured Oreb and Zeeb, the two generals of the Midian army. They killed Oreb at <char style="add">the big rock which is now called</char> the rock of Oreb, and they killed Zeeb at <char style="add">the place where people crush grapes that is now called</char> the winepress of Zeeb. Afterwards, the Israelis cut off the heads of Oreb and Zeeb and brought them to Gideon, while he was near the Jordan River.<verse eid="JDG 7:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JDG 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Gideon killed Zebah and Zalmunna</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 8:1"/>Then the descendants of Ephraim said to Gideon, “Why have you acted toward us like this? When you went out to fight against the people of Midian, why did you not summon us <char style="add">to help you</char>?” They rebuked Gideon severely.<verse eid="JDG 8:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 8:2"/>But Gideon replied, “I have done [RHQ] very little compared with what you have done! My small clan of descendants of Abiezer only started the battle, but <char style="add">your very large group of</char> descendants of Ephraim <char style="add">helped me to finish the task very well. It is like</char> the final grapes of the harvest being much better than the first grapes that are picked. <verse eid="JDG 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 8:3"/>God enabled you to defeat Oreb and Zeeb, the generals of the army from Midian. That is [RHQ] much more important than what I did!” After Gideon told them that, they no longer resented what he had done.<verse eid="JDG 8:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 8:4"/>Then Gideon and his 300 men <char style="add">went east and</char> crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. Although they were very tired, they continued to pursue their enemies. <verse eid="JDG 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 8:5"/>When they arrived at Succoth <char style="add">town</char>, Gideon said to the town leaders, “Please give my men some food! They are very tired. We are pursuing Zebah and Zalmunna, the kings of Midian.”<verse eid="JDG 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 8:6"/>But the leaders of Succoth replied, “You have not caught [RHQ] Zebah and Zalmunna yet. So why should we give food to your troops <char style="add">now? Catch them first, and then we will give you food</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 8:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 8:7"/>Gideon replied, “<char style="add">Because you said that</char>, after Yahweh enables us to defeat Zebah and Zalmunna, we will return. And then we will make whips from thorns from the desert, and with them we will rip the flesh off your bones!”<verse eid="JDG 8:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 8:8"/>From there, Gideon <char style="add">and his 300 men</char> went to Peniel and asked for food there, but the people gave him the same answer. <verse eid="JDG 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 8:9"/>So he said to the men of Peniel, “After I defeat those kings, I will return and tear down this tower!”<verse eid="JDG 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 8:10"/>By that time, Zebah and Zalmunna had gone to Karkor <char style="add">town</char> with 15,000 troops. They were all that were left of the armies that had come from the east. 120,000 of their men had already been killed. <verse eid="JDG 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 8:11"/>Gideon <char style="add">and his men</char> went east along the road on which caravans travel. They went past Nobah and Jogbehah <char style="add">villages</char> and arrived at the enemy camp by surprise. <verse eid="JDG 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 8:12"/>Zebah and Zalmunna fled, but Gideon’s men pursued them and captured them and all their warriors.<verse eid="JDG 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 8:13"/>After that, Gideon and his men <char style="add">took Zebah and Zalmunna with them and</char> started to return, going through Heres Pass. <verse eid="JDG 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 8:14"/>There he captured a young man from Succoth, and demanded that he write down the names of all of the leaders in the town. The young man wrote down seventy-seven names. <verse eid="JDG 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 8:15"/>Then Gideon and his men returned to Succoth and said to those leaders, “Here are Zebah and Zalmunna. When we were here before, you made fun of me and said ‘You have not [RHQ] caught Zebah and Zalmunna yet! After you catch them, we will give your exhausted men some food.’ ” <verse eid="JDG 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 8:16"/>Then Gideon’s men took the town leaders and whipped them with whips made from briers from the desert, to teach them <char style="add">that they deserved to be punished for not giving them any food</char>. <verse eid="JDG 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 8:17"/>Then <char style="add">they went to</char> Peniel and tore down the tower, and killed all the men in the town.<verse eid="JDG 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 8:18"/>Then Gideon said to Zebah and Zalmunna, “The men you killed near Tabor <char style="add">Mountain</char>, what did they look like?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 8:18">They replied, “They were like you; they all looked like they were sons of a king.”<verse eid="JDG 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 8:19"/>Gideon replied, “They were my brothers! Just as surely as Yahweh lives, I would not kill you if you had not killed them.” <verse eid="JDG 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 8:20"/>Then he turned to his oldest son, Jether. He said to him, “Kill them!” But Jether was only a boy, and he was afraid, so he did not pull out his dagger <char style="add">to kill them</char>.<verse eid="JDG 8:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 8:21"/>Then Zebah and Zalmunna said to Gideon, “Do not ask a young boy to do the work that a man should do!” So Gideon killed both of them. Then he took the gold ornaments from the necks of their camels.<verse eid="JDG 8:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Gideon refused to be their king</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 8:22"/>Then a group of Israeli men <char style="add">came to</char> Gideon and said to him, “You be our ruler! <char style="add">We want</char> you and your son and your grandsons <char style="add">to</char> be our rulers, because you rescued us from the Midian army.”<verse eid="JDG 8:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 8:23"/>But Gideon replied, “No, I will not rule over you, and my son will not rule over you. Yahweh will rule over you.” <verse eid="JDG 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 8:24"/>Then he said, “I request only one thing. I request that each of you give me one earring from the things you captured after the battle.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 8:24">[All the men descended from Ishmael wore gold earrings.] <verse eid="JDG 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 8:25"/>They replied, “We will be glad to give earrings to you!” So they spread a cloth <char style="add">on the ground</char>, and each man threw on it one gold earring that he had taken <char style="add">from a man he had killed in the battle</char>. <verse eid="JDG 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 8:26"/>The weight of all the earrings was ◄43 pounds/19.4 kg.►. That did not include other things <char style="add">that they gave to Gideon</char>—the other ornaments or the pendants or the clothes that the kings of Midian wore or the gold chains that were on the necks of their camels. <verse eid="JDG 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 8:27"/>Gideon made/decorated a sacred vest from the gold, and later he put it in his hometown, Ophrah. But soon the Israeli people started to worship the vest. So it became like a trap [MET] for the people, <char style="add">causing them to worship it instead of worshiping only God</char>.<verse eid="JDG 8:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Gideon died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 8:28"/>That is how the Israelis defeated the people from Midian. The people of Midian did not become strong enough to attack Israel again. So while Gideon was alive, there was peace in the land for 40 years.<verse eid="JDG 8:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 8:29"/>Gideon went back home to live there. <verse eid="JDG 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 8:30"/>He had many wives, and they bore him seventy sons. <verse eid="JDG 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 8:31"/>He also had a slave wife in Shechem <char style="add">town</char>, who bore him a son whom he named Abimelech. <verse eid="JDG 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 8:32"/>Gideon died when he was very old. They buried his body in the grave where his father Joash was buried, at Ophrah, in the land belonging to the descendants of Abiether.<verse eid="JDG 8:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 8:33"/>But as soon as Gideon died, the Israelis <char style="add">stopped worshiping God and started worshiping the images of the god Baal, like</char> [MET] adultresses <char style="add">leave their husbands and go to sleep with other men</char>. They made a <char style="add">statue of a</char> new god called Baal-Berith. <verse eid="JDG 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 8:34"/>They forgot about Yahweh, the one who had rescued them from all their enemies that surrounded them. <verse eid="JDG 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 8:35"/>And even though Gideon had done many good things for the Israelis, they were not kind to Gideon’s family.<verse eid="JDG 8:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JDG 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Abimelech became king in Shechem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 9:1"/>Gideon’s son Abimelech went to <char style="add">talk with</char> his mother’s brothers in Shechem <char style="add">city</char>. He said to them and to all his mother’s relatives, <verse eid="JDG 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 9:2"/>“Ask all the leaders of your city: ‘Do you <char style="add">think it would be</char> good for all 70 of Gideon’s sons to rule over you? Or would it be better to have only one of his sons, <char style="add">me</char>, to rule over you?’ And do not forget that I am your relative! [MTY]”<verse eid="JDG 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 9:3"/>So Abimelech’s mother’s brothers spoke to all the leaders of Shechem about what Abimelech had said. They said to each other, “We should allow Abimelech to rule over us, because he is our relative.” <verse eid="JDG 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 9:4"/>So the leaders of Shechem took from the temple of <char style="add">their god</char> Baal-Berith ◄almost 2 pounds/0.8 kg.► of silver and gave it to Abimelech. With that silver he paid some worthless troublemakers to help him, and they went with Abimelech wherever he went. <verse eid="JDG 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 9:5"/>They went to Ophrah, his father’s town, and murdered 69 of his 70 brothers, the sons of his father Gideon. They killed all those men on one huge rock. But Gideon’s youngest son Jotham hid <char style="add">from Abimelech and his men</char>, and he escaped. <verse eid="JDG 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 9:6"/>Then all the leaders of Shechem and Beth-Millo gathered under the big sacred tree in Shechem. There they appointed Abimelech to be their leader.<verse eid="JDG 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 9:7"/>When Jotham heard about that, he climbed up Gerizim Mountain. He stood at the top of the mountain and shouted to the people <char style="add">down below</char>, “You leaders of Shechem, listen to me, in order that God will listen to you! <verse eid="JDG 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 9:8"/>One day the trees decided to appoint a king to rule over all of them. So they said to the olive tree, ‘You be our king!’<verse eid="JDG 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 9:9"/>“But the olive tree said, ‘No! <char style="add">I will not be your king</char> Men and gods enjoy the oil from my fruit. I will not [RHQ] stop producing <char style="add">olives from which we make</char> that oil, in order to rule over you other trees!’<verse eid="JDG 9:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 9:10"/>“Then the trees said to the fig tree, ‘You come and be our king!’<verse eid="JDG 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 9:11"/>“But the fig tree replied, ‘No! I do not want to [RHQ] stop producing my good sweet fruit, and rule over you other trees!’<verse eid="JDG 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 9:12"/>“Then the trees said to the grapevine, ‘Come and be our king!’<verse eid="JDG 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 9:13"/>“But the grapevine replied, ‘No! <char style="add">I will not be your king</char> The new wine <char style="add">that is made from my grapes</char> causes people and gods <char style="add">who drink it</char> to become very happy. I do not want to stop producing grapes and rule over you other trees!’ [RHQ]<verse eid="JDG 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 9:14"/>“Then all the trees said to the thornbush, ‘Come and be our king!’<verse eid="JDG 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 9:15"/>“The thornbush replied, ‘If you truly want to appoint me to be your king, come into the shade of my <char style="add">tiny branches</char>. But if you do not want to do that, I hope/desire that fire will come out from me and burn up all the huge cedar trees in Lebanon <char style="add">country</char>!’”<verse eid="JDG 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 9:16"/>“<char style="add">After</char> Jotham <char style="add">finished telling them this parable, he</char> said, “So now <char style="add">I ask you</char>, were you being completely honest and sincere when you appointed Abimelech to be your king [RHQ]? And have you treated Gideon and his family [RHQ] fairly? Have you rewarded Gideon by honoring him as he deserved <char style="add">because of all the good things he did for you</char>? No! <verse eid="JDG 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 9:17"/>“<char style="add">Do not forget that</char> my father fought a battle for you, and he was willing to die for you <char style="add">if that had been necessary</char>, to save you from the Midian people-group. <verse eid="JDG 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 9:18"/>But now you have rebelled against my father’s family, and you have killed 69 of his sons on one huge rock. And you have appointed Abimelech—who is the son of my father’s slave girl, <char style="add">not the son of his wife</char>—to be the king who will rule you people of Shechem. You have done that only because he is one of your relatives! <verse eid="JDG 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 9:19"/>So, if today you have truly acted fairly and sincerely toward Gideon and his family, I hope/desire that he will cause you to be happy and that you will cause him to be happy. <verse eid="JDG 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 9:20"/>But if what you did was not right, I wish/desire that Abimelech will burn up all of you leaders of Shechem and Beth-Millo with fire! And I also hope/desire that the leaders of Shechem and Beth-Millo will cause fire to burn up Abimelech!”<verse eid="JDG 9:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 9:21"/>
    <char style="add">After</char> Jotham <char style="add">finished saying that, he</char> escaped from them and ran away to Beer <char style="add">town</char>. He stayed there because he was afraid that his brother Abimelech <char style="add">would try to kill him</char>.<verse eid="JDG 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Abimelech and his men killed the people of Shechem</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 9:22"/>Abimelech <char style="add">became the leader of all the people of Israel. He</char> ruled them for three years. <verse eid="JDG 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 9:23"/>Then God sent an evil spirit <char style="add">to cause trouble</char> between Abimelech and the leaders of Shechem, with the result that the leaders of Shechem rebelled against Abimelech. <verse eid="JDG 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 9:24"/>The leaders of Shechem had previously helped Abimelech to kill 69 of Gideon’s sons, who were his brothers. So now God sent the evil spirit to punish all of them. <verse eid="JDG 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 9:25"/>The leaders of Shechem ◄set an ambush/sent men to hide► on the hilltops to ambush Abimelech. Those men robbed everyone who passed by. But someone told Abimelech about it, <char style="add">so he did not go near them</char>.<verse eid="JDG 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 9:26"/>There was a man named Gaal, the son of Ebed, who moved into Shechem <char style="add">city</char>, along with his brothers. Soon the leaders of Shechem started to trust him. <verse eid="JDG 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 9:27"/>They went out <char style="add">of the city</char> to their vineyards and picked some grapes. They pressed the grapes <char style="add">to make juice, and then they made wine</char>. Then they had a feast in the temple of their god, and they ate <char style="add">a lot of food</char> and drank <char style="add">a lot of wine</char>. Then they cursed Abimelech. <verse eid="JDG 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 9:28"/>Gaal said, “◄Why should <char style="add">we allow</char> Abimelech to rule over us?/We should not allow Abimelech to rule over us!► [RHQ] He is only one of Gideon’s sons <char style="add">so he really does not belong to us</char> [RHQ]! And he appointed Zebul, the governor of our city, to be his deputy! We should ◄serve/be loyal to► <char style="add">one of the descendants of</char> Hamor, <char style="add">the founder of our city</char>, and let him be our leader, not Abimelech [RHQ]! <verse eid="JDG 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 9:29"/>If you would appoint me to be your leader, I would get rid of Abimelech. I would say to him, ‘Get your army ready, <char style="add">and then come to fight us</char>!’”<verse eid="JDG 9:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 9:30"/>When someone told Zebul what Gaal said, he was very angry. <verse eid="JDG 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 9:31"/>He secretly sent some messengers to Abimelech. They told him, “Gaal and his brothers have come here to Shechem, and they are causing <char style="add">the people of</char> the city to rebel against you. <verse eid="JDG 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 9:32"/>You and your men should get up during the night and go and hide in the fields outside the city. <verse eid="JDG 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 9:33"/>As soon as the sun rises in the morning, get up and attack the city. When Gaal and his men come out to fight against you, you can do to them whatever you want to.”<verse eid="JDG 9:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 9:34"/>So Abimelech and all the men who were with him got up during the night. They <char style="add">divided into</char> four groups, <char style="add">and </char> hid <char style="add">in the fields</char> near Shechem. <verse eid="JDG 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 9:35"/><char style="add">The next morning</char>, Gaal went out and stood at the entrance to the city gate. While he was standing there, Abimelech and his soldiers came out of their hiding places <char style="add">and started walking toward the city</char>.<verse eid="JDG 9:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 9:36"/>When Gaal saw the soldiers, he said to Zebul, “Look! There are people coming down from the hills!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 9:36">But Zebul said, “You are seeing only the shadows <char style="add">of trees</char> on the hills. They <char style="add">are not people; they</char> only resemble people.” <verse eid="JDG 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JDG 9:37"/>But Gaal <char style="add">looked</char> again <char style="add">and</char> said, “Look! There are people coming down from the top of the sacred mountain! There is a group of them coming down from where the tree is where people talk with the spirits of dead people!”<verse eid="JDG 9:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JDG 9:38"/>Zebul said to Gaal, “Now ◄what good is your bragging?/your bragging is worthless!► [MTY, RHQ] You said, ‘◄Why should we serve Abimelech/We should not allow Abimelech to rule over us►?’ You made fun of these men. So now go out and fight them!”<verse eid="JDG 9:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 9:39"/>So Gaal led the men of Shechem outside <char style="add">the city</char> to fight Abimelech <char style="add">and his men</char>. <verse eid="JDG 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 9:40"/>Abimelech and his men pursued them, and they killed many of Gaal’s men before they could return <char style="add">safely</char> inside the city gate. <verse eid="JDG 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JDG 9:41"/>Abimelech then stayed at Arumah, <char style="add">about five miles away from Shechem</char>, and Zebul’s men forced Gaal and his brothers to leave Shechem.<verse eid="JDG 9:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JDG 9:42"/>The next day, the people of Shechem <char style="add">got ready to leave the city and work</char> in their fields. When someone told Abimelech about that, <verse eid="JDG 9:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JDG 9:43"/>he divided his men into three groups, and told them to hide in the fields. So they did that. And when they saw the people coming out of the city, they jumped up and attacked them. <verse eid="JDG 9:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JDG 9:44"/>Abimelech and the men who were with him ran to the city gate. The other two groups ran out to the people in the fields and attacked them. <verse eid="JDG 9:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JDG 9:45"/>Abimelech and his men fought all day. They captured the city and killed all the people. They tore down all the buildings, and then they threw salt over the ruins <char style="add">in order that nothing would grow there again</char>.<verse eid="JDG 9:45"/></para>
  <para style="s1">They killed the people in the fortress</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="JDG 9:46"/>When the leaders who lived in the tower/fortress outside of Shechem heard what had happened, they ran and hid inside the <char style="add">fortress, which was also a</char> temple of <char style="add">their god</char> El-Berith. <verse eid="JDG 9:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JDG 9:47"/>But someone told Abimelech that all the leaders had gathered there. <verse eid="JDG 9:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JDG 9:48"/>So he and all the men who were with him went up Zalmon Mountain <char style="add">which is near Shechem</char>. Abimelech cut some branches of trees with an axe, and put them on his shoulders. Then he said to all the men who were with him, “Quickly, do what I have just done!” <verse eid="JDG 9:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JDG 9:49"/>So his men all cut branches <char style="add">then carried them down the mountain</char>, following Abimelech. They went to the fortress and piled the branches against its walls. Then they kindled a fire, and the fire burned down the fortress and killed all the people who were inside. So all the people who were inside the fortress—about 1,000 men and women—died.<verse eid="JDG 9:49"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Abimelech was killed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="JDG 9:50"/>Then Abimelech and his men went to Thebes <char style="add">city</char>. They surrounded it and captured it. <verse eid="JDG 9:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JDG 9:51"/>But there was a strong tower inside the city. So all the men, women, and leaders of the city ran to the tower. When they were all inside, they locked the door. Then they climbed up to the roof of the tower. <verse eid="JDG 9:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JDG 9:52"/>Abimelech and his men came to the tower and tried to get in the door, <char style="add">but they could not</char>. Then Abimelech prepared to light a fire to burn down the door. <verse eid="JDG 9:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JDG 9:53"/>But when Abimelech came near the doorway, a woman <char style="add">who was on the roof</char> dropped a big grinding stone on his head, and crushed his skull.<verse eid="JDG 9:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="JDG 9:54"/>Abimelech quickly called to the young man who carried Abimelech’s weapons, and said, “Pull out your sword and kill me with it! I do not want people to say ‘It was a woman who killed Abimelech.’” So the young man thrust his sword into Abimelech, and Abimelech died. <verse eid="JDG 9:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JDG 9:55"/>When the Israeli soldiers saw that Abimelech was dead, they all returned to their homes.<verse eid="JDG 9:55"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="56" style="v" sid="JDG 9:56"/>In that way God punished Abimelech for the evil things that he had done to his father and especially for killing all 69 of his brothers. <verse eid="JDG 9:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JDG 9:57"/>God also punished the men of Shechem for the evil things that they had done. And when those things happened, it fulfilled what Gideon’s son Jotham said when he cursed <char style="add">Abimelech and the leaders of Shechem</char>.<verse eid="JDG 9:57"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JDG 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Tola ruled the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 10:1"/>After Abimelech died, Tola the son of Puah and grandson of Dodo became the leader to rescue the Israeli people <char style="add">from their enemies</char>. He belonged to the tribe of Issachar, but he lived in Shamir <char style="add">city</char> in the hilly area where the descendants of Ephraim live. <verse eid="JDG 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 10:2"/>He ruled the Israeli people for 23 years. Then he died and was buried in Shamir.<verse eid="JDG 10:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jair ruled the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 10:3"/>After Tola died, Jair, from <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, became the Israelis’ leader, and he ruled them for 22 years. <verse eid="JDG 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 10:4"/>He had thirty sons, and each of them had his own donkey to ride on. They each controlled a different town in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>. That region is still named ‘The Towns of Jair’. <verse eid="JDG 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 10:5"/>When Jair died, he was buried in Kamon <char style="add">city</char>.<verse eid="JDG 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Ammon people-group oppressed the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 10:6"/>Again the Israelis did things that Yahweh said were wrong/evil. They worshiped <char style="add">the idols of their god</char> Baal and <char style="add">their goddess</char> Astarte. They also worshiped the gods of the Aram, Sidon, Moab, and Ammon people-groups, and the gods of the Philistia people-group. They abandoned Yahweh and stopped worshiping him. <verse eid="JDG 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 10:7"/>So Yahweh was very angry with them, and he allowed the Philistia and Ammon people-groups to defeat [IDM] the Israelis. <verse eid="JDG 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 10:8"/>In that same year, those people started to oppress the Israelis who lived in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. That was where the Amor people-group also lived. were They caused the Israelis who lived in that region to suffer for 18 years. <verse eid="JDG 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 10:9"/>Then the people of the Ammon people-group crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to fight against the people of the tribes of Judah, Benjamin, and Ephraim. They caused the Israelis’ lives to be very miserable. <verse eid="JDG 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 10:10"/>So the Israelis cried out to Yahweh, saying “We have sinned against you. We have abandoned you, and we have been worshiping <char style="add">the idols of their god</char> Baal.”<verse eid="JDG 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 10:11"/>Yahweh answered them, saying, “When the people of Egypt, and the Amor and Ammon and Philistia people-groups <verse eid="JDG 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 10:12"/>and the Sidon and Amalek and Maon people-groups were cruel to you, you cried out to me, and then I rescued you. <verse eid="JDG 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 10:13"/>But now you have abandoned me again, and you have been worshiping other gods. So I will not rescue you again. <verse eid="JDG 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 10:14"/>You have chosen those gods <char style="add">to be the ones that you worship</char>. So call to them to help you. Allow them to rescue you when you have a lot of trouble!”<verse eid="JDG 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 10:15"/>But the Israeli people said to Yahweh, “Truly we have sinned. Punish us in whatever way you wish to, but please rescue us now!” <verse eid="JDG 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 10:16"/>Then the Israelis threw away the <char style="add">idols of the</char> gods that belonged to other people-groups, and they worshiped Yahweh again. He saw that they were suffering very much, and he felt sorry [IDM] for them.<verse eid="JDG 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 10:17"/>The Ammon people-group gathered to fight <char style="add">against the Israelis</char>, and they set up their tents in <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>. The Israeli men also gathered and set up their tents at Mizpah, <char style="add">which was a city in Gilead</char>. <verse eid="JDG 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 10:18"/>The Israeli leaders said, “Who will lead our soldiers to attack the Ammon people-group? The one who will lead us will become the leader of all us who live in this Gilead <char style="add">region</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 10:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JDG 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Jephthah was chosen to be their leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 11:1"/>
    <char style="add">There was a man</char> from <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> named Jephthah. He was a great warrior. His father was also named Gilead. But his mother was a prostitute. <verse eid="JDG 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 11:2"/>Gilead’s wife gave birth to several sons. When they grew up, they forced Jephthah to leave home, saying to him, “You are the son of a prostitute, <char style="add">not the son of our mother</char>. So <char style="add">when</char> our father <char style="add">dies</char>, you will not receive any of his property.” <verse eid="JDG 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 11:3"/>So Jephthah ran away from his brothers, and he went to the Tob region. While he was there, some worthless men started to spend a lot of time with him.<verse eid="JDG 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 11:4"/>Some time later, the Ammon people-group started to fight against the Israelis. <verse eid="JDG 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 11:5"/>When that happened [DOU], the leaders of <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> went to Jephthah to bring him back from the Tob region <char style="add">to their area</char>. <verse eid="JDG 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 11:6"/>They said to him, “Come <char style="add">with us</char> and lead our army, and <char style="add">help us to</char> fight against the men from the Ammon people-group!”<verse eid="JDG 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 11:7"/>But Jephthah replied, “You hated me [RHQ] previously! You forced me to leave my father’s house! So why are you coming to me now, <char style="add">asking me to help you</char> when you are experiencing trouble?”<verse eid="JDG 11:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 11:8"/>The leaders from Gilead replied, “<char style="add">Yes, we are having trouble, and</char> that is the reason that we have come to you now. If you come with us and <char style="add">help us to</char> fight against the Ammon people-group, <char style="add">after we defeat them, we will appoint</char> you to be the leader of all us people in <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 11:9"/>Jephthah replied, “If I go back to Gilead with you to fight against the Ammon people-group, and if Yahweh helps us to defeat them, will you truly appoint me to be your leader?” <verse eid="JDG 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 11:10"/>They replied, “Yahweh is listening to everything that we say. <char style="add">So he will punish us </char> if we do not do everything that you tell us to do.” <verse eid="JDG 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 11:11"/>So Jephthah went with them back to <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, and the people appointed him to be their leader and the commander of their army. And Jephthah solemnly promised to Yahweh there at Mizpah <char style="add">to serve him well</char>.<verse eid="JDG 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jephthah’s message to the king of the Ammon people-group</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 11:12"/>Jephthah sent some messengers to the king of the Ammon people-group. They asked the king, “What have we <char style="add">done to make you angry, with the result </char> that your army is coming to fight <char style="add">against the people</char> in our land?”<verse eid="JDG 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 11:13"/>The king replied, “<char style="add">We have come to fight against you Israelis because</char> you took our land when you came here from Egypt. You took all our land east of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, from the Arnon <char style="add">River in the south</char> to the Jabbok <char style="add">River in the north</char>. So if you now give it back to us, there ◄will be peace between us/we will not fight against you►.”<verse eid="JDG 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 11:14"/>
    <char style="add">The messengers returned to Jephthah and told him what the king had said</char>. So Jephthah sent the messengers to the king again. <verse eid="JDG 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 11:15"/>They said to him, “This is what Jephthah says: ‘It is not <char style="add">true </char> that we Israelis took the land from the Moab people-group and the Ammon people-group. <verse eid="JDG 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 11:16"/>When the Israeli people came out of Egypt, they walked through the desert to the Red Sea, and then <char style="add">walked across it and traveled to Kadesh town at the border of the Edom region</char>. <verse eid="JDG 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 11:17"/>They sent messengers to the king of the Edom people-group, to say to him, “Please allow us Israelis to walk across your land.” But the king of the Edom people-group refused. Later we sent the same message to the king of the Moab people-group, but he also refused to allow the Israelis to go through his land. So the Israelis stayed at Kadesh <char style="add">for a long time</char>. <verse eid="JDG 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 11:18"/>Then the Israelis went into the desert and walked outside the borders of the Edom and Moab regions. They walked east of the Moab region, east of the Arnon <char style="add">River, which is the eastern border of the Moab region</char>. They did not cross that river to enter <char style="add">the </char> Moab <char style="add">region</char>.<verse eid="JDG 11:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 11:19"/>‘Then the Israelis sent a message to Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group, who lived in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char>. They asked him, “Will you please allow us Israeli people to cross through your land to arrive at the land to which we <char style="add">are going</char>.” <verse eid="JDG 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 11:20"/>But Sihon did not trust the Israelis; <char style="add">he thought that they would steal some of the things in his land</char>. So he gathered all his troops and they set up their tents at Jahaz <char style="add">village</char> and then they attacked the Israelis. <verse eid="JDG 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 11:21"/>But Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, enabled the Israeli army to defeat [IDM] Sihon and his army. Then they ◄took possession of/started to live in► all the land where the Amor people-group had lived. <verse eid="JDG 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 11:22"/>The Israelis took all the land that belonged to the Amor people-group, from the Arnon <char style="add">River in the south</char> to the Jabbok <char style="add">River in the north</char>, and from the desert <char style="add">in the east</char> to the Jordan <char style="add">River in the west</char>.<verse eid="JDG 11:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 11:23"/>‘It was Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, who forced the Amor people-group to leave as the Israelis advanced. So do you now think that you can force the Israelis to leave [RHQ]? <verse eid="JDG 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 11:24"/>You take the land that your god Chemosh has given to you. And we will live in the land that Yahweh our God has given to us! <verse eid="JDG 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 11:25"/>◄You are no/Are you► better than Zippor’s son Balak, who was the king of the Moab people-group? He never [RHQ] quarreled with the Israeli people, and he never started to fight against us [RHQ]! <verse eid="JDG 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 11:26"/>For 300 years the Israeli people have lived in Heshbon and Aroer <char style="add">cities in your region</char>, and in the surrounding towns, and in all the cities along the Arnon <char style="add">River</char>. Why have you people of the Ammon people-group not taken back those cities during all those years [RHQ]? <verse eid="JDG 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 11:27"/>We have not sinned against you, but you are sinning against me by attacking me <char style="add">and my army</char>. I trust that Yahweh, the great judge, will decide whether we Israelis are right, or whether you people of the Ammon people-group are right.’ ”<verse eid="JDG 11:27"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 11:28"/>But the king of the Ammon people-group did not pay attention to that message from Jephthah.<verse eid="JDG 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 11:29"/>Then the Spirit of Yahweh took control of Jephthah. Jephthah went through <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> and through the area where the tribe of Manasseh lived, <char style="add">to enlist/gather men for his army</char>. <char style="add">He finally gathered them together</char> in Mizpah <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> to fight against the Ammon people-group. <verse eid="JDG 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 11:30"/>There Jephthah made a solemn promise to Yahweh. He said, “If you will enable my army to defeat [IDM] the Ammon people-group, <verse eid="JDG 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 11:31"/>when I return from the battle, I will sacrifice to you the first person who comes out of my house <char style="add">to greet me</char>. It will be a sacrifice that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 11:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 11:32"/>Then Jephthah <char style="add">and his men</char> went from Mizpah to attack the Ammon people-group, and Yahweh enabled his army to defeat them. <verse eid="JDG 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 11:33"/>Jephthah and his men killed them, from Aroer <char style="add">city</char> all the way to the area around the city of Minnith. They destroyed 20 cities, as far as <char style="add">the city of</char> Abel Keramim. So the Israelis <char style="add">completely</char> defeated the Ammon people-group.<verse eid="JDG 11:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 11:34"/>When Jephthah returned to his home in Mizpah, his daughter was the first one to come out of the house to meet him. She was <char style="add">joyfully</char> playing a tambourine and dancing. She was his only child; he had no sons and no other daughters. <verse eid="JDG 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 11:35"/>When Jephthah saw his daughter, he tore his clothes <char style="add">to show that he was very sad about what he was going to do</char>. He said to her, “My daughter, you have caused me to become very sad [DOU] because I made a solemn promise to Yahweh <char style="add">to sacrifice the first one who came out of my house</char>, and I must do what I promised.”<verse eid="JDG 11:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JDG 11:36"/>His daughter said, “My father, you made a solemn promise to Yahweh. So you must do to me what you promised, because <char style="add">you said that you would do that if</char> Yahweh helped you to defeat our enemies, the Ammon people-group.” <verse eid="JDG 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JDG 11:37"/>Then she also said, “But allow me to do one thing. ◄First/before you do what you promised►, allow me to go up into the hilly area and wander around for two months. Since I will never be married <char style="add">and have children</char>, allow me and my friends to go and cry together.”<verse eid="JDG 11:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JDG 11:38"/>Jephthah replied, “All right, you may go.” So she left for two months. She and her friends stayed in the hills and they cried for her because she would never be married. <verse eid="JDG 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 11:39"/>After two months, she returned to her father Jephthah, and he did to her what he had vowed. So his daughter never was married.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 11:39">Because of that, the Israelis now have a custom. <verse eid="JDG 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 11:40"/>Every year the young Israeli women go <char style="add">into the hills</char> for four days to remember <char style="add">and cry about what happened to</char> the daughter of Jephthah.<verse eid="JDG 11:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JDG 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Jephthah’s army defeated the tribe of Ephraim</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 12:1"/>The men of the tribe of Ephraim summoned their soldiers, and they crossed <char style="add">the Jordan River</char> to <char style="add">the town of </char> Zaphon <char style="add">to talk with</char> Jephthah. They said to him, “◄Why did you not ask us for help?/You should have requested us► to help your army fight the Ammon people-group. So we will burn down your house while you are in it.”<verse eid="JDG 12:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 12:2"/>Jephthah replied, “The Ammon people-group were oppressing us greatly. When we were prepared to start to attack them, I requested you to come and help us, but you refused. My men and I defeated the Ammon people-group, but you did not help us. <verse eid="JDG 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 12:3"/>When I saw that you would not help us, I was willing to be killed in the battle against the Ammon people-group. But Yahweh helped us to defeat them. <char style="add">You did not help us when we requested it before</char>, so ◄why have you come here today to fight against me?/you should not have come here today to fight against me.►” [RHQ]<verse eid="JDG 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 12:4"/>Then Jephthah summoned the men of <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> to fight <char style="add">against the men of the tribe of</char> Ephraim. The men of the tribe of Ephraim said, “You men from <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> are men who deserted us. Long ago you left us and moved to the area between our tribe and the tribe of Manasseh.” <char style="add">Because of their saying that</char>, the men of <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char> attacked the men of the tribe of Ephraim. <verse eid="JDG 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 12:5"/>The men of Gilead captured that ◄ford/place where people can walk across► at the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to go to the land where the tribe of Ephraim live. Whenever one of the soldiers from the tribe of Ephraim came to the ford to try to escape, he would say, “Let me cross the river.” Then the men of Gilead would ask him, “Are you from the tribe of Ephraim?” If he said “No,” <verse eid="JDG 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 12:6"/>they would say to him, “Say the word ‘Shibboleth’.” The men of Ephraim could not pronounce that word correctly. So if the person from the tribe of Ephraim said ‘Sibboleth’, <char style="add">they would know that he was lying and that he was really from the tribe of Ephraim, and</char> they would kill him there at the ford.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 12:6">So the men of Gilead killed 42,000 people from the tribe of Ephraim at that time.<verse eid="JDG 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 12:7"/>Jephthah, the man from <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>, was a leader of the Israeli people for six years. Then he died and was buried in a town in <char style="add">the</char> Gilead <char style="add">region</char>.<verse eid="JDG 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Ibzan became their leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 12:8"/>After Jephthah died, a man named Ibzan, from Bethlehem, became the leader of the Israeli people. <verse eid="JDG 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 12:9"/>He had 30 sons and 30 daughters. He forced all his daughters to marry men who were not in his clan, and brought women from outside his clan to marry his sons. He was the leader of the Israeli people for seven years. <verse eid="JDG 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 12:10"/>When he died, he was buried in Bethlehem.<verse eid="JDG 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Elon became their leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 12:11"/>After Ibzan died, a man named Elon, from the tribe of Zebulun, became the leader of the Israeli people. He was their leader for ten years. <verse eid="JDG 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 12:12"/>Then he died and was buried in Aijalon <char style="add">city</char> in the area where the tribe of Zebulun lives.<verse eid="JDG 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Abdon became their leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 12:13"/>After Elon died, a man named Abdon who was the son of Hillel, from Pirathon <char style="add">city, in the area where the tribe of Ephraim live</char> became the leader of the Israeli people. <verse eid="JDG 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 12:14"/>He had 40 sons and 30 grandsons. Each of them had his own donkey on which to ride. Abdon was the leader of the Israeli people for eight years. <verse eid="JDG 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 12:15"/>When Abdon died, he was buried in Pirathon, in the hilly area where the descendants of Amalek lived previously, <char style="add">but now it is the area where the tribe of Ephraim lives</char>.<verse eid="JDG 12:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JDG 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Samson was born</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 13:1"/>Again the Israeli people did things that Yahweh said were very evil. So Yahweh enabled the people of Philistia to conquer them. They ruled over the Israelis for 40 years.<verse eid="JDG 13:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 13:2"/>There was a man named Manoah from the descendants of Dan who lived in Zorah <char style="add">town</char>. His wife was unable to become pregnant, so they had no children. <verse eid="JDG 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 13:3"/>One day, Yahweh appeared to Manoah’s wife in the form of an angel, and said to her, “Even though you have not been able to give birth to any children until now, you will soon become pregnant and give birth to a son. <verse eid="JDG 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 13:4"/><char style="add">From now until he is born</char>, you must not drink any wine or other alcoholic/fermented drink, and you must not eat any food that will make you unacceptable to God. <verse eid="JDG 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 13:5"/>After you give birth to your son, you must never allow his hair to be cut. He must be dedicated to God from the day he is born until the day he dies. He is the one who will rescue <char style="add">many of</char> the Israeli people from the people of Philistia.”<verse eid="JDG 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 13:6"/>The woman ran and told her husband, “A prophet came to me. He looked awesome, like an angel from God. I did not ask where he came from, and he did not tell me his name. <verse eid="JDG 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 13:7"/>But he told me, ‘You will become pregnant and give birth to a son. Until then, you must not drink any wine or any alcoholic/fermented drink, and you must not eat any food that would make you unacceptable to God. Your son must be dedicated to God from the day he is born until the day he dies.’”<verse eid="JDG 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 13:8"/>Then Manoah prayed to Yahweh, saying, “O Yahweh, I plead with you, allow that prophet whom you sent to us to come again, and teach us how we should raise the boy who will be born to us.”<verse eid="JDG 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 13:9"/>God did what Manoah asked, and Yahweh again appeared to his wife in the form of an angel, while she was out in the field. But again her husband Manoah was not with her. <verse eid="JDG 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 13:10"/>So she quickly ran and said to her husband, “The man who appeared to me a few days ago has come back again!”<verse eid="JDG 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 13:11"/>Manoah ran back with his wife, and asked, “Are you the man who talked with my wife a few days ago?” He replied, “Yes, I am.”<verse eid="JDG 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 13:12"/>Manoah asked him, “When what you promised occurs <char style="add">and my wife gives birth to a son</char>, what rules must he obey, and what work will he do <char style="add">when he grows up</char>?”<verse eid="JDG 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 13:13"/>Yahweh replied, “Your wife must obey all the instructions I gave her. <verse eid="JDG 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 13:14"/><char style="add">Before the baby is born</char>, she must not eat grapes, or drink wine or any other alcoholic/fermented drink, or eat anything that would make her unacceptable to God.”<verse eid="JDG 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 13:15"/>Then Manoah said, “Please stay here until we can kill and cook a young goat for you.”<verse eid="JDG 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 13:16"/>Yahweh replied, “I will stay here, but I will not eat anything. However, you may kill an animal and sacrifice it as a burned offering to Yahweh.” (Manoah did not realize that the <char style="add">man he thought was an</char> angel was really Yahweh.)<verse eid="JDG 13:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 13:17"/>Then Manoah asked him, “What is your name? When what you have promised happens, we want to honor you.”<verse eid="JDG 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 13:18"/>Yahweh replied, “◄Why do you ask me my name?/You should not ask me my name.► [RHQ] It is ◄wonderful/it cannot be understood►.” <verse eid="JDG 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 13:19"/>Then Manoah killed a young goat and burned it on a rock, along with a grain offering, as a sacrifice to Yahweh. And Yahweh did an amazing thing while Manoah and his wife watched. <verse eid="JDG 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 13:20"/>Flames from the altar blazed up toward the sky, and Yahweh ascended in the flames. When Manoah and his wife saw that, they prostrated themselves on the ground. <verse eid="JDG 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 13:21"/>Although Yahweh did not appear in the form of an angel to Manoah and his wife again, Manoah realized that the <char style="add">man they thought was an</char> angel was really Yahweh.<verse eid="JDG 13:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 13:22"/>So he said, “Now we will die, because we have seen God!”<verse eid="JDG 13:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 13:23"/>But his wife said, “No, we will not die, because if Yahweh intended to kill us, he would not have accepted the burned offering and the grain offering. And he would not have appeared to us and told us the wonderful thing that would happen to us, and he would not have performed this miracle.”<verse eid="JDG 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 13:24"/>When their son was born, they named him Samson. Yahweh blessed him as he grew up. <verse eid="JDG 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 13:25"/>And while he was in Mahaneh-Dan, which is between Zorah and Eshtaol <char style="add">towns</char>, Yahweh’s Spirit began to control him.<verse eid="JDG 13:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JDG 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Samson’s riddle</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 14:1"/>One day when Samson was in Timnah <char style="add">town</char>, he saw a young Philistine woman there. <verse eid="JDG 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 14:2"/>When he returned home, he told his mother and father, “I saw a young Philistine woman in Timnah, and I want you to get her for me so I can marry her.”<verse eid="JDG 14:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 14:3"/>His mother and father objected very strongly. They said, “Is there no woman from our tribe, or from the other Israeli tribes, that you could marry? Why must you go to the heathen Philistines to get a wife?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 14:3">But Samson told his father, “Get her for me! She is the one I want!” <verse eid="JDG 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 14:4"/>His mother and father did not realize that Yahweh was arranging this. He was preparing a way for <char style="add">Samson to defeat</char> the Philistines, who were ruling over Israel at that time. <verse eid="JDG 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 14:5"/>So, as Samson was going down to Timnah, followed by his mother and father, a young lion attacked Samson near the vineyards close to Timnah. <verse eid="JDG 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 14:6"/>Then Yahweh’s Spirit came upon Samson powerfully, with the result that he tore the lion apart with his hands. He did it <char style="add">as easily</char> as if it were a young goat. But he did not tell his mother and father about it. <verse eid="JDG 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 14:7"/>When they arrived in Timnah, Samson talked with the young woman, and he liked her very much. <char style="add">And his father made arrangements for the wedding</char>.<verse eid="JDG 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 14:8"/>Later, when Samson returned to Timnah for the wedding, he turned off the path to see the carcass of the lion. He discovered that <char style="add">after other creatures had eaten all the flesh</char>, a swarm of bees <char style="add">had made a hive in the skeleton and</char> had made some honey. <verse eid="JDG 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 14:9"/>So he scooped some of the honey into his hands and ate some of it as he was walking along. He also gave some of it to his mother and father, but he did not tell them that he had taken the honey from the skeleton of the lion, <char style="add">because anyone dedicated to God was not to touch any corpse</char>.<verse eid="JDG 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 14:10"/>As his father was making the final arrangements for the marriage, Samson gave a party <char style="add">for the young men in that area</char>. That was the custom for men to do when they were about to be married. <verse eid="JDG 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 14:11"/>Thirty young man were invited to the party.<verse eid="JDG 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 14:12"/>Samson said to them, “Allow me to tell you a riddle. If you tel me the meaning of my riddle during these seven days of the celebration, I will give each of you a linen robe and an extra set of clothes. <verse eid="JDG 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 14:13"/>But if you cannot tell me the meaning, you must each give me a linen robe and an extra set of clothes.” They replied, “All right. Tell us your riddle.”<verse eid="JDG 14:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 14:14"/>So he said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 14:14">“From the thing that eats came something to eat;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 14:14">out of something strong came something sweet.”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="JDG 14:14">But for three days they could not tell him the meaning of the riddle.<verse eid="JDG 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 14:15"/>On the fourth day, they said to Samson’s bride, “Ask your husband to tell you the meaning of the riddle. If you do not do that, we will burn down your father’s house, with you inside it! Did you invite us here only to make us poor <char style="add">by forcing us to buy a lot of clothes for your husband</char>?”<verse eid="JDG 14:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 14:16"/>So Samson’s wife came to him, crying, and said to him, “You do not really love me. You hate me! You have told a riddle to my friends, but you have not told me the meaning of the riddle!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 14:16">He replied, “I have not told the meaning of the riddle even to my mother and father, so why should I tell it to you?” <verse eid="JDG 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 14:17"/>She continued to cry every time she was with him, all during the rest of the celebration. Finally, on the seventh day, because she continued to nag him, he told her the meaning of the riddle. Then she told it to the young men.<verse eid="JDG 14:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 14:18"/>So, before sunset on the seventh day, the young men came to Samson and said to him,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 14:18">“What/Nothing is sweeter than honey [RHQ].</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 14:18">What/Nothing is stronger than a lion [RHQ]!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 14:18">Samson replied, “<char style="add">You should not force a heifer to</char> plow a field [MET].</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 14:18">Similarly, if you had not forced my bride to ask me about the riddle [MET],</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 14:18">you would not have known the answer to my riddle!”<verse eid="JDG 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 14:19"/>Then Yahweh’s Spirit powerfully took control of Samson. He went down to <char style="add">the coast at</char> Ashkelon <char style="add">town</char>, and killed 30 men. He took their clothes <char style="add">and went back to Timnah</char> and gave them to the men who had told him the meaning of the riddle. But he was very angry about what had happened, so he went back home to live with his mother and father. <verse eid="JDG 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 14:20"/>So ◄Samson’s wife was given/the bride’s father gave Samson’s wife► to the man who who had been Samson’s best man at the wedding, <char style="add">but Samson did not know that</char>.<verse eid="JDG 14:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JDG 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Samson got revenge on the Philistines</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 15:1"/>During the time that they harvested wheat, Samson took a young goat to Timnah as a present for his wife. He planned to sleep with [EUP] his wife, but her father would not let him go into <char style="add">her room</char>.<verse eid="JDG 15:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 15:2"/>He said to Samson, “I really thought that you hated her. So I gave her to the man who had been your best man at the wedding, and she married him. But look, her younger sister is [RHQ] more beautiful than she is. You can marry her!”<verse eid="JDG 15:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 15:3"/>Samson replied, “No! And this time I have a right to get revenge on you Philistines!” <verse eid="JDG 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 15:4"/>Then he went out <char style="add">into the fields</char> and caught 300 foxes. He tied their tails together, two-by-two. He fastened torches to each pair of tails. <verse eid="JDG 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 15:5"/>Then he lit the torches and let the foxes run through the fields of the Philistines. The fire <char style="add">from the torches</char> burned all the grain to the ground, including the grain that had been cut and piled in bundles. The fire also burned down their grapevines and their olive trees.<verse eid="JDG 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 15:6"/>The Philistines asked, “Who did this?” Someone told them, “Samson did it. He married a woman from Timnah, but then his father-in-law gave her to the man who was Samson’s best man at the wedding, and she married him.” So the Philistines went <char style="add">to Timnah</char> and got the woman and her father, and burned them to death.<verse eid="JDG 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 15:7"/>Samson <char style="add">found out about that, and he</char> said to them, “Because you have done this, I will not stop until I get revenge on you!” <verse eid="JDG 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 15:8"/>So he attacked the Philistines furiously, and killed many of them. Then he went <char style="add">to hide</char> in a cave in the large rock at a place called Etam.<verse eid="JDG 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 15:9"/>The Philistines <char style="add">did not know where he was, so they </char> went up to where the descendants of Judah lived, set up their tents near Lehi <char style="add">town and then raided the town</char>. <verse eid="JDG 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 15:10"/>The men there asked the Philistines, “Why have you attacked us?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 15:10">The Philistines replied, “We have come to capture Samson. We have come to get revenge on him for what he did to us.”<verse eid="JDG 15:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 15:11"/>
    <char style="add">Someone there knew where Samson was hiding</char>. So 3,000 men from Judah went down to get Samson at the cave in the rock where he was hiding. They said to Samson, “Do you not realize that the people of Philistia are ruling over us? Do you not realize what they will do to us?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 15:11">Samson replied, “The only thing I did was that I got revenge on them for what they did to me.”<verse eid="JDG 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 15:12"/>But the men from Judah said to him, “We have come to tie you up and put you in the hands of the Philistines.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 15:12">Samson said, “All right, but promise me that you yourselves will not kill me!”<verse eid="JDG 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 15:13"/>They replied, “We will just tie you up and take you to the Philistines. We will not kill you.” So they tied him with two new ropes, and led him away from the cave. <verse eid="JDG 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 15:14"/>When they arrived at Lehi, the Philistines came toward him, shouting <char style="add">triumphantly</char>. But Yahweh’s Spirit came upon Samson powerfully. He snapped the ropes on his arms as easily as if they were stalks of burned flax, and the ropes fell off his wrists. <verse eid="JDG 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 15:15"/>Then he saw a donkey’s jawbone lying on the ground. It was fresh, <char style="add">so it was hard</char>. He picked it up and killed about 1,000 Philistine men with it. <verse eid="JDG 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 15:16"/>Then Samson wrote this poem:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 15:16">“With the jawbone of a donkey</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 15:16">I have made them like a heap of <char style="add">dead</char> donkeys.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 15:16">With the jawbone of a donkey</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 15:16">I killed 1,000 men.”<verse eid="JDG 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 15:17"/>When he finished killing those men, he threw the jawbone away, and later that place was called Jawbone Hill.<verse eid="JDG 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 15:18"/>Then Samson was very thirsty, so he called out to Yahweh, “You have given me strength to win a great victory. So now must I die because of being thirsty, with the result that those heathen Philistines will take away my body <char style="add">and mutilate it</char>?” <verse eid="JDG 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 15:19"/>So God caused water to gush out of a depression in the ground at Lehi. Samson drank from it and soon felt strong again. He named that place ‘The spring of the one who called out’. That spring is still there at Lehi.<verse eid="JDG 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 15:20"/>Samson was the leader of the Israeli people for 20 years, but during that time the Philistines <char style="add">were the ones who really ruled over the land</char>.<verse eid="JDG 15:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JDG 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Samson removed the gate at Gaza</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 16:1"/>One day Samson went to Gaza <char style="add">city in the Philistia area</char>. He spent some time with a prostitute. <verse eid="JDG 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 16:2"/>People soon found out that Samson was there, so the men of Gaza gathered together at the city gate and waited all night. They said to themselves, “When it dawns tomorrow morning, we will kill him <char style="add">when he tries to leave the city</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 16:3"/>But Samson did not stay there all night. At midnight, he got up. He went to the city gate, he took hold of its two posts, and he lifted it up out of the ground, with its <char style="add">connecting cross</char> bar still attached. He put it on his shoulders and carried it <char style="add">many miles</char> uphill to Hebron.<verse eid="JDG 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 16:4"/>Later Samson fell in love with a woman named Delilah, <char style="add">and started to live with her</char>. She lived in Sorek Valley <char style="add">in the Philistia area</char>. <verse eid="JDG 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 16:5"/>The Philistine leaders went to her and said, “Find out from Samson what makes him so strong. And find out how we can subdue him and tie him up securely. If you do that, each of us will give you 1,100 pieces of silver.”<verse eid="JDG 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 16:6"/>So Delilah said to Samson, “Please tell me what makes you so strong, and tell me how someone can subdue you and tie you up.”<verse eid="JDG 16:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 16:7"/>Samson said, “If someone ties me with seven new bowstrings, ones that are not dry yet, I will become as weak as other men.”<verse eid="JDG 16:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 16:8"/>So <char style="add">after Delilah told that to the Philistine leaders</char>, they brought seven new bowstrings to Delilah. <verse eid="JDG 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 16:9"/>Then she hid the men in one of the rooms in her house. Then <char style="add">while Samson was sleeping</char>, she tied him up with the bowstrings. Then she called out, “Samson! The Philistines have come here to capture you!” But Samson snapped the bowstrings as easily as though they were strings that had been singed in a fire. So the Philistines did not find out what made Samson so strong.<verse eid="JDG 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 16:10"/>Then Delilah said to Samson, “You have deceived me and lied to me! Now tell me <char style="add">the truth,</char> how someone can tie you up securely.”<verse eid="JDG 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 16:11"/>Samson replied, “If someone ties me with new ropes, ones that have never been used, I will be as weak as other men.”<verse eid="JDG 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 16:12"/>So again, <char style="add">she told the Philistine leaders, and</char> they <char style="add">came and</char> hid in the room as they had done before. And again, while Samson was sleeping, she took the new ropes and tied him up with them. Then she called out, “Samson! The Philistines have come to capture you!” But Samson snapped the ropes on his arms as easily as if they were threads.<verse eid="JDG 16:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 16:13"/>Then Delilah said, “You have deceived me and lied to me <char style="add">again</char>! Please tell me how someone can tie you up securely!” Samson replied, “If you weave the seven braids of my hair into the threads you are weaving on the loom, and then fasten those threads with the pin <char style="add">that makes the threads tight</char>, then I will be as weak as other men.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 16:13">So again, while Samson was sleeping on her lap, Delilah held the seven braids of his hair, and wove them into the threads on the loom, <verse eid="JDG 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 16:14"/>and she tightened them with the pin. Then she called out, “Samson! The Philistines have come to capture you!” But Samson woke up and pulled out the pin, and pulled his hair from the threads on the loom.<verse eid="JDG 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 16:15"/>Then Delilah said to him, “How can you say that you love me when you do not tell me the truth about yourself? You have deceived me three times, and you still have not told me what really makes you so strong!” <verse eid="JDG 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 16:16"/>Day after day she nagged him like that. He thought he would die from her nagging [IDM].<verse eid="JDG 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 16:17"/>Finally Samson told her the truth. He said, “I have been set apart for God since the day I was born. And because of that, my hair has never been cut. If my hair were shaved off, my strength would be gone, and I would be as weak as other men.”<verse eid="JDG 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 16:18"/>Delilah realized that this time he had told her the truth. So she summoned the Philistine leaders again, saying, “Come back one more time, because Samson has really told me everything <char style="add">about why he is so strong</char>”. So the Philistine leaders returned and brought to Delilah the money <char style="add">that they promised to give her</char>. <verse eid="JDG 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 16:19"/>Again she lulled Samson to sleep, with his head in her lap. Then she called one of the Philistine men to come and shave off Samson’s hair. As he did that, Samson began to get weaker. And finally his strength was all gone.<verse eid="JDG 16:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 16:20"/>Then <char style="add">after she tied him up</char>, she called out, “Samson! The Philistines have come to capture you!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 16:20">He woke up and thought, “I will do as I did before. I will shake <char style="add">these ropes</char> off myself and be free!” But he did not realize that Yahweh had left him.<verse eid="JDG 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 16:21"/>So the Philistine men seized him and gouged out his eyes. Then they took him to Gaza. There they put him in prison and bound him with bronze chains. They made him <char style="add">turn a millstone to</char> grind grain <char style="add">every day</char>. <verse eid="JDG 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 16:22"/>But his hair started to grow again.<verse eid="JDG 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Samson killed many thousands of Philistines when he died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 16:23"/>
    <char style="add">Several months later</char> the Philistine leaders celebrated a big festival. During the festival they offered sacrifices to their god Dagon. They praised him, saying, “Our god has enabled us to defeat our great enemy Samson!”<verse eid="JDG 16:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 16:24"/>And when the other people saw Samson, they also praised their god Dagon, saying,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JDG 16:24">“Samson ruined our crops and killed many of our people,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 16:24">but our god has put our enemy into our hands.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JDG 16:24">Our god helped us to capture the one who has killed so many of us!”<verse eid="JDG 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 16:25"/>By that time the people were half-drunk. They shouted, “Bring Samson out of the prison! Bring him here so that he can entertain us!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 16:25">So they brought Samson from the prison and made fun of him. Then they made him stand in the center of the temple. They made him stand between the two pillars that held up the roof. <verse eid="JDG 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 16:26"/>Samson said to the servant who was leading him by his hand, “Place my hands against the two pillars. I want to rest against them.” <verse eid="JDG 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 16:27"/>At that time the temple was full of men and women. All the Philistine leaders were also there. And there were about 3,000 people on the roof, watching Samson and making fun of him. <verse eid="JDG 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 16:28"/>Then Samson prayed, saying, “Yahweh, my Lord, think about me again! Please give me strength one more time, so that I may get revenge on the Philistines for gouging out my eyes!” <verse eid="JDG 16:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 16:29"/>Then Samson put his hands on the two center pillars of the temple. He put his right hand on one pillar and his left hand on the other pillar. <verse eid="JDG 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 16:30"/>Then he shouted <char style="add">to God</char>, “Let me die with the Philistines!”, and he pushed with all his strength. <char style="add">The pillars collapsed</char>, and the temple crashed down on the Philistine leaders and all the other Philistine people, <char style="add">and they all died</char>. So Samson killed more people when he died than he had killed all during his life.<verse eid="JDG 16:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 16:31"/>Later his brothers and their relatives went down <char style="add">from Zorah to Gaza</char> to get his body. They took it back home and buried it between Zorah and Eshtaol, at the place where Samson’s father Manoah was buried. Samson had been Israel’s leader for 20 years.<verse eid="JDG 16:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JDG 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Micah made idols and hired a priest</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 17:1"/>There was a man named Micah who lived in the hilly area where the tribe of Ephraim live. <verse eid="JDG 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 17:2"/>One day he said to his mother, “I heard you curse whoever stole ◄1,100 pieces/28 pounds/13 kg.► of silver from your house. I am the one who took the silver, and I still have it.” His mother replied, “My son, I pray that Yahweh will bless you <char style="add">for admitting that you took it</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 17:3"/>Micah gave all the silver back to his mother. Then she said <char style="add">to herself</char>, “I will give <char style="add">some of</char> this silver to Yahweh.” And she said to her son, “My son, I want you to make an idol and a statue <char style="add">from this silver</char>. So I will give <char style="add">some of</char> this silver back to you <char style="add">for making these things</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 17:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 17:4"/>So when he gave all the silver to his mother, she took ◄200 pieces/about 5 pounds/1.6 kg.► of it to a ◄silversmith/man who made things from silver►. With the silver that man made an idol and a statue, <char style="add">and gave them to Micah</char>. Micah put them in his house.<verse eid="JDG 17:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 17:5"/>He had in his house a special ◄shrine/place for putting sacred things►. He made a sacred vest and some small idols <char style="add">and put them in this shrine along with the big idol and the statue</char>. Then Micah chose one of his sons to become his priest. <verse eid="JDG 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 17:6"/>At that time, the Israeli people did not have a king. So <char style="add">Micah and everyone else</char> did whatever they considered to be the right thing to do.<verse eid="JDG 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 17:7"/>There was a young man who had been living in Bethlehem in the area where the tribe of Judah lives. He <char style="add">wanted to work as a priest because he</char> was a member of the tribe of Levi. <verse eid="JDG 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 17:8"/>So he left Bethlehem to find another place to live <char style="add">and work</char>. He came to Micah’s house in the hilly area where the tribe of Ephraim live.<verse eid="JDG 17:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 17:9"/>Micah asked him, “Where are you from?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 17:9">He replied, “I come from Bethlehem. I am from the tribe of Levi, and I am looking for a place to live <char style="add">and work as a priest</char>.” <verse eid="JDG 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 17:10"/>Micah said to him, “Stay with me, and you can become like a father <char style="add">to counsel me</char>, and be my priest. Each year I will give to you ten pieces of silver and some <char style="add">new</char> clothes. And I will provide food for you.” <verse eid="JDG 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 17:11"/>So the young man agreed to live with Micah. He became like one of Micah’s own sons. <verse eid="JDG 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 17:12"/>Micah appointed him to be a priest, and he lived in Micah’s house. <verse eid="JDG 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 17:13"/>Then Micah said, “Now I know that Yahweh will do good things for me, because I have a man from the tribe of Levi to be my priest.”<verse eid="JDG 17:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JDG 18"/>
  <para style="s1">The tribe of Dan took Micah’s priest and his idols</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 18:1"/>At that time the Israelis had no king.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 18:1">Also at that time, the tribe of Dan was still searching for some land where they could live. The other Israeli tribes had <char style="add">been able to</char> ◄<char style="add">capture/take possession of</char>► <char style="add">the</char> land that had been allotted to them, but the tribe of Dan had not been able to do that. <verse eid="JDG 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 18:2"/>So they chose five soldiers from their clans, men who lived in Zorah and Eshtaol <char style="add">cities</char>, to go through the land and explore it <char style="add">and try to find some land where their tribe could live</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 18:2">They came to Micah’s house in the hilly area where the tribe of Ephraim lived, and they stayed there that night. <verse eid="JDG 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 18:3"/>While they were in his house and they heard the young man who had become Micah’s priest talking, they recognized from ◄his accent/the way that he talked► <char style="add">that he was from the southern part of Israel</char>. So they went to him and asked him, “Who brought you here? What are you doing here? Why did you come here?”<verse eid="JDG 18:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 18:4"/>He told them the things that Micah had done for him. And he said, “Micah ◄has hired me/is paying me to work for him►, and I have become his priest.”<verse eid="JDG 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 18:5"/>So they said to him, “Please ask God if we will succeed <char style="add">in what we are trying to do</char> on this journey.”<verse eid="JDG 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 18:6"/>The young man replied, “Things will go well for you. Yahweh will go with you on this journey.”<verse eid="JDG 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 18:7"/>
    <char style="add">The next day</char> the five men left. When they came to Laish <char style="add">city</char>, they saw that the people there lived safely, like the people in Sidon <char style="add">city</char> did. The people there thought that they were safe/protected <char style="add">from any enemies</char>, and they had plenty of <char style="add">good fertile</char> land. They lived very far from the people of Sidon, <char style="add">so the people of Sidon would not be able to help defend/protect them</char>. They had no other ◄allies/groups nearby that would help them in battles►.<verse eid="JDG 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 18:8"/>When those five men returned to Zorah and Eshtaol, their relatives asked them “What did you find out?”<verse eid="JDG 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 18:9"/>They replied, “We have found some land, and it is very good. We should go and attack the people <char style="add">who live there</char>. Why are you staying here and doing nothing [RHQ]? Do not wait any longer! We should go immediately and take possession of that land! <verse eid="JDG 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 18:10"/>When you go there, you will see that there is plenty of land, and it has everything <char style="add">that we will need</char>. The people there are not expecting anyone to attack them. Surely God is giving that land to us.”<verse eid="JDG 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 18:11"/>So 600 men from the tribe of Dan left Zorah and Eshtaol, carrying their weapons. <verse eid="JDG 18:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 18:12"/>On their way they set up their tents near Kiriath-Jearim <char style="add">city</char> in <char style="add">the area where the tribe of</char> Judah <char style="add">lives</char>. That is why the area west of Kiriath-Jearim was named ‘Camp of Dan’, and that is still its name. <verse eid="JDG 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 18:13"/>From there, they went to the hilly area where the tribe of Ephraim lives. And they arrived at Micah’s house.<verse eid="JDG 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 18:14"/>The five men who had explored the land near Laish said to their fellow Israelis, “Do you know that in one of these houses there is a sacred vest, several idols, and a statue? <char style="add">We think that</char> you know what you should do.” [RHQ] <verse eid="JDG 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 18:15"/>So they went to the house where the man from the tribe of Levi lived, which was the house where Micah lived, and they greeted the young man from the tribe of Levi <char style="add">who had become Micah’s priest</char>. <verse eid="JDG 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 18:16"/>The 600 men of the tribe of Dan stood outside the gate of the house, carrying their weapons. <verse eid="JDG 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 18:17"/>The five men who had explored the land went into Micah’s house, and took all the idols, the sacred vest, and the statue. While they did that, the 600 men stood outside the gate, <char style="add">talking</char> with the priest.<verse eid="JDG 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 18:18"/>When the priest saw them bringing out the idols and the sacred vest and the statue, he said to them, “What are you doing?”<verse eid="JDG 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 18:19"/>They replied, “Be quiet! Do not say anything! You come with us and be <char style="add">like</char> a father to us and a priest for us. Is it better for you to <char style="add">stay here and</char> be a priest for the people in the house of one man, or to be a priest for a clan, and a priest for a whole tribe of Israelis?” [RHQ] <verse eid="JDG 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 18:20"/>The priest liked what they were suggesting. So he took the sacred vest and the idols, and he <char style="add">prepared to</char> go with the men from the tribe of Dan. <verse eid="JDG 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 18:21"/>They all put their little children and their animals and everything else that they owned in front of them.<verse eid="JDG 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 18:22"/>After they had gone a little distance from Micah’s house, Micah <char style="add">saw what was happening. He</char> quickly summoned the men who lived near him, and they ran and caught up with the men from the tribe of Dan. <verse eid="JDG 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 18:23"/>They shouted at them. The men of the tribe of Dan turned around and said to Micah, “What is the problem? Why have you gathered these men <char style="add">to pursue us</char>?”<verse eid="JDG 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 18:24"/>Micah shouted, “You took the silver idols that were made for me! You also took my priest! I do not have anything left [RHQ]! So why do you ask me, ‘What is the problem?’”<verse eid="JDG 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 18:25"/>The men from the tribe of Dan replied, “You should not shout loudly like that! One of our angry men might attack you and kill you and your family!” <verse eid="JDG 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 18:26"/>Then the men from the tribe of Dan continued walking. Micah realized that there was a very large group of them, <char style="add">so that it would be useless for him to try to fight them</char>. So he turned around and went home.<verse eid="JDG 18:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 18:27"/>The men of the tribe of Dan were carrying the things that had been made for Micah, and they also took his priest, and they continued traveling to Laish. They attacked the people who were peacefully living there, and killed them with their swords, and then they burned everything in the city. <verse eid="JDG 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 18:28"/>Laish was far from <char style="add">the city of</char> Sidon, <char style="add">so the people of Sidon could not rescue the people of Laish</char>. And the people of Laish had no other allies. Laish was in a valley near Beth-Rehob <char style="add">town</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 18:28">The people of the tribe of Dan rebuilt the city and started to live there. <verse eid="JDG 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 18:29"/>They gave to the city a <char style="add">new</char> name, Dan, in honor of their ancestor Dan, who was one of the sons of Jacob. <verse eid="JDG 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 18:30"/>The people of the tribe of Dan set up <char style="add">in the city</char> the idols <char style="add">that had been made for Micah</char>. Jonathan, who was the son of Gershom and the grandson of Moses, was appointed to be their priest. His descendants continued to be priests until the Israelis were captured and taken <char style="add">to Assyria</char>. <verse eid="JDG 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 18:31"/>After the people of the tribe of Dan set up the idols that had been made for Micah, <char style="add">they worshiped those idols, even though</char> the Sacred Tent <char style="add">where they had been commanded to worship</char> God, was at Shiloh.<verse eid="JDG 18:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JDG 19"/>
  <para style="s1">A Levite and his concubine</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 19:1"/>At that time the Israeli people had no king.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 19:1">There was a man from the tribe of Levi who lived in a remote place in the hilly area where the tribe of Ephraim lives. He had previously taken as a wife a woman who was a slave. She was from Bethlehem, in the area where the tribe of Judah lives. <verse eid="JDG 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 19:2"/>But she started to sleep with other men also. Then she left him and returned to her father’s house in Bethlehem. She stayed there for four months. <verse eid="JDG 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 19:3"/>Then her husband took his servant and two donkeys and went to Bethlehem. He went to ask her to come back to live with him again. When he arrived at her father’s house, she invited him to come in. Her father was happy to see him. <verse eid="JDG 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 19:4"/>The woman’s father asked him to stay. So he stayed there for three days. During that time he ate and drank and slept there.<verse eid="JDG 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 19:5"/>On the fourth day, they all got up early in the morning. The man from the tribe of Levi was preparing to leave, but the woman’s father said to him, “Eat something before you go.” <verse eid="JDG 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 19:6"/>So the two men sat down to eat and drink together. Then the woman’s father said to him, “Please stay another night. Relax/Rest and have a joyful time.” <verse eid="JDG 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 19:7"/>The man from the tribe of Levi wanted to leave, but the woman’s father requested him to stay one more night. So he stayed again that night. <verse eid="JDG 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 19:8"/>On the fifth day, the man got up early and prepared to leave. But the woman’s father said to him again, “Have something to eat. Wait until this afternoon, <char style="add">and then leave</char>.” So the two men ate together.<verse eid="JDG 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 19:9"/>In the afternoon, when the man from the tribe of Levi and his slave wife and his servant got up to leave, the woman’s father said, “It will soon be dark. The day is almost over. Stay here tonight and have a good/joyful time. Tomorrow morning you can get up early and leave for your home.” <verse eid="JDG 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 19:10"/>But the man from the tribe of Levi did not want to stay for another night. He put saddles on his two donkeys, and started to go with his slave wife <char style="add">and his servant</char> toward Jebus <char style="add">city</char>, which is <char style="add">now named</char> Jerusalem.<verse eid="JDG 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 19:11"/>Late in the afternoon, they came near to Jebus. The servant said to his master, “We should stop in this city where the Jebus people-group live, and stay here tonight.”<verse eid="JDG 19:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 19:12"/>But his master said, “No, it would not be good for us to stay here where foreign people live. There are no Israeli people here. We will go on to Gibeah <char style="add">city</char>.” <verse eid="JDG 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 19:13"/>He said to his servant, “Let’s go. It is not far to Gibeah. We can go there, or we can go a bit further to Ramah. We can stay in one of those two cities tonight.” <verse eid="JDG 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 19:14"/>So they continued walking. When they came near Gibeah, where people from the tribe of Benjamin live, the sun was setting. <verse eid="JDG 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 19:15"/>They stopped to stay there that night. They went to the public square of that city and sat down. But no one <char style="add">who passed by</char> invited them to stay in their house for that night.<verse eid="JDG 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 19:16"/>Finally, in the evening, an old man came by. He had been working in the fields. He was from the hilly area of the tribe of Ephraim, but at that time he was living in Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 19:17"/>He realized that the man from the tribe of Levi was only traveling and did not have a home in that city. So he asked the man, “Where have you come from? And where are you going?”<verse eid="JDG 19:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 19:18"/>He replied, “We are traveling from Bethlehem to my home in the hilly area where people of the tribe of Ephraim live. I went from there to Bethlehem, but now we are going to <char style="add">Shiloh</char> where Yahweh’s Sacred tent (OR, my house) is. No one here has invited us to stay in their house tonight. <verse eid="JDG 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 19:19"/>We have straw and food for our donkeys, and bread and wine for me and the young woman and my servant. We do not need anything else.”<verse eid="JDG 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 19:20"/>The old man said, “I wish that things will go well for you, but I would like to provide what you need. Do not stay here in the square tonight.” <verse eid="JDG 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 19:21"/>Then the old man took them to his house. He gave food to the donkeys. He <char style="add">gave water to the man and the woman and the servant to</char> wash their feet. And he gave them something to eat and drink.<verse eid="JDG 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 19:22"/>While they were having a good/joyful time together, some wicked men from that city surrounded the house and started to bang on the door. They shouted to the old man, “Bring out to us the man who has come to your house. We want to have sex with him.”<verse eid="JDG 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 19:23"/>The old man went outside and said to them, “Friends, I will not do that. That would be a very evil thing. This man is a guest in my house. You should not do such a terrible/disgraceful/shameful thing! <verse eid="JDG 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 19:24"/>Look, my daughter is here. She is <char style="add">still</char> a virgin. And this man’s slave wife is here. I will bring them out to you now. You may do to them whatever you wish, but do not do such a terrible/disgraceful/shameful thing to this young man!”<verse eid="JDG 19:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 19:25"/>But the men did not pay attention to what he said. So the man from the tribe of Levi took his slave wife and sent her to them, outside the house. They raped [EUP] her and abused her all night. Then at dawn, they allowed her to go. <verse eid="JDG 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 19:26"/>She returned to the old man’s house, where her husband was staying, but she fell down at the doorway and lay there all night.<verse eid="JDG 19:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JDG 19:27"/>In the morning, when the man from the tribe of Levi got up, he went outside of the house to continue his journey. He saw his slave wife lying there at the doorway of the house. Her hands were on the doorsill. <verse eid="JDG 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JDG 19:28"/>He said to her, “Get up! Let’s go!” But she did not answer, <char style="add">because she had died</char>. He put her body on the donkey and traveled to his home.<verse eid="JDG 19:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 19:29"/>When he arrived home, he took a knife and cut the body of the slave woman into twelve pieces. Then he sent one piece to each area of Israel, <char style="add">along with a message telling what had happened</char>. <verse eid="JDG 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 19:30"/>Everyone who saw a piece of the body and the message said, “Nothing like this has ever happened before. Not since our ancestors left Egypt <char style="add">have we heard of such a terrible thing</char>. We need to think carefully about it. Someone should decide what we should do.”<verse eid="JDG 19:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JDG 20"/>
  <para style="s1">The war between the tribe of Benjamin and the other tribes of Israel</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 20:1"/>All the Israelis, from Dan <char style="add">city in the north</char> to Beersheba <char style="add">city in the south</char>, and even from <char style="add">the </char> Gilead <char style="add">region on the east side of the Jordan River, heard what had happened. So they</char> they gathered together at Mizpah, <char style="add">at the place where they worshiped</char> Yahweh. <verse eid="JDG 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 20:2"/>The leaders of <char style="add">eleven of</char> the tribes of Israel stood in front of the people who gathered there. There were 400,000 men with swords who were there. <verse eid="JDG 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 20:3"/>The people of the tribe of Benjamin heard that the other Israelis had gone up to Mizpah, <char style="add">but none of the men from their tribe went to the meeting there</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:3">The Israelis who had come to Mizpah asked about the evil thing that had happened. <verse eid="JDG 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 20:4"/>So the husband of the woman who had been killed replied, “My slave wife and I came to Gibeah <char style="add">city</char>, wanting to stay there that night. <verse eid="JDG 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 20:5"/>That evening, the men of Gibeah came to attack me. They surrounded the house <char style="add">where I was staying</char> and wanted to <char style="add">have sex with me and then</char> kill me. They <char style="add">raped and</char> abused my slave wife <char style="add">all night</char>, and she died. <verse eid="JDG 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 20:6"/>I took her body home and cut it into pieces. Then I sent one piece to each area of Israel, <char style="add">because I wanted you all to know about</char> this wicked and disgraceful/shameful thing <char style="add">that</char> has been done here in Israel. <verse eid="JDG 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 20:7"/>So now, all you Israeli people, speak, and tell me what you think should be done!”<verse eid="JDG 20:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 20:8"/>All the people stood up, and in unison said, “None of us will go home! Not one of us will return to his house! <verse eid="JDG 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 20:9"/>This is what we must do to <char style="add">the people of</char> Gibeah. First, we will ◄cast lots/throw marked stones► <char style="add">to determine which group should attack them</char>. <verse eid="JDG 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 20:10"/>We will choose ◄one tenth/one from every ten► of the men from all the Israeli tribes. Those men will go and find food for the men who will go to attack the people of Gibeah. Then the other men will go to Gibeah to ◄pay the people back/punish them► for this terrible thing that they have done <char style="add">here</char> in Israel.” <verse eid="JDG 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 20:11"/>And all the Israeli people agreed <char style="add">that the people of Gibeah should be punished</char>.<verse eid="JDG 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 20:12"/>Then the Israeli men sent messengers throughout the tribe of Benjamin. They demanded, “Do you realize that some of your men have done a very evil thing? <verse eid="JDG 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 20:13"/>Bring those wicked men to us, in order that we can execute them. <char style="add">By doing that</char>, we will be doing what should be done because of this evil thing that has happened in Israel.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:13">But the <char style="add">people of the</char> tribe of Benjamin did not pay attention to their fellow Israelis. <verse eid="JDG 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 20:14"/>The men of the tribe of Benjamin left their cities and gathered at Gibeah to fight the <char style="add">other</char> Israelis. <verse eid="JDG 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 20:15"/>In that one day the men of the tribe of Benjamin recruited 26,000 soldiers who knew how to fight using swords. They also chose/recruited 700 men from Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 20:16"/>From all those soldiers there were 700 men who were left-handed, and each of them could sling a stone at <char style="add">a target that was very small and as narrow as</char> a hair, and the stone always hit the target!<verse eid="JDG 20:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 20:17"/>There were 400,000 men from the other Israeli tribes who had swords.<verse eid="JDG 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 20:18"/>Those other Israelis went up to Bethel and asked God, “Which tribe should be the first to attack the men from the tribe of Benjamin?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:18">Yahweh answered, “<char style="add">The men from the tribe of</char> Judah should go first.”<verse eid="JDG 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 20:19"/>The next morning, the Israeli men went and set up their tents near Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 20:20"/>Then they went to fight against <char style="add">the men from the tribe of</char> Benjamin, and stood in their positions for fighting a battle, <char style="add">facing Gibeah</char>. <verse eid="JDG 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 20:21"/>The men of the tribe of Benjamin came out of Gibeah and fought against them, and they killed 22,000 Israeli men on that day. <verse eid="JDG 20:21"/><verse number="22-23" style="v" sid="JDG 20:22-23"/><char style="add">Late that afternoon</char>, the <char style="add">remaining</char> Israeli men went to the place of worship and cried until the sun set. Then they asked Yahweh, “Should we attack the men of the tribe of Benjamin again, even though they are our fellow Israelis?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:22-23">Yahweh replied, “Yes, attack them again.” So the Israeli men encouraged each other. <verse eid="JDG 20:22-23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 20:24"/>The next day they again stood in their positions for fighting, just like they had done on the previous day. <verse eid="JDG 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 20:25"/>The men of the tribe of Benjamin came out of Gibeah and attacked the Israelis, and killed 18,000 more of their men.<verse eid="JDG 20:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JDG 20:26"/>
    <char style="add">In the afternoon</char>, all the people of Israel <char style="add">who had not been killed</char> again went to Bethel. There they sat down and cried to Yahweh, and they ◄fasted/abstained from eating food► until it was evening. They brought some offerings which they burned completely <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and they also brought some offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. <verse eid="JDG 20:26"/><verse number="27-28" style="v" sid="JDG 20:27-28"/>At that time, the Sacred Chest that contained the stone tablets on which were written the Ten Commandments was there at Bethel. A priest named Phinehas, the son of Eleazar and grandson of Aaron, often stood in front of that chest <char style="add">and talked with Yahweh</char>. While he stood there on that day, he asked Yahweh, “Shall we go again to fight against our fellow Israelis from the tribe of Benjamin, or shall we stop fighting against them?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:27-28">Yahweh answered, “Go again tomorrow, because tomorrow I will enable you to defeat them.” <verse eid="JDG 20:27-28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JDG 20:29"/>So <char style="add">the next day, 10,000 of</char> the Israeli men ◄set up ambushes/went to hide► <char style="add">in the fields</char> around Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JDG 20:30"/>The <char style="add">other</char> Israeli men went and stood in their positions for fighting a battle just like they had done on the previous days. <verse eid="JDG 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JDG 20:31"/>When the men of the tribe of Benjamin came out of the city to fight against them, the Israeli men retreated away from the city, and the men of the tribe of Benjamin pursued them. The men of the tribe of Benjamin killed many Israelis, like they had done before. They killed about 30 Israelis. They killed some in the fields, and they killed some on the road that went to Bethel and on the road that went to Gibeah.<verse eid="JDG 20:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JDG 20:32"/>The men of the tribe of Benjamin said, “We are defeating them like we did before!” But then Israeli men did what they had planned. The main group of Israeli men retreated a short distance from the city, to <char style="add">trick</char> the men of Gibeah and cause them to pursue the Israeli men along the roads outside the city.<verse eid="JDG 20:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JDG 20:33"/>The main group of Israeli men left their positions and retreated, and then they stood in their battle positions again at a place named Baal-Tamar. <verse eid="JDG 20:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JDG 20:34"/>Then <char style="add">while the men of Gibeah were running out of the city toward them</char>, the other 10,000 Israelis came out from the places where they had been hiding, west of Gibeah. They were men who had come from all parts of Israel. There was a very big battle. But the men of the tribe of Benjamin did not know that they were about to suffer a disastrous defeat. <verse eid="JDG 20:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JDG 20:35"/>Yahweh enabled the Israeli men to defeat the men of the tribe of Benjamin. They killed 25,000 of them, even though they all were using swords.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JDG 20:35">
    <char style="add">This is what happened</char>: <verse eid="JDG 20:35"/><verse number="36-38" style="v" sid="JDG 20:36-38"/>The main group of Israeli men arranged with the men who would be hiding that they should send up a smoke signal to enable the main group of soldiers to know when they should attack. Then the main group of Israeli men retreated for a short distance, because they knew that the other Israeli men who had been hiding on the other side of Gibeah would attack the people of the tribe of Benjamin by surprise. So <char style="add">after the main group of Israeli men retreated a little distance</char>, the men who had been hiding rushed out and ran into Gibeah and used their swords to kill everyone in the city. <char style="add">Then they started to burn the buildings</char>.<verse eid="JDG 20:36-38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JDG 20:39"/>By that time, the men of the tribe of Benjamin said, “We are winning the battle, as we did before!” <verse eid="JDG 20:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JDG 20:40"/>But then smoke <char style="add">from the burning buildings</char> began to rise up from the city. The men of the tribe of Benjamin turned around and saw that the whole city was burning. <verse eid="JDG 20:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JDG 20:41"/>Then the main group of Israeli men <char style="add">also saw the smoke, and they knew that the smoke signaled that they should</char> turn around and begin to attack. The men of the tribe of Benjamin were very afraid, because they realized that they were about to suffer a disastrous defeat. <verse eid="JDG 20:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JDG 20:42"/>So the men of the tribe of Benjamin tried to run away toward the desert to escape from the Israeli men, but they were not able to escape, because the Israeli men who had burned the two cities came out of those cities and killed many of them. <verse eid="JDG 20:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JDG 20:43"/>They surrounded <char style="add">some of</char> the men of the tribe of Benjamin, and pursued the others to the area east of Gibeah. <verse eid="JDG 20:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JDG 20:44"/>They killed 18,000 strong soldiers of the tribe of Benjamin. <verse eid="JDG 20:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JDG 20:45"/>Then the rest of the men of the tribe of Benjamin realized that they had been defeated. They ran toward the desert to Rimmon Rock, but the Israeli men killed 5,000 more men of the tribe of Benjamin along the roads. They pursued the rest of them to Gidom, and they killed 2,000 more men of the tribe of Benjamin there.<verse eid="JDG 20:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="JDG 20:46"/>Altogether, there were 25,000 men of the tribe of Benjamin who were killed, all of whom had swords. <verse eid="JDG 20:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JDG 20:47"/>But 600 men of the tribe of Benjamin ran to Rimmon Rock in the desert. They stayed there for four months. <verse eid="JDG 20:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JDG 20:48"/>Then the Israeli men went back to the land belonging to the tribe of Benjamin, and killed the people in every city. They also killed all the animals, and destroyed everything else that they found there. And they burned all the cities that they came to.<verse eid="JDG 20:48"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JDG 21"/>
  <para style="s1">They found wives for the men of the tribe of Benjamin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JDG 21:1"/>When the Israeli men gathered at Mizpah <char style="add">before the battle started</char>, they vowed, “None of us will ever allow one of our daughters to marry any man from the tribe of Benjamin!” <verse eid="JDG 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JDG 21:2"/>But now the Israelis went to Bethel and they cried loudly to Yahweh all day, until the sun went down. <verse eid="JDG 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JDG 21:3"/>They kept saying, “Yahweh, God of us Israeli people, <char style="add">it is as though</char> one of the tribes of us Israelis does not exist any more! ◄Why has this happened to us?/It is terrible that this has happened to us!►” [RHQ]<verse eid="JDG 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JDG 21:4"/>Early the next morning the people built an altar. Then they completely burned some sacrifices <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and also offered other sacrifices to maintain fellowship with God.<verse eid="JDG 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JDG 21:5"/>Then, because they had vowed that anyone who did not meet with them at Mizpah <char style="add">to help fight the men of the tribe of Benjamin</char> would be killed, they asked among themselves, “Were there any of the tribes of Israel who did not come to Mizpah to meet with us in the presence of Yahweh?”<verse eid="JDG 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JDG 21:6"/>The Israelis felt sorry for their fellow Israelis from the tribe of Benjamin. They said, “Today one of our Israeli tribes ◄has disappeared/no longer exists►. <verse eid="JDG 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JDG 21:7"/>Yahweh heard us solemnly declare that we would not allow any of our daughters to marry any man from the tribe of Benjamin. What can we do to make certain that the men of the tribe of Benjamin who were not killed will have wives?” <verse eid="JDG 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JDG 21:8"/>Then <char style="add">one of</char> them asked, “What group from any of the tribes of Israel did not send any men here to Mizpah?” <verse eid="JDG 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JDG 21:9"/><char style="add">They realized that</char> when the soldiers were counted, there was no one from Jabesh-Gilead <char style="add">city</char> who had come there.<verse eid="JDG 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JDG 21:10"/>So all the Israelis decided to send 12,000 very good soldiers to Jabesh-Gilead to kill the people there with their swords, even to kill the married women and children. <verse eid="JDG 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JDG 21:11"/><char style="add">They told this to those men</char>: “This is what you must do: You must kill every man in Jabesh-Gilead. You must also kill every married woman. <char style="add">But do not kill the unmarried women</char>.” <verse eid="JDG 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JDG 21:12"/>So those soldiers <char style="add">went to Jabesh-Gilead and killed all the men, married women, and children. But they</char> found 400 unmarried young women there. So they brought them to their camp at Shiloh, in Canaan, <char style="add">across the river from the Gilead area that belonged to the tribe of Benjamin</char>.<verse eid="JDG 21:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JDG 21:13"/>Then all the Israelis <char style="add">who had gathered</char> sent a message to the 600 men who were at Rimmon Rock. They said that they would like to make peace with them. <verse eid="JDG 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JDG 21:14"/>So the men came back from Rimmon Rock. The Israelis gave to them the women from Jabesh-Gilead whom they had not killed. But there were <char style="add">only 400 women. But there were</char> not enough women <char style="add">for those 600 men</char>.<verse eid="JDG 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JDG 21:15"/>The Israelis <char style="add">still</char> felt sorry for the men of the tribe of Benjamin, because Yahweh had ◄decimated/almost wiped out► one of the Israeli tribes. <verse eid="JDG 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JDG 21:16"/>The Israeli leaders said, “We have killed all the married women of the tribe of Benjamin. Where can we get women to be wives of the men who are still alive? <verse eid="JDG 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JDG 21:17"/>These men must have wives to give birth to children, in order that their families will continue. If that does not happen, all the people of one of the tribes of Israel will die. <verse eid="JDG 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JDG 21:18"/>But we cannot allow our daughters to marry these men, because we vowed that Yahweh will curse anyone who gives one of his daughters to become a wife of any man of the tribe of Benjamin.” <verse eid="JDG 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JDG 21:19"/>Then <char style="add">one of</char> them ◄had an idea/thought of something that they could do►. He said, “Every year there is a festival to honor Yahweh at Shiloh, which is north of Bethel and east of the road that extends from Bethel to Shechem, and it is south of Lebonah <char style="add">city</char>.”<verse eid="JDG 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JDG 21:20"/>So the Israeli leaders told the men of the tribe of Benjamin, “<char style="add">When it is the time for that festival</char>, go to Shiloh and hide in the vineyards. <verse eid="JDG 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JDG 21:21"/>Keep watching for the young women to come out of the city to dance. <char style="add">When they come out</char>, all of you should run out of the vineyards. Each of you can seize one of the young women of Shiloh. Then you can all return to your homes <char style="add">with those women</char>. <verse eid="JDG 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JDG 21:22"/>If their fathers or brothers come to us and complain <char style="add">about what you have done</char>, we will say to them, ‘Be kind to the men of the tribe of Benjamin. When we fought them, we did not leave any women alive to become their wives, and you did not give those young women to the men from the tribe of Benjamin. <char style="add">They stole them</char>. So you will not be guilty, <char style="add">even though you said that you would not allow any of your daughters to marry one of them</char>.’ ”<verse eid="JDG 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JDG 21:23"/>So that is what the men of the tribe of Benjamin did. <char style="add">They went to Shiloh at the time of the festival</char>. And when the young women were dancing, each man caught one of them and took her away and married her. Then they took their wives back to the land that God had given to them. They rebuilt their cities <char style="add">that had been burned down</char>, and they lived there.<verse eid="JDG 21:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JDG 21:24"/>The other Israelis went to their homes in the areas where their tribes and clans lived, the areas that God had allotted to them.<verse eid="JDG 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JDG 21:25"/>At that time, the Israeli people did not have a king. Everyone did what they themselves thought was right.<verse eid="JDG 21:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JDG 21"/>
</usx>
