<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JHN" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">JOHN</para>
  <para style="toc1">John</para>
  <para style="toc2">John</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jhn</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book is the Gospel that John wrote. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">John</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JHN 1"/>
  <para style="s1">John 1:1-18</para>
  <para style="s1">This book is about Jesus, who was eternally with God but also became a human being to reveal God to mankind.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 1:1"/>The one who expresses [MET] ◄<char style="add">God’s character/what God is like</char>► has always existed ◄from the beginning [MTY] <char style="add">of everything/before everything began</char>►. He has always existed with God, and he has God’s nature. <verse eid="JHN 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 1:2"/>He always existed with God <char style="add">before</char> he began [MTY] <char style="add">to create anything</char>. <verse eid="JHN 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 1:3"/>He is the one by whom <char style="add">God</char> caused everything to exist. He is the one who created absolutely everything [LIT]. <verse eid="JHN 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 1:4"/>He is the one who <char style="add">caused everything to</char> live. He, who caused us people to live, <char style="add">revealed to us the truth about God as</char> a light [MET] <char style="add">reveals what is in the darkness</char>. <verse eid="JHN 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 1:5"/>People do not want him to reveal <char style="add">that what they do is evil</char> [MET], just <char style="add">like</char> darkness <char style="add">is evil</char>. But <char style="add">just like</char> darkness cannot put out light [MET], <char style="add">evil people have never prevented the one who was like a light from revealing God’s truth</char> (OR, <char style="add">evil people have never</char> understood the <char style="add">one who was like</char> a light.)<verse eid="JHN 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 1:6"/>A man whose name was John was sent by God {God sent a man whose name was John}. <verse eid="JHN 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 1:7"/>He came to tell people <char style="add">about the one who was like</char> [MET] a light. He came to show that everything that the <char style="add">one who was like a light</char> [MET] said was true, in order that he could enable all people to believe <char style="add">in the one who was like a light</char>. <verse eid="JHN 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 1:8"/>John himself was not the <char style="add">one who was like a</char> light [MET]. Instead, he came to tell others about that <char style="add">one who was like a</char> light. <verse eid="JHN 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 1:9"/><char style="add">While John was doing that</char>, the one who was truly <char style="add">like</char> a light was about to show himself to the world. He was the one who enables all people <char style="add">to know about God, as</char> a light [MET] enables <char style="add">people to know what is in the darkness</char>.<verse eid="JHN 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 1:10"/>Although the one <char style="add">who was like a light</char> was <char style="add">here</char> on the earth, and although he was the one whom <char style="add">God</char> caused to create everything, <char style="add">most</char> people [MTY, HYP] did not realize who he <char style="add">was</char>. (OR, although he was the one whom <char style="add">God</char> caused to create everything, <char style="add">most</char> people did not accept him.) <verse eid="JHN 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 1:11"/>Although he came to the land that belonged to him <char style="add">because he created it, most of</char> his own people, <char style="add">the Jews</char>, rejected him (OR, did not accept him). <verse eid="JHN 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 1:12"/>But those <char style="add">of us who welcomed him, God</char> authorized <char style="add">that we would have a relationship with</char> him [MET] <char style="add">like</char> children <char style="add">have a relationship with their father</char>. We were people who believed <char style="add">that what he said</char> about himself [MTY] <char style="add">was true</char>. <verse eid="JHN 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 1:13"/>We became <char style="add">like God’s children</char>, not because our ancestors <char style="add">belonged to God</char>, or because of someone’s sexual desires, nor because some man desired to have children like himself. Instead, we were caused by God {God caused us} to become <char style="add">like</char> his children.<verse eid="JHN 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 1:14"/>The one who expresses [MET] ◄<char style="add">God’s character/what God is like</char>► became a human being, and he lived among us <char style="add">for a while</char>. As a result, we saw how wonderful he is. He came from <char style="add">God</char> his father, and there was no other person as wonderful as he. He was wonderful because he always acted ◄kindly toward us/in ways we did not deserve►, and he always <char style="add">spoke</char> truthfully to us <char style="add">about God</char>.<verse eid="JHN 1:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 1:15"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> when John was telling people about him, <char style="add">he saw Jesus</char>. Then he shouted to them, “I told you <char style="add">previously</char> that someone will come later who is more important than I am, since he existed <char style="add">long</char> before me. This <char style="add">is the man I was talking about</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 1:16"/>We have all benefited very much from what he has done. Again and again, he has acted in kind way toward us in ways we did not deserve. <verse eid="JHN 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 1:17"/>Moses proclaimed <char style="add">God’s</char> laws <char style="add">to our ancestors</char>. But what Jesus Christ did for us <char style="add">was much better</char>. He acted in kindness toward us in ways we did not deserve and told us the truth <char style="add">about God</char>. <verse eid="JHN 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 1:18"/>No one has ever seen God. But God’s only Son, <char style="add">Jesus</char>, who has always had a very close relationship with God, has told us about God.<verse eid="JHN 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When religious authorities asked John about his identity, he said he was preparing people for the coming of the Messiah, who was much more important than himself.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 1:19-28">John 1:19-28</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 1:19"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] in Jerusalem <char style="add">city</char> sent some <char style="add">Jewish</char> priests and ◄Levites/men who worked in the temple► to where John was, to ask him some questions. They said to him, “What do you <char style="add">claim about</char> yourself?” <verse eid="JHN 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 1:20"/>So John told them the truth, and he told them clearly [DOU]. He said, “<char style="add">I</char> am not ◄the Messiah/God’s chosen king►!” <verse eid="JHN 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 1:21"/>Then they asked him, “Then what <char style="add">do you say about yourself</char>? Are you <char style="add">the prophet</char> Elijah <char style="add">that was prophesied to return</char> {◄<char style="add">someone/another prophet</char>► <char style="add">prophesied would return</char>} <char style="add">before the Messiah</char>?” He replied, “No, <char style="add">I</char> am not.” Then they asked him, “Are you the prophet <char style="add">like Moses that</char> ◄<char style="add">we are waiting for/God promised to send</char>►?” He replied, “No.” <verse eid="JHN 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 1:22"/>So they asked him, “Then who do you <char style="add">claim to be</char>? <char style="add">Tell us</char> so that we can <char style="add">go back and</char> report to those who sent us. What do you say about yourself?” <verse eid="JHN 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 1:23"/>John replied, “<char style="add">I</char> am the one <char style="add">the prophet Isaiah said</char> would proclaim <char style="add">this new message</char> loudly <char style="add">to the people who would pass by</char> in this desolate area: ‘Prepare <char style="add">yourselves to receive</char> the Lord when he comes [MET], <char style="add">just like people prepare</char> a road <char style="add">for an important official</char>.<verse eid="JHN 1:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 1:24"/>Some of those people <char style="add">who were questioning</char> John were ones who had been sent by the Pharisee <char style="add">religious group</char> {whom the Pharisee <char style="add">religious group</char> had sent}. <verse eid="JHN 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 1:25"/>They asked John, “Since <char style="add">you say</char> you are not the Messiah, nor <char style="add">the prophet</char> Elijah, nor the prophet <char style="add">like Moses</char>, <char style="add">what authority</char> do you have? <char style="add">Furthermore</char>, why are you baptizing <char style="add">Jews, treating them as though they were non-Jews who wanted to become Jews</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 1:26"/>John replied, “I am <char style="add">just</char> baptizing people with water <char style="add">to prepare them to welcome the Messiah</char>. But <char style="add">right now</char> someone is among you whom you people do not know. <verse eid="JHN 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 1:27"/>He <char style="add">will preach to you</char> after I <char style="add">am gone</char>. <char style="add">He is so important that</char> I am not worthy to <char style="add">serve him as a slave</char> [MET] <char style="add">by</char> untying his sandals.”<verse eid="JHN 1:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 1:28"/>Those things happened at <char style="add">a place called</char> Bethany, on the <char style="add">east</char> side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, where John was baptizing people.<verse eid="JHN 1:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John the Baptizer announced that Jesus was the one who would become a sacrifice to remove guilt for sin, and how God had confirmed that Jesus was the Son of God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 1:29-34">John 1:29-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 1:29"/>The next day John saw Jesus coming toward him. He said to the people, “Look! Here is the <char style="add">man whom</char> God <char style="add">has appointed to be a sacrifice</char> [MET], <char style="add">like</char> the lambs <char style="add">that the people of Israel sacrificed! By sacrificing himself</char> he will <char style="add">make it possible for everyone in</char> the world to be no longer <char style="add">guilty for having</char> sinned. <verse eid="JHN 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 1:30"/>He is the one about whom I said <char style="add">before</char>, ‘Someone will come later who is more important than I am, since he existed <char style="add">long</char> before me.’ <verse eid="JHN 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 1:31"/>I myself did not <char style="add">previously</char> recognize that he <char style="add">was the Messiah</char>. But <char style="add">now I know who he is</char>, and I have baptized people with water to enable <char style="add">you people of</char> Israel to recognize who he is.”<verse eid="JHN 1:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 1:32"/>John spoke clearly <char style="add">what God had shown him about Jesus</char>. He said, “I saw <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit as he was descending from heaven in the form of a dove. The Spirit remained on Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 1:33"/>I myself did not know <char style="add">previously</char> that he <char style="add">was the Messiah</char>. However, <char style="add">God</char> sent me to baptize people with water, <char style="add">people who said they wanted to turn from their sinful ways. While I was doing that</char>, God told me, ‘The man on whom you will see my Spirit descend and remain is the one who will put the Holy Spirit within you <char style="add">(pl) to truly change your lives</char>.’ <verse eid="JHN 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 1:34"/>I saw <char style="add">the Spirit descend on him</char>, and I tell you that he is ◄the Son of God/the person who is both God and man►.”<verse eid="JHN 1:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After John declared again that Jesus would be a sacrifice to remove guilt for sin, four men decided to become Jesus’ disciples.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 1:35-42">John 1:35-42</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 1:35"/>The next day John was at the same place again ◄with two of us/with two of his disciples►. <verse eid="JHN 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 1:36"/>When he saw Jesus passing by, he said, “Look! There is the man God <char style="add">has appointed to be a sacrifice, like</char> the lambs [MET] <char style="add">the people of Israel have sacrificed!</char>” <verse eid="JHN 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 1:37"/>◄When we/those two disciples► heard John say this, we/they went with Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 1:38"/>Jesus turned around and saw us/them coming behind him. So he asked us/them, “What do you want?” We/They replied, “Teacher, <char style="add">tell us</char> where you are staying, <char style="add">because we want to talk with you</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 1:39"/>He replied, “Come <char style="add">with me</char>, and you will see <char style="add">where I am staying</char>!” So we/they went with him and saw where he was staying. We/They stayed with him until about 4 o’clock (OR, from about 4 PM until the next day).<verse eid="JHN 1:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 1:40"/>◄One of us/One of the two men► who heard what John had said and who went with Jesus was Andrew, Simon Peter’s <char style="add">younger</char> brother. <verse eid="JHN 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 1:41"/><char style="add">After Andrew left Jesus</char>, the first thing he did was to find his own <char style="add">older</char> brother Simon and say to him, “We have found the Messiah!” <verse eid="JHN 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 1:42"/>Then he took Simon to Jesus. Jesus looked intently at him, and then said, “You are Simon. Your father’s name is John. You will be given {<char style="add">I</char> will give you} the name Cephas.” <char style="add">Cephas is an Aramaic name that means ‘solid rock’. It</char> means <char style="add">the same in Greek as the name</char> Peter.<verse eid="JHN 1:42"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told Nathaniel that he knew about him supernaturally, but that he would do things that were more surprising than that.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 1:43-51">John 1:43-51</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 1:43"/>The next day <char style="add">Jesus</char> decided to leave <char style="add">the Jordan River valley</char>. He went to Galilee <char style="add">district</char> and (OR, on the way there he) found a man named Philip. Jesus said to him, “Come with me!” <verse eid="JHN 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 1:44"/>Philip and Andrew and Peter were all from Bethsaida <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="JHN 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 1:45"/>Then Philip <char style="add">searched for</char> Nathaniel and found him, and said to him, “We have met <char style="add">the Messiah</char>, the one Moses <char style="add">wrote about</char>! The prophets also <char style="add">prophesied that he would come</char>. He is Jesus, from Nazareth <char style="add">town</char>. His father’s name is Joseph.” <verse eid="JHN 1:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 1:46"/>Nathaniel replied, “Nazareth? ◄Nothing good can come from <char style="add">such an unimportant place</char>!/Can anything good come from <char style="add">such an unimportant place</char>?► [RHQ]” Philip replied, “Come and see!” <verse eid="JHN 1:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 1:47"/>When Jesus saw Nathaniel approaching, he said about Nathaniel, “Here is an example of a good Israelite! He never deceives anyone!” <verse eid="JHN 1:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 1:48"/>Nathaniel asked him, “How do you know what I <char style="add">am like</char>?” Jesus replied, “I saw you before Philip called you, when you were <char style="add">by yourself</char> under the fig tree.” <verse eid="JHN 1:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 1:49"/>Then Nathaniel declared, “Teacher, you <char style="add">must be</char> ◄the Son of God/the person who is both God and man►! You are the King of Israel <char style="add">we have been waiting for</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 1:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 1:50"/>Jesus replied to him, “You [RHQ] believe <char style="add">those things about me</char> because I told you I saw you when you were under the fig tree. <char style="add">I was able to see you supernaturally even though I was far away from you</char>. But you will see <char style="add">me do</char> things that are more surprising than that!” <verse eid="JHN 1:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 1:51"/>Then Jesus said to him, “This is the absolute truth: <char style="add">Just like what your ancestor Jacob saw long ago in a vision</char>, some day you <char style="add">(pl)</char> will see heaven opened up, and you will see God’s angels ascending from me and descending on me, the one who came from heaven.”<verse eid="JHN 1:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JHN 2"/>
  <para style="s1">In Cana Jesus did his first miracle, turning water into delicious wine.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 2:1-11">John 2:1-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 2:1"/>Two days later there was a wedding <char style="add">celebration</char> in Cana <char style="add">town</char>, in Galilee <char style="add">district</char>. Jesus’ mother was there. <verse eid="JHN 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 2:2"/>Jesus and <char style="add">we</char> his disciples <char style="add">were also there, because</char> we had been invited {someone had invited us} also. <verse eid="JHN 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 2:3"/>When the guests had drunk all the wine <char style="add">that was there</char>, Jesus’ mother said to him, “The wine is all gone; <char style="add">can you do something about that</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 2:4"/>Jesus said to her, “Ma’am/Woman, ◄do not <char style="add">tell </char> me <char style="add">what to do</char>!/why do you <char style="add">tell </char> me <char style="add">what to do</char>?► [RHQ] It is not yet time [MTY] <char style="add">to show </char> that I am <char style="add">the Messiah by working miracles</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 2:5"/>Then Jesus’ mother said to the servants, “Do whatever he tells you!” <verse eid="JHN 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 2:6"/>There were six <char style="add">empty</char> stone jars there. The Jews <char style="add">habitually put water in them</char> to use for washing things <char style="add">to make them acceptable to God</char>. Each jar held ◄20 to 30 gallons/80 to 120 liters►. <verse eid="JHN 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 2:7"/>Jesus said to the servants, “Fill the jars with water!” So they filled the jars to the brim. <verse eid="JHN 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 2:8"/>Then he told them, “Now, ladle out some <char style="add">of it</char> and take it ◄to the head waiter/to the master of ceremonies►.” So the servants did that. <verse eid="JHN 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 2:9"/>◄The head waiter/The master of ceremonies► tasted the water, which had now become wine. He did not know where the wine had come from, but the servants who had ladled out the wine knew. <char style="add">The wine was delicious</char>! So he called the bridegroom over, <verse eid="JHN 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 2:10"/>and said to him, “Everyone <char style="add">else</char> serves the best wine first. Then when the guests have drunk so much <char style="add">that they cannot tell the difference</char>, <char style="add">they serve</char> the cheap wine. But you <char style="add">have not done what others do</char>. You have kept the best wine until now!” <verse eid="JHN 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 2:11"/>That was the first miracle that Jesus did. He did it in Cana <char style="add">town</char>, in Galilee <char style="add">district</char>. By doing it he showed how awesome he is, and as a result, <char style="add">we</char> his disciples believed that he <char style="add">truly was the Messiah</char>.<verse eid="JHN 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus and others went to Capernaum and stayed there several days.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 2:12">John 2:12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 2:12"/>Jesus then went down to Capernaum <char style="add">city</char> with his mother and <char style="add">younger</char> brothers and <char style="add">us</char> his disciples. We stayed there several days.<verse eid="JHN 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After Jesus expelled the merchants from the temple, the Jewish leaders wanted him to do a miracle to show by what authority he did that. He told them metaphorically that he would become alive again three days after he died.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 2:13-25">John 2:13-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 2:13"/>Later, when it was almost time for the Jewish Passover <char style="add">celebration</char>, Jesus <char style="add">and we his disciples</char> went up to Jerusalem. <verse eid="JHN 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 2:14"/>There, in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>, he saw some men who were selling cattle, sheep, and pigeons <char style="add">for sacrifices</char>. He also saw men who were sitting at tables, <char style="add">making a big profit as they</char> gave people <char style="add">Temple tax</char> coins in exchange for <char style="add">their Roman</char> coins. <verse eid="JHN 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 2:15"/>Then Jesus made a whip from some cords and <char style="add">used it to</char> chase out the sheep and cattle from the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>. By overturning their tables he scattered the coins of the men who were exchanging them. <verse eid="JHN 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 2:16"/>He said to those who were selling doves, “Take these doves away <char style="add">from here</char>! Stop <char style="add">defiling</char> my Father’s Temple <char style="add">by</char> making it a market!” <verse eid="JHN 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 2:17"/>Then <char style="add">we</char> disciples remembered that these words had been written {that <char style="add">someone/David</char> had written <char style="add">these words</char>} <char style="add">in the Scriptures prophesying what the Messiah would say</char>: “Others [PRS] will strongly oppose me because I greatly desire that <char style="add">people respect</char> your Sacred Tent.”<verse eid="JHN 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 2:18"/>So <char style="add">one of</char> the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] replied to him, “What miracle will you perform to show us that <char style="add">you have authority from God</char> to do these things?” <verse eid="JHN 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 2:19"/>Jesus replied to them, “If/When you destroy this temple, I will build it again within three days.” <verse eid="JHN 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 2:20"/>So the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] said, “We have been building this Temple for 46 years <char style="add">and it is not finished yet</char>! So ◄there is no way you will build it within three days!/how will you build it within three days?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 2:21"/>But when Jesus said that about the temple, <char style="add">he was really talking about</char> his own body. <verse eid="JHN 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 2:22"/><char style="add">Later</char>, after Jesus had <char style="add">died and had</char> become alive again, <char style="add">we</char> his disciples remembered the words he had said. As a result, we believed <char style="add">what had been prophesied in</char> the Scriptures <char style="add">about the Messiah becoming alive again</char>, and we believed that what Jesus said <char style="add">was true</char>.<verse eid="JHN 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 2:23"/>While Jesus was in Jerusalem at the Passover celebration, many people came to believe <char style="add">that he was the Messiah</char> because they saw the miracles he was performing. <verse eid="JHN 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 2:24"/>But he did not let them tell him what he should do <char style="add">as the Messiah</char>, because he knew within himself what they were all <char style="add">thinking</char>. <verse eid="JHN 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 2:25"/>He did not need anyone to tell him what others were thinking, because he already knew what they were <char style="add">thinking and wanting</char>.<verse eid="JHN 2:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JHN 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told Nicodemus that people needed to be born again spiritually to have eternal life.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 3:1-15">John 3:1-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 3:1"/>There was a man named Nicodemus, who was a member of the Jewish religious council. He belonged to the Pharisee <char style="add">religious sect</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 3:2"/>He went to see Jesus at night, <char style="add">to talk to him about God’s kingdom</char>. He said to Jesus, “Teacher, <char style="add">we believe that</char> you are a teacher who has come from God. <char style="add">We believe this because</char> we know that someone could perform the miracles you are doing only if God were helping him.” <verse eid="JHN 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 3:3"/>Jesus replied to him, “Listen to this carefully: Unless people are born again and <char style="add">have a new life from God</char>, they cannot even see the place where God rules [MET]!” <verse eid="JHN 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 3:4"/>Then Nicodemus said to him, “◄No one can be born when he is old!/How can anyone be born when he is old?► [RHQ] ◄There is no way he can enter his mother’s womb and be born a second time!/How can he enter his mother’s womb and be born a second time?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 3:5"/>Jesus answered, “Note this: Being born naturally is not <char style="add">enough</char>; people need to also be born <char style="add">spiritually</char> by God’s Spirit. If that does not happen, they cannot experience God ruling [MET] <char style="add">their lives</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 3:6"/>Humans give birth to humans. But those who are born <char style="add">again </char> as a result of what <char style="add">God’s </char> Spirit <char style="add">does receive a new </char> spiritual <char style="add">nature from God</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 3:7"/>Do not be surprised about my telling you that you must be born again <char style="add">and have a new life from God</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 3:8"/><char style="add">Let me illustrate</char>: The wind blows wherever it wants to blow. You hear its sound, but you do not know where the wind comes from or where it is going. Similarly, those <char style="add">who do not know God cannot understand/control/predict</char> how people are born again as a result of what God’s spirit <char style="add">does</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 3:9"/>Nicodemus replied to him, “How can that happen?” <verse eid="JHN 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 3:10"/>Jesus replied to him, “You <char style="add">(sg)</char> are a <char style="add">well-known</char> teacher among <char style="add">us</char> Israelite people, so ◄I am surprised that you do not understand these things!/how is it that you do not understand these things?► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 3:11"/>Listen to this carefully: ◄My disciples and I/I► tell you <char style="add">(pl)</char> about the things that my disciples and I have seen and know <char style="add">are true</char>, but you <char style="add">(pl)</char> do not admit that what my disciples and I are saying <char style="add">is true</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 3:12"/>I have told you about the things <char style="add">that happen here</char> on earth that are true, but you <char style="add">(pl)</char> do not believe me. So if I tell you <char style="add">(sg)</char> about things <char style="add">that happen</char> in heaven, ◄you certainly will not believe me!/how will you believe me?► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 3:13"/>I am the only one who has gone up to heaven; no one else has gone up there. I am also the one who came down from heaven. <char style="add">So I know what happens there</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 3:14"/><char style="add">Long ago when the Israelite people rebelled against God</char> in the desolate area, <char style="add">God sent poisonous snakes to bite them</char>. But when Moses lifted up <char style="add">on a pole</char> the <char style="add">model of a</char> poisonous snake, <char style="add">everyone who looked at that model was healed from their snake bites</char>. Similarly, <char style="add">even though I</char> am the one who came from heaven, <char style="add">some day people</char> will lift me up <char style="add">on a cross to kill me</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 3:15"/>As a result, everyone who believes/trusts in me will have eternal life.”<verse eid="JHN 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God sent his Son into the world to save everyone who trusts in him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 3:16-21">John 3:16-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 3:16"/>God loved us people [MTY] in the world so much that he gave his only Son <char style="add">as a sacrifice for us</char>, in order that everyone who believes in him would not be separated from God forever. Instead, they would have eternal life. <verse eid="JHN 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 3:17"/>When God sent his Son into the world, his purpose was not to punish the <char style="add">people in</char> [MTY] the world for their sins. Instead, he sent him in order that they might be saved by him {he might save them} <char style="add">from being</char> ◄<char style="add">guilty/punished</char>► <char style="add">for their sins</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 3:18"/>Everyone who trusts in his Son, <char style="add">God says that they</char> will not be punished {that he will not punish them}. But God has already <char style="add">said that</char> everyone who does not trust in his Son will be punished {that he will punish everyone who does not trust in his Son}, because they have not trusted in what his only Son <char style="add">has done for them</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 3:19"/>The <char style="add">one who was like a</char> light [MET] <char style="add">to reveal God’s truth to us</char> came into the world. But people loved doing what was <char style="add">evil, like</char> darkness [MET] <char style="add">is evil</char>, instead of loving the <char style="add">one who was like a</char> light. That is the reason <char style="add">God will</char> judge people <char style="add">and condemn them</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 3:20"/>Everyone who does what is evil hates the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> light, and they will not come to the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> light, because it would be shown {<char style="add">the one who is like a light</char> would show} that their deeds <char style="add">are evil, and he would rebuke them</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 3:21"/>But those who live according to <char style="add">God’s</char> truth come to the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> light, in order that it may be seen clearly {that people may see clearly} that the things they have done, they did them because <char style="add">they have depended</char> on God.<verse eid="JHN 3:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When many people began to become Jesus’ disciples, and John the Baptizer declared that Jesus was greater than he, the Jewish leaders rejected John’s and Jesus’ testimony that Jesus was equal to God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 3:22-36">John 3:22-36</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 3:22"/>Some time later Jesus and we disciples went to Judea district. He stayed with us there and <char style="add">directed us as we</char> baptized people.<verse eid="JHN 3:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 3:23"/>John <char style="add">the Baptizer</char> was also baptizing people. He was doing that at Aenon <char style="add">village</char> near Salim <char style="add">town in Samaria district</char>, because there were many springs in that area. <char style="add">Many</char> people kept coming <char style="add">to John</char> and were being baptized {he was baptizing them}. <verse eid="JHN 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 3:24"/>That happened before John was put {they put John} in prison. <verse eid="JHN 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 3:25"/>Then some of John’s disciples and a certain Jew started arguing about the Jewish rituals of washing things <char style="add">to make them acceptable to God</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 3:26"/>Then those disciples went to John and said to him, “Teacher, <char style="add">do you remember</char> the man who was with you when you were baptizing people on the other side of the Jordan River? He is the one you were telling us about. Well, now he is baptizing people, and many people are going to him <char style="add">instead of coming to us</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 3:27"/>John replied, “A person can become <char style="add">important</char> only if God [MTY] permits it. <char style="add">So</char> we <char style="add">should not be jealous about Jesus being popular</char>! <verse eid="JHN 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 3:28"/>You yourselves can verify what I said. I told you that I am not ◄the Messiah/God’s promised king►. Instead, I <char style="add">told you that</char> I was sent {that <char style="add">God</char> sent me} to prepare the way for him. <verse eid="JHN 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 3:29"/><char style="add">Let me illustrate</char> [MET]: <char style="add">He is like a</char> ◄<char style="add">bridegroom/man who is being married</char>►, <char style="add">and I am like his friend</char>. The friend of the bridegroom stands there and waits <char style="add">for him to come</char>. That friend is very happy when he hears the bridegroom’s voice <char style="add">when he arrives</char>. Similarly, I am very happy <char style="add">about what you have told me</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 3:30"/>It is necessary for Jesus to become more important <char style="add">by making more disciples than I have</char>, and for me to become less <char style="add">important</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 3:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 3:31"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus</char> came from heaven. He is more important than anyone else. Those who are born from <char style="add">parents here</char> on earth [MTY] are just humans, and they speak about things <char style="add">that happen here</char> on the earth. But since Jesus came from heaven, his <char style="add">words are</char> more important than anyone else’s. <verse eid="JHN 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 3:32"/>He tells people what he has seen and what he heard <char style="add">in heaven</char>, but very few people [HYP] listen to what he says. <verse eid="JHN 3:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 3:33"/>Those who have accepted what he has said verify that what God has said is true. <verse eid="JHN 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 3:34"/><char style="add">We know it is true</char> because <char style="add">Jesus</char>, the one God sent, speaks the message of God. <char style="add">That is also true</char> because God causes his Spirit to live <char style="add">in Jesus</char> to completely <char style="add">direct everything he says and does</char>. <verse eid="JHN 3:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 3:35"/>God loves his Son, and has caused him to have control/power over everything. <verse eid="JHN 3:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 3:36"/>Those who trust in <char style="add">God’s</char> Son have eternal life. But those who reject God’s Son will never have <char style="add">eternal</char> life. Instead, God is angry with them <char style="add">and he will surely punish them</char>.<verse eid="JHN 3:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JHN 4"/>
  <para style="s1">John 4:1-30</para>
  <para style="s1">While Jesus talked with a Samaritan woman, he showed by his God-given knowledge of her personal life that he is the life-giving Messiah.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-2" style="v" sid="JHN 4:1-2"/>
    <char style="add">At that time, many people were asking</char> Jesus to baptize them. He did not baptize people; it was <char style="add">we</char> his disciples who were doing the baptizing. But when some of the Pharisee <char style="add">religious group</char> heard <char style="add">people say that</char> Jesus was making more disciples than John <char style="add">the Baptizer</char> and was baptizing them, <char style="add">they became very jealous</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:1-2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 4:3"/>When the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> heard about that, <char style="add">so that the Pharisees would not cause trouble for him</char>, he left Judea <char style="add">district</char>, and went again <char style="add">with us disciples</char> to Galilee district.<verse eid="JHN 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 4:4"/>
    <char style="add">He</char> knew that God wanted him to travel through Samaria <char style="add">district</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 4:5"/>So we arrived at a town named Sychar in Samaria <char style="add">district</char>. That was near the plot of ground that <char style="add">our ancestor</char> Jacob had given to his son Joseph <char style="add">long ago</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:5"/><verse number="6-8" style="v" sid="JHN 4:6-8"/>The well that <char style="add">used to</char> belong to Jacob was on that plot of ground. Jesus was tired from walking. So while <char style="add">we</char> disciples went into the town to buy some food, he sat down alongside the well. It was about noontime. A woman who <char style="add">lived there</char> in Samaria came to get some water <char style="add">from the well</char>. Jesus said to her, “Will you give me <char style="add">from the well</char> some water <char style="add">to drink</char>?” The <char style="add">woman knew that</char> Jews did not like ◄<char style="add">to touch things that belong to</char> Samaritans/<char style="add">to</char> come near Samaritans►, (OR, Jews did not like to associate with Samaritans,) <verse eid="JHN 4:6-8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 4:9"/>so the woman said to him, “You are a Jew, and I am from Samaria. Furthermore, I am a woman. So ◄<char style="add">I am surprised</char> that you are asking me for a drink <char style="add">of water</char>!/how is it that you are asking me for a drink <char style="add">of water</char>?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 4:10"/>Jesus replied to her, “If you <char style="add">(sg)</char> knew what God <char style="add">wanted to</char> give you, and if you knew who I am, the one who is asking you for a drink, you would have asked me, and I would have given you water that gives life.” <verse eid="JHN 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 4:11"/>She <char style="add">thought he was talking about</char> ordinary <char style="add">water. So she</char> said to him, “Sir, you do not have a bucket <char style="add">or a rope with which to get water from the well</char>, and the well is deep. So <char style="add">since you cannot get water from this well</char>, where can you get that life-giving water? <verse eid="JHN 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 4:12"/>Our ancestor Jacob left us this well. He drank water from it, and there was <char style="add">enough good water</char> so that his sons and his flocks <char style="add">of sheep</char> and goats drank from it also. <char style="add">Do you claim that</char> you are greater than Jacob, <char style="add">and because of that you can give us life-giving water</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 4:13"/>Jesus replied to her, “Everyone who drinks water from this <char style="add">well</char> will later become thirsty again. <verse eid="JHN 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 4:14"/>But those who drink the water that I will give them will never be thirsty again. On the contrary, the water that I give them will become in their inner beings like a spring of water that will enable them to have eternal life.” <verse eid="JHN 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 4:15"/>The woman <char style="add">did not understand that Jesus was speaking figuratively about something that would sustain her spiritually. So she</char> said to him, “Sir, give me that kind of water so that I will not get thirsty again, and so that I will not have to keep returning here to get water!”<verse eid="JHN 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 4:16"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus knew that she did not understand, but he wanted to show her by his God-given knowledge of her personal life that because he was the Messiah he could supply her spiritual need. So</char> he said to her, “Woman, go and call your husband, and bring him here!” <verse eid="JHN 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 4:17"/>She replied, “I do not have a husband!” Jesus said to her, “You said that you do not have a husband, and that is true. <verse eid="JHN 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 4:18"/>It is also true that you have had five husbands <char style="add">one by one</char>. And the man you are living with now is not your husband! What you have said is very true.”<verse eid="JHN 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 4:19"/>The woman said to him, “Sir, I perceive you must be a prophet <char style="add">because you are</char> able <char style="add">to know people’s secrets</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 4:20"/>But <char style="add">let me ask you a different question</char>: Our ancestors worshipped God here on <char style="add">Gerizim Mountain</char>, but you <char style="add">Jews</char> say that Jerusalem is the place where we must worship <char style="add">God. So who is right</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 4:21"/>Jesus said to her, “Woman, believe me <char style="add">when I say that</char> there will be a time when it will not <char style="add">matter whether</char> you worship <char style="add">God our</char> Father on this mountain or in Jerusalem <char style="add">or somewhere else</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 4:22"/>You <char style="add">people from Samaria</char> do not know the one you are worshipping. But we <char style="add">(exc) Jews</char> know whom we worship, because it is from <char style="add">us</char> Jews that <char style="add">God has sent the one who</char> will save people <char style="add">from the guilt of their sins</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 4:23"/>However, there will be a time when those who genuinely worship God will worship him as <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">directs</char> and according to <char style="add">God’s</char> truth. In fact, that time is now. Those are the kind of worshipers my Father seeks. <verse eid="JHN 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 4:24"/>God is a spiritual being. So it is necessary that those who worship him must worship him as his Spirit <char style="add">directs</char> and <char style="add">according to God’s</char> truth.” <verse eid="JHN 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 4:25"/>The woman said to him, “I know that the Messiah is coming. When he comes, he will tell us everything <char style="add">we need to know</char>.” (‘Messiah’ and ‘Christ’ <char style="add">both mean ‘God’s promised king</char>’.) <verse eid="JHN 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 4:26"/>Jesus said to her, “I, the one speaking to you, am <char style="add">the Messiah</char>!”<verse eid="JHN 4:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 4:27"/>Just then <char style="add">we</char> disciples returned <char style="add">from town</char>. <char style="add">Since it was contrary to our custom for Jewish religious teachers to converse with a woman they did not know</char>, we were surprised that he was talking to a woman. However, none of us asked her, “What do you want?” and none of us asked him, “Why are you talking with her?”<verse eid="JHN 4:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 4:28"/>The woman left her water jar there and went into the town. She said to the people there, <verse eid="JHN 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 4:29"/>“Come and see a man who <char style="add">was able to</char> tell me all about my past life [HYP], <char style="add">even though I never met him before</char> Could this man be the Messiah?” <verse eid="JHN 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 4:30"/>So <char style="add">many people</char> left the town and started going to where Jesus was.<verse eid="JHN 4:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told his disciples that what sustained him was doing his Father’s will, which meant convincing non-Jewish people to believe in him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 4:31-38">John 4:31-38</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 4:31"/>Meanwhile, we disciples were urging him, “Teacher, eat <char style="add">some of the food we brought</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 4:32"/>But he said to us, “I have food to eat that you do not know anything about!” <verse eid="JHN 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 4:33"/>So we started saying to each other, “◄Surely no one has brought him any food <char style="add">when we</char> were not <char style="add">here</char>!/Has anyone brought him any food <char style="add">when we</char> were not <char style="add">here</char>?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 4:34"/>Jesus said to us, “Doing what <char style="add">my Father</char> who sent me wants <char style="add">me to do</char> and finishing the work he <char style="add">gave me to do</char> is ◄<char style="add">what sustains me/like</char> my food► [MET]. <verse eid="JHN 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 4:35"/><char style="add">At this time of the year</char> you are saying (OR, your ancestors used to say), ‘There are four months left before we harvest <char style="add">the crops</char>.’ But I say to you, look carefully <char style="add">at the non-Jewish people around here. God says, ‘They are ready to accept my message</char> [MET], <char style="add">like crops in</char> fields that are ready for people to harvest. <verse eid="JHN 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 4:36"/><char style="add">If you help them to accept my message</char>, I will reward you [MET], <char style="add">as an owner of a field</char> pays those who harvest the crops. Because of your work, people will gain eternal life.’ <char style="add">I have been telling people God’s message. That is like</char> [MET] a man who plants seeds. <char style="add">You will help people to accept my message. That will be like</char> [MET] harvesting crops. <char style="add">When that happens</char>, both you and I will rejoice. <verse eid="JHN 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 4:37"/>As a result, this saying will become true: One person plants <char style="add">seeds</char>, but others harvest <char style="add">the crops</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 4:38"/>I am sending you <char style="add">to enable people to accept my message, but you will not be the first ones who tell them God’s message</char>. Others <char style="add">previously</char> worked hard <char style="add">to tell people God’s message</char>, and now you will be harvesting the results of their work.”<verse eid="JHN 4:38"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Many Samaritans believed that Jesus was the Messiah.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 4:39-42">John 4:39-42</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 4:39"/>Many of the Samaria <char style="add">district</char> people who <char style="add">lived</char> in that town believed that Jesus <char style="add">was the Messiah</char> because they heard what that woman said <char style="add">about Jesus</char>, “That man <char style="add">was able to</char> tell me all about my past life [HYP]!” <verse eid="JHN 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 4:40"/>So when those people of Samaria came to Jesus, they urged him to stay with them. So we stayed there two days. <verse eid="JHN 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 4:41"/>Many more of those people believed ◄<char style="add">in Jesus/that he was the Messiah</char>► because of what he said. <verse eid="JHN 4:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 4:42"/>They told the woman, “We believe in Jesus <char style="add">now</char>, but not <char style="add">just </char> because of what you told us. Now we have heard him ourselves. And now we know that this man truly is the one who <char style="add">can </char> save <char style="add">people</char> [MTY] <char style="add">from the guilt of their sins</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 4:42"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After Jesus healed an official’s son, the official and his family believed that Jesus is the Messiah.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 4:43-54">John 4:43-54</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43-44" style="v" sid="JHN 4:43-44"/>Jesus had said <char style="add">previously</char> that people did not honor prophets <char style="add">like himself when they tried to teach people</char> in their own home area. So, two days later, Jesus and <char style="add">we</char> disciples left that area and went to <char style="add">his own area in</char> Galilee <char style="add">district, because he knew that people there would not think very highly of him, and as a result the Jewish leaders would not be jealous</char>. <verse eid="JHN 4:43-44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 4:45"/>However, when we arrived in Galilee <char style="add">district, many</char> of the people there welcomed him, because they had been in Jerusalem during the <char style="add">Passover</char> celebration and had seen all the things he did there. <verse eid="JHN 4:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 4:46"/>Jesus went again to Cana in Galilee <char style="add">district</char>. That was where he <char style="add">previously</char> turned water into wine. There was one of the king’s officials who lived in Capernaum, whose son was very sick. <verse eid="JHN 4:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 4:47"/>When that man heard <char style="add">others say</char> that Jesus had returned to Galilee <char style="add">district</char> from Judea <char style="add">district</char>, he went to Jesus <char style="add">in Cana</char> and pleaded with him, “Please come down <char style="add">to Capernaum</char> and heal my son, who is about to die!” <verse eid="JHN 4:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 4:48"/>Jesus said to him, “You people will believe my message only if you see me perform <char style="add">more</char> miracles!” <verse eid="JHN 4:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 4:49"/>But the official said to him, “Sir, ◄<char style="add">I</char> believe <char style="add">in you/I believe that you came from God</char>►. <char style="add">So please</char> come down <char style="add">to my home</char> before my son dies!” <verse eid="JHN 4:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 4:50"/>Jesus said to him, “Then you may go <char style="add">home</char>. Your son ◄will live/not die►!” The man believed what Jesus said, and left. <verse eid="JHN 4:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 4:51"/><char style="add">The next day</char> while he was on the way home, his servants met him. They told him, “Your child is going to live!” <verse eid="JHN 4:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 4:52"/>He asked them, “At what time did my son start to become well?” They said to him, “His fever ceased yesterday <char style="add">afternoon</char> at one o’clock.” <verse eid="JHN 4:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 4:53"/>Then the boy’s father realized that this was the time Jesus told him, “Your son will ◄live/not die►.” So he and all the people in his house believed <char style="add">that Jesus was the Messiah</char>.<verse eid="JHN 4:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 4:54"/>That was the second miracle that Jesus performed in Galilee <char style="add">district</char>, after he had returned from Judea <char style="add">district</char>.<verse eid="JHN 4:54"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JHN 5"/>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish leaders did not like the fact that Jesus healed a paralyzed man on the Sabbath day.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 5:1-13">John 5:1-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 5:1"/>Some time later, Jesus went up to Jerusalem when the Jews were having <char style="add">another</char> celebration. <verse eid="JHN 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 5:2"/>At one of the gates <char style="add">into the city</char> called the Sheep Gate, there is a pool. In our language we call it Bethzatha. <char style="add">Around the pool</char> were five open areas with roofs over them. <verse eid="JHN 5:2"/><verse number="3-4" style="v" sid="JHN 5:3-4"/>Many people were lying there. They were people who were blind, lame, or paralyzed.<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">5:3-4 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">send down an angel, and the angel would stir the water. Then the first person who got down into the water after the water was stirred would be healed of whatever disease that person had.</char></note> <verse eid="JHN 5:3-4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 5:5"/>One of those who was there had been paralyzed for 38 years. <verse eid="JHN 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 5:6"/>Jesus saw him lying there and found out that the man had been like that for a long time. He said to the man, “Do you want to become well?” <verse eid="JHN 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 5:7"/>The paralyzed man replied to him, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, sir, <char style="add">I want to get well, but</char> there is no one to help me get down into the pool when the water is stirred {stirs}. While I am trying to get <char style="add">to the pool</char>, someone else always gets there before me.” <verse eid="JHN 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 5:8"/>Jesus said to him, “Get up! Then pick up your mat and walk!” <verse eid="JHN 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 5:9"/>The man immediately was healed. He picked up his mat and started walking!</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 5:9">The day on which this happened was a Jewish day of rest. <verse eid="JHN 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 5:10"/>So the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> said to the man who had been healed, “Today is ◄the Sabbath/our rest day►, and <char style="add">in our Jewish</char> laws <char style="add">it is written that people should not work on our</char> ◄<char style="add">Sabbath/rest day</char>►, so you should not be carrying your mat!” <verse eid="JHN 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 5:11"/>The man replied to them, “The man who healed me, he himself said to me, ‘Pick up your mat and walk!’” <verse eid="JHN 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 5:12"/>They asked him, “Who is the man who said to you, ‘Pick it up and walk!’?” <verse eid="JHN 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 5:13"/>But since Jesus had disappeared in the crowd <char style="add">without telling the man his name</char>, the man did not know who it was <char style="add">who had healed him</char>.<verse eid="JHN 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish leaders became very angry with Jesus for saying that he was the man who was also God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 5:14-18">John 5:14-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 5:14"/>Later, Jesus found the man in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>. He <char style="add">told the man his name, and</char> said to him, “Listen! You are healed! So stop sinning! If you do not stop sinning, something will happen to you that will be worse <char style="add">than the illness you had before</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 5:15"/>The man went away and told the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] that it was Jesus who had healed him. <verse eid="JHN 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 5:16"/>So the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] started to harass Jesus, because Jesus was doing these things ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day►. <verse eid="JHN 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 5:17"/>Then Jesus replied to them, “My Father has always been working every day, <char style="add">including</char> ◄<char style="add">the Sabbath/the day of rest</char>►, up until now. I am doing the same thing!” <verse eid="JHN 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 5:18"/>The Jewish leaders [SYN] considered that he was disobeying their rules about ◄the Sabbath/the day of rest►, and that by saying that God was his Father, he was making himself equal with God. And they considered that both these things were grounds for killing him. So they tried even harder to find a way to kill him.<verse eid="JHN 5:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus replied to their objections by stating five reasons why they should believe that he is the ◄Son of/man who was also► God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 5:19-45">John 5:19-45</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 5:19"/>Jesus replied to them by saying, “You need to know this: I can do nothing by my own <char style="add">authority</char>. I do only the <char style="add">kind of</char> things that I see <char style="add">my</char> Father doing. Whatever kinds of things my Father is doing, those are the things I am doing. <verse eid="JHN 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 5:20"/><char style="add">My</char> Father loves me, and he shows me everything that he is doing. He will show me <char style="add">the miracles</char> that <char style="add">he wants me to do</char> that will be greater than the ones that <char style="add">you have already seen me do</char>, so that you may be amazed. <verse eid="JHN 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 5:21"/><char style="add">For example</char>, just like <char style="add">my</char> Father causes people who have died to become alive again, I will give <char style="add">eternal</char> life to everyone that I want to. <verse eid="JHN 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 5:22"/>Furthermore, <char style="add">my</char> Father is not the one who judges people <char style="add">concerning their sins</char>. Instead, he has given to me the work of judging people, <verse eid="JHN 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 5:23"/>in order that all people may honor me, just like they honor <char style="add">my</char> Father. <char style="add">My</char> Father <char style="add">considers that</char> anyone who does not honor me is not honoring <char style="add">him</char>, the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 5:24"/>Listen to this carefully: Those who hear my message and believe that <char style="add">God</char> is the one who sent me have eternal life. <char style="add">God will</char> not ◄condemn them/say that he will punish them►. They are no longer separated from God. Instead, they have <char style="add">eternal</char> life.<verse eid="JHN 5:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 5:25"/>Listen to this carefully: There will be a time when those who are ◄spiritually dead/separated from God► will hear the voice of me, ◄the Son of God/the man who is also God►. In fact, it is that time already. Those who hear <char style="add">and pay attention to my message</char> will have <char style="add">eternal</char> life. <verse eid="JHN 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 5:26"/><char style="add">My</char> Father has <char style="add">power to</char> make things live. Similarly, he has given me the <char style="add">power to enable</char> people to live <char style="add">eternally</char>. <verse eid="JHN 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 5:27"/>Because I am the one who came from heaven, he has given me the authority to judge people <char style="add">concerning their sins</char>. <verse eid="JHN 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 5:28"/>Do not be surprised about that, because there will be a time when all people who have died will hear my voice, <verse eid="JHN 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 5:29"/>and they will become alive again. Those who have lived good <char style="add">lives</char> will rise <char style="add">from their graves</char> and live forever. But those who have lived evil lives will rise, and I will ◄condemn them/declare that I will punish them <char style="add">for their sins</char>►. <verse eid="JHN 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 5:30"/>I do not do anything <char style="add">like that</char> by my own authority. I judge people only according to what I hear <char style="add">my Father tell me</char>. I will judge people fairly, because I do not want to please only myself. Instead, I want to please <char style="add">my Father</char>, who sent me.<verse eid="JHN 5:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 5:31"/>If I were the <char style="add">only</char> one to tell people about myself, <char style="add">people could rightly say that</char> what I say is not true. <verse eid="JHN 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 5:32"/>But there is someone else who tells people about me. And I know that what he tells people about me is true. <verse eid="JHN 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 5:33"/>As for you, when you sent messengers to John <char style="add">the Baptizer to ask about me</char>, he told the truth <char style="add">about me</char>. <verse eid="JHN 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 5:34"/>I do not <char style="add">need that</char> people tell others <char style="add">about me</char>. But instead, I am reminding <char style="add">you about what John told people about me</char>, in order that you will <char style="add">believe it and</char> be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save you}. <verse eid="JHN 5:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 5:35"/><char style="add">John’s message about me</char> (OR, <char style="add">John</char>) [MET] was <char style="add">like</char> a lamp that shines brightly. For a short while you were willing to be made happy <char style="add">by that message</char> {to let <char style="add">that message</char> make you happy}.<verse eid="JHN 5:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 5:36"/>But there is something else that tells you about me. <char style="add">It should prove who I am</char> more than what John <char style="add">said about me</char>. The miracles [PRS] that <char style="add">my</char> Father told me to do, the miracles that I am performing, show (OR, prove) to people that my Father sent me. <verse eid="JHN 5:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 5:37"/>Furthermore, <char style="add">my</char> Father, who sent me, tells people about me. You have never heard his voice or seen him. <verse eid="JHN 5:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 5:38"/>Furthermore, you have not believed in <char style="add">me</char>, the one he sent. So you have not <char style="add">believed</char> his message in your inner beings. <verse eid="JHN 5:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 5:39"/>You carefully study (OR, Study) the Scriptures, because you think that by <char style="add">studying</char> them you will <char style="add">find the way to</char> have eternal life. And those Scriptures tell people about me! <verse eid="JHN 5:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 5:40"/>But you refuse ◄to come to me/to believe my message► in order that you may have <char style="add">eternal</char> life.<verse eid="JHN 5:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 5:41"/>It does not <char style="add">matter to</char> me whether people praise me. <verse eid="JHN 5:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 5:42"/>But you <char style="add">want people to praise you</char>. I know that within yourselves you do not love God. <verse eid="JHN 5:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 5:43"/>Although I have come to earth with my Father’s authority [MTY], you do not accept me. But if someone else comes with his own authority [MTY], you accept him! <verse eid="JHN 5:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 5:44"/>You accept your praising each other, but you do not try to do things that will result in God himself praising you. So ◄there is no way you can believe <char style="add">in me</char>!/how can you believe <char style="add">my message</char>?► [RHQ]<verse eid="JHN 5:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 5:45"/>But do not think that I am the one who will accuse you while <char style="add">my</char> Father is listening! No, it is Moses who will accuse you! You thought that he would <char style="add">defend you</char>. <verse eid="JHN 5:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 5:46"/>Moses wrote about me, so if you had believed what he <char style="add">wrote</char>, you would have believed what I <char style="add">said</char> <verse eid="JHN 5:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 5:47"/>But because you did not believe what he wrote <char style="add">about me</char>, ◄you will certainly not believe what I say!/how will you believe what I say?► [RHQ]”<verse eid="JHN 5:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JHN 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus miraculously fed more than 5,000 people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 6:1-15">John 6:1-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 6:1"/>Some time later, when Jesus was in Galilee district, near the time of the Jewish Passover celebration, Jesus went <char style="add">with us disciples by boat</char> and crossed to another place along Galilee Lake. This lake is <char style="add">also called</char> Tiberias Lake. <verse eid="JHN 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 6:2"/>A large crowd of people kept following Jesus <char style="add">on land</char> because they had been seeing the miracles he performed <char style="add">by healing</char> sick people. <verse eid="JHN 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 6:3"/>Jesus went up on the hillside and sat down with <char style="add">us</char> disciples <char style="add">to teach us</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 6:4"/>Then he looked up and saw a great crowd of people coming toward him. <verse eid="JHN 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 6:5"/>He said to Philip, “Where will we buy food for all these people to eat?” <verse eid="JHN 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 6:6"/>He asked this only to find out if Philip believed what <char style="add">Jesus could do</char>, because Jesus already knew what he himself was going to do. <verse eid="JHN 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 6:7"/>Philip replied to him, “<char style="add">Even if we had</char> the amount of money a man earns in eight months, that would not be enough to buy bread so that each person could have a little bit!” <verse eid="JHN 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 6:8"/>Another one of <char style="add">us</char> disciples, Andrew, who was Simon Peter’s <char style="add">younger</char> brother, said to Jesus, <verse eid="JHN 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 6:9"/>“There is a boy here who has five small barley loaves and two <char style="add">cooked</char> fish. But ◄they will not help much among so many people!/what good will that do among so many people?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 6:10"/>Jesus said, “Tell the people to sit down!” There was plenty of grass there, so they all sat down <char style="add">comfortably</char>. There were about 5,000 men <char style="add">among the crowd</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 6:11"/>Then Jesus took the small loaves and the fish and thanked <char style="add">God</char> for them. Then he <char style="add">gave them to us, and we</char> distributed the small loaves and the fish to all the people sitting on the ground. <char style="add">Because God caused the food to keep increasing</char>, everyone ate as much as they wanted. <verse eid="JHN 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 6:12"/>When everyone had all the food they wanted, he said to <char style="add">us</char> disciples, “Gather up the pieces that are left over. Do not let anything be wasted!” <verse eid="JHN 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 6:13"/>So we gathered up the pieces of the small loaves that were left over by those who had eaten. We filled twelve baskets with those pieces!<verse eid="JHN 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 6:14"/>After the people saw that miracle that Jesus had performed, <char style="add">many of</char> them started to say, “Surely this is the prophet <char style="add">like Moses</char> that <char style="add">God promised</char> to send to the world!” <verse eid="JHN 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 6:15"/>So, because Jesus realized that they were about to come and seize him to make him <char style="add">their</char> king, he left them again and went up into the hills by himself.<verse eid="JHN 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus miraculously walked on the water.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 6:16-24">John 6:16-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 6:16"/>When it was evening, <char style="add">we</char> disciples went down to <char style="add">Galilee</char> Lake. <verse eid="JHN 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 6:17"/>When it became dark and Jesus had still not joined us, <char style="add">we</char> got into a boat and went across the lake towards Capernaum <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 6:18"/>A strong wind started to blow and caused the water ◄to become very rough/to have high waves►. <verse eid="JHN 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 6:19"/>After we had rowed ◄three or four miles/five or six kilometers►, we saw Jesus coming near the boat; he was walking on the water! So we were terrified! <verse eid="JHN 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 6:20"/>But he said to us, “Do not be afraid! It is I!” <verse eid="JHN 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 6:21"/>We were glad to take him into the boat. As soon as <char style="add">we</char> did that, the boat reached the shore where <char style="add">we</char> were going!<verse eid="JHN 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 6:22"/>The next day the crowd of people that had stayed on the other side of the lake <char style="add">were perplexed about how Jesus had left that area</char>. They knew that there had been only one boat there <char style="add">the previous day</char>. They knew that we had gone away in it by ourselves. They knew that Jesus had not gone with us. <verse eid="JHN 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 6:23"/>Then some <char style="add">men came</char> from Tiberias <char style="add">city</char> in boats. <char style="add">They were hoping to take some of the crowd back to Tiberias</char>. They arrived near the place where the people had eaten the food after Jesus had given thanks <char style="add">and caused it to multiply</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 6:24"/>When the crowd realized that neither Jesus nor we disciples were there, <char style="add">some of</char> them got into those boats and they sailed to Capernaum to find Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 6:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught them figuratively of the need for them to take for themselves the benefits of his sacrificing himself and shedding his blood to atone for their sins.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 6:25-59">John 6:25-59</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 6:25"/>When they found him <char style="add">in Capernaum</char> further around the lake, they asked him, “Teacher, <char style="add">since you(sg) did not come in a boat</char>, when <char style="add">and how</char> did you get here?” <verse eid="JHN 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 6:26"/>Jesus replied to them, “Listen to this carefully: Do you know why you are looking for me? It is not because you saw <char style="add">me perform</char> miracles <char style="add">and as a result have realized who I really am</char>. No! You are looking for me <char style="add">only</char> because you had plenty of bread to eat <char style="add">after I provided it for you by performing a miracle</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 6:27"/>Stop desiring food that will soon spoil! Instead, desire to get <char style="add">spiritual</char> food that will last forever! Yearn for eternal life! That is what I, the one who came from heaven, will give you. God <char style="add">my</char> Father has shown that he approves of me <char style="add">enabling me to do that</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 6:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 6:28"/>Then the people asked him, “What things should we do <char style="add">to please</char> God?” <verse eid="JHN 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 6:29"/>Jesus replied, “What God <char style="add">wants you</char> to do is this: He wants you to believe that <char style="add">I am</char> the one he has sent.” <verse eid="JHN 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 6:30"/>So they said to him, “Then perform <char style="add">another</char> miracle so that we may see it and believe that <char style="add">you came from God</char>. What miracle would you like to perform? <verse eid="JHN 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 6:31"/>Our ancestors ate the <char style="add">food called</char> manna <char style="add">that God provided for them by a miracle</char> in the desolate area. This is written {<char style="add">The Psalmist</char> wrote this} <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char> about <char style="add">what Moses caused to happen:</char> ‘He gave them food from heaven to eat.’ <char style="add">Will you perform a miracle like that</char>?”<verse eid="JHN 6:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 6:32"/>So Jesus said to them, “The truth is that it was not Moses who gave your <char style="add">ancestors</char> that food from heaven. No, it was my Father <char style="add">who gave it to them. And my Father is the one</char> who gives you the true food from heaven. <verse eid="JHN 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 6:33"/>The true bread from God came down from heaven, and he is the one who will give <char style="add">eternal</char> life to <char style="add">the people of</char> the world [MTY].”<verse eid="JHN 6:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 6:34"/>
    <char style="add">Not understanding what he meant</char>, they said to him, “Sir, give us that kind of bread all the time!” <verse eid="JHN 6:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 6:35"/>Jesus said to them, “<char style="add">Just like</char> food [MET] <char style="add">sustains physical life</char>, I am the <char style="add">one who enables you to have spiritual</char> life. Those who <char style="add">eat ordinary food and drinks will later be hungry and thirsty</char>. But those who come to me <char style="add">to receive that life</char> will never again <char style="add">lack anything spiritually</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 6:36"/>I told you before that you have seen my <char style="add">miracles, but after seeing them, instead of understanding who I am</char>, you have not believed in me. <verse eid="JHN 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 6:37"/>All the people that <char style="add">my</char> Father entrusts to me will come to me, and I will certainly ◄welcome/never send away► [LIT] anyone who comes to me. <verse eid="JHN 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 6:38"/>When I came down from heaven, it was not to do what I want. Instead, I came to do what ◄<char style="add">God/my Father</char>►, who sent me, wants. <verse eid="JHN 6:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 6:39"/>What the one who sent me wants is that I ◄keep forever all/never lose any► [LIT] of those whom he has entrusted to me. He wants me to cause all of them to become alive again ◄on the last day/on the day <char style="add">when I judge everyone</char>► [MTY]. <verse eid="JHN 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 6:40"/><char style="add">Long ago in the desolate area when those who were bitten by snakes looked at the bronze replica of a snake, they were healed</char> [MET]. What my Father wants is that <char style="add">similarly</char> everyone who looks at <char style="add">what</char> I <char style="add">have done</char> and believes in me will have eternal life. I will cause them to become alive again ◄on the last day/on the day <char style="add">when I judge everyone</char>► [MTY].”<verse eid="JHN 6:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 6:41"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] began to grumble about him because he said, “I am the one who is <char style="add">like</char> true bread who came down from heaven.” <verse eid="JHN 6:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 6:42"/>They said, “◄This man is Jesus, the son of Joseph!/Isn’t this man the son of Joseph?► [RHQ] We know <char style="add">the names of</char> both his father and his mother. <char style="add">He certainly did not come from heaven</char>, so ◄he is <char style="add">lying</char> by saying ‘I came from heaven.’/why is he now saying, ‘I came from heaven?’► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 6:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 6:43"/>Jesus replied to them, “Stop grumbling among yourselves <char style="add">about what I just said</char>! <verse eid="JHN 6:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 6:44"/><char style="add">My</char> Father, who sent me, makes people want to come to me. No others will come to me <char style="add">to receive eternal life</char>. Those who come to me are the only ones who will believe in me. I will ◄cause them to be alive again/raise them <char style="add">from the dead</char>► ◄on the last day/on the <char style="add">judgment</char> day►. <verse eid="JHN 6:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 6:45"/>It was written ◄<char style="add">by one of the prophets/by the prophet Isaiah</char>► {◄<char style="add">One of the prophets/The prophet Isaiah</char>► wrote} <char style="add">about all those who will trust in me</char>, ‘God will teach them all.’ Everyone who listens to what <char style="add">my</char> Father <char style="add">says</char> and learns from him will ◄come to/believe in► me. <verse eid="JHN 6:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 6:46"/>I came from God. I am the only one who has seen <char style="add">my</char> Father. No one else has seen him. <verse eid="JHN 6:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 6:47"/>Listen to this carefully: Everyone who believes ◄<char style="add">my message/in me</char>► has eternal life. <verse eid="JHN 6:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 6:48"/><char style="add">Just like</char> food [MET] <char style="add">sustains your physical life</char>, I am the <char style="add">one who enables you to have spiritual</char> life. <verse eid="JHN 6:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 6:49"/>Even though your ancestors ate the manna <char style="add">while they were traveling</char> in the desolate area, they died <char style="add">anyway</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 6:50"/>But the bread <char style="add">I am talking about</char> is something that came down from heaven. If people eat that bread, their <char style="add">spirits</char> will never die. <verse eid="JHN 6:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 6:51"/>I am the one who came down from heaven to enable people to have <char style="add">spiritual</char> life. If people take what I will give them, they will live forever. What I will give them is my flesh, which I will give to <char style="add">all the people in</char> [MTY] the world in order that they may have <char style="add">spiritual</char> life.”<verse eid="JHN 6:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 6:52"/>Then the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] began to argue among themselves. They said, “◄There is no way this man can give us his flesh to eat!/How can this man give us his flesh to eat?►” [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 6:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 6:53"/>So, <char style="add">speaking figuratively of the need for them to accept for themselves the benefits of his sacrificing himself and shedding his blood to atone for their sins</char> [MET], Jesus said to them, “Listen carefully to this: <char style="add">Although</char> I am the one who came from heaven, if you do not eat my flesh and drink my blood, you will not have eternal life. <verse eid="JHN 6:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 6:54"/>Those who eat my flesh and drink my blood have eternal life, and I will cause them to become alive again at ◄the last day/the <char style="add">judgment</char> day►, <verse eid="JHN 6:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 6:55"/>because my flesh and my blood are truly spiritual food. <verse eid="JHN 6:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 6:56"/>Those who eat my flesh and drink my blood will have a close relationship with me, and I will have a close relationship with them. <verse eid="JHN 6:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 6:57"/><char style="add">My</char> Father, who is the <char style="add">source of everything that</char> lives, sent me, and I live because <char style="add">my</char> Father has <char style="add">given me life</char>. Similarly those who eat my <char style="add">flesh</char> will live <char style="add">eternally</char> because of what I <char style="add">do for them</char>. <verse eid="JHN 6:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="JHN 6:58"/><char style="add">I am</char> the true bread that came down from heaven. Although our ancestors ate <char style="add">manna</char>, they <char style="add">later</char> died <char style="add">anyway</char>. But those who eat this bread will live forever.” <verse eid="JHN 6:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JHN 6:59"/>He said this while he was teaching people in ◄the synagogue/the Jewish meeting place► in Capernaum.<verse eid="JHN 6:59"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Some of Jesus’ disciples left him because of this teaching.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 6:60-71">John 6:60-71</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="JHN 6:60"/>After they heard him say that, many of his disciples said, “What he is teaching is hard <char style="add">to understand</char>; ◄it is very difficult for anyone to accept it!/how can anyone accept it?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 6:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="JHN 6:61"/>Jesus was aware that his disciples were grumbling about it, so he said to them, “◄I am sorry that this is offending you./Is this offending you?► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 6:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="JHN 6:62"/>◄<char style="add">Perhaps you will believe my message</char> if you see me, the one who came from heaven, ascending <char style="add">there</char> to where I was before!/<char style="add">(What will you think if you see me</char>, the one who came from heaven, ascending <char style="add">there</char> to where I was before)?► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 6:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="JHN 6:63"/><char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit is the one who gives people <char style="add">eternal</char> life. Human efforts are no help at all <char style="add">for giving people eternal life</char>. The message I have spoken to you <char style="add">gives spiritual</char> life (OR, <char style="add">comes from</char> God’s Spirit <char style="add">and gives eternal</char> life.) <verse eid="JHN 6:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="JHN 6:64"/>But there are some of you who do not believe <char style="add">my message.” Jesus said that</char> because he knew from the time he started [MTY] <char style="add">his ministry</char> which of them would not believe his message. He also knew who would ◄betray him/enable his enemies to seize him►.<verse eid="JHN 6:64"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="65" style="v" sid="JHN 6:65"/>Then he continued by saying, “That is why I told you that only those whom my Father has enabled <char style="add">to believe in me</char> will come to me <char style="add">and receive eternal life</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 6:65"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" sid="JHN 6:66"/>From that <char style="add">time</char>, many of his disciples left him and no longer went with him. <verse eid="JHN 6:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="JHN 6:67"/>So he said to <char style="add">us</char> twelve <char style="add">apostles</char>, “You do not want to leave me also, do you?” <verse eid="JHN 6:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="JHN 6:68"/>Simon Peter replied to him, “Lord, <char style="add">we</char> will not <char style="add">leave you</char>, <char style="add">because</char> ◄there is no other person <char style="add">like you</char> to whom we can go!/what other person is there like <char style="add">you</char> to whom we can go?► [RHQ] You have the message about eternal life! <verse eid="JHN 6:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="JHN 6:69"/>We have come to believe for certain that you are the holy one <char style="add">who has come</char> from God!” <verse eid="JHN 6:69"/><verse number="70" style="v" sid="JHN 6:70"/>Then Jesus replied to us, “<char style="add">You are saying that as though all</char> you twelve <char style="add">men</char> whom I have chosen [RHQ] believe that. But one of you is <char style="add">under the control of</char> Satan!” <verse eid="JHN 6:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="JHN 6:71"/>He was talking about Judas, the <char style="add">son</char> of Simon, from Kerioth <char style="add">village</char>. <char style="add">Even though</char> Judas was one of us twelve <char style="add">apostles</char>, he was about ◄to betray Jesus/to enable Jesus’ enemies to seize him►.<verse eid="JHN 6:71"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JHN 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus rejected his younger brothers’ suggestion that he go immediately to Jerusalem.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 7:1-9">John 7:1-9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 7:1"/>After those things happened, Jesus went around in Galilee <char style="add">province</char>. He did not want to travel in Judea <char style="add">province</char>, because he knew that the Jewish <char style="add">leaders there</char> were wanting to kill him. <verse eid="JHN 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 7:2"/>But when the time of the Jewish celebration <char style="add">called</char> ‘Celebration of <char style="add">Living in</char> Shelters’ was near, <verse eid="JHN 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 7:3"/>Jesus’ <char style="add">younger</char> brothers said to him, “<char style="add">Since many people</char> here <char style="add">have left you</char>, you should leave and go to Judea <char style="add">province and perform</char> some miracles there, so that your disciples may see them! <verse eid="JHN 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 7:4"/>No one who wants to become famous does things secretly. <char style="add">You say</char> you are doing these miracles, <char style="add">so do some miracles there</char> so that everyone [MTY] can see them!” <verse eid="JHN 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 7:5"/><char style="add">They said this critically</char>, because even <char style="add">though they were</char> his own <char style="add">younger</char> brothers, they did not believe he <char style="add">was from God</char>. <verse eid="JHN 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 7:6"/>So Jesus said to them, “It is not yet time for me [MTY] <char style="add">to go to the celebration</char>. For you, any time is right <char style="add">to go to the celebration</char>. <verse eid="JHN 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 7:7"/><char style="add">The people</char> [MTY] <char style="add">who</char> ◄<char style="add">do not believe in me/do not belong to God</char>► cannot hate you, but they hate me because I tell them that what they are doing is evil. <verse eid="JHN 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 7:8"/>You <char style="add">(pl)</char> go ahead to the celebration. I am not going up <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> to the celebration <char style="add">yet</char>, because now is not the right time for me <char style="add">to go</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 7:9"/>After he said that, Jesus stayed <char style="add">a little longer</char> in Galilee.<verse eid="JHN 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus went to the celebration.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 7:10-13">John 7:10-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 7:10"/>However, <char style="add">a few days</char> after his younger brothers left to go up to the celebration, he went also. He went, along with <char style="add">us</char> disciples, but no others went with us. <verse eid="JHN 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 7:11"/>At the celebration, the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> were looking for him. They were asking people, “Has Jesus come?” <verse eid="JHN 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 7:12"/>Among the crowds, many people were whispering about Jesus. Some were saying, “He is a good man!” But others were saying instead, “No! He is deceiving the crowds!” <verse eid="JHN 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 7:13"/>But no one was speaking so that others could hear them, because they were afraid of the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN].<verse eid="JHN 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After Jesus taught people, the Jewish leaders wanted to arrest him, but many others believed he was the Messiah.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 7:14-36">John 7:14-36</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 7:14"/>In the middle of the days of the celebration, Jesus went to the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char> and began to teach people. <verse eid="JHN 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 7:15"/>The Jewish <char style="add">elders</char> were amazed <char style="add">at what he was saying</char>. They said, “This man never studied <char style="add">in one of our religious schools</char>! So ◄how can he have learned <char style="add">so much about Scripture</char>?/it is difficult for us to believe that he has learned <char style="add">so much about Scripture</char>!► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 7:16"/>Jesus replied to them, “What I teach does not come from myself. It comes from <char style="add">God</char>, the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 7:17"/>Those who choose to do what God wants will find out whether what I teach comes from God or whether I am speaking with <char style="add">only</char> my own <char style="add">authority</char>. <verse eid="JHN 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 7:18"/>Those who speak with <char style="add">only</char> their own <char style="add">authority</char> do that <char style="add">only</char> so that others will honor them. But I am <char style="add">doing things so that others</char> will honor the one who sent me, and I am someone who speaks the truth. I never lie. <verse eid="JHN 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 7:19"/><char style="add">Think about</char> the laws that Moses gave you [RHQ]. None of you <char style="add">completely</char> obeys those laws. So why are you trying to kill me, <char style="add">saying I do not obey the laws concerning</char> ◄<char style="add">the Sabbath/the Jewish day of rest</char>►?”<verse eid="JHN 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 7:20"/>Someone in the crowd answered, “<char style="add">By saying this you show that</char> you are crazy (OR, A demon is controlling you)! Certainly no one is trying to kill you!” <verse eid="JHN 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 7:21"/>Jesus replied to them, “Because I did a miracle <char style="add">of healing someone</char> ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day►, you are all shocked. <verse eid="JHN 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 7:22"/>Moses gave you <char style="add">a law that you must</char> circumcise <char style="add">the male children and that you must do that exactly seven days after they are born. Actually</char>, it was your ancestors, <char style="add">Abraham and Isaac and Jacob</char>, not Moses, who <char style="add">started that ritual</char>. But because of that law, you sometimes circumcise them ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day►, <char style="add">but that is working, too</char> <verse eid="JHN 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 7:23"/>You <char style="add">sometimes</char> circumcise boys ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day► so that the law of Moses is not disobeyed {<char style="add">you</char> do not disobey the law of Moses}, so ◄it is ridiculous that you are angry with me, saying <char style="add">I worked</char> ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day► by healing a man!/why are you angry with me, saying <char style="add">I worked</char> ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day► by healing a man?► [RHQ] <char style="add">Healing someone is far more helpful than circumcising a baby boy</char>! <verse eid="JHN 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 7:24"/>Stop deciding whether my healing this man is wrong according to what you see! Instead, decide according to what is really the right action <char style="add">to help people</char>”!<verse eid="JHN 7:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 7:25"/>Some of the people from Jerusalem were saying, “◄This is the man that they are trying to kill!/Isn’t this the man that they are trying to kill?► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 7:26"/>He is saying these things ◄publicly/in front of many people►, but our <char style="add">Jewish</char> rulers are not saying anything to <char style="add">oppose</char> him. Is that because they have decided that he is truly ◄the Messiah/God’s chosen king►? <verse eid="JHN 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 7:27"/>But <char style="add">he cannot be the Messiah, because</char> we know where this man came from. When the Messiah really comes, no one will know where he comes from.”<verse eid="JHN 7:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 7:28"/>
    <char style="add">They said that because they thought Jesus was born in Nazareth</char>. So while Jesus was teaching <char style="add">people</char> in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>, he shouted, “Yes, <char style="add">you say that</char> you know me, and <char style="add">you think</char> you know [IRO] where I am from. But I have come here not ◄because I appointed myself/with my own authority►. Instead, <char style="add">God</char> is the one who truly sent me. You do not know him. <verse eid="JHN 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 7:29"/>But I know him, because I have come from him. He is the one who sent me!”<verse eid="JHN 7:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 7:30"/>Then they tried to seize him <char style="add">because he said that he had come from God</char>. But no one put their hands on him <char style="add">to do that</char>, because it was not yet the time [MTY] <char style="add">for him to die</char>. <verse eid="JHN 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 7:31"/>But many of the crowd believed that he <char style="add">had come from God</char>. They said, “When the Messiah comes, he certainly will not do more miracles than this man has done, will he?” <verse eid="JHN 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 7:32"/>The Pharisees heard them whispering these things about him. So they and the chief priests sent some Temple guards to seize him.<verse eid="JHN 7:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 7:33"/>Then Jesus said, “I will be with you for only a short time. Then I will return to the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 7:34"/>Then you will search for me, but you will not find me. And you will not be able to come to the place where I am.” <verse eid="JHN 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 7:35"/>So the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] said to themselves, “Where is this man about to go with the result that we will not be able to find him? <char style="add">Some Jewish people have</char> dispersed <char style="add">and live</char> among Greek people. He is not intending to go <char style="add">and live among them</char> and teach them, is he? <verse eid="JHN 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 7:36"/>When he said ‘You will search for me, but you will not be able to find me,’ and when he said ‘You will not be able to come to the place where I am,’ what <char style="add">did he mean</char>?”<verse eid="JHN 7:36"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Many people were divided after Jesus said that the Spirit would produce eternal life within those who come to him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 7:37-53">John 7:37-53</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 7:37"/>
    <char style="add">On each of the seven days of the celebration, the high priest poured out some water on the altar in the Temple to remember how God provided water for the people in the desolate area long ago. But the water he poured did not help anyone who was thirsty. So</char> on the last day of the festival, which was the most important day, Jesus stood up <char style="add">in the Temple courtyard</char> and said with a loud voice, “Those who are thirsty should come to me to drink <char style="add">what I will give them</char>. <verse eid="JHN 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 7:38"/>Just like the Scriptures teach, streams of water shall flow out from within those who believe in me, and that water will cause them to live <char style="add">eternally</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 7:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 7:39"/>When Jesus said that, he was referring to <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit, whom those who believed in Jesus would receive later. Up to that time God had not sent the Spirit <char style="add">to live within believers</char>, because Jesus had not yet <char style="add">died and returned to his</char> glorious <char style="add">home in</char> heaven, <char style="add">from where he would send the Spirit</char>.<verse eid="JHN 7:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 7:40"/>When some of the crowd heard those words, they said, “Surely this man is the prophet <char style="add">whom God promised to send who would be like Moses</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 7:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 7:41"/>Others said, “He is the Messiah!” But others, <char style="add">thinking Jesus was born in Galilee</char>, said, “The Messiah will not come from Galilee <char style="add">province</char>, will he? <verse eid="JHN 7:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 7:42"/>◄Did <char style="add">a prophet</char> not write in the Scriptures that the Messiah will come from <char style="add">King</char> David’s family, and be born in Bethlehem, where <char style="add">King</char> David lived?/<char style="add">It is written</char> in the Scriptures that the Messiah will come from <char style="add">King</char> David’s family, and be born in Bethlehem, where <char style="add">King</char> David lived!► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 7:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 7:43"/>So the people were divided because of <char style="add">what they thought about</char> Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 7:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 7:44"/>Some people wanted to seize him, but no one tried <char style="add">to do that</char>.<verse eid="JHN 7:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 7:45"/>So the Temple guards returned to the chief priests and the Pharisees, <char style="add">the ones who had sent them to arrest Jesus</char>. They said to the guards, “Why did you not <char style="add">seize him and</char> bring him <char style="add">here</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 7:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 7:46"/>They replied, “No one ever spoke such <char style="add">amazing things</char> as this man does!” <verse eid="JHN 7:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 7:47"/>Then the Pharisees replied, “Have you been deceived {Has <char style="add">he</char> deceived you}, too? <verse eid="JHN 7:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 7:48"/>◄None of our rulers nor any of us Pharisees have believed that &lt;he <char style="add">is the Messiah</char>!/he <char style="add">came from God</char>!&gt;/Have any of our <char style="add">Jewish</char> rulers or any of us Pharisees believed that &lt;he <char style="add">is the Messiah</char>?/he <char style="add">came from God</char>?&gt;► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 7:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 7:49"/>Not one! But, on the contrary, some of this crowd <char style="add">have believed in him</char>. They do not know <char style="add">the true teachings of</char> our laws! They will go to hell <char style="add">for listening to him</char>!”<verse eid="JHN 7:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 7:50"/>Then Nicodemus spoke. He was the one who earlier went to Jesus <char style="add">at night</char>. He was also a member of the Jewish council. He said to <char style="add">the rest of the Council members</char>, <verse eid="JHN 7:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 7:51"/>“<char style="add">We</char> have not listened to what he says to find out what he is doing. ◄It is not permitted in our <char style="add">Jewish</char> law [PRS] for us to say, before questioning someone, that we must punish him!/Is it permitted in our <char style="add">Jewish</char> law [PRS] for us to say, before questioning someone, that we must punish him?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 7:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 7:52"/>They replied to him, “◄Are you another <char style="add">disgusting person</char> from Galilee?/<char style="add">You talk like</char> another <char style="add">disgusting person</char> from Galilee!► [RHQ] Read <char style="add">what is written in the Scriptures</char> You will find that no prophet comes from Galilee <char style="add">province, like he does</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 7:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 7:53"/>[Then they all left and went to their own homes.<verse eid="JHN 7:53"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JHN 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus evaded a trap about condemning a woman who had been caught committing adultery.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 8:1-11">John 8:1-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 8:1"/>But Jesus went <char style="add">with us disciples</char> to Olive <char style="add">Tree</char> Hill <char style="add">and we stayed near there that night</char>. <verse eid="JHN 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 8:2"/>Early the next morning, we returned to the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>. Many people gathered around Jesus, so he sat down to teach them. <verse eid="JHN 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 8:3"/>Then men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws and some of [SYN] the Pharisee <char style="add">religious group</char> brought a woman to him. She was seized {<char style="add">They</char> had <char style="add">arranged to</char> seize her} while she was having sex with a man who was not her husband. They made her stand up in front of the group <char style="add">that was listening to Jesus</char>. <verse eid="JHN 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 8:4"/>Then they said to Jesus, “Teacher, this woman was seized {<char style="add">we</char> seized this woman} while she was having sex with a man who is not her husband. <verse eid="JHN 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 8:5"/>Moses commanded us in the laws that <char style="add">he gave us</char> that we should throw stones at such women <char style="add">and kill them</char>. So what do you say <char style="add">we should do</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 8:6"/>They asked this question as a trap so that they could accuse him. <char style="add">If he said that they should not kill her, they would shame him for disobeying the law of Moses. If he said that they should kill her, they could accuse him to the Roman governor</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:6">But Jesus bent down and wrote something on the ground with his finger. <verse eid="JHN 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 8:7"/>While they continued to question him, he stood up and said to them, “Whichever one of you has never sinned can be the first one to start throwing stones at her.” <verse eid="JHN 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 8:8"/>Then he stooped down and wrote <char style="add">some more</char> on the ground. <verse eid="JHN 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 8:9"/>After they heard what he said, those <char style="add">who were questioning him</char> went away, one by one, the older ones first <char style="add">and then the younger ones, knowing they were all sinners</char>. Finally only Jesus was there, along with the woman. <verse eid="JHN 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 8:10"/>Jesus stood up and asked her, “Woman, where are they? Has no one said you must die for your sin?” <verse eid="JHN 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 8:11"/>She said, “No, sir, no one.” Then Jesus said, “I do not condemn you either. Go <char style="add">home</char> now, and do not continue your sinful <char style="add">life</char> any longer!”]<verse eid="JHN 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus replied to the Pharisees’ objection to his claim to be like a light for the people of the world.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 8:12-20">John 8:12-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 8:12"/>Jesus spoke to the people again. He said, “I am <char style="add">like</char> a light [MET] for <char style="add">all the people in</char> [MTY] the world. <char style="add">Just like a light reveals what has been in the darkness</char> [MET], <char style="add">I reveal God’s truth to them</char>. Those who walk in the darkness <char style="add">are unaware of what is around them</char>. But those who become my disciples will always be aware <char style="add">of God’s truth</char> [MET]. They will have my light <char style="add">which shows them how to have eternal</char> life.” <verse eid="JHN 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 8:13"/>So the Pharisees said to him, “You are just telling about yourself! <char style="add">Since there is no one else to verify these things that you say about yourself</char>, <char style="add">we</char> do not <char style="add">need to accept that</char> what you say is true.” <verse eid="JHN 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 8:14"/>Jesus replied, “Even if I were the <char style="add">only one to</char> say these things about myself, what I say is true, because I know that I came from <char style="add">heaven</char>, and I know that I am going <char style="add">back to heaven</char>. But <char style="bd">you</char> do not know where I came from or where I am going. <verse eid="JHN 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 8:15"/><char style="bd">You</char> judge people according to human standards. <char style="add">The reason</char> that <char style="bd">I</char> am <char style="add">here is</char> not ◄to condemn people/to say that I will punish people► <char style="add">for their sins</char>. <verse eid="JHN 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 8:16"/>But if I did judge <char style="add">people</char>, what I decided would be correct, because I am not the <char style="add">only</char> one <char style="add">who will decide those things</char>. I and the one who sent me will both decide. <verse eid="JHN 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 8:17"/>It is written {<char style="add">Moses</char> wrote} in your law that if <char style="add">at least</char> two people testify that <char style="add">some event has happened</char>, <char style="add">people should consider</char> that what they say is true. <verse eid="JHN 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 8:18"/>I am telling you about myself, and the other one who is telling you about me is <char style="add">my</char> Father who sent me. <char style="add">So you should believe that what we declare is true</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 8:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 8:19"/>Then they asked him, “<char style="add">If you have a</char> father whom <char style="add">we can question about you</char>, where is he?” Jesus replied, “You do not know <char style="add">who</char> I <char style="add">really am</char>. If you knew who I <char style="add">really am</char>, you would know who my Father is also.” <verse eid="JHN 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 8:20"/>He said these things when he was in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>, near the place where the people put their offerings. <char style="add">This was also very close to the place where the Jewish council met</char>. But no one seized him to arrest him, because it was not yet time [MTY] <char style="add">for him to suffer and die</char>.<verse eid="JHN 8:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus replied to the Pharisees’ continued rejection of Jesus’ claims about himself.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 8:21-30">John 8:21-30</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 8:21"/>Jesus also said to them, “I <char style="add">will soon be</char> going away. Then <char style="add">at the end of your life</char> you will seek me, but you will die <char style="add">without God forgiving</char> your sins. Where I will go, you will not be able to come.” <verse eid="JHN 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 8:22"/>So the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> said among themselves, “Is he going to kill himself? Is that the reason that he said, ‘Where I go, you will not be able to come’?” <verse eid="JHN 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 8:23"/>But Jesus continued by saying to them, “You were born here in this world, but I came from heaven. You belong to those who are opposed to God [MTY]. I do not belong to them. <verse eid="JHN 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 8:24"/>I told you that you will die <char style="add">without God forgiving</char> your sins. If you do not believe that I am <char style="add">who I say that I am</char>, you will die <char style="add">without God forgiving</char> your sins.”<verse eid="JHN 8:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 8:25"/>So they said to him, “You! Who do you think you are?” Jesus said to them, “Ever since I began <char style="add">teaching</char>, I have been telling you who I am! <verse eid="JHN 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 8:26"/>I could judge you and say that <char style="add">you are guilty of</char> many things. But instead, <char style="add">I will say only</char> what the one who sent me tells me to say. <char style="add">What he says</char> is true, and I tell the people in the world [MTY] what I have heard from him.”<verse eid="JHN 8:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 8:27"/>They did not understand that he was talking about his Father <char style="add">in heaven</char>. <verse eid="JHN 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 8:28"/>So Jesus said, “I am the one who came down from heaven, but when you lift me up <char style="add">on a cross to kill me</char>, you will know who I am. You will also know that I do not do anything with my own <char style="add">authority</char>. Instead, I say just what <char style="add">my</char> Father has taught me. <verse eid="JHN 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 8:29"/>He is the one who sent me, and he helps me. Because I always do the things that please him, he has never abandoned me.” <verse eid="JHN 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 8:30"/>As Jesus was saying these things, many people believed that he <char style="add">was</char> ◄<char style="add">from God/the Messiah</char>►.<verse eid="JHN 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told his critics which people were true believers like Abraham and which ones really were serving Satan.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 8:31-59">John 8:31-59</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 8:31"/>Then Jesus said to the Jews who now said they believed in him, “If you continue to <char style="add">live in accordance with</char> my message, you will truly be my disciples. <verse eid="JHN 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 8:32"/>Then you will know <char style="add">God’s</char> truth, and as a result of <char style="add">your believing his</char> truth, he [PRS] will free you <char style="add">from being controlled by the one who has made you his slaves</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 8:33"/>They replied to him, “We are descendants of Abraham. We have never been anyone’s slaves. So why do you say <char style="add">we will</char> be freed <char style="add">from being someone’s slaves</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 8:34"/>Jesus replied, “Listen carefully to what I am going to tell you. All those who continue to sin are <char style="add">forced to obey</char> their sinful desires [MET], <char style="add">just like</char> a slave <char style="add">is forced to obey his master</char>. <verse eid="JHN 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 8:35"/>A slave is not a permanent member of a family. But a son is a member of a family forever. <char style="add">Similarly, you say you are members of God’s family because you are descendants of Abraham, but really, because you are like slaves of your sinful desires, you are no longer permanent members of God’s family</char>. <verse eid="JHN 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 8:36"/>So if you allow me to free you, you will truly be free. <verse eid="JHN 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 8:37"/>I know that you are Abraham’s descendants. But you are trying to kill me because <char style="add">you are not</char> allowing [PRS] my message to continue <char style="add">to change</char> your inner being. <verse eid="JHN 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 8:38"/>I am telling you what I saw when I was with <char style="add">my</char> Father. But you do the things that you have heard from your father.”<verse eid="JHN 8:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 8:39"/>They replied to him, “Abraham is our ancestor.” Jesus said to them, “If you were Abraham’s descendants, <char style="add">your character would be like Abraham’s character, and</char> you would do <char style="add">good</char> things like Abraham did. <verse eid="JHN 8:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 8:40"/>I have been telling you the truth that I heard from God, but you are trying to kill me. Abraham did not do things like that. <verse eid="JHN 8:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 8:41"/>No! You are doing the things that your <char style="add">real</char> father does.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 8:41">They said to him, “<char style="add">We do not know about you, but</char> we are not illegitimate children. And <char style="add">spiritually</char>, we have only one Father. That is God, and you do not know who your father is!” <verse eid="JHN 8:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 8:42"/>Jesus said to them, “If God were your father, you would love me, because I came from God, and now I have come here <char style="add">to this world</char>. My coming was not ◄because I <char style="add">appointed</char> myself/with my own <char style="add">authority</char>►. He sent me. <verse eid="JHN 8:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 8:43"/>◄And I will tell you why you do not understand what I say./Do you know why you do not understand what I say?► [RHQ] It is because you do not want to accept my message. <verse eid="JHN 8:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 8:44"/>You belong to your father, ◄the devil/Satan►, and you desire to do what he wants. He has <char style="add">caused people to become</char> murderers from the time when <char style="add">people</char> first <char style="add">sinned</char>. He has abandoned <char style="add">God’s</char> truth because he is a liar by his nature. Whenever he lies, he is speaking according to his <char style="add">nature</char>, because he is a liar and is the one who originates [MET] all lies. <verse eid="JHN 8:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 8:45"/>But because I tell you the truth, you do not believe me! <verse eid="JHN 8:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 8:46"/><char style="add">Since I have never sinned</char>, ◄none of you can show that I have sinned./can anyone among you show that I have sinned?► [RHQ] So, since I tell you the truth, ◄there is no good reason for your not believing me!/why is it that you do not believe me?► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 8:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 8:47"/>Those who belong to God habitually obey God’s message. You do not belong to God, so you do not obey his message.”<verse eid="JHN 8:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 8:48"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] replied to him, “◄We are certainly right by saying that you <char style="add">believe what is false as</char> the Samaritans <char style="add">do</char>!/Are we not right by saying that you <char style="add">believe what is false as</char> the Samaritans <char style="add">do</char>?► [RHQ] And that ◄a demon/an evil spirit► <char style="add">controls</char> you!” <verse eid="JHN 8:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 8:49"/>Jesus replied, “A demon does not <char style="add">control</char> me! I honor my Father, and you do not honor me! <verse eid="JHN 8:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 8:50"/>I am not trying to honor myself. There is someone else who desires <char style="add">to honor me</char>, and he is the one who will judge <char style="add">whether it is I who am telling the truth or whether it is you who are telling the truth</char>. <verse eid="JHN 8:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 8:51"/>But the truth is that anyone who obeys what I say will never die!”<verse eid="JHN 8:51"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 8:52"/>Then the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN], <char style="add">thinking that he was talking about ordinary death and not about spiritual death</char>, said to him, “Now we are sure that a demon <char style="add">controls</char> you! Abraham and the prophets died <char style="add">long ago</char>! But you say that anyone who obeys what you teach will never die! <verse eid="JHN 8:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 8:53"/>◄You are certainly not greater than our ancestor Abraham!/Do you think you are greater than our ancestor Abraham?► [RHQ] He died, and all the prophets died, so who do you think you are <char style="add">by saying something like that</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 8:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 8:54"/>Jesus replied, “If I were honoring myself, that would be worthless. My Father is the one who you say is your God. He is the one who honors me. <verse eid="JHN 8:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 8:55"/>Although you do not know him, I know him <char style="add">and have a close relationship with him</char>. If I said that I did not know him, I would be a liar like you are. But I know him, and I obey what he says. <verse eid="JHN 8:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JHN 8:56"/>Your ancestor Abraham was happy when he thought about what I would <char style="add">do during</char> my life [MTY]. <char style="add">It was as though</char> he saw that, and was happy.”<verse eid="JHN 8:56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="JHN 8:57"/>Then the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] said to him, “You are not 50 years old yet! So ◄you certainly did not see him!/how could you have seen him?► [RHQ] <char style="add">Because he died long ago</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 8:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="JHN 8:58"/>Jesus said to them, “The truth is that I existed before Abraham was born!” <verse eid="JHN 8:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JHN 8:59"/>So, <char style="add">because they were very angry about Jesus thus saying that he</char> ◄<char style="add">had eternally existed/was equal with God</char>►, they picked up stones to throw at him <char style="add">to kill him</char>. But <char style="add">Jesus</char> caused them not to be able to see him, and he left the Temple courtyard.<verse eid="JHN 8:59"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JHN 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus healed a man who was born blind.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 9:1-12">John 9:1-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 9:1"/>As Jesus walked along <char style="add">with us</char>, he saw a man who had been blind from the time he was born. <verse eid="JHN 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 9:2"/>We disciples asked him, “Teacher, was this man blind from when he was born because his parents sinned or because he himself sinned?” <verse eid="JHN 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 9:3"/>Jesus replied, “His being blind was not because he or his parents sinned. Instead, <char style="add">he has been blind</char> in order that <char style="add">people can</char> see the power of God {the power of God can be seen} as a result of <char style="add">what will now happen</char> to him. <verse eid="JHN 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 9:4"/>While there is still time, I must do the work that the one who sent me <char style="add">wants me to do. Just like daytime is followed by</char> nighttime when people do not work, <char style="add">at the end of our lives</char> [MET] <char style="add">it is too late for us to do what God wants</char>. <verse eid="JHN 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 9:5"/>While I am still <char style="add">living</char> in this world, I am the <char style="add">one who enables people to know about God, like</char> [MET] <char style="add">a</char> light enables the people in [MTY] this world <char style="add">to see what is in the darkness</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 9:6"/>After he said that, he spat on the ground. He made <char style="add">a little bit of</char> mud with the saliva, and put it on the man’s eyes. <verse eid="JHN 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 9:7"/>Then he said to him, “Go and wash in Siloam pool!” (That name means ‘sent;’ <char style="add">just like they sent the water by a channel into the pool, God sent Jesus</char>). So the man went and washed <char style="add">in the pool</char>, and when he went home he was able to see! <verse eid="JHN 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 9:8"/>His neighbors and others who previously had seen him when he was begging said, “He is the man who used to sit here and beg, isn’t he?” <verse eid="JHN 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 9:9"/>Some said, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, he is.” Others said, “No, <char style="add">he is not</char>. It is <char style="add">just</char> a man who looks like him!” But the man himself said, “Yes, I am that man!” <verse eid="JHN 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 9:10"/>So they said to him, “How is it that now you can see?” <verse eid="JHN 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 9:11"/>He replied, “The man whose name is Jesus made some mud and put it on my eyes. Then he told me to go to Siloam <char style="add">pool</char> and wash. So I went there and washed, and then I could see.” <verse eid="JHN 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 9:12"/>They said to him, “Where is that man <char style="add">now</char>?” He said, “I do not know.”<verse eid="JHN 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Pharisees investigated the healing of the blind man.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 9:13-41">John 9:13-41</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 9:13"/>They took to the Pharisees the man who was previously blind. <verse eid="JHN 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 9:14"/>The day on which Jesus made the mud and enabled the man to see again was a ◄Sabbath/Jewish day of rest►. <char style="add">The Pharisees considered that healing someone was work, and their rules did not permit people to do any work</char> ◄<char style="add">on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day</char>►. <verse eid="JHN 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 9:15"/>So the Pharisees also asked that man, “How did you become able to see?” He said to them, “The man put mud on my eyes. Then I washed, and now I can see!” <verse eid="JHN 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 9:16"/>So some of the Pharisees said, “Since this man <char style="add">Jesus</char> disobeys <char style="add">our rules about working</char> ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day►, he is not from God.” But others said, “If he was a sinner, ◄he could certainly not do such miracles!/how could he do such miracles?► [RHQ]” So they were divided. <verse eid="JHN 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 9:17"/>So one of them said to the blind man again, “You are the man whom he enabled to see. What do you yourself say about him?” The man said, “<char style="add">I think</char> he is a prophet!” <char style="add">So they told him to go</char>.<verse eid="JHN 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 9:18"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] still did not believe that the man was blind when he was born, and that he was <char style="add">now</char> able to see. So they sent someone to bring the man’s parents. <verse eid="JHN 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 9:19"/><char style="add">When they got there</char>, one of <char style="add">the Jewish leaders</char> asked them, “Is that man your son? Do you say that he was blind when he was born? <char style="add">If that is true</char>, how is he now able to see?” <verse eid="JHN 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 9:20"/>His parents replied, “We know that he is our son. We know that he was blind when he was born. <verse eid="JHN 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 9:21"/>But we do not know how he is able to see now. We also do not know who enabled him to see. Ask our son! He is old enough <char style="add">to answer questions from authorities like you</char> He can tell you himself!” <verse eid="JHN 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 9:22"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] had previously declared that they would prevent anyone who declared that Jesus was the Messiah from <char style="add">entering</char> their synagogues. His parents <char style="add">knew that, so</char> they were afraid of the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN]. <verse eid="JHN 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 9:23"/>That is the reason that they said, “He is old enough <char style="add">to answer questions</char>, so ask him!”<verse eid="JHN 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 9:24"/>So they sent someone to bring back to them the man who had been blind. <char style="add">When he got there</char>, the <char style="add">Jewish leaders</char> said to him, “Knowing that God <char style="add">is listening</char> [IDM], tell the truth! We know that the man who healed you is a sinner.” <verse eid="JHN 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 9:25"/>He replied, “I do not know if he is a sinner or not. But one thing I do know is that I was blind, but now I can see!” <verse eid="JHN 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 9:26"/>So they said to him, “What did he do to you? How did he enable you to see?” <verse eid="JHN 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 9:27"/>He replied, “I told you that already, but you did not [RHQ] pay attention! Why do you want to hear me tell you again? ◄Do you also want to become his disciples?/You talk as though [IRO] you also want to become his disciples [RHQ]►.” <verse eid="JHN 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 9:28"/>Then they insulted him angrily. They said, “You are that man’s disciple, but we are Moses’ disciples! <verse eid="JHN 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 9:29"/>We know that God spoke to Moses; but this man, we do not know where he is from or where he <char style="add">gets any authority</char> from!” <verse eid="JHN 9:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 9:30"/>The man replied, “That is very surprising! You <char style="add">say that</char> you do not know where he <char style="add">gets any authority</char>. But he enabled me to see! <verse eid="JHN 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 9:31"/>We know that God does not help sinners <char style="add">who ask God to help them</char>. Instead, he listens to <char style="add">and helps</char> godly people who pray. He listens to people who do what God wants. <verse eid="JHN 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 9:32"/>No one has ever enabled a man to see who was blind when he was born <char style="add">like I was</char>. That has never happened since the world began! <verse eid="JHN 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 9:33"/>So if this man had not come from God, he would not be able to do anything <char style="add">like that</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 9:34"/>They replied to him, “You ◄were born <char style="add">as a result of your parents’</char> sin [EUP]/bastard►! ◄Do you think you are qualified to teach us?/You are not qualified to teach us!► [RHQ]” Then they threw him out <char style="add">of the synagogue</char>.<verse eid="JHN 9:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 9:35"/>Jesus heard <char style="add">people say</char> that they had thrown that man out. He found the man and said to him, “Do you believe that the one who came down from heaven <char style="add">is the Messiah</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 9:36"/>The man answered, “Sir, who is he? <char style="add">Tell me</char>, in order that I may believe in him.” <verse eid="JHN 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 9:37"/>Jesus said to him, “You have seen him. <char style="add">In fact, it is I</char>, the one who am speaking to you.” <verse eid="JHN 9:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 9:38"/>The man said, “Lord, I believe that <char style="add">you are the Messiah</char>!” Then he <char style="add">knelt down before</char> Jesus and worshipped him.<verse eid="JHN 9:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 9:39"/>Jesus said, “I have come into this world to judge <char style="add">the people in the world</char>. The result will be that <char style="add">those who realize that they do not know God’s truth will perceive it. That is like</char> [MET] <char style="add">enabling</char> those who are blind to see. But the result will also be that people who <char style="add">falsely think</char> [IRO] that <char style="add">they understand God’s truth will never understand it. That is like</char> [MET] <char style="add">people</char> who are blind remaining blind permanently.” <verse eid="JHN 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 9:40"/>Some of the Pharisees who were with him heard him say that, and said to him, “You are not suggesting that we are <char style="add">like</char> blind people, are you?” <verse eid="JHN 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 9:41"/>Jesus said to them, “If you <char style="add">realized that you did not yet know God’s truth, but you wanted to, then you would be like</char> blind people <char style="add">who wanted to see. God would be able to</char> forgive your sins. But you are now <char style="add">falsely</char> claiming that you <char style="add">know God’s truth, so you are like people who are blind who claim that they</char> can see. <char style="add">Because of that, God is not able to</char> forgive your sins.”<verse eid="JHN 9:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JHN 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus explained why he is like a good shepherd.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 10:1-21">John 10:1-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 10:1"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus continued by saying to us</char>, “Listen carefully to what I say. Anyone who does not enter <char style="add">the sheep pen</char> through the gate, if he climbs in some other way, he is a thief or a bandit. <verse eid="JHN 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 10:2"/>The man who enters <char style="add">the pen</char> through the gate is the shepherd of the sheep. <verse eid="JHN 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 10:3"/>The man who watches the gate at <char style="add">night</char> opens the gate for him. The sheep recognize the shepherd’s voice. He summons his own sheep by <char style="add">calling out</char> the names <char style="add">he has given</char> them. Then he leads them outside <char style="add">the pen</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 10:4"/>After he has brought out all his own <char style="add">sheep</char>, he goes in front of them. His sheep follow him because they recognize <char style="add">and pay attention to</char> his voice. <verse eid="JHN 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 10:5"/>But they will never follow a stranger. Instead, they will run away from him, because they do not recognize a stranger’s voice.”<verse eid="JHN 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 10:6"/>Jesus said that [MET] <char style="add">to illustrate the difference between himself and the Pharisees, who were deceiving the people</char>. But they did not understand what he was telling them. <verse eid="JHN 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 10:7"/>So Jesus spoke to them again. He said, “Listen carefully to what I am saying. I am <char style="add">like</char> [MET] a gate for the sheep <char style="add">to enter the sheepfold, because I am the one who allows people to enter God’s presence</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 10:8"/>All of <char style="add">your religious leaders</char> who have come previously <char style="add">without my authority</char> are <char style="add">like</char> [MET] thieves and bandits <char style="add">because they act violently and dishonestly for their own benefit</char>. But <char style="add">just like</char> sheep do not <char style="add">obey strangers, God’s people do not</char> pay attention to them. <verse eid="JHN 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 10:9"/>I am <char style="add">like</char> a gate. Those will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save all those} who come <char style="add">to God</char> by <char style="add">trusting in</char> me. <char style="add">Just like sheep</char> go in and out <char style="add">through the gate safely</char> to find pasture [MET], <char style="add">I will provide for them and protect them</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 10:10"/>Thieves come <char style="add">to a sheep pen</char> only to steal or kill or destroy <char style="add">sheep</char> [MET]. <char style="add">Similarly, your religious leaders injure God’s people spiritually</char>. But I have come in order that people may have <char style="add">eternal/spiritual</char> life, and that they may have abundantly <char style="add">all they need to sustain them spiritually</char>.<verse eid="JHN 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 10:11"/>I am <char style="add">like</char> a good shepherd. A good shepherd <char style="add">is willing to</char> die to save the sheep [MET]. <char style="add">Similarly, I am ready to sacrifice myself to save those who belong to me</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 10:12"/>A worker whom someone has hired <char style="add">to look after the sheep</char> is not <char style="add">like</char> the shepherd or the one who owns the sheep. So when he sees a wolf coming, he leaves the sheep and runs away. Then the wolf attacks the flock of sheep and <char style="add">seizes one sheep and</char> causes <char style="add">the others</char> to scatter. <verse eid="JHN 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 10:13"/>The worker runs away because he is <char style="add">only</char> a man whom someone has hired. He is not <char style="add">really</char> concerned about <char style="add">what happens to</char> the sheep [MET]. <char style="add">Similarly, your religious teachers do not really care what happens to you</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 10:14"/>I am <char style="add">like</char> a good shepherd. <char style="add">Just like a good shepherd knows his</char> sheep [MET], I know those who belong to me, and they know me <verse eid="JHN 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 10:15"/>in the same way as <char style="add">my</char> Father knows me and I know <char style="add">my</char> Father. Furthermore, I am <char style="add">ready to</char> sacrifice myself for <char style="add">those who belong to me</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 10:16"/>And I have other people <char style="add">who are not Jews</char> who <char style="add">will some day</char> belong to me. They will be <char style="add">like</char> [MET] sheep from another sheep pen. I must bring them <char style="add">to God/myself</char> also. They will pay attention to what I say, and eventually <char style="add">all those who belong to me</char> will be <char style="add">like</char> one flock, and <char style="add">I</char> will be <char style="add">like</char> [MET] their one shepherd. <verse eid="JHN 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 10:17"/>The reason <char style="add">my</char> Father loves me is that I will sacrifice my life. But <char style="add">after I do that</char>, I will become alive again. <verse eid="JHN 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 10:18"/>No one is causing me to die. Instead, I <char style="add">have chosen to</char> sacrifice myself. I have authority to sacrifice myself and I have authority to become alive again. That is what my Father has commanded me to do.”<verse eid="JHN 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 10:19"/>After hearing these words <char style="add">that Jesus said</char>, the Jews were divided again. <verse eid="JHN 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 10:20"/>Many of them said, “A demon is <char style="add">controlling</char> him and has caused him to become crazy. ◄It is useless to listen to him!/Why should we listen to him?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 10:21"/>But others said, “What he is saying is not something a man whom a demon is controlling would say. ◄No demon could enable a blind man to see <char style="add">like he did!/</char> How could a demon enable a blind man to see <char style="add">like he did</char>?► [RHQ]”<verse eid="JHN 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish leaders tried to kill or arrest Jesus for claiming that he was equal with God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 10:22-42">John 10:22-42</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 10:22"/>Then it was time for the celebration <char style="add">to remember when our ancestors</char> rededicated <char style="add">the Temple in Jerusalem</char>. It was in winter. <verse eid="JHN 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 10:23"/>Jesus was in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>, walking in <char style="add">the place that people called King</char> Solomon’s porch. <verse eid="JHN 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 10:24"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] gathered around him and said, “How long will you keep us from knowing for sure <char style="add">if you are the Messiah</char>? If you are the Messiah, tell us clearly!” <verse eid="JHN 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 10:25"/>Jesus answered them, “I have told you <char style="add">that I am the Messiah</char>, but you do not believe me! You should know who I am because of the miracles I do with my Father’s authority [MTY]. <verse eid="JHN 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 10:26"/>But instead, you do not believe in me because you do not belong to <char style="add">me. You are like</char> [MET] sheep <char style="add">who belong to a different shepherd</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 10:27"/><char style="add">Just like sheep</char> heed the voice <char style="add">of their true shepherd</char> [MET], my <char style="add">people pay attention to what I say</char>. I know them, and they have become my disciples. <verse eid="JHN 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 10:28"/>I will give them eternal life. No one will separate them from me, not ever. No one shall ever pull them away from belonging to me. <verse eid="JHN 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 10:29"/><char style="add">Those</char> that my Father has given to me are more precious than anything else (OR, My Father, who has given them to me, is greater than anything that opposes them). So no one can pull them away from belonging to him [MTY]. <verse eid="JHN 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 10:30"/><char style="add">My</char> father and I are equal.”<verse eid="JHN 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 10:31"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] again picked up stones to throw at Jesus <char style="add">and kill him because they were angry at his saying that he was equal with God</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 10:32"/>But Jesus said to them, “You have seen me perform many miracles that my Father <char style="add">told me to do. You should realize from seeing them that I am equal with God</char>. So, because of which of these miracles [IRO] are you wanting to <char style="add">kill me by</char> throwing stones at me?” <verse eid="JHN 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 10:33"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] replied, “We are <char style="add">wanting to</char> throw stones at you not because you performed a great miracle. Instead, <char style="add">we are wanting to do it</char> because you are dishonoring God. You are just a man, but you are saying that you are God!” <verse eid="JHN 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 10:34"/>Jesus replied to them, “In the Scriptures it is written {◄<char style="add">someone/the Psalmist</char>► has written} [RHQ] <char style="add">what God said to the rulers whom he had appointed</char>, ‘I have said that you are <char style="add">like</char> gods.’ <verse eid="JHN 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 10:35"/>God said that <char style="add">to those leaders when he appointed them. No one objected to that</char>. And nothing that is in Scripture can be set aside {no one can set aside anything that is in Scripture}. <verse eid="JHN 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 10:36"/>But I am the one <char style="add">my</char> Father set apart to completely belong to him. He sent me here into this world. So ◄why are you angry with me for saying that <char style="add">I am equal with God when I say</char> that I am the man who is also God?/you should not be angry with me for saying that <char style="add">I am equal with God when I say</char> that I am the person who is both God and man!► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 10:37"/>If I were not doing the miracles that my Father <char style="add">told me to do, I would not expect</char> you to believe in me. <verse eid="JHN 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 10:38"/>But because I perform these miracles, believe <char style="add">what</char> these miracles <char style="add">show about me</char>, even though you do not believe what I <char style="add">say</char>. If you do that, then you will know and understand that <char style="add">my</char> Father has a close relationship with me, and I have a close relationship with <char style="add">my</char> Father.”<verse eid="JHN 10:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 10:39"/>After they heard that, they tried to seize him again, but he got away from them.<verse eid="JHN 10:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 10:40"/>Then Jesus went, along <char style="add">with us</char>, back across <char style="add">to the east side of</char> the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. We went to the place where John was previously baptizing <char style="add">people</char>. He/We stayed there <char style="add">for a few weeks</char>. <verse eid="JHN 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 10:41"/>Many people came to Jesus. They were saying, “John never performed a miracle, <char style="add">but this man has performed many miracles</char>! Everything that John said about this man is true!” <verse eid="JHN 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 10:42"/>Many people <char style="add">who came</char> there believed ◄<char style="add">that Jesus was the Messiah/that Jesus truly had come from God</char>►.<verse eid="JHN 10:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JHN 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus’ friend, Lazarus, died.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 11:1-16">John 11:1-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 11:1"/>
    <char style="add">One time</char> there was a man whose name was Lazarus who was <char style="add">very</char> sick. He lived in Bethany <char style="add">village</char>, where his <char style="add">older</char> sisters Mary and Martha also lived. <verse eid="JHN 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 11:2"/>Mary was the woman who <char style="add">later</char> poured perfume on the feet of the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char>, and then wiped his feet with her hair. <verse eid="JHN 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 11:3"/>So the two sisters sent <char style="add">someone to tell</char> Jesus <char style="add">about Lazarus</char>, saying, “Lord, the one you love <char style="add">very much</char> is very sick.” <verse eid="JHN 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 11:4"/><char style="add">They hoped that Jesus would come</char>, but when Jesus heard the message, he said, “His being sick will not end in his dying. Instead, it will result in <char style="add">people realizing</char> how great God is, and that I, God’s son, may be honored {that people may honor me, God’s son}, because of <char style="add">what I will do</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 11:5"/>Jesus loved Martha and her <char style="add">younger</char> sister <char style="add">Mary</char> and Lazarus. <verse eid="JHN 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 11:6"/>But when Jesus heard that Lazarus was sick, he stayed <char style="add">where he was</char> for two more days.<verse eid="JHN 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 11:7"/>But Jesus <char style="add">wanted to see Lazarus</char>. So he said to us disciples, “Let’s go back to Judea.” <verse eid="JHN 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 11:8"/>We said, “Teacher, just a short while ago the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] wanted to <char style="add">kill you by</char> throwing stones at you. So ◄<char style="add">we think that you should not</char> go back there again!/<char style="add">are you sure that you want to</char> go back there again?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 11:9"/><char style="add">To show us that nothing bad could happen to him until the time that God had chosen</char> [MET], Jesus replied, “There are [RHQ] twelve hours in the daytime, <char style="add">which is enough time to do what God wants us to do</char>. People who walk in the daytime will not stumble <char style="add">over things they cannot see</char>, because they see things by the light from the sun. <verse eid="JHN 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 11:10"/>It is when people walk in the nighttime that they stumble over things, because they have no light.”<verse eid="JHN 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 11:11"/>After he said that, he told us, “Our friend Lazarus has gone to sleep. But I will go there so that I can wake him up.” <verse eid="JHN 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 11:12"/>So we said to him, “Lord, if he is sleeping, he will get well. <char style="add">So you do not need to risk your life by going there</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 11:13"/>Jesus was speaking <char style="add">figuratively</char> about Lazarus’ death, but we thought that he was talking about really being asleep. <verse eid="JHN 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 11:14"/>So then he told us plainly, “Lazarus is dead. <verse eid="JHN 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 11:15"/>But for your sake I am glad that I was not there <char style="add">when he died</char>, because I want you to believe <char style="add">more firmly that I</char> ◄<char style="add">am the Messiah/came from God</char>►. So now, <char style="add">instead of staying here</char>, let’s go to him.” <verse eid="JHN 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 11:16"/>Then Thomas, who was {whom they} called ‘The Twin’, said to the rest of us disciples, “Let’s all go, so that we may die with Jesus <char style="add">when his enemies kill him</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Lazarus’ sisters expressed disappointment that Jesus did not come and heal Lazarus before he died.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 11:17-40">John 11:17-40</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 11:17"/>When we arrived <char style="add">close to Bethany</char>, someone told Jesus that Lazarus <char style="add">had died and had been buried and his body had</char> been in the tomb for four days. <verse eid="JHN 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 11:18"/>Bethany is less than ◄two miles/three kilometers► from Jerusalem. <verse eid="JHN 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 11:19"/>Many Jews had come <char style="add">from Jerusalem</char> to console Martha and Mary over <char style="add">the death of</char> their <char style="add">younger</char> brother. <verse eid="JHN 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 11:20"/>When Martha heard <char style="add">someone say</char> that Jesus was coming, she went <char style="add">along the road</char> to meet him. But Mary stayed in the house. <verse eid="JHN 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 11:21"/>When Martha <char style="add">got to where Jesus was</char>, she said to him, “Lord, if you had been here, my brother would not have died <char style="add">because you would have healed him</char>! <verse eid="JHN 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 11:22"/>But I know that even now God will do for you whatever you ask <char style="add">concerning my brother</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 11:23"/>Jesus said to her, “Your brother will become alive again!” <verse eid="JHN 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 11:24"/>Martha said to him, “I know that he will become alive again when all people become alive again on the <char style="add">Judgment</char> day.” <verse eid="JHN 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 11:25"/>Jesus said to her, “I am the one who <char style="add">enables people to</char> become alive again and who <char style="add">causes people to</char> live <char style="add">eternally</char>. Those who believe in me, even if they die, will live <char style="add">again</char>. <verse eid="JHN 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 11:26"/>Furthermore, all those who believe in me while they are alive, <char style="add">their souls</char> will not die <char style="add">forever</char>. Do you believe that?” <verse eid="JHN 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 11:27"/>She said to him, “Yes, Lord! I believe that you are the Messiah, ◄the Son of God/the man who is also God►. You are the one <char style="add">God promised to send</char> into the world!”<verse eid="JHN 11:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 11:28"/>After she said that, she returned <char style="add">to the house</char> and took her <char style="add">younger</char> sister, Mary, aside and said to her, “The Teacher is close <char style="add">to our village</char>, and he wants to talk to you.” <verse eid="JHN 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 11:29"/>When Mary heard that, she got up quickly and went to him. <verse eid="JHN 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 11:30"/>Jesus had not yet entered the village; he was still at the place where Martha met him. <verse eid="JHN 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 11:31"/>The Jews who were in the house with Mary, consoling her, saw Mary get up quickly and go outside. So they followed her, thinking that she was going to the tomb <char style="add">where they had buried Lazarus</char>, in order to cry there.<verse eid="JHN 11:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 11:32"/>When Mary got to where Jesus was and saw him, she prostrated herself at his feet and said, “Lord, if you had been here, my <char style="add">younger</char> brother would not have died!” <verse eid="JHN 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 11:33"/>When Jesus saw her crying, and saw that the Jews who had come with her were also crying, he was very angry <char style="add">that Satan had caused Lazarus to die</char> (OR, very troubled) and disturbed in his spirit. <verse eid="JHN 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 11:34"/>He said, “Where have you buried ◄him/his body►?” They said to him, “Lord, come and see.” <verse eid="JHN 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 11:35"/>Jesus began to cry. <verse eid="JHN 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 11:36"/>Then <char style="add">some of</char> the Jews said, “Look how much he loved Lazarus!” <verse eid="JHN 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 11:37"/>But some others said, “He enabled a blind man to see. So ◄he should have been able to <char style="add">heal this man so that</char> he did not die!/why did he not <char style="add">heal this man so that</char> he did not die?► [RHQ]”<verse eid="JHN 11:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 11:38"/>Within himself Jesus was again very angry <char style="add">about Lazarus dying</char> (OR, very troubled). He came to the tomb. It was a cave. The entrance had been covered with a large stone. <verse eid="JHN 11:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 11:39"/>Jesus said, “Take away the stone!” Martha, <char style="add">who, as I mentioned before, was an older</char> sister of the man who had died, said, “Lord, his <char style="add">body</char> has been <char style="add">in the tomb</char> for four days, so now there will be a bad smell!” <verse eid="JHN 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 11:40"/>Jesus said to her, “I told [RHQ] you that if you believed <char style="add">in</char> ◄<char style="add">me/what I can do</char>►, you would see how great God is! Have <char style="add">you forgotten that</char>?”<verse eid="JHN 11:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus caused Lazarus to be alive again.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 11:41-48">John 11:41-48</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 11:41"/>So they took away the stone. Then Jesus looked up <char style="add">toward heaven</char> and said, “My Father, I thank you that you heard me <char style="add">when I prayed about this earlier</char>. <verse eid="JHN 11:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 11:42"/>I know that you always hear me <char style="add">when I pray</char>. But instead <char style="add">of just praying silently</char>, I said that for the sake of the people who are standing here. I want them to believe that you sent me.” <verse eid="JHN 11:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 11:43"/>After he said that, he shouted, “Lazarus, come out!” <verse eid="JHN 11:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 11:44"/>The man who <char style="add">had been</char> dead came out! The strips of cloth were still wrapped around his <char style="add">hands and feet</char>, and a cloth was still around his face, <char style="add">but he came out</char>! Jesus said to them, “Take off the cloths so that he can walk easily!” <char style="add">So they did that</char>.<verse eid="JHN 11:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 11:45"/>As a result, many of the Jews who had come to <char style="add">see</char> Mary and who had seen what Jesus did, believed that he ◄<char style="add">was the Messiah/had come from God</char>►. <verse eid="JHN 11:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 11:46"/>But some of the <char style="add">others</char> went to the Pharisees and told them what Jesus had done. <verse eid="JHN 11:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 11:47"/>So the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered all the members of the <char style="add">Jewish</char> Council together. They started saying <char style="add">to each other</char>, “What are we going to do <char style="add">about Jesus</char>? He is performing many miracles! <verse eid="JHN 11:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 11:48"/>If we allow him to keep <char style="add">doing this</char>, everyone will believe ◄in him/that he <char style="add">is the Messiah</char>►, <char style="add">and they will make him their king</char>. Then the Roman <char style="add">army</char> will come and destroy our Temple and our whole nation of Israel!”<verse eid="JHN 11:48"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish leaders decided to kill Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 11:49-57">John 11:49-57</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 11:49"/>One of the <char style="add">Jewish Council</char> members was Caiaphas. He was the Jewish high priest that year. <char style="add">Hinting that they should get rid of Jesus</char>, he said to them, “You <char style="add">talk as though you</char> do not know anything [HYP]! <verse eid="JHN 11:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 11:50"/>You do not realize that it would be much better for us if one man died for the sake of the people rather than that <char style="add">the Romans kill</char> all the <char style="add">people of our Jewish</char> nation.” <verse eid="JHN 11:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JHN 11:51"/>He said that, not because he thought of it himself. Instead, since he was the high priest that year, he was prophesying that Jesus would die for the whole <char style="add">Jewish</char> nation. <verse eid="JHN 11:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="JHN 11:52"/>But he was also prophesying that Jesus would die, not just for the Jews, but for all the people living in other lands who <char style="add">would belong</char> to God, in order that he would unite <char style="add">all of them into</char> one <char style="add">group</char>. <verse eid="JHN 11:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JHN 11:53"/>So from that day the <char style="add">Jewish leaders</char> started to make plans how they could kill Jesus.<verse eid="JHN 11:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="JHN 11:54"/>Because of that, Jesus no longer traveled around publicly among the Jewish people. Instead, he left <char style="add">Jerusalem, along</char> with us disciples, and went to a village called Ephraim, in an area near the desolate region. We stayed there <char style="add">for a while</char>.<verse eid="JHN 11:54"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="JHN 11:55"/>When it was almost time for the Jewish Passover <char style="add">celebration</char>, many <char style="add">Jews</char> went up to Jerusalem from other places in the country. They went there to perform the rituals to make themselves acceptable <char style="add">to God</char> before the Passover <char style="add">celebration started</char>. <verse eid="JHN 11:55"/><verse number="56-57" style="v" sid="JHN 11:56-57"/>The Jewish chief priests and Pharisees issued an order that if anyone found out where Jesus was, that person should report it to them, in order that they could seize him. <char style="add">So the people thought that Jesus would</char> probably <char style="add">not dare to come to the celebration</char>. But they kept looking for him, and as they were standing in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char> they were saying to each other, “What do you think? He will not come to the celebration, will he?”<verse eid="JHN 11:56-57"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JHN 12"/>
  <para style="s1">A woman anointed Jesus with perfume</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 12:1"/>Six days before the Passover <char style="add">celebration started</char>, Jesus arrived in Bethany <char style="add">village, along with us</char>. That was where Lazarus lived. He was the man Jesus <char style="add">previously</char> caused to be alive again after he died. <verse eid="JHN 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 12:2"/>There they gave a dinner to <char style="add">honor</char> Jesus. Martha served the meal. <char style="add">Her younger brother</char>, Lazarus, was among the people who were eating with Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 12:3"/>Then Mary took <char style="add">a bottle</char> of expensive perfume <char style="add">called</char> nard and poured it on Jesus’ feet <char style="add">to honor him</char>. Then she wiped his feet with her hair. The whole house was filled with the <char style="add">beautiful</char> smell of the perfume.<verse eid="JHN 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 12:4"/>But one of his disciples, Judas Iscariot, (OR, Judas, the man from Kerioth <char style="add">Town</char>) objected. He was the one who later enabled Jesus’ enemies to seize him. <verse eid="JHN 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 12:5"/>He said, “◄We should have sold this perfume and given <char style="add">the money</char> to poor people!/Why did <char style="add">we</char> not sell this perfume and give <char style="add">the money for it</char> to the poor people?► [RHQ] We could have gotten 300 days’ wages for it!” <verse eid="JHN 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 12:6"/>He said that, not because he cared about the poor people, but instead, because he was a thief. He was the one who kept the bag <char style="add">of funds that people gave to help Jesus and us his disciples</char>, and he often stole some of the money that was {that <char style="add">people</char>} put into it. <verse eid="JHN 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 12:7"/>Then Jesus said, “Do not bother her! <char style="add">She bought this perfume</char> in order to save it until the day when they will bury me <char style="add">after I die</char>. <verse eid="JHN 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 12:8"/>There will always be poor people among you, <char style="add">so you can help them whenever you want to</char>. But I will not be with you much longer, <char style="add">so it is good that she showed right now how much she appreciates me</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish leaders decided to kill Lazarus, too.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 12:9-11">John 12:9-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 12:9"/>A large crowd of Jews heard <char style="add">people say</char> that Jesus was there <char style="add">in Bethany</char>. So they came, not only <char style="add">to see</char> Jesus but also to see Lazarus, the man whom he had caused to become alive again after he died. <verse eid="JHN 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 12:10"/>So the chief priests decided to kill Lazarus also, <verse eid="JHN 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 12:11"/>because many of the Jews were <char style="add">deserting them and</char> going to Jesus and believing in him because of <char style="add">Jesus causing</char> Lazarus <char style="add">to be alive again</char>.<verse eid="JHN 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus entered Jerusalem as a king, but a humble one.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 12:12-19">John 12:12-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 12:12"/>The next day the huge crowd of people that had come <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> for the <char style="add">Passover</char> celebration heard that Jesus was coming to Jerusalem. <verse eid="JHN 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 12:13"/>So they <char style="add">cut</char> branches from some palm trees and took the branches out <char style="add">of the city</char> to <char style="add">wave them when they</char> met him. Some of them were shouting things like, “Hooray!” “May the Lord <char style="add">God</char> bless the one who is coming with his authority [MTY]!” Some other people were shouting, “<char style="add">May God bless</char> the King of Israel!” <verse eid="JHN 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 12:14"/>When Jesus <char style="add">came near to Jerusalem</char>, he got a young donkey and sat on it <char style="add">as he rode into the city</char>. By doing this, <char style="add">he fulfilled</char> what had been written {what <char style="add">a prophet</char> had written} <char style="add">in Scripture</char>,<verse eid="JHN 12:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 12:15"/>You people of Jerusalem,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:15">do not be afraid!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:15">Look! Your king is coming!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:15">He is riding on a donkey’s colt!<verse eid="JHN 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 12:16"/>At first <char style="add">we</char> disciples did not understand those things. But after Jesus had returned to heaven, we realized that those things had been written {that <char style="add">a prophet</char> had written those things} about him, and that <char style="add">by</char> doing those things for him <char style="add">the people had fulfilled what the prophet prophesied</char>.<verse eid="JHN 12:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 12:17"/>The crowd that was with him continued to tell other people that he called Lazarus to come out of the tomb, <char style="add">and that Lazarus had then become alive again</char>. <verse eid="JHN 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 12:18"/>Because of that, many people, because they heard <char style="add">others say</char> that he had performed this miracle, went to meet him. <verse eid="JHN 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 12:19"/>So the Pharisees said to each other, “It is obvious that we are making no progress <char style="add">in trying to stop him! It looks like</char> [HYP] everyone [MTY] is becoming his disciple!”<verse eid="JHN 12:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told some Greeks what people who wanted to be his disciples had to be ready to do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 12:20-28a">John 12:20-28a</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 12:20"/>Among those who went up <char style="add">to Jerusalem</char> to worship <char style="add">God</char> during the <char style="add">Passover</char> celebration were some Greeks. <verse eid="JHN 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 12:21"/>They came to Philip, who was from Bethsaida <char style="add">town</char> in Galilee <char style="add">province</char>. They <char style="add">wanted him</char> to do something for them. They said, “Sir, we would like to talk with Jesus.” <verse eid="JHN 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 12:22"/>So after Philip went and told that to Andrew, they both went and told Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 12:23"/>Then, <char style="add">to show them that he must die in order to give eternal life to non-Jews like those Greeks</char>, Jesus replied to them, “It is time for <char style="add">God</char> to honor me, the one who came from heaven. <char style="add">That will happen when I die</char>. <verse eid="JHN 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 12:24"/>Listen to this carefully: <char style="add">My life is like a seed</char> [MET]. If <char style="add">someone</char> does not plant a kernel of grain in the ground, it does not change. It remains only one <char style="add">seed</char>. But if it changes <char style="add">after it is planted in the ground, it will grow and</char> produce many seeds. <verse eid="JHN 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 12:25"/>Anyone who strongly wants to keep on living <char style="add">here on earth</char> will surely lose his life forever. But anyone who is willing to die [HYP] <char style="add">for my sake</char> will surely gain eternal life. <verse eid="JHN 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 12:26"/>If <char style="add">any of these Greeks or</char> anyone <char style="add">else</char> wants to serve me, they must become my disciples. Then, <char style="add">after they die</char>, they will be where I am, <char style="add">in heaven</char>. My Father will honor all those who serve me.<verse eid="JHN 12:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 12:27"/>Now I am deeply disturbed. ◄I do not know what to say./What shall I say?► [RHQ] Should I say, ‘<char style="add">My</char> Father, save me from this time <char style="add">when I will suffer and die!’</char>? No, <char style="add">I should not say that, because</char> the reason I came ◄<char style="add">into this world/from heaven</char>► was that I would <char style="add">suffer</char> [MTY] now. <verse eid="JHN 12:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 12:28"/>My Father, show how great you are!”</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="JHN 12:28">God encouraged Jesus about his coming death by a voice from heaven.</para>
  <para style="sr" vid="JHN 12:28">
    <ref loc="JHN 12:28b-36a">John 12:28b-36a</ref></para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 12:28">Then <char style="add">God</char> spoke [EUP] from heaven, saying, “I have already shown how great <char style="add">I am</char>, and I will do it again!” <verse eid="JHN 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 12:29"/>The crowd that was there heard <char style="add">it but they did not understand the words. Some said</char> it was thunder. Others said an angel had spoken to him. <verse eid="JHN 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 12:30"/>Jesus replied to them, “The voice that you heard speaking <char style="add">was God’s voice, but</char> it was not for my benefit. It was for your benefit! <verse eid="JHN 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 12:31"/>Now is the time for <char style="add">God</char> to judge <char style="add">the people in</char> [MTY] the world. Now is the time when <char style="add">I</char> will destroy <char style="add">the power of Satan</char>, the one who rules this world. <verse eid="JHN 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 12:32"/>But as for me, when I am lifted {when <char style="add">men</char> lift me} up from the ground <char style="add">on a cross, I will make a way for</char> gathering everyone to myself.” <verse eid="JHN 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 12:33"/>He said this to show us the way in which he was going to die.<verse eid="JHN 12:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 12:34"/>
    <char style="add">Someone in</char> the crowd answered him, “We understand from the Scriptures that the Messiah will live forever. So why do you say that the one who came from heaven, <char style="add">who is the Messiah</char>, will be lifted up {that <char style="add">men</char> will lift up the one who came from heaven, <char style="add">who is the Messiah</char>,} on a cross? What kind of man who came from heaven are you <char style="add">talking about</char>? (OR, That’s not the <char style="add">kind</char> of Messiah <char style="add">we are expecting</char>!)” <verse eid="JHN 12:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 12:35"/>Then Jesus said to them, “<char style="add">My message is like</char> [MET] a light for you. <char style="add">I</char> will be with you for only a little while longer. Live and act <char style="add">as you should</char> while I am still with you, <char style="add">because suddenly you will have no more opportunity to hear my message! You do not want to be like</char> [MET] <char style="add">someone</char> who cannot see where he is going any more <char style="add">when it suddenly</char> becomes dark! <verse eid="JHN 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 12:36"/>Believe in my message [MET] while you still have an opportunity to do it, in order that you may become people who have accepted my truth [MET]!”</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="JHN 12:36">Most of the Jewish leaders continued to reject Jesus’ message.</para>
  <para style="sr" vid="JHN 12:36">
    <ref loc="JHN 12:36b-43">John 12:36b-43</ref></para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 12:36">After Jesus said those things, he left them and hid from them. <verse eid="JHN 12:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 12:37"/>Although he had done many miracles while people were watching, <char style="add">most of</char> them refused to believe that he <char style="add">is</char> ◄<char style="add">the Messiah/from God</char>►. <verse eid="JHN 12:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 12:38"/><char style="add">Their stubbornness and refusal to believe was similar to the stubbornness of the people that</char> the prophet Isaiah wrote about long ago:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:38">Lord, ◄hardly anyone has believed our message!/who has believed our message?► [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:38">Most people refused to accept it,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:38">even though you showed them your power!<verse eid="JHN 12:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 12:39"/>That was the reason why they were unable to believe. <char style="add">It was like</char> Isaiah wrote somewhere else that God said:<verse eid="JHN 12:39"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 12:40"/>They have <char style="add">refused to understand; they acted as though they were</char> blind people!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:40">They were insensible in their inner beings!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:40">As a result, they have not perceived <char style="add">my truth</char>!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:40">They have not understood it in their inner beings!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 12:40">They have not turned <char style="add">from their sinful lives</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="JHN 12:40">and because of that I cannot help them!<verse eid="JHN 12:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 12:41"/>Isaiah wrote that because <char style="add">it was as though</char> he saw <char style="add">ahead of time</char> how great Jesus would be, and he prophesied <char style="add">those things</char> about him.<verse eid="JHN 12:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 12:42"/>Although most of the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] did not believe that Jesus is ◄<char style="add">the Messiah/from God</char>►, some of them believed in him. But they would not tell anyone that they believed in him, because <char style="add">they were afraid that if they said that</char>, the Pharisees would not let them worship in the synagogues. <verse eid="JHN 12:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JHN 12:43"/>They wanted people to praise them more than they wanted God to praise them.<verse eid="JHN 12:43"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus warned that God would condemn those who rejected his message.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 12:44-50">John 12:44-50</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="JHN 12:44"/>
    <char style="add">Another day, when</char> Jesus <char style="add">was teaching the people, he</char> shouted, “Those who believe in me, they are not believing in <char style="add">me alone</char>. Instead, <char style="add">it is as though</char> they also believe in the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 12:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JHN 12:45"/>When they see me <char style="add">and what I am doing, it is as though</char> they are seeing the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 12:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JHN 12:46"/>I have come into the world <char style="add">to show people God’s truth</char>, as a light <char style="add">shows people what is around them</char>. I have come in order that people who believe in me will not remain <char style="add">ignorant of God’s truth</char> [MET], <char style="add">as those who are</char> in the darkness <char style="add">are ignorant of what is around them</char>.<verse eid="JHN 12:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="JHN 12:47"/>As for those who hear my message but do not obey <char style="add">its commands</char>, I am not <char style="add">the one who</char> judges them. <char style="add">The main reason</char> that I came ◄<char style="add">into the world/from heaven</char>► was not to judge <char style="add">the people of</char> [MTY] the world. Instead, I came to save them <char style="add">from being punished for their sins</char>. <verse eid="JHN 12:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="JHN 12:48"/>There is something that will judge those who reject me and do not accept my message. On the judgment day <char style="add">God</char> will condemn them <char style="add">because they rejected</char> the message that I have told them. <verse eid="JHN 12:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JHN 12:49"/>I have not said things from my own <char style="add">authority</char>. Instead, <char style="add">my</char> Father, the one who sent me, instructed me what to say and how I should say it. <verse eid="JHN 12:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JHN 12:50"/>I know that <char style="add">paying attention to</char> what he has instructed us <char style="add">leads to</char> eternal life. So whatever I say is exactly (OR, only) what <char style="add">my</char> Father has told me to say.”<verse eid="JHN 12:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JHN 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus washed the disciples’ feet as an example of humble service to each other.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 13:1-17">John 13:1-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 13:1"/>When it was the evening before the Passover celebration, Jesus knew that it was time for him to leave this world and <char style="add">to return</char> to <char style="add">his</char> Father <char style="add">in heaven</char>. He loved us who <char style="add">were his disciples</char>. He knew <char style="add">we would continue to live here</char> in this world, so now he <char style="add">showed us</char> how completely he loved us. <verse eid="JHN 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 13:2"/>We were eating <char style="add">the Passover meal</char>. ◄The devil/Satan► had already suggested to Judas Iscariot (OR, Judas, the man from Kerioth <char style="add">Town</char>), the son of Simon, that he should ◄betray Jesus/enable Jesus’ enemies to seize him►. <verse eid="JHN 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 13:3"/>But Jesus knew that his Father had given to him complete authority <char style="add">to control the situation</char>. He knew that he had come from God and would soon return to God. <verse eid="JHN 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 13:4"/><char style="add">But before he left us, he wanted to show us how we should love each other</char>. <char style="add">So</char> he got up from where he was eating. He took off his <char style="add">outer</char> cloak and wrapped a <char style="add">long</char> towel around his waist, <char style="add">as a slave would do</char>. <verse eid="JHN 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 13:5"/>Then he poured some water in a basin. He began to wash our feet, and then dry them with the towel that he had wrapped around himself.<verse eid="JHN 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 13:6"/>When he came to Simon Peter, Peter said to him, “Lord, it is not right for you [RHQ] to <char style="add">humble yourself by</char> washing my feet!” <verse eid="JHN 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 13:7"/>Jesus replied to him, “Now you do not understand <char style="add">the meaning of</char> what I am doing, but you will understand later.” <verse eid="JHN 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 13:8"/>Peter said, “I will never, ever, <char style="add">allow you to</char> wash my feet!” Jesus replied to him, “If I do not wash you, you cannot continue ◄to be my <char style="add">disciple/to belong to</char> me►.” <verse eid="JHN 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 13:9"/>So Simon Peter said to him, “Lord, <char style="add">in that case</char>, do not wash only my feet. Wash my hands and my head, <char style="add">too</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 13:10"/><char style="add">Then, to show him that after God had cleansed people from being guilty for sin, they needed only for God to forgive their daily sins</char> [MET], Jesus said to him, “Those who have recently bathed need only to have their feet washed, <char style="add">because they get dirty very quickly on the dusty roads</char>. The <char style="add">rest of their bodies are</char> clean. Similarly, I have made you <char style="add">disciples</char> free/clean <char style="add">from the guilt of your sins</char>, although not all of you are free from guilt.” <verse eid="JHN 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 13:11"/>He knew which one <char style="add">of us</char> was going to betray him. That is the reason he said, “Not all of you are free from guilt.”<verse eid="JHN 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 13:12"/>After he finished washing our feet, he put his cloak back on. Then he sat down and said to us, “Do you understand what I have done for you? <verse eid="JHN 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 13:13"/>You <char style="add">show that you respect me by</char> calling me ‘Teacher’ and ‘Lord’. You are right to say that, because I am your teacher and your Lord. <verse eid="JHN 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 13:14"/>But if I, who am your teacher and your Lord, have washed your feet, you ought to <char style="add">serve each other by doing things like</char> washing each other’s feet. <verse eid="JHN 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 13:15"/>I have made myself an example for you in order that you should <char style="add">humbly serve each other</char> as I have done for you. <verse eid="JHN 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 13:16"/>Listen to this carefully: A servant is not greater than his master. A messenger is not greater than the one who has sent him. <char style="add">So, since you are not greater than I am, you should not be proud and unwilling to serve each other</char>. <verse eid="JHN 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 13:17"/>Since you now know these things, <char style="add">God will</char> be pleased with you if you do them.”<verse eid="JHN 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus predicted that one of them would betray him to his enemies.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 13:18-30">John 13:18-30</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 13:18"/>“I am not saying that <char style="add">God will bless</char> all of you. I knew <char style="add">what all of you were like when</char> I chose you. But <char style="add">I also chose the one who will betray me</char>, in order that what is written in Scripture might be fulfilled {to fulfill what someone/the psalmist wrote in Scripture}, ‘The one who is <char style="add">acting like he is my friend by</char> eating with me has become my enemy [IDM].’<verse eid="JHN 13:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 13:19"/>I am telling you <char style="add">about someone betraying me</char> before it happens, in order that when it happens, you may continue to believe that I am ◄<char style="add">the Messiah/who I say I am</char>►. <verse eid="JHN 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 13:20"/>Listen to this carefully: Those who accept any one of you whom I am sending out, <char style="add">God will consider that</char> they are accepting me. And those who accept me, <char style="add">God will consider that</char> they are accepting <char style="add">my Father</char>, who sent me.”<verse eid="JHN 13:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 13:21"/>After Jesus said this, he was very troubled. He solemnly declared, “Listen to this carefully: One of you is going to enable <char style="add">my enemies</char> to seize me.” <verse eid="JHN 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 13:22"/>We looked at each other. We had no way <char style="add">to know</char> whom he was talking about. <verse eid="JHN 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 13:23"/><char style="add">I</char>, the <char style="add">man other people call</char> ‘the one Jesus loved’, was sitting very close to Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 13:24"/>Simon Peter motioned to me to indicate that I should ask Jesus whom he was talking about. <verse eid="JHN 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 13:25"/>So I leaned close to Jesus and asked him, “Lord, who is it?” <verse eid="JHN 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 13:26"/>Jesus answered, “It is the one to whom I will give this piece of bread after I dip it <char style="add">in the sauce in the dish</char>.” Then, <char style="add">to show us that he knew who would enable his enemies to seize him</char>, after he dipped the bread <char style="add">in the sauce</char>, he gave it to Judas Iscariot (OR, Judas, the man from Kerioth <char style="add">Town</char>). <verse eid="JHN 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 13:27"/>As soon as <char style="add">Judas ate</char> the bread, Satan took control of him. Then Jesus said to him, “What you are going to do, do quickly.” <verse eid="JHN 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 13:28"/>But none of the rest of us who were sitting there knew why Jesus said that to him. <verse eid="JHN 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 13:29"/>Since Judas took care of the money <char style="add">people gave us to help us</char>, some thought Jesus was telling him to <char style="add">go and</char> buy some things we needed for the <char style="add">Passover</char> celebration. <char style="add">Some thought he was telling him</char> to give some money to poor people. <verse eid="JHN 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 13:30"/>As soon as Judas had eaten the bread, he left. It was dark <char style="add">outside</char>, and it was dark [MET] <char style="add">in his soul, too</char>.<verse eid="JHN 13:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus commanded his disciples that they should love each other.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 13:31-35">John 13:31-35</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 13:31"/>After Judas left, Jesus said, “Now it will be shown {<char style="add">my Father</char> will show} how wonderful I, the one who came from heaven, am. And by what I do it will be seen {people will see} how great God is. <verse eid="JHN 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 13:32"/>Since by what I do people will see how awesome God is, God himself will show people how awesome I am. And he will do that very soon.<verse eid="JHN 13:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 13:33"/>
    <char style="add">You whom I love as though you were</char> my children, I will continue with you only a short time longer. Then you will look for me, but I will not be here. Just like I told the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN], I am telling you now, that where I am going, you cannot come <char style="add">yet</char>. <verse eid="JHN 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 13:34"/>Now I am giving you a new commandment: You must love each other. You must love each other in the way that I have loved you. <verse eid="JHN 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 13:35"/>If you keep loving each other, everyone <char style="add">who is aware of that</char> [HYP] will know that you are my disciples.”<verse eid="JHN 13:35"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus also prophesied that Peter would deny that he knew Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 13:36-38">John 13:36-38</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 13:36"/>Simon Peter said to him, “Lord, where are you going?” Jesus replied, “The place where I am going, you cannot come with me now, but you will come there later.” <verse eid="JHN 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 13:37"/>Peter said, “Lord, why can I not come with you now? I <char style="add">am ready</char> to die for you!” <verse eid="JHN 13:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 13:38"/>Jesus answered, “<char style="add">You say</char> [RHQ] that you <char style="add">are ready</char> to die for me. But the truth is that before the rooster crows <char style="add">early tomorrow morning</char>, you will say three times that you do not <char style="add">know</char> me!”<verse eid="JHN 13:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JHN 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus encouraged his disciples and told them that he is the only way to the Father.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 14:1-14">John 14:1-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 14:1"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus continued by saying to us</char>, “Stop being anxious/worried. Keep on trusting in God (OR, You are trusting in God); also keep trusting in me. <verse eid="JHN 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 14:2"/>Where my Father is <char style="add">in heaven</char> there is plenty of room! If that were not true, I would have told you. I am about to go <char style="add">there</char> to prepare a place for you. <verse eid="JHN 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 14:3"/>And because I will go <char style="add">there</char> and prepare a place for you, I will return and take you there to be with me. I will do that so that you may also be where I am. <verse eid="JHN 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 14:4"/>You know the road to the place where I am going.”<verse eid="JHN 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 14:5"/>Thomas said to him, “Lord, we do not know where you are going. <char style="add">So</char> how can we know the road?” <verse eid="JHN 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 14:6"/>Jesus said to him, “I am the road [MET] <char style="add">to where my Father is</char>. I am the <char style="add">one who reveals</char> [MET] the truth <char style="add">about God</char> and the <char style="add">one who gives eternal</char> life <char style="add">to people</char>. I am the only one who can <char style="add">enable people</char> to come to <char style="add">my</char> Father. There is no other way. <verse eid="JHN 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 14:7"/>If you <char style="add">really</char> knew who I was, you would have known my Father also. From now on, you know him, and <char style="add">it is as though</char> you have seen him.”<verse eid="JHN 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 14:8"/>Philip said to him, “Lord, show us your Father and that will be enough for us!” <verse eid="JHN 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 14:9"/>Jesus said to him, “Philip, I have been with you for a long time. So ◄surely you should know who I <char style="add">really am</char>!/why have you not come to know who I <char style="add">really am</char>?► [RHQ] Those who have seen me, <char style="add">it is as though</char> they have seen <char style="add">my</char> Father. So ◄why do you say ‘Show us <char style="add">your</char> Father’?/you should not say ‘Show us <char style="add">your</char> Father’!► [RHQ] <verse eid="JHN 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 14:10"/>Do you not [RHQ] believe that I have a close relationship with <char style="add">my</char> Father, and that <char style="add">my</char> Father has a close relationship with me? The messages that I tell you do not come from me. They come from my Father, who has a close relationship with me. He is enabling me to <char style="add">teach these things, and</char> to perform the miracles that he <char style="add">wants me to perform</char>. <verse eid="JHN 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 14:11"/>Believe that I have a close relationship with <char style="add">my</char> Father and that <char style="add">my</char> Father has a close relationship with me. If you do not believe that just because of what I say, believe it because of the miracles themselves <char style="add">that I have done</char>. <verse eid="JHN 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 14:12"/>Listen to this carefully: <char style="add">You</char> who trust in me will do the <char style="add">kinds of</char> miracles <char style="add">that I have done</char>. <char style="add">Because of what I will do for you</char> (OR, <char style="add">Because I will send God’s Spirit to you</char>) after I go to my Father, you will be able to do <char style="add">miracles</char> that will be greater than <char style="add">the ones I have done</char>. <verse eid="JHN 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 14:13"/>And whatever you, using my authority, ask me to do, I will do it, in order that I can show <char style="add">you</char> how great <char style="add">my</char> Father is. <verse eid="JHN 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 14:14"/>Anything that you ask <char style="add">my Father to do, anything that you ask</char> with my <char style="add">authority</char> [MTY], I will do.”<verse eid="JHN 14:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus promised to send the Holy Spirit to them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 14:15-31">John 14:15-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 14:15"/>“If you love me, you will do what I have commanded you. <verse eid="JHN 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 14:16"/>Then I myself will request <char style="add">my</char> Father, and he will send you someone else who will ◄encourage/be like a legal counsel for► you. <verse eid="JHN 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 14:17"/><char style="add">I am talking about</char> the Spirit, who <char style="add">will teach you God’s</char> truth. He will be with you forever. Those who are opposed to God [MTY] cannot receive him, because they cannot understand what he <char style="add">does</char>, and they cannot know who he is. But you know who he is, because he is with you and he will be inside you. <verse eid="JHN 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 14:18"/><char style="add">When I leave you</char>, I will not let you be alone/helpless [MET]. <char style="add">When I send the Spirit, it will be like</char> I am coming back to you (OR, <char style="add">When I rise from the dead</char>, I will come back to you.) <verse eid="JHN 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 14:19"/>Soon those who do not belong to God [MTY] will not see me any more. But <char style="add">when the Spirit comes to you, it will be as though</char> you will be seeing me again (OR, But <char style="add">after I become alive again</char>, you will see me again.) Because I will be alive again, you also will have <char style="add">eternal</char> life. <verse eid="JHN 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 14:20"/>At that time you will know that I have a close relationship with my Father, and you will have a close relationship with me, and I will have a close relationship with you. <verse eid="JHN 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 14:21"/>Those who have accepted my commands and obey them are the people who love me. My Father will love those who love me. I also will love them, and I will fully reveal to them <char style="add">what I am like</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 14:22"/>Then Judas spoke to him. He was not Judas Iscariot (OR, Judas, the man from Kerioth <char style="add">Town</char>), <char style="add">but instead a disciple whose other name was Thaddeus</char>. He said, “Lord, what has happened so that you can fully reveal to us what you are like, and not reveal that to those who do not belong to God [MTY]?” <verse eid="JHN 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 14:23"/>Jesus replied to him, “Those who love me will obey what I have told them. My Father will <char style="add">also</char> love them. It is those people whom my Father and I will <char style="add">be able to</char> come to and ◄live with/have a personal relationship with►. <verse eid="JHN 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 14:24"/>But those who do not love me will not obey what I have told them. <char style="add">So I cannot reveal to them what I am really like</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 14:24">These words that I am telling you have not come just from me. They came from <char style="add">my</char> Father, the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 14:25"/>I have told you all these things while I am still with you. <verse eid="JHN 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 14:26"/>But <char style="add">my</char> Father will send the Holy Spirit. He is the one who will ◄encourage/be like a legal counsel for► you. He will come with my authority [MTY]. He will teach you all of <char style="add">God’s truth that you need to know</char>. He will also cause you to remember all the things that I have told you. <verse eid="JHN 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 14:27"/>As I leave you, I am causing you to have <char style="add">inner</char> peace. This <char style="add">inner</char> peace comes from me. I am not causing you to have something that those who do not belong to God [MTY] can give you. <char style="add">So</char> stop being anxious/worried, and do not be afraid.<verse eid="JHN 14:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 14:28"/>You heard me say to you, ‘I am going away, but <char style="add">later</char> I will come back to you.’ If you loved me, you would be glad that I am going back to <char style="add">my</char> Father, because <char style="add">my</char> Father is greater than I am, <char style="add">and there he will honor me and will send the Spirit to you</char>. <verse eid="JHN 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 14:29"/>I have told you <char style="add">these things now</char> before they happen, so that when they happen you will believe <char style="add">that what I said is true</char>. <verse eid="JHN 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 14:30"/>I will not <char style="add">be able to</char> talk to you much longer, because what happens to me will be as though <char style="add">Satan</char>, the ruler of this world, is coming <char style="add">to attack me</char>. But he has no <char style="add">control over what happens to</char> me. <verse eid="JHN 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 14:31"/>Instead, the people who do not belong to God [MTY] must learn <char style="add">from what happens to me</char> that I love <char style="add">my</char> Father, and I am doing the things that he has commanded me to do. Now, let’s get up and leave here.”<verse eid="JHN 14:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JHN 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught them that they needed to remain closely united to him in order to live in a way that would please God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 15:1-17">John 15:1-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 15:1"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus talked to us as we were walking along. Speaking figuratively of the need for us to live in a way that God wants us to, he said</char>, “I am like [MET] a genuine vine, <char style="add">not like those Jewish leaders who do not teach the truth</char>. My father is like [MET] a gardener who <char style="add">works to</char> take care of a vineyard. <verse eid="JHN 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 15:2"/><char style="add">Just like a gardener</char> cuts off the branches that bear no grapes [MET], <char style="add">God gets rid of those who do not please him even though they say that they belong to him</char>. Those branches that bear fruit, <char style="add">the gardener</char> trims so that they may bear more grapes. <char style="add">Similarly, my Father disciplines/corrects those who live as he wants them to live</char>. <verse eid="JHN 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 15:3"/>You are already <char style="add">like</char> the branches <char style="add">that a gardener</char> trims because <char style="add">you have believed</char> the message that I have told you. <verse eid="JHN 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 15:4"/>Remain having a close relationship with me. <char style="add">If you do that</char>, I will remain having a close relationship with you. A branch <char style="add">of a vine</char> cannot bear fruit <char style="add">if it is cut off and left</char> by itself. To bear fruit, it must remain attached to the vine. Similarly, you cannot <char style="add">live the way that God wants you to</char> if you do not remain united to me [MET].<verse eid="JHN 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 15:5"/>I am <char style="add">like</char> [MET] a vine. You are <char style="add">like</char> [MET] the branches. All those who have a close relationship with me and with whom I have a close relationship will <char style="add">do much that pleases God, like</char> [MET] <char style="add">a vine that</char> bears much fruit. <char style="add">Remember that</char> you can do nothing [HYP] <char style="add">that truly pleases God</char> without my <char style="add">help</char>. <verse eid="JHN 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 15:6"/><char style="add">A gardener cuts off and</char> throws away useless branches. Then, after they dry up, <char style="add">he</char> picks them up and throws them into a fire and burns them [SIM]. Similarly, everyone who does not remain having a close relationship with me, <char style="add">God</char> will get rid of. <verse eid="JHN 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 15:7"/>If you remain having a close relationship with me and you keep <char style="add">living in accordance with</char> my message, you can ask <char style="add">God to do</char> anything for you, and he will do it. <verse eid="JHN 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 15:8"/>The way my Father is honored is by your {The way you honor my Father is by} doing much that pleases him [MET], and by doing that, you will show that you are my disciples.<verse eid="JHN 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 15:9"/>I have loved you just as <char style="add">my</char> Father has loved me. Now keep living in <char style="add">a way that is appropriate for those whom</char> I love. <verse eid="JHN 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 15:10"/>If you obey what I have commanded you, you will be acting in <char style="add">a way that is appropriate for those whom</char> I love, just like I have obeyed what my Father has commanded me and I act <char style="add">in a way that is appropriate for someone</char> whom he loves. <verse eid="JHN 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 15:11"/>I have told you these things so that you may be joyful as I <char style="add">am joyful</char>, and that you may be completely joyful. <verse eid="JHN 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 15:12"/>What I am commanding you is this: Love each other just like I have loved you. <verse eid="JHN 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 15:13"/>The best way that people can show that they love someone is to die for that person. There is no way that you can love someone in a greater way than that. <verse eid="JHN 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 15:14"/>You <char style="add">show that you</char> are my friends if you keep doing what I have commanded you. <verse eid="JHN 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 15:15"/>I will no longer call you my servants, because servants do not know <char style="add">why</char> their masters <char style="add">want them to</char> do things. Instead, I have said that you are my friends, because I, <char style="add">acting like a friend</char>, have revealed to you everything that my Father told me. <verse eid="JHN 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 15:16"/>You did not decide to become my <char style="add">disciples</char>. Instead, I chose you, so that you would do many things that please him [MET]. The results of what you do will last <char style="add">forever</char>. I also chose you so that <char style="add">my</char> Father will do for you whatever you, using my authority, ask him to do [MTY]. <verse eid="JHN 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 15:17"/><char style="add">I repeat what</char> I have commanded you: Love each other.”<verse eid="JHN 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught them that those who were opposed to God would hate them, too.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 15:18-16:4">John 15:18—16:4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 15:18"/>“The people who are opposed to God will hate you. When that happens, remember that they hated me first. <verse eid="JHN 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 15:19"/>If you belonged to those who are opposed to God [MTY], they would love <char style="add">you like they love</char> those who belong to them. But you do not belong to those who are opposed to God [MTY]. Instead, I chose you so that you would separate yourselves from [MTY] them. That is why those who are opposed to God [MTY] hate you. <verse eid="JHN 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 15:20"/>Remember these words that I told you: ‘No servant is greater than his master.’ <char style="add">That means that you, who are like my servants, cannot expect people to treat you better than they treat me</char>. So, since they have ◄persecuted me/caused me to suffer►, they will ◄persecute you/cause you to suffer► also. If they had paid attention to the things I taught them, they would pay attention to what you teach them. <verse eid="JHN 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 15:21"/>They will treat you like that because you <char style="add">belong to</char> me [MTY], and because they do not know the one who sent me. <verse eid="JHN 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 15:22"/>If I had not come and spoken <char style="add">God’s message</char> to them, they would not be guilty <char style="add">of rejecting me and my message</char>. But now <char style="add">I have come and told them God’s message, so</char> they will have no excuse <char style="add">when God judges them</char> for their sin. <verse eid="JHN 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 15:23"/>All those who hate me, <char style="add">it is as though</char> they hate my Father as well. <verse eid="JHN 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 15:24"/>If I had not done among them the <char style="add">miracles</char> that no one else ever did, they would not be guilty of the sin <char style="add">of rejecting me</char>. But now, <char style="add">although</char> they have seen <char style="add">those miracles</char>, they have hated both me and my Father. <verse eid="JHN 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 15:25"/>But this has happened in order that these words that have been written in their Scriptures might be fulfilled {to fulfill this that <char style="add">◄someone/the Psalmist</char>► wrote in their Scriptures}: ‘They hated me for no reason.’<verse eid="JHN 15:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 15:26"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char> I will send to you from <char style="add">my</char> Father the one who will ◄encourage/be like a legal counsel for► you. He is the Spirit <char style="add">who will teach you God’s</char> truth. He will come from my Father. He will tell people about me. <verse eid="JHN 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 15:27"/>But you <char style="add">disciples</char> must also tell people <char style="add">about me</char>, because you have been with me from the time when I started <char style="add">my ministry</char> [MTY].”<verse eid="JHN 15:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JHN 16"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 16:1"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus continued by saying to us</char>, “I have told you these things in order that you will not stop trusting in me <char style="add">when people</char> ◄<char style="add">cause you to suffer/persecute you</char>►. <verse eid="JHN 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 16:2"/>They will not allow you to worship in ◄synagogues/<char style="add">their</char> meeting places►. In fact, there will be a time when anyone who kills you will think that he is serving God <char style="add">by doing that</char>. <verse eid="JHN 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 16:3"/>They will do such things because they have never known who I <char style="add">really am</char>, nor who <char style="add">my</char> Father <char style="add">is</char>. <verse eid="JHN 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 16:4"/>I have told you these things in order that when <char style="add">they start</char> ◄<char style="add">to cause you to suffer</char>/to <char style="add">persecute you</char>► [MTY], you will remember that I warned you. I did not tell you these things when you first started <char style="add">to accompany me</char> [MTY] because I was with you, <char style="add">and they were causing trouble for me, not for you</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told them some things that the Holy Spirit would do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 16:5-15">John 16:5-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 16:5"/>“Now I am <char style="add">about to</char> return to the one who sent me. But <char style="add">I am disappointed that</char> none of you is asking me, ‘Where are you going?’ <verse eid="JHN 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 16:6"/>Instead, because I have told you these things, you are very sad. <verse eid="JHN 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 16:7"/>But the truth is that it is good for you that I am going away, because if I do not go away, the <char style="add">Holy Spirit</char>, who will ◄encourage/be like a legal counsel for► you will not come to you. But when I go, I will send him to you. <verse eid="JHN 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 16:8"/>When he comes, he will prove that those who do not belong to God [MTY] <char style="add">are wrong about what is</char> sinful and about who is really righteous and about whom <char style="add">God will</char> judge <char style="add">and condemn for their sin</char>. <verse eid="JHN 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 16:9"/><char style="add">He will tell people that their greatest</char> sin is that they do not believe in me. <verse eid="JHN 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 16:10"/><char style="add">He will tell people that</char> because I am going <char style="add">back</char> to my Father, and you will no longer see me, <char style="add">you will know that I am the one who was truly</char> righteous. <verse eid="JHN 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 16:11"/><char style="add">He will tell people that the fact</char> that <char style="add">God</char> has already determined that <char style="add">he</char> will punish <char style="add">Satan</char>, the one who rules this world, shows that <char style="add">some day God</char> will also punish <char style="add">those who do not belong to him</char>.<verse eid="JHN 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 16:12"/>I have many more things that <char style="add">I would like</char> to tell you, but you are not able to accept them now. <verse eid="JHN 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 16:13"/>But <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit is the one who will teach you <char style="add">God’s</char> truth. When he comes, he will guide you so that you <char style="add">understand</char> all <char style="add">spiritual</char> truth. He will not speak from his own <char style="add">authority</char>. Instead, it is the things that he hears <char style="add">my Father say</char> that he will tell you. He will also tell you about things that will happen <char style="add">later</char>. <verse eid="JHN 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 16:14"/>He will honor me by revealing my <char style="add">truth</char> to you. <verse eid="JHN 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 16:15"/>Everything that <char style="add">my</char> Father has is mine. That is why I said that the Spirit is able to reveal my truth to you.”<verse eid="JHN 16:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told them that after he left they would be sad, but that they would later be joyful when they saw him again.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 16:16-33">John 16:16-33</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 16:16"/>“After a short time <char style="add">I will leave you, and</char> you will not see me. Then a short time <char style="add">after that</char> you will see me <char style="add">again</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 16:17"/><char style="add">So</char> some of us said to each other, “What does he mean by saying ‘After a short time you will not see me,’ and ‘A short time after that you will see me again’? And <char style="add">what does he mean by</char> ‘Because I am going back to <char style="add">my</char> Father’?” <verse eid="JHN 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 16:18"/>We kept asking each other, “What <char style="add">does he mean by</char> saying ‘After a little while’? We do not understand what he is saying.”<verse eid="JHN 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 16:19"/>Jesus realized that we wanted to ask him <char style="add">about that</char>. So he said to us, “You are asking [RHQ] each other <char style="add">what I meant</char> when I said, ‘After a short time you will not see me, and then a short time <char style="add">after that</char> you will see me <char style="add">again</char>.’ <verse eid="JHN 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 16:20"/>Listen to this carefully: <char style="add">After I</char> ◄<char style="add">leave you/die</char>►, those who oppose God [MTY] will be happy, but you will be sad. But <char style="add">later</char> you will stop being sad and you will become joyful. <verse eid="JHN 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 16:21"/>A woman who is about to bear a child feels pain, because that is <char style="add">what happens</char> [MTY] <char style="add">at</char> that time. But after her baby is born, she forgets that pain, because she is very joyful that her child has been born. <verse eid="JHN 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 16:22"/>It will be the same with you. <char style="add">I will soon die and</char> you will be sad. But after that, I will see you again. Then you will be joyful, and no one will be able to stop you from being joyful. <verse eid="JHN 16:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 16:23"/>When that happens, you will not ask me any questions <char style="add">about anything</char>. Listen to this carefully: <char style="add">After that happens, my</char> Father will do for you anything you ask, because of his relationship with me [MTY]. <verse eid="JHN 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 16:24"/>Up to the present time, using my authority you have not asked <char style="add">God to do</char> anything for you [MTY]. Now keep asking <char style="add">him for things that you need. If you do that</char>, you will receive them, and then you will be completely joyful.<verse eid="JHN 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 16:25"/>Although I have been speaking these things using figurative language, there will soon be a time when I will no longer use that kind of language. Instead, I will tell you plainly ◄about my Father/what my Father <char style="add">wants</char>►. <verse eid="JHN 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 16:26"/>At that time, you will ask <char style="add">him for things</char> ◄because you belong to me/with my authority► [MTY]. I will not <char style="add">need to</char> ask <char style="add">my</char> Father to do what you ask. <verse eid="JHN 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 16:27"/><char style="add">My</char> Father himself loves you because you have loved me and because you have believed that I came from God <char style="add">my Father</char>, <char style="add">so he wants you to ask</char> him (OR, <char style="add">so he does not need anyone to persuade</char> him <char style="add">to help you</char>) <verse eid="JHN 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 16:28"/>I came from <char style="add">my</char> Father into this world. Very soon I will be leaving this world and going <char style="add">back</char> to my Father.”<verse eid="JHN 16:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 16:29"/>Then <char style="add">we</char>, his disciples, said, “Now you are speaking plainly, without using figurative language. <verse eid="JHN 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 16:30"/>Now we understand that you know everything. You do not need anyone to ask you questions <char style="add">about anything, because you know what we want to ask before we ask you</char>. That <char style="add">also</char> leads us to believe that you came from God.”<verse eid="JHN 16:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 16:31"/>Jesus replied, “Now you [RHQ] say that you believe <char style="add">that I came from God</char>. <verse eid="JHN 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 16:32"/>But listen! There will soon be a time, and that time is already here, when you will all run away! Each of you will run away to your own home. You will leave me, and I will be alone. But I will not <char style="add">really</char> be alone <char style="add">at that time</char>, because <char style="add">my</char> Father is always with me. <verse eid="JHN 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 16:33"/>I have told you these things in order that you may have <char style="add">inner</char> peace because of your relationship with me. In this world you will have trouble. But be courageous! I have defeated those who are opposed to me [MTY], and <char style="add">you can defeat them, too</char>!”<verse eid="JHN 16:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JHN 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus prayed that God would honor him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 17:1-5">John 17:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 17:1"/>After Jesus said those things, he looked <char style="add">up</char> toward heaven. Then he prayed, “<char style="add">My</char> Father, it is now the time [MTY] <char style="add">for me to suffer and die</char>. Honor me <char style="add">as I do that</char>, in order that I may honor you. <verse eid="JHN 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 17:2"/>You gave me authority over all people, in order that I might enable all those whom you chose <char style="add">to come</char> to me to live eternally. <verse eid="JHN 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 17:3"/><char style="add">The way for people</char> to live eternally is for them to know that you are the only true God, and to know that <char style="add">I</char>, Jesus, am the Messiah, the one you have sent. <verse eid="JHN 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 17:4"/>I have honored you here on this earth by completing all the work that you gave me to do. <verse eid="JHN 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 17:5"/><char style="add">My</char> Father, now honor me when I am with you <char style="add">again</char>, by causing me to have the greatness I had when I was with you before the world began.”<verse eid="JHN 17:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus prayed that God would protect his disciples.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 17:6-19">John 17:6-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 17:6"/>“I have revealed <char style="add">what</char> you <char style="add">are like</char> to the people whom you brought to me from among those who do not belong to you [MTY]. Those <char style="add">who came to me</char> belonged to you, and you brought them to me. Now they have obeyed your message. <verse eid="JHN 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 17:7"/>Now they know that everything you have given me, <char style="add">your message and your work</char>, comes from you. <verse eid="JHN 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 17:8"/>I gave them the message that you gave me, and they have accepted it. They now know for certain that I came from you. They now believe that you sent me. <verse eid="JHN 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 17:9"/>I am praying for them. I am not praying for those <char style="add">who do not belong to you</char> [MTY]. Instead, <char style="add">I am praying</char> for those whom you have brought to me, because they belong to you. <verse eid="JHN 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 17:10"/>All <char style="add">the disciples</char> that I have belong to you, and all those who belong to you also belong to me. They have shown how great I am. <verse eid="JHN 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 17:11"/>I will not be <char style="add">staying</char> in the world any longer. I will be coming back to you. They, however, will be <char style="add">here</char> in the world <char style="add">among those who are opposed to you</char>. <char style="add">My</char> Holy Father, protect them from spiritual harm by your power [MTY], the power that you gave me, in order that they may be united as we are united. <verse eid="JHN 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 17:12"/>While I have been with them, I have <char style="add">completely</char> protected them by the power [MTY] that you gave me. As a result, only one of them will be eternally separated from you. He is the one who was doomed to be eternally separated from you. <char style="add">That has happened</char> to fulfill <char style="add">what a prophet wrote</char> in the Scriptures <char style="add">would happen</char>.<verse eid="JHN 17:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 17:13"/>
    <char style="add">Father</char>, now I am about to return to you. I have said these things while I am still <char style="add">here</char> in the world in order that my <char style="add">disciples</char> may fully experience being joyful, as I have been joyful. <verse eid="JHN 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 17:14"/>I have given them your message. As a result, those who are opposed to you [MTY] have hated them, because <char style="add">my disciples</char> do not belong to those who oppose you [MTY], just like I do not belong to those who oppose you [MTY]. <verse eid="JHN 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 17:15"/>I am asking you, not that you take them out of this world, but instead that you protect them from <char style="add">Satan</char>, the evil one. <verse eid="JHN 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 17:16"/>They do not belong to those who are opposed to you [MTY], just like I also do not belong to them. <verse eid="JHN 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 17:17"/>Set <char style="add">my disciples</char> apart so that they may ◄completely belong to/serve► you, by <char style="add">enabling them to live in accordance with</char> what is true. Your message is true. <verse eid="JHN 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 17:18"/>Just like you sent me here into this world, now I surely will be sending them <char style="add">to other places</char> in [MTY] the world. <verse eid="JHN 17:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 17:19"/>I dedicate myself to completely belong to you, in order that they also may truly be dedicated {dedicate themselves} completely to you.”<verse eid="JHN 17:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus prayed for future believers.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 17:20-26">John 17:20-26</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 17:20"/>“I am praying not only for these <char style="add">eleven disciples</char>. I am praying also for those who <char style="add">will</char> believe in me as a result of <char style="add">hearing</char> their message. <verse eid="JHN 17:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 17:21"/><char style="add">My</char> Father, <char style="add">I want</char> all of them to be united, just like I am united with you because of my relationship with you, and as you are united with me because of your relationship with me. I also want them to be united with us. <char style="add">I want that to happen</char> so that those who do not know you [MTY] may know that you sent me. <verse eid="JHN 17:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 17:22"/>I have honored my disciples just like you honored me, in order that they may be united, as we are united. <verse eid="JHN 17:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 17:23"/>I want them to be united just like they are united with me and as you are united with me. May they be completely united, in order that those who do not belong to you [MTY] may know that you sent me and that you have loved them just like you have loved me.<verse eid="JHN 17:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 17:24"/>
    <char style="add">My</char> Father, I want <char style="add">the disciples</char> you have brought to me to <char style="add">some day</char> be with me <char style="add">in heaven</char>, where I will be. I want them to see my greatness. I want them to see the greatness you gave me because you loved me. You gave me that greatness before you created the world.<verse eid="JHN 17:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 17:25"/>
    <char style="add">My</char> righteous Father, although the people who do not belong to you [MTY] do not know what you <char style="add">are like</char>, I know what you <char style="add">are like</char>, and my disciples know that you sent me. <verse eid="JHN 17:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 17:26"/>I have revealed to them <char style="add">what</char> you <char style="add">are like</char>, and I will continue to reveal to them <char style="add">what</char> you <char style="add">are like</char>. I will do that in order that they may love <char style="add">others</char> just like you love me, and in order that I may be in them <char style="add">by my Spirit</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 17:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JHN 18"/>
  <para style="s1">They seized Jesus in a grove of olive trees.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 18:1-11">John 18:1-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 18:1"/>After Jesus finished praying, he went across the Kidron Brook, along with <char style="add">us</char> disciples, to a grove <char style="add">of olive trees</char>.<verse eid="JHN 18:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 18:2"/>Judas, who was <char style="add">about to</char> enable Jesus’ enemies to seize him, knew that <char style="add">he would probably be</char> there. <char style="add">He knew that because</char> Jesus often gathered there with us. <verse eid="JHN 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 18:3"/>So Judas came to that grove. He was leading a troop of Roman <char style="add">soldiers</char> and some Temple guards who had been sent by the Pharisees and chief priests. They were carrying torches and lamps and weapons. <verse eid="JHN 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 18:4"/>Jesus knew everything that was about to happen to him. So <char style="add">as they approached</char>, he stepped forward and asked them, “Who are you looking for?” <verse eid="JHN 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 18:5"/>They replied to him, “Jesus, the man from Nazareth.” He replied, “That is who I am.” Judas, the one who was enabling his enemies to seize him, was with them. <verse eid="JHN 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 18:6"/>When Jesus told them, “That is who I am,” they lurched backward and fell down on the ground <char style="add">because of his power</char>. <verse eid="JHN 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 18:7"/>He asked them again, “Who are you looking for?” They said, “Jesus, <char style="add">the man</char> from Nazareth.” <verse eid="JHN 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 18:8"/>Jesus replied, “I told you that I am Jesus. So since I am the one you are looking for, allow these <char style="add">disciples of mine</char> to go.” <verse eid="JHN 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 18:9"/><char style="add">This happened</char> in order that <char style="add">when they did what he asked them to do</char>, the words would be fulfilled that he had prayed, “I will never lose any of those whom God has brought to me.”<verse eid="JHN 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 18:10"/>Simon Peter had a <char style="add">long</char> dagger. So he drew it and <char style="add">tried to kill</char> the high priest’s servant, <char style="add">but he only</char> cut off the man’s right ear. The servant’s name was Malchus. <verse eid="JHN 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 18:11"/>Jesus said to Peter, “Put your sword <char style="add">back</char> into its sheath! ◄I must endure what <char style="add">my</char> Father wants me to suffer./Do you not think that I must endure what <char style="add">my</char> Father wants me to suffer?► [MET, RHQ]”<verse eid="JHN 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">They took Jesus to be questioned by Annas, the former high priest.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 18:12-14">John 18:12-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 18:12"/>Then the troop of soldiers, along with their commander and the Jewish Temple guards, seized Jesus. They tied his hands <char style="add">behind his back</char>. <verse eid="JHN 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 18:13"/>Then they took him first to Annas, <char style="add">who was previously the high priest</char>. He was the father-in-law of Caiaphas. Caiaphas was the high priest that year. <verse eid="JHN 18:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 18:14"/>Caiaphas was the one who <char style="add">previously</char> advised the Jewish <char style="add">Council</char> that it would be better if one man died for the sake of the people <char style="add">than for all the people of the Jewish nation to die</char>.<verse eid="JHN 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter denied that he was Jesus’ disciple.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 18:15-18">John 18:15-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 18:15"/>Simon Peter and <char style="add">I</char> were following Jesus. Because the high priest knew <char style="add">me</char>, <char style="add">his doorkeeper permitted me</char> to enter the courtyard. <verse eid="JHN 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 18:16"/>But Peter <char style="add">had to</char> wait outside near the doorway. However, since I knew the high priest, I went back to the doorway and spoke to the girl who was guarding the entrance. Then <char style="add">she allowed</char> Peter to come in. <verse eid="JHN 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 18:17"/>The servant girl who was guarding the doorway said to Peter, “Surely you are not another disciple of that man <char style="add">they have arrested</char>, are you?” He said, “I am not.” <verse eid="JHN 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 18:18"/>It was cold, so the high priest’s slaves and Temple guards made a charcoal fire and were standing around it to keep warm. Peter was also standing near it, warming himself.<verse eid="JHN 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The High Priest questioned Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 18:19-24">John 18:19-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 18:19"/>
    <char style="add">While Peter was doing that</char>, the high priest asked Jesus about his disciples and about what he was teaching people. <verse eid="JHN 18:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 18:20"/>Jesus replied, “I have always spoken where many people [MTY, HYP] could hear me. I have taught them in ◄the synagogues/their meeting places► and in the Temple courtyard, in places where many [HYP] Jews come together. I have spoken nothing secretly. <verse eid="JHN 18:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 18:21"/><char style="add">So</char> ◄why are you asking me questions <char style="add">like this illegally</char>?/you should not be asking me questions <char style="add">like this illegally</char>!► [RHQ] Ask the people who heard what I taught! They certainly know what I said!” <verse eid="JHN 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 18:22"/>After Jesus said that, one of the Temple guards standing near him slapped him on his face. He said, “◄That is not the way you should answer the high priest!/Is that the way you should answer the high priest?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 18:23"/>Jesus replied to him, “If I said something that was contrary <char style="add">to your laws</char>, you could tell <char style="add">me that what I said that</char> was wrong. But because I said only what was right, ◄you should not be striking me!/why are you striking me?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="JHN 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 18:24"/>Then after Jesus’ hands were tied {after they tied Jesus hands} <char style="add">again</char>, Annas sent him to Caiaphas, the high priest.<verse eid="JHN 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter denied two more times that he knew Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 18:25-27">John 18:25-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 18:25"/>As Simon Peter was standing warming himself <char style="add">at the fire</char>, someone else said to him, “You are not one of that man’s disciples, are you?” He denied <char style="add">that he was</char>, and said, “I am not.” <verse eid="JHN 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 18:26"/><char style="add">Later</char> one of the high priest’s servants, a man who was a relative of the man whose ear Peter had cut off <char style="add">before</char>, said to him, “I saw you with that man in the grove <char style="add">of olive trees</char>, did I not?” <verse eid="JHN 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 18:27"/>Peter again denied it. Immediately a rooster crowed, <char style="add">as Jesus had said would happen</char>.<verse eid="JHN 18:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Pilate the governor questioned Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 18:28-40">John 18:28-40</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 18:28"/>Then the <char style="add">Jewish leaders</char> [SYN] led Jesus from the <char style="add">home of</char> Caiaphas to the headquarters <char style="add">of Pilate, the Roman governor</char>. It was before dawn. <char style="add">Pilate was a non-Jew</char>, <char style="add">and they thought that if they entered his headquarters</char>, they would become unacceptable to God {God would reject them}, <char style="add">and as a result</char> they would not be able to eat <char style="add">the food during</char> the Passover <char style="add">celebration</char>. <char style="add">Because of that, they did not want to enter Pilate’s headquarters</char>. <verse eid="JHN 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 18:29"/>So Pilate came out to <char style="add">talk to</char> them. He said, “What law do you say that this man has disobeyed?” <verse eid="JHN 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 18:30"/><char style="add">They knew that Jesus had not disobeyed any Roman law, so they did not want to answer him. Instead</char>, they said, “If this man were not a criminal, we would not have brought him to you!” <verse eid="JHN 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 18:31"/>Then Pilate said to them, “Take him yourselves, and judge him according to your own laws!” Then the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] said, “<char style="add">No! We want him executed, but we want you Romans to execute him, because</char> we Jews have no right to execute anyone!” <verse eid="JHN 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 18:32"/><char style="add">The Romans executed people by nailing them to a cross</char>. <char style="add">So</char>, as a result of what <char style="add">the Jewish leaders said</char>, it was fulfilled {<char style="add">the Romans</char> would fulfill} what Jesus had said previously about the way he was going to die.<verse eid="JHN 18:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 18:33"/>Pilate then went back inside his headquarters. He summoned Jesus. <char style="add">Because the Jewish leaders had said that Jesus claimed to be a king</char>, Pilate said to Jesus <char style="add">scornfully</char>, “Are you the king of the Jews?” <verse eid="JHN 18:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 18:34"/>Jesus replied, “Are you asking that because you yourself <char style="add">want to know if I claim to be a king</char>, or because ◄someone else/Caiaphas► said <char style="add">that I claim to be their king</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 18:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 18:35"/>Pilate replied, “I am not a Jew, <char style="add">so</char> ◄<char style="add">I cannot understand these matters!/how can I understand these matters</char>?► [RHQ] It was your fellow Jews and your chief priests who brought you to me! What have you done <char style="add">to make them want to execute you</char>?” <verse eid="JHN 18:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 18:36"/>Jesus replied, “It is not people in [MTY] this world who are <char style="add">making me</char> king. If it was people in this world who were making me a king, my disciples would have fought in order that the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] would be prevented {to prevent the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN]} from seizing me. But it is not <char style="add">someone here in</char> this world who is making me a king.” <verse eid="JHN 18:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 18:37"/>Then Pilate said to him, “So <char style="add">are you saying that</char> you are a king?” Jesus replied, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, what you have said about my being a king <char style="add">is correct</char>. I was born to become a king, and I came into this world to tell people the truth <char style="add">about God</char>. Everyone who <char style="add">believes</char> the truth pays attention to what I say.” <verse eid="JHN 18:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 18:38"/>Pilate said to him, “<char style="add">How can anyone know</char> what the truth is?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 18:38">After he said that, he went outside and talked to the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] again. He said to them, “I do not find that he has done anything at all for which I should punish him. <verse eid="JHN 18:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 18:39"/>But you <char style="add">Jews</char> customarily, <char style="add">every year</char> during the Passover <char style="add">celebration</char>, ask me to release for you <char style="add">someone who is in prison</char>. So would you like for me to release for you the <char style="add">man who you</char> Jews <char style="add">say is your</char> king?” <verse eid="JHN 18:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 18:40"/>They shouted again, “No, do not <char style="add">release</char> this man! Instead, <char style="add">release</char> Barrabas!” But Barrabas was <char style="add">in prison because he was</char> a revolutionist!<verse eid="JHN 18:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JHN 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Pilate finally permitted them to crucify Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 19:1-16a">John 19:1-16a</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 19:1"/>Then Pilate took Jesus <char style="add">inside and had soldiers</char> ◄scourge Jesus/strike Jesus with a whip that had pieces of metal or bone fastened to it►. <verse eid="JHN 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 19:2"/>The soldiers also took <char style="add">some branches with</char> thorns and wove them to make <char style="add">something like</char> a crown. Then they put it on his head. They also put a purple robe on him. <char style="add">They did these things to ridicule him by pretending that he was a king</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 19:3"/>Then they kept coming to him and saying, “Hooray for the King of the Jews [IRO]!” and slapping him <char style="add">on his face</char>.<verse eid="JHN 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 19:4"/>Once more Pilate came outside and said to the crowd, “Look! I am bringing him out to you so that you may know that I do not find that he has done anything for which we should punish him <char style="add">any more</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 19:5"/>When Jesus came out, wearing the crown of thorns and the purple robe, Pilate said to them, “Look at this <char style="add">wretched</char> man!” <verse eid="JHN 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 19:6"/>When the chief priests and Temple guards saw him, they shouted, “Command your soldiers to kill him by nailing him to a cross! Crucify him!” Pilate, <char style="add">knowing that they could not legally do it themselves</char>, said to them, “You yourselves take him and nail him to a cross! As for me, I do not find that he has done anything for which we should punish him.” <verse eid="JHN 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 19:7"/>The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] replied, “<char style="add">Our ancestor Moses gave us</char> the law that says we must kill anyone <char style="add">who claims to be God</char>. This man claims that he is ◄the Son of/the man who is also► God, <char style="add">so you must have him killed</char> {<char style="add">command your soldiers to kill him</char>}.” <verse eid="JHN 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 19:8"/>When Pilate heard that, he was more afraid <char style="add">of what would happen to himself if he commanded the soldiers to kill Jesus</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 19:9"/>So he <char style="add">took Jesus</char> back inside the headquarters. He said to Jesus, “Where do you <char style="add">really</char> come from?” But Jesus did not answer him. <verse eid="JHN 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 19:10"/>So Pilate said to him, “Are you refusing to answer me? Do you not know that I have authority to release you, and I <char style="add">also</char> have authority to <char style="add">have</char> you crucified {command my soldiers to crucify you}?” <verse eid="JHN 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 19:11"/>Jesus replied, “The only authority you have is what has been given to you by God [MTY] {what God [MTY] has given you}. The <char style="add">high priest</char> put me into your hands. <char style="add">He has done to me what he wanted to do, and you do not really want to do it</char>. So he is guilty of committing a greater sin than you are.”<verse eid="JHN 19:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 19:12"/>Because of that, Pilate kept trying to release Jesus. But the Jewish <char style="add">leaders </char>[SYN], <char style="add">threatening to report to the Emperor that Pilate was not going to punish a man who claimed he was a king</char>, continued to shout, “Anyone who claims that he is a king is opposing the Emperor! So if you release this man, <char style="add">we will make sure that</char> the Emperor <char style="add">learns about it, and then he will not consider you as</char> his friend!” <verse eid="JHN 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 19:13"/>When Pilate heard that, he brought Jesus out again. He sat down at the place where he made decisions <char style="add">about punishing people</char>. The place was called {People called it} The Stone Pavement. In the Aramaic language its name was Gabbatha. <verse eid="JHN 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 19:14"/>It was almost noontime, on the day that they prepared <char style="add">things for</char> the Passover <char style="add">celebration</char> (OR, the day before the <char style="add">Sabbath during</char> the Passover <char style="add">celebration</char>).</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:14">Pilate said to the Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN], <char style="add">ridiculing them</char>, “Look at your king!” <verse eid="JHN 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 19:15"/>They shouted, “Take him away! Take him away! <char style="add">Have</char> him crucified {Command your soldiers to nail him to a cross}!” Pilate said to them, “<char style="add">He is</char> your king! Do you really want me to <char style="add">tell my soldiers to</char> nail him to a cross?” The chief priests replied, “The Emperor is our king! We do not have any other king!” <verse eid="JHN 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 19:16"/>Then <char style="add">at last</char> Pilate agreed to do <char style="add">what they wanted, and he told the soldiers</char> to crucify Jesus.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="JHN 19:16">They nailed Jesus to a cross.</para>
  <para style="sr" vid="JHN 19:16">
    <ref loc="JHN 19:16b-24">John 19:16b-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 19:16">Then the soldiers took Jesus away. <verse eid="JHN 19:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 19:17"/><char style="add">As they left</char>, he himself was carrying the cross <char style="add">on which they were going to nail him</char>. They went to a place called The Place of a Skull. In the Aramaic language it is called {they call it} Golgotha. <verse eid="JHN 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 19:18"/>There, <char style="add">after removing most of his clothes</char>, the soldiers nailed him to the cross. They also <char style="add">nailed</char> two other <char style="add">criminals to crosses</char>. There was one on each side, and Jesus was in the middle.<verse eid="JHN 19:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 19:19"/>Pilate also <char style="add">had them</char> write <char style="add">on a board</char> a notice <char style="add">that stated why they were executing him</char>, and fasten it to the cross. But all they wrote was ‘Jesus from Nazareth, the King of the Jews’. <verse eid="JHN 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 19:20"/>Many Jews were <char style="add">able to</char> read this sign, because the place where Jesus was nailed {where they nailed Jesus} to the cross was very close to <char style="add">Jerusalem, where many people had come for the celebration</char>, and because it was written {they wrote it} in three languages: Hebrew, Latin, and Greek. <verse eid="JHN 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 19:21"/>So the Jewish priests went back to Pilate and protested, saying to him, “Change what they have written from ‘The King of the Jews’ to ‘This man said that he is the King of the Jews’!” <verse eid="JHN 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 19:22"/>Pilate replied, “What I <char style="add">told them to</char> write is what they have written, <char style="add">and I</char> will not <char style="add">change it</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 19:23"/>After the soldiers nailed Jesus to the cross, they took his clothes and divided them into four parts, one part for each soldier. But they kept his cloak <char style="add">separate</char>. This cloak was without seam, woven <char style="add">from top to bottom</char>, one piece of cloth. <verse eid="JHN 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 19:24"/>So they said to each other, “Let’s not tear it. Instead, let’s <char style="add">decide</char> ◄<char style="add">by</char> throwing lots/<char style="add">by</char> gambling► who will get it.” So that is what the soldiers did. As a result, these words were fulfilled {they fulfilled these words} that <char style="add">the Psalmist had written</char> in Scripture,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 19:24">They divided <char style="add">most of</char> my clothes among themselves.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="JHN 19:24">They cast lots for <char style="add">one piece of</char> my clothing.<verse eid="JHN 19:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus entrusted his mother to John’s care.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 19:25-27">John 19:25-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 19:25"/>Near the cross where <char style="add">they had nailed</char> Jesus stood his mother, his mother’s sister, Mary the <char style="add">wife</char> of Clopas, and <char style="add">another</char> Mary, the woman from Magdala <char style="add">village</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 19:26"/>Jesus saw his mother standing there. He also saw me standing nearby. Then he said to his mother, “This man <char style="add">will now be like</char> your son.” <verse eid="JHN 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 19:27"/>And he said to me, “<char style="add">Treat this</char> woman as [MET] your mother.” So from that time I took her to my home <char style="add">and took care of her</char>.<verse eid="JHN 19:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus died.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 19:28-37">John 19:28-37</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 19:28"/>Later, Jesus knew that everything <char style="add">that God sent him to do</char> had now been completed {that he had now completed everything <char style="add">that God sent him to do</char>}, <char style="add">but he knew that something else that was written in</char> the Scriptures <char style="add">had</char> to be fulfilled {<char style="add">that he had</char> to fulfill <char style="add">something else that they had written in</char> the Scriptures}. So he said, “I am thirsty!” <verse eid="JHN 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 19:29"/>There was a jar of sour wine there. So <char style="add">someone took</char> a stalk of <char style="add">a plant called</char> hyssop and <char style="add">fastened</char> a sponge <char style="add">to it. Then</char> he dipped <char style="add">the sponge into the wine and</char> lifted it up to Jesus’ lips. <verse eid="JHN 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 19:30"/>When Jesus tasted the sour wine, he shouted, “<char style="add">I</char> have finished <char style="add">all that I came to do</char>!” Then he bowed his head and ◄died/handed over his spirit <char style="add">to God</char>►.<verse eid="JHN 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 19:31"/>That was the day that they prepared <char style="add">everything for their</char> ◄<char style="add">Sabbath/day of rest</char>►. The next day was a special day of rest, <char style="add">because it was the day of rest during the Passover celebration</char>. The Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN] did not want the bodies <char style="add">of the three men</char> to remain on the cross during their ◄Sabbath/day of rest► <char style="add">because leaving bodies hanging overnight would be contrary to their Jewish laws</char>. So they went to Pilate and asked him <char style="add">to command that</char> the legs <char style="add">of the three men on the crosses</char> be broken {the <char style="add">soldiers</char> to break the legs <char style="add">of the three men on the crosses</char>}, <char style="add">so that they would die quickly</char>. Then their <char style="add">bodies</char> could be taken down <char style="add">and buried</char> {someone could take down their bodies <char style="add">and bury them</char>}. <verse eid="JHN 19:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JHN 19:32"/>So, <char style="add">after Pilate agreed</char>, the soldiers went and broke the legs of the first man whom they had nailed on a cross near Jesus. Then they broke the legs of the second man. <verse eid="JHN 19:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JHN 19:33"/>But when they came to Jesus, they saw that he was dead already. So they did not break his legs. <verse eid="JHN 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JHN 19:34"/>Instead, one of the soldiers pierced Jesus’ side with a spear <char style="add">to make sure that Jesus was dead</char>. Immediately blood <char style="add">clots</char> and <char style="add">other</char> liquid flowed out, <char style="add">which showed that Jesus was really dead</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JHN 19:35"/>I, <char style="add">John</char>, saw this myself, and what I am writing is true. I <char style="add">know that</char> I am telling the truth, and I am saying this in order that you may believe <char style="add">in</char> (OR, <char style="add">my testimony about</char>) <char style="add">Jesus</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JHN 19:36"/>These things happened in order that these words would be fulfilled {to fulfill these words} <char style="add">that are written in</char> Scripture: “Not one of his bones will be broken {No one will break any of his bones}.”<verse eid="JHN 19:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JHN 19:37"/>And <char style="add">they fulfilled</char> another Scripture passage <char style="add">that has these words</char>: ‘They will look on the one whom they have pierced’.<verse eid="JHN 19:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joseph and others put Jesus’ body in a cave.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 19:38-42">John 19:38-42</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JHN 19:38"/>Later, Joseph, from Arimathea <char style="add">town, went to Pilate and</char> asked Pilate <char style="add">to allow him</char> to take Jesus’ body <char style="add">down from the cross</char>. Joseph was a disciple of Jesus, but he did not tell anyone that, because he was afraid of the <char style="add">other</char> Jewish <char style="add">leaders</char> [SYN]. Pilate permitted him to take Jesus’ body, so he went, along <char style="add">with others</char>, and they took Jesus’ body <char style="add">down from the cross</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JHN 19:39"/>Nicodemus was one of them. He was the man who previously went to visit Jesus at night. Nicodemus bought an <char style="add">expensive</char> mixture of myrrh and aloe <char style="add">spices to put on the body</char>. It weighed about ◄75 pounds/35 kilograms►. <verse eid="JHN 19:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JHN 19:40"/>They took the body of Jesus and wrapped strips of linen cloth around it, putting the spices in with the strips of cloth. They did this according to the Jewish customs <char style="add">about burying bodies in tombs</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JHN 19:41"/>Close to the place where Jesus was crucified {where they nailed Jesus to the cross} there was a grove <char style="add">of trees</char>, and <char style="add">at the edge of</char> that grove was a new burial cave. Nobody had ever been put in that cave <char style="add">previously</char>. <verse eid="JHN 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JHN 19:42"/>The Jewish day of rest would start <char style="add">at sunset, and they had to finish burying his body before then</char>. So, since that cave was nearby, they laid Jesus’ body there <char style="add">and rolled a huge stone in front of the entrance</char>.<verse eid="JHN 19:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JHN 20"/>
  <para style="s1">On Sunday morning they discovered that Jesus’ tomb was empty.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 20:1-9">John 20:1-9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 20:1"/>Early on Sunday morning, while it was still dark, Mary, the woman from Magdala <char style="add">village</char>, went to the <char style="add">burial</char> cave <char style="add">with some other women</char>. They saw that the stone had been removed {that someone had removed the stone} from the <char style="add">entrance to the</char> cave. <verse eid="JHN 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 20:2"/>So Mary ran to where Simon Peter and I <char style="add">were staying in Jerusalem</char>. She said to us, “They have taken the Lord’s <char style="add">body</char> out of the burial cave, and we do not know where they have put it!” <verse eid="JHN 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 20:3"/>So Peter and I started going to the cave. <verse eid="JHN 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 20:4"/>We were both running, but I ran faster than Peter and got there first. <verse eid="JHN 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 20:5"/>I stooped down <char style="add">at the entrance</char> and looked inside. I saw the strips of linen cloth lying there <char style="add">where his body had been laid</char>, but I did not go inside. <verse eid="JHN 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 20:6"/>Then Simon Peter, who was running behind me, arrived. He went inside the cave. He, too, saw the strips of linen cloth lying there. <verse eid="JHN 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 20:7"/>He also <char style="add">saw the</char> cloth that they had <char style="add">wrapped</char> around Jesus’ head. It had been folded and put {Someone had folded it and put it} aside, separate from the linen strips. <verse eid="JHN 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 20:8"/>Then I also went inside. I saw <char style="add">those things</char> and I believed <char style="add">that Jesus had truly become alive again</char>. <verse eid="JHN 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 20:9"/>Before this happened, we did not understand from <char style="add">what the prophets had written in</char> the Scriptures, that he had to become alive again after he died.<verse eid="JHN 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus appeared to Mary from Magdala.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 20:10-18">John 20:10-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 20:10"/>Then <char style="add">we two</char> disciples went back to where we were staying. <char style="add">In the meantime</char>, Mary <char style="add">returned to the cave</char>. <verse eid="JHN 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 20:11"/>As she stood outside the cave crying, she stooped down to look inside the cave. <verse eid="JHN 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 20:12"/>She saw two angels in very white <char style="add">clothing</char>, sitting at the place where Jesus’ body had been laid. One was where his head had been, and the other was where his feet had been. <verse eid="JHN 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 20:13"/>They said to her, “Woman, why are you crying?” She said to them, “They have taken away <char style="add">the body of</char> my Lord, and I do not know where they have put it!” <verse eid="JHN 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 20:14"/>After she said that, she turned around and saw Jesus standing <char style="add">there</char>, but she did not know that it was Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 20:15"/>He said to her, “Woman, why are you crying? Who are you looking for?” Thinking that he was the gardener, she said to him, “Sir, if you have taken his <char style="add">body</char> away, tell me where you have put it. Then I will get it <char style="add">and bury it properly</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 20:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 20:16"/>Jesus said to her, “Mary!” She turned toward him <char style="add">again and recognized him</char>. Then she exclaimed in Aramaic, “Rabboni!” which means ‘Teacher’. <verse eid="JHN 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 20:17"/>Jesus said to her, “Stop clinging to me, because I have not yet returned to my Father. Go to my disciples and tell them, ‘I am about to return to my Father and your Father, to the one who is my God and your God’.” <verse eid="JHN 20:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 20:18"/>So Mary went to where <char style="add">we</char> disciples were and told us that she had seen the Lord <char style="add">alive again</char>. She also told us what Jesus said that she <char style="add">should tell us</char>.<verse eid="JHN 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus appeared to many of his disciples.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 20:19-25">John 20:19-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 20:19"/>On that Sunday evening <char style="add">we</char> disciples gathered together. The doors were locked {<char style="add">We</char> locked the doors} because we were afraid that <char style="add">the Jewish leaders</char> [SYN] <char style="add">might arrest us. Suddenly</char> Jesus appeared <char style="add">miraculously</char> and stood among us! He said to us, “May God give you <char style="add">inner</char> peace!” <verse eid="JHN 20:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 20:20"/>After he said that, he showed us <char style="add">the wounds in</char> his hands and his side. We were very happy when we saw the Lord! <verse eid="JHN 20:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 20:21"/>Jesus said to us again, “May God give you peace! Just like <char style="add">my</char> Father sent me, now I am sending you <char style="add">to proclaim my message</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 20:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 20:22"/>After saying that, he breathed on us and said, “Receive the Holy Spirit! <verse eid="JHN 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 20:23"/>If you forgive people for their having sinned, <char style="add">God will already</char> have forgiven them. If you do not forgive them, <char style="add">God</char> has not forgiven them.”<verse eid="JHN 20:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 20:24"/>One of us disciples, Thomas, the one whom we called The Twin, was not with us when Jesus appeared to us. <verse eid="JHN 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 20:25"/>When the rest of us told him that we had seen the Lord, he said to us, “If I do not see the marks of the nails in his hands and put my fingers in the place where the nails were, and put my hands into the place in his side <char style="add">where the soldier thrust the spear</char>, I will certainly not believe <char style="add">that he was the one you saw</char>!”<verse eid="JHN 20:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus appeared to all of his disciples, including Thomas.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 20:26-29">John 20:26-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JHN 20:26"/>A week later we were in <char style="add">the house</char> again. This time Thomas was with us. Although the doors had been locked {<char style="add">we</char> had locked the doors}, Jesus <char style="add">again</char> appeared <char style="add">miraculously</char> and stood among us. He said, “May God give peace to you!” <verse eid="JHN 20:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JHN 20:27"/>Then he <char style="add">showed</char> Thomas <char style="add">his hands</char> and said to him, “Put your finger here! Look at <char style="add">the wounds in</char> my hands! Reach out your hand and put it in <char style="add">the wound in</char> my side! Stop doubting [LIT/DOU]! Instead, believe <char style="add">that I am alive again</char>!” <verse eid="JHN 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JHN 20:28"/>Thomas answered him, “<char style="add">You are truly</char> my Lord and my God!” <verse eid="JHN 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JHN 20:29"/>Jesus said to him, “Because you have seen me, you have believed <char style="add">that about me</char>. But God <char style="add">is truly</char> pleased with those who have believed <char style="add">that about me</char>, even though they have not seen me!”<verse eid="JHN 20:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John stated the purpose of this book.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 20:30-31">John 20:30-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JHN 20:30"/>
    <char style="add">We</char> disciples saw Jesus perform many other miracles, but <char style="add">I</char> have not written about them in this book. <verse eid="JHN 20:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JHN 20:31"/>But these <char style="add">that I have written about, I</char> have written about them in order that you may believe that Jesus is the Messiah, ◄the Son of God/the man who is also God►, and in order that you may have <char style="add">eternal</char> life <char style="add">by trusting</char> ◄in him<char style="add">/</char>in what he <char style="add">has done for you</char>► [MTY].<verse eid="JHN 20:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JHN 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus appeared to seven disciples and enabled them miraculously to catch a lot of fish.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 21:1-14">John 21:1-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JHN 21:1"/>After that, Jesus showed himself to <char style="add">us</char> disciples when we were at Tiberias Lake, <char style="add">which is another name for Galilee Lake</char>. This is what happened: <verse eid="JHN 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JHN 21:2"/>Simon Peter, Thomas who was called {whom <char style="add">we</char> called} The Twin, Nathaniel from Cana <char style="add">town</char> in Galilee, my older brother and I, and two other disciples were together. <verse eid="JHN 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JHN 21:3"/>Simon Peter said to us, “<char style="add">I</char> am going to <char style="add">try to</char> catch some fish.” We said, “We will go with you.” So we went down <char style="add">to the lake</char> and got into the boat. But that night we caught nothing. <verse eid="JHN 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JHN 21:4"/>Early the next morning, Jesus stood on the shore, but we did not know that it was Jesus. <verse eid="JHN 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JHN 21:5"/>He called out to us, “My friends, you have not <char style="add">caught</char> any fish, have you?” We answered, “You are correct, <char style="add">we have not caught any</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JHN 21:6"/>He said to us, “Throw your net out from the right-hand side of the boat! Then you will find some!” We did that, and we caught so many fish <char style="add">in the net</char> that we were unable to pull the net into <char style="add">the boat</char>! <verse eid="JHN 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JHN 21:7"/><char style="add">But I knew that it was Jesus</char>, <char style="add">so</char> I said to Peter, “It is the Lord!” Peter had taken off his cloak <char style="add">while he was working</char>, but as soon as he heard <char style="add">me say</char> “It is the Lord!” he wrapped his cloak around himself and jumped into the water <char style="add">and swam to shore</char>. <verse eid="JHN 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JHN 21:8"/>The rest of us came <char style="add">to the shore</char> in the boat, pulling the net full of fish. We were not far from shore, only about 100 yards/meters. <verse eid="JHN 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JHN 21:9"/>When <char style="add">we</char> got to the shore, we saw that there was a fire of burning coals there, with a <char style="add">large</char> fish on the fire, and <char style="add">some</char> buns. <verse eid="JHN 21:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JHN 21:10"/>Jesus said to us, “Bring some of the fish that you have just caught!” <verse eid="JHN 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JHN 21:11"/>Simon Peter got in <char style="add">the boat</char> and dragged the net to the shore. It was full of large fish. There were 153 of them! But in spite of there being so many fish, the net was not torn. <verse eid="JHN 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JHN 21:12"/>Jesus said to us, “Come and eat some breakfast!” None of us dared to ask him, “Who are you?” because we knew that it was the Lord. <verse eid="JHN 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JHN 21:13"/>Jesus took the buns and gave them to us. He did the same with the fish. <verse eid="JHN 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JHN 21:14"/>That was the third time that Jesus appeared to <char style="add">us</char> disciples after <char style="add">God</char> caused him to become alive again after he died.<verse eid="JHN 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus asked Peter three times if he really loved Jesus. Then Jesus told Peter how Peter would die.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 21:15-19">John 21:15-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JHN 21:15"/>When we had finished eating, Jesus said to Simon Peter, “John’s <char style="add">son</char> Simon, do you love me more than these <char style="add">other disciples do</char>?” Peter said to him, “Yes, Lord, you know that you are dear to me (OR, that I love you).” Jesus said, “Give to <char style="add">those who belong to</char> me <char style="add">what they need spiritually, like</char> [MET] <char style="add">a shepherd provides</char> food for his lambs.” <verse eid="JHN 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JHN 21:16"/>Jesus said to him again, “John’s <char style="add">son</char> Simon, do you love me?” He replied, “Yes, Lord, you know that you are dear to me (OR, that I love you).” Jesus said to him, “Take care of <char style="add">those who belong to</char> me, <char style="add">like</char> [MET] a <char style="add">shepherd takes care of his</char> sheep.” <verse eid="JHN 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JHN 21:17"/>Jesus said to him a third time, “John’s son Simon, am I really dear to you (OR, do you really love me)?” Peter was grieved because Jesus asked him this three times, <char style="add">and because the third time he changed the question</char>. He said, “Lord, you know everything. You know that you are dear to me (OR, that I love you).” Jesus said, “Give to <char style="add">those who belong to</char> me <char style="add">what they need spiritually, as</char> [MET] <char style="add">a shepherd provides</char> food for <char style="add">his</char> sheep. <verse eid="JHN 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JHN 21:18"/>Now listen to this carefully: When you were young, you put your clothes on by yourself, and you went wherever you wanted to go. But when you are old, you will stretch out your arms, and someone will fasten them <char style="add">with a rope</char> and will lead you to a place where you do not want to <char style="add">go</char>.” <verse eid="JHN 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JHN 21:19"/>Jesus said this to indicate how Peter would die ◄<char style="add">violently/on a cross</char>► in order to honor God. Then Jesus said to him, “Keep being my faithful disciple <char style="add">until you die</char>.”<verse eid="JHN 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Peter asked Jesus what would happen to John.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 21:20-23">John 21:20-23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JHN 21:20"/>Peter turned around and saw that I was following them. I was the one who leaned close to Jesus during the <char style="add">Passover</char> meal and said, “Lord, who is going to enable your enemies to seize you?” <verse eid="JHN 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JHN 21:21"/>When Peter saw me, he asked, “Lord, what <char style="add">is going to happen</char> to him?” <verse eid="JHN 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JHN 21:22"/>Jesus said to him, “If I want him to remain <char style="add">alive</char> until I return, ◄that is not your concern!/what is that to you?► [RHQ] You be my <char style="add">faithful</char> disciple!” <verse eid="JHN 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JHN 21:23"/>Some of the other believers heard <char style="add">a report of</char> what Jesus had said about me, and <char style="add">they thought that Jesus meant</char> that I would not die. But Jesus did not say that I would not die. He said only, “If I want him to remain <char style="add">alive</char> until I return, ◄that is not your concern!/what is that to you?► [RHQ]”<verse eid="JHN 21:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A statement about the truth and accuracy of this document.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="JHN 21:24-25">John 21:24-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JHN 21:24"/>
    <char style="add">I, John</char>, am the disciple who has seen all these things and I have written them down.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JHN 21:24">My <char style="add">fellow apostles</char> and I know that what <char style="add">I have written</char> is true.<verse eid="JHN 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JHN 21:25"/>Jesus did many other things. If they would <char style="add">all</char> be written {If people would write them <char style="add">all</char>} down <char style="add">in detail</char>, I suppose that the whole world would not have enough space [HYP] to contain the books that would be written {that they would write} <char style="add">about what he did</char>.<verse eid="JHN 21:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JHN 21"/>
</usx>
