<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="JOS" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">JOSHUA</para>
  <para style="toc1">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc2">Joshua</para>
  <para style="toc3">Jos</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of the Israeli people possessing the land that God had promised to give them. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Joshua</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="JOS 1"/>
  <para style="s1">What Yahweh commanded Joshua</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 1:1"/>After Moses, who served Yahweh <char style="add">well</char>, died, Yahweh said to Nun’s son Joshua, who had been Moses’ assistant, <verse eid="JOS 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 1:2"/>“<char style="add">You know that</char> my servant Moses is <char style="add">now</char> dead. So now get ready to lead all these <char style="add">Israeli</char> people across the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. Enter the land that I will soon give to you. <verse eid="JOS 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 1:3"/>I will give to you all the land that you walk on, as I promised Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 1:4"/>That land will extend from the desert <char style="add">in the south</char>, to the Lebanon <char style="add">Mountains in the northwest</char>, and to the big Euphrates River <char style="add">in the northeast</char>, and to the Mediterranean Sea on the west. <char style="add">It will include</char> all the land where the descendants of Heth <char style="add">live</char>. <verse eid="JOS 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 1:5"/>No group will be able to oppose <char style="add">and defeat</char> you during your life. I will help you as I helped Moses. I will always be with [LIT] you; I will never forsake you.<verse eid="JOS 1:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 1:6"/>“Be strong and courageous, because you are the one who will lead these Israeli people <char style="add">and enable them</char> to possess the land that I solemnly promised to their ancestors that I would give them. <verse eid="JOS 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 1:7"/>Just be strong and very courageous. Be sure to obey all the laws that my servant Moses gave to you. In order that you may be successful wherever you go, do not stop obeying any of them [IDM]. <verse eid="JOS 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 1:8"/>Make sure to habitually read <char style="add">to the people some of</char> the laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char>. Meditate on those laws <char style="add">every</char> day and <char style="add">every</char> night. And be sure to obey all those laws. If you do that, you will be successful in everything that you do [DOU]. <verse eid="JOS 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 1:9"/>Do not forget [RHQ] that I have commanded you to be strong and courageous. Do not be afraid, and do not be discouraged, because I, Yahweh, your God, will ◄be with/help► you wherever you go.”<verse eid="JOS 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 1:10"/>Then Joshua commanded the leaders of the people of Israel, <verse eid="JOS 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 1:11"/>“Go throughout the camp and tell the people this: ‘Prepare all the food that you will take with you, because the day after tomorrow you will cross this Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, in order to possess the land that Yahweh, our God, is about to give you.’ ”<verse eid="JOS 1:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">What Joshua commanded the eastern tribes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 1:12"/>But to the <char style="add">clans that were</char> descendants of Reuben and Gad, and to the half clan <char style="add">that were descendants</char> of Manasseh, Joshua said, <verse eid="JOS 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 1:13"/>“Do not forget what Moses, the servant of Yahweh, commanded you: ‘Yahweh, your God, has given you this land in order that you can <char style="add">live here</char> safely/peacefully.’ <verse eid="JOS 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 1:14"/>Your wives and your children and your livestock may stay <char style="add">here</char> in this land on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, but all your soldiers must cross <char style="add">the river</char>, ahead of the people of the other tribes. They must take all their weapons with them. You must continue to help your fellow Israelis <verse eid="JOS 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 1:15"/>until they are able to live there safely/peacefully, as Yahweh has enabled you to do. You must help them until after they have conquered all the people in the land that Yahweh, your God, is giving them. After that, your soldiers may return to live in this land that Moses gave to you here on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 1:16"/>The people answered Joshua, “We will do everything that you have commanded us to do, and we will go wherever you tell us to go. <verse eid="JOS 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 1:17"/>As we obeyed all that Moses told us to do, we will obey all that you tell us to do. We pray that Yahweh will ◄be with/help► you as he ◄was with/helped► Moses. <verse eid="JOS 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 1:18"/>Anyone who ◄rejects what you say/opposes you► and does not obey what you command [DOU], we will execute. But we want you to be strong and courageous!”<verse eid="JOS 1:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="JOS 2"/>
  <para style="s1">How Rahab helped the Israeli spies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 2:1"/>Then Joshua <char style="add">chose</char> two men from <char style="add">their camp at</char> Acacia. He told them, “Go <char style="add">across the Jordan River</char> and secretly find out all that you can about the land on that side of the river, especially about Jericho <char style="add">city</char>.” So the two men crossed <char style="add">the river and entered Jericho</char>. They entered the house of a prostitute, whose name was Rahab. They stayed in her house <char style="add">that night</char>. <verse eid="JOS 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 2:2"/>But someone <char style="add">saw them and</char> told the king of Jericho, “Some Israeli men have come here tonight to spy out the land!” <verse eid="JOS 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 2:3"/>So the king sent some messengers to tell Rahab, “Bring out the men who came and entered your house, <char style="add">so that we can kill them</char>, because they have come <char style="add">here</char> to ◄spy out/find out all they can about► this land!” <verse eid="JOS 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 2:4"/>She told them that the two men had gone to her house. But she had hidden the two men there. So when the messengers came to her house, she told them, “Two men came here, but I did not know where they had come from. <verse eid="JOS 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 2:5"/>At dusk, just before ◄guards closed the city gate/the city gates were closed►, the two men left. I do not know where they went. So, go quickly and search for them! Perhaps you may catch them!” <verse eid="JOS 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 2:6"/>But <char style="add">she was lying,</char> she had taken the two men up to the <char style="add">flat</char> roof of her house and had hidden them under the piles of flax that she had laid on the roof. <verse eid="JOS 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 2:7"/>The messengers went out of the city to search for the two men. Immediately, the guards shut the city gate. The messengers went along the road that leads down to the place where people can walk across the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, <char style="add">but they did not find the two men</char>.<verse eid="JOS 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 2:8"/>Before the two men lay down <char style="add">to sleep</char> that night, Rahab went up to the roof <verse eid="JOS 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 2:9"/>and said to them, “We know that Yahweh <char style="add">is about to</char> give this land to you Israelis, and as a result all the people living in this land are terrified because of you. <verse eid="JOS 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 2:10"/>We have heard about how Yahweh dried up the water of the Red Sea for you to cross it when you left Egypt. And we have heard how you killed Sihon and Og, the two kings of the tribe of Amor who lived east of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. You <char style="add">Israelis</char> totally destroyed everyone <char style="add">and everything in their kingdom</char>. <verse eid="JOS 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 2:11"/>When we heard about those things, we were very dismayed. We no longer have enough courage to fight against you, because we know that Yahweh, the God whom you <char style="add">worship</char>, is helping you. <char style="add">And we know that</char> he rules everything in heaven and here on earth. <verse eid="JOS 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 2:12"/>So now <char style="add">I want you to</char> solemnly promise me, and ask Yahweh to punish you if you do not do what you promise. Solemnly promise me that you will act kindly to me and my family, because I have acted kindly to you. <verse eid="JOS 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 2:13"/>Do something to prove that you will ◄spare the lives of/not kill► my father and my mother, my brothers and sisters, and all of their families. Promise me that you <char style="add">Israelis</char> will not kill us <char style="add">when you destroy this city</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 2:14"/>The two men replied, “We desire that God will cause us to die if we do not do as we say! If you do not tell others what we <char style="add">are planning to</char> do, we will act kindly toward you all when Yahweh enables us to possess the land.” <verse eid="JOS 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 2:15"/><char style="add">One of</char> the outside walls of the house where Rahab lived was part of the wall <char style="add">that was around</char> the city. So she fastened a rope outside the window <char style="add">that was in that wall</char>, by which the men could climb down the wall. <verse eid="JOS 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 2:16"/>Then she said to them, “When you leave the city, go up into the hills so that the men who are searching for you will not find you. Hide in caves in the hills for three days, until the men who are searching for you return to the city. Then you can return safely to your camp.” <verse eid="JOS 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 2:17"/>The two men <char style="add">gave her a red cord, and</char> said to her, “This is what you must do; if you do not do this, we will not be required to do what we have vowed to do. <verse eid="JOS 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 2:18"/>You must tie this red cord in the window that has the rope by which we will climb down. You must let the cord hang there. And you must bring your father and your mother and your brothers and all the others in your family inside the house. Then, when our army enters your land, we will see the cord, and we will not kill the people in your house. <verse eid="JOS 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 2:19"/>If anyone in your family goes outside this house into the street, <char style="add">our soldiers</char> will kill them, and we will not be guilty [MTY] for doing that. But if anyone who is in this house with you is injured, we will be guilty for causing that. <verse eid="JOS 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 2:20"/>But if you tell anyone what we <char style="add">are planning to</char> do, we are not required to do what we have vowed to do.” <verse eid="JOS 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 2:21"/>Rahab said, “I agree to do what you say.” So they climbed down the rope and left. And she left the red cord tied in the window. <verse eid="JOS 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 2:22"/>When the two men left the city, they went up into the hills. They stayed there for three days, while the men <char style="add">who had been sent by the king</char> continued to search for them. They searched all along the road, but they did not find the two men. So they returned to the city. <verse eid="JOS 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 2:23"/>Then the two men started back toward their camp. They went down from the hills, went down to the river, crossed it at the place where people can walk across it, and returned to their camp. They told Joshua everything that had happened to them. <verse eid="JOS 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 2:24"/>They said to Joshua, “We are sure that Yahweh is going to enable us to possess everything that is in that land. The people there are terrified [IDM] because of us.”<verse eid="JOS 2:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="JOS 3"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis crossed the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 3:1"/>Joshua <char style="add">and all the other Israelis</char> got up early <char style="add">the next</char> morning. They left <char style="add">their camp at</char> Acacia and went <char style="add">down</char> to the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. They camped there for two nights. <verse eid="JOS 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 3:2"/>Then the leaders went throughout the camp, <verse eid="JOS 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 3:3"/>telling the people, “You will see some of the priests, who are descendants of Levi, carrying the chest that contains the Ten Commandments that Yahweh our God gave us. When you see them, leave the places where you are camped and follow them. <verse eid="JOS 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 3:4"/>You have not been ◄here/along this road► before, <char style="add">so you must follow the priests</char>. But do not walk close to the chest. Stay ◄1,000 yards/900 meters► from the chest. <char style="add">The chest is sacred, so ◄God will punish you/you will be punished► if you come close to it</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 3:5"/>Then Joshua told the people, “Perform the ceremonies needed to make yourselves acceptable to Yahweh, because tomorrow he is going to do things for you that will amaze you!”<verse eid="JOS 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 3:6"/>Then Joshua said to the priests, “Carry the chest and go in front of the <char style="add">rest of the</char> people.” So they lifted up the chest and went ahead.<verse eid="JOS 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 3:7"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “This is the day that I will begin to show all the Israeli people that you are a great leader. Then they will honor you, and know that I am with/helping you as I ◄was with/helped► Moses. <verse eid="JOS 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 3:8"/>Tell the priests who are carrying the chest that contains the Ten Commandments, ‘When you come to the edge of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, stand in the water.’” <verse eid="JOS 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 3:9"/>Then Joshua said to the Israeli people, “Come close to me in order that you can listen to what Yahweh, your God, is saying.” <verse eid="JOS 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 3:10"/><char style="add">When they came near</char>, he said to them, “This is how you will know that God, who is all-powerful, is among you, and that he will expel for you the descendants of Canaan, Heth, Hiv, Periz, Girgash, Amor, and Jebus <char style="add">who are now living in that land</char>. <verse eid="JOS 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 3:11"/>Keep in mind that Yahweh is the one who rules over all the earth. The chest belongs to him, and it will be carried into the Jordan River ahead of you. <verse eid="JOS 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 3:12"/>So choose twelve men, <char style="add">one from each</char> of the tribes of Israel, <char style="add">and I will tell you later what I want them to do</char>. <verse eid="JOS 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 3:13"/>As for the priests who are carrying the chest, as soon as they put their feet into the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, the water will stop flowing. It will pile up because I will cause it to be blocked upstream.”<verse eid="JOS 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 3:14"/>So when the <char style="add">Israeli</char> people packed up their tents in order to cross the river, the priests who were carrying the chest containing the Ten Commandments went in front of them. <verse eid="JOS 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 3:15"/><char style="add">It was springtime</char>, when people harvest their crops, <char style="add">and </char> at that time the river floods over its banks. But as soon as the priests reached the edge of the river and stepped into the water, <verse eid="JOS 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 3:16"/>the water stopped flowing. The water piled up far <char style="add">upstream</char>, at a town named Adam, near Zarethan. The water stopped flowing down to the Dead Sea. So the people were able to cross the river near Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 3:17"/>The priests who were carrying the chest containing the Ten Commandments that Yahweh <char style="add">had given them</char> stood on dry ground in the middle of the Jordan <char style="add">riverbed</char>, while the rest of the Israeli people crossed the river <char style="add">as though they were crossing</char> dry ground.<verse eid="JOS 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="JOS 4"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israeli people and Joshua set up memorials</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 4:1"/>After all the people of the Israeli nation had finished crossing the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, Yahweh said to Joshua, <verse eid="JOS 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 4:2"/>“When you choose the twelve men, one from each tribe, whom I mentioned previously, tell them to pick up <char style="add">large</char> stones from the middle of the Jordan riverbed, where the priests are <char style="add">still</char> standing. <verse eid="JOS 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 4:3"/>Tell them to carry the stones with you and put them down at the place where you will stay tonight.”<verse eid="JOS 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 4:4"/>So Joshua chose twelve men, one from each tribe. He called them together, and said to them, <verse eid="JOS 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 4:5"/>“Go into the middle of the Jordan riverbed, to <char style="add">where the priests are standing, holding</char> the chest that Yahweh, your God, gave you. Each of you must pick up a <char style="add">large</char> stone, one for each tribe, <char style="add">and carry it</char> on your shoulder <char style="add">to our camp</char>. <verse eid="JOS 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 4:6"/><char style="add">Then pile them up</char> to be a memorial for you. In the future, when your children ask, ‘What do these stones mean?’, <verse eid="JOS 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 4:7"/>tell them that the water in the Jordan River was blocked off when the priests were carrying the chest <char style="add">that contained</char> the Ten Commandments that Yahweh <char style="add">gave us</char>. When the chest was carried into the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, the water was blocked off <char style="add">so that we could cross the riverbed</char>. These stones will be a memorial for the descendants of us Israeli people forever.”<verse eid="JOS 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 4:8"/>So those Israeli men did what Joshua told them to do. They went and picked up twelve <char style="add">large</char> stones from the middle of the Jordan <char style="add">riverbed</char>, one stone for each of the tribes, just as Yahweh had told Joshua. They carried the stones to their camp and put them down. <verse eid="JOS 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 4:9"/>Then Joshua set up twelve <char style="add">other large</char> stones <char style="add">in a pile</char>, in the middle of the Jordan <char style="add">riverbed</char>, where the priests who carried the chest containing the Ten Commandments were standing. And those stones are still there.<verse eid="JOS 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 4:10"/>The priests who carried the chest remained standing in the middle of the Jordan <char style="add">riverbed</char> until the people had finished doing everything that Yahweh had commanded Joshua to tell them to do. Those were the same instructions that Moses had given to Joshua. The Israeli people crossed <char style="add">the riverbed</char> quickly. <verse eid="JOS 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 4:11"/>As soon as all of them had crossed, as the people watched, the priests carried the chest <char style="add">the rest of the way across the river</char>. <verse eid="JOS 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 4:12"/>The soldiers of the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and of half of the soldiers of the tribe of Manasseh, crossed over ahead of the rest of the Israeli people, carrying their weapons, as Moses had commanded. <verse eid="JOS 4:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 4:13"/>As Yahweh was watching, there were about 40,000 of those soldiers, carrying weapons ready for battle, who crossed the riverbed to the plains near Jericho, <char style="add">ready</char> to fight.<verse eid="JOS 4:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 4:14"/>On that day, all the people of Israel saw that Yahweh had caused Joshua to be a great leader. And they honored Joshua for the rest of his life, just as they had honored Moses. <verse eid="JOS 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 4:15"/>Yahweh said to Joshua, <verse eid="JOS 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 4:16"/>“<char style="add">Now</char> tell the priests who are carrying the chest containing the Ten Commandments to come up from the Jordan <char style="add">riverbed</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 4:17"/>So Joshua commanded the priests to do that. <verse eid="JOS 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 4:18"/>Then the priests, carrying the chest containing the Ten Commandments that Yahweh <char style="add">had given to Moses</char>, came up out of the riverbed. And as soon as they walked up out of the riverbed onto the riverbank, the water of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> flowed again, and flooded <char style="add">over the river banks</char> as it had done before.<verse eid="JOS 4:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 4:19"/>It was on the tenth day of the first month <char style="add">of that year</char> that the people crossed over the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and camped at <char style="add">a place called</char> Gilgal, on the east side of <char style="add">the land near</char> Jericho <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="JOS 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 4:20"/>The men <char style="add">who were carrying</char> the twelve <char style="add">large</char> stones from the Jordan <char style="add">riverbed brought them to</char> Joshua, <char style="add">and he</char> set them up at Gilgal <verse eid="JOS 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 4:21"/>Joshua said to the Israeli people, “In the future, when your children and grandchildren ask, ‘◄What do these stones <char style="add">mean/Why are these stones here►</char>?’, <verse eid="JOS 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 4:22"/>tell them, ‘We Israeli people crossed the Jordan <char style="add">River as though we were crossing</char> on dry ground. <verse eid="JOS 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 4:23"/>As we were watching, Yahweh, your God, dried up the river until we had all crossed over. Yahweh, the God whom we worship, did to the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> just like he did to the Red Sea, when he caused it to become dry as <char style="add">our parents</char> were watching, until they all crossed over it. <verse eid="JOS 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 4:24"/>Yahweh did that in order that all the people-groups of the earth may know that he [MTY] is very powerful, and in order that you may always ◄be in awe of/revere► Yahweh, your God.’”<verse eid="JOS 4:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="JOS 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 5:1"/>All the kings of the people-groups to the west of the Jordan River and all the kings of the groups who were descendants of Canaan and who lived close to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea heard about how Yahweh had dried up the water of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> until all we Israeli people had crossed over. So they became very dismayed. They no longer were courageous enough to fight us.<verse eid="JOS 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Israeli males were circumcised at Gilgal</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 5:2"/>While <char style="add">they were camped at Gilgal</char>, Yahweh said to Joshua, “<char style="add">The Israeli males who lived in Egypt were circumcised before they left there. Now</char> make knives from flint stones and circumcise all the Israeli males <char style="add">who have been born since then</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 5:3"/>So Joshua <char style="add">made knives and</char> circumcised the Israeli males at a place that is now called ‘Circumcision Hill’. <verse eid="JOS 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 5:4"/><char style="add">The reason they did that is that all the men who left Egypt</char>, those who were old enough to be soldiers, died in the desert after they left Egypt. <verse eid="JOS 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 5:5"/>They had been circumcised in Egypt, but the baby boys who had been born while their parents were camping in the desert after they left Egypt had not been circumcised. <verse eid="JOS 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 5:6"/>Our Israeli ancestors traveled around in the desert for 40 years, and all the men who were old enough to be soldiers had died. <char style="add">The women had also died</char>. They had not obeyed Yahweh, so Yahweh said that they would not arrive at the land that he had promised to our ancestors that he would give to us, a land that was very fertile [MTY]. <verse eid="JOS 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 5:7"/>The sons of those who had disobeyed Yahweh were the ones whom Joshua circumcised at Gilgal. They were circumcised because they had not been circumcised <char style="add">while they were traveling in the desert</char>. <verse eid="JOS 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 5:8"/>After all the Israeli males had been circumcised, they remained in the camp and rested until their wounds were healed. <verse eid="JOS 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 5:9"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “<char style="add">Because your forefathers were slaves in Egypt</char>, the Egyptians felt a revulsion toward you. But today I have removed the revulsion the Egyptians have had toward you.” Because of that, the people called the place ‘Gilgal’, <char style="add">which sounds like the Hebrew word ‘removed’,</char> and it still has that name.<verse eid="JOS 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 5:10"/>In the evening of the fourteenth day of that month, while the Israeli people were camped at Gilgal, on the plain near Jericho <char style="add">city</char>, they celebrated the Passover <char style="add">Festival</char>. <verse eid="JOS 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 5:11"/>The next day, they found some barley grain in the fields in that area. So they took that and roasted it and ate it with bread that was made without yeast. <verse eid="JOS 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 5:12"/>The next day, <char style="add">God</char> stopped <char style="add">sending </char> manna for the Israeli people to eat. After that, they ate food that was grown in Canaan.<verse eid="JOS 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The commander of Yahweh’s army appeared to Joshua.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 5:13"/>One day when Joshua came near Jericho, he looked up and saw a man standing in front of him. The man was holding a sword in his hand. Joshua approached him and asked him, “Are you <char style="add">going to fight</char> for us or against us?” <verse eid="JOS 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 5:14"/>The man replied, “I am not <char style="add">planning to fight with you</char> or <char style="add">against you</char>. Instead, I am the commander of Yahweh’s army <char style="add">in heaven</char>, and I have come <char style="add">down from there to assure you that Yahweh will help you</char>.” Then Joshua bowed down with his face on the ground ◄to show his respect for/to worship► the man, and said to him, “Tell me what <char style="add">you want me to do</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 5:15"/>The commander of Yahweh’s army replied, “Take off your sandals! <char style="add">I am Yahweh, and</char> the ground on which you are standing is holy because I am here.” So Joshua took off his sandals.<verse eid="JOS 5:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="JOS 6"/>
  <para style="s1">The walls of Jericho collapsed and the Israelis captured the city.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 6:1"/>Meanwhile, the guards of Jericho shut the gates of the city tightly, because <char style="add">they were afraid</char> of the Israeli <char style="add">army</char>. No one was allowed to go into the city or go out of it. <verse eid="JOS 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 6:2"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “Listen <char style="add">to what I say</char>! I am going to enable your army [SYN] to capture/conquer [MTY] Jericho and its king and its soldiers. <verse eid="JOS 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 6:3"/>So your army must march around the city for six days, once each day. <verse eid="JOS 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 6:4"/>Tell seven priests to march around with them. Each priest must carry a trumpet. Four other priests must carry the sacred chest, and they must walk behind the priests who are carrying the trumpets. On the seventh day, the army must march around the city seven times, and the priests must be blowing the trumpets while they march. <verse eid="JOS 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 6:5"/><char style="add">After they have all marched around the city seven times</char>, the priests must blow their trumpets <char style="add">once</char>, very loudly. When the Israeli people/soldiers hear that, they must shout loudly. Then the wall of the city will collapse, and all the Israeli people/soldiers will go straight into the city.”<verse eid="JOS 6:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 6:6"/>So Joshua summoned the priests and said to them, “Tell four priests to carry the chest <char style="add">that contains</char> the Ten Commandments that Yahweh <char style="add">gave to us</char>. <char style="add">Tell</char> seven <char style="add">other</char> priests to carry trumpets and walk in front of them.” <verse eid="JOS 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 6:7"/>And Joshua told the soldiers, “Start marching! March around the city, with several soldiers with weapons marching in front. Behind them will march the seven priests with trumpets, and behind them will march the four priests carrying Yahweh’s <char style="add">sacred</char> chest.”<verse eid="JOS 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 6:8"/>After Joshua told that to the army, the seven priests, each carrying a sacred trumpet, started marching, blowing their trumpets. The four priests who were carrying Yahweh’s sacred chest followed them. <verse eid="JOS 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 6:9"/>The group of soldiers carrying weapons marched in front of the priests who were blowing their trumpets, and the rest of the soldiers followed <char style="add">the four men carrying</char> the chest. While <char style="add">they were all marching</char>, <char style="add">the seven priests</char> were blowing their trumpets. <verse eid="JOS 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 6:10"/>But <char style="add">the rest of</char> the people <char style="add">were silent, because</char> Joshua had commanded them, “Do not make a war cry. Do not yell or say anything until the day when I tell you to shout. On that day, you must shout <char style="add">loudly</char>!” <verse eid="JOS 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 6:11"/>So the men carrying Yahweh’s sacred chest and all the others did what Joshua told them to do. They marched around the city once. Then they all returned to their camp and stayed there that night.<verse eid="JOS 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 6:12"/>The next morning, Joshua and the priests got up early, and the four priests carried Yahweh’s sacred chest <char style="add">again</char>. <verse eid="JOS 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 6:13"/>The seven priests who were carrying trumpets went in front of <char style="add">the men carrying</char> the chest. The seven priests were blowing their trumpets as they marched. The group of soldiers carrying weapons went in front of all the others, and the rest of the army followed all the others. All the time, the seven priests were blowing their trumpets. <verse eid="JOS 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 6:14"/>So on that second day they again marched around the city once and then returned to their camp. They did the same thing for six days.<verse eid="JOS 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 6:15"/>On the seventh day, they got up at dawn, and they all marched around the city the same way that they had done before, but this time they marched around the city seven times. <verse eid="JOS 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 6:16"/>As they were marching around the seventh time, when the priests were about to blow the long/loud blast on their trumpets, Joshua commanded the people, “Shout, because Yahweh will enable you to capture the city! <verse eid="JOS 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 6:17"/>Yahweh has declared that you must destroy [IDM] the city and everything in it <char style="add">to show that it belongs to him</char>. You must spare only Rahab the prostitute and the others who are in her house, because she hid the spies whom we sent there. <verse eid="JOS 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 6:18"/>And because Yahweh has declared that everything must be destroyed [IDM], you must not take [EUP] any of the things in the city. If you take anything, you will cause Yahweh to destroy our own camp and cause terrible things to happen to us. <verse eid="JOS 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 6:19"/>But all the silver and gold and articles made from iron and bronze that you find, you must set apart for Yahweh. You must put those things in his treasury.”<verse eid="JOS 6:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 6:20"/>So they did what Joshua told them to do. When the priests blew a long blast on their trumpets, the people/army shouted loudly, and the wall of the city collapsed! Then the Israeli soldiers rushed in and captured the city. <verse eid="JOS 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 6:21"/>They killed [IDM] every living thing in the city—men and women, young people and old people, even cattle and sheep and donkeys.<verse eid="JOS 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 6:22"/>Then Joshua said to the two men ◄who had spied on/whom he had sent to learn all they could about► the land, “Go to the prostitute’s house. Bring her out, along with all her family, just as you promised to her.” <verse eid="JOS 6:22"/><verse number="23-25" style="v" sid="JOS 6:23-25"/>So those two spies/men went into Rahab’s house and brought her out. They also brought out her father and mother and her brothers, and all the rest of her family. Joshua’s men spared Rahab the prostitute. They also did not kill all her relatives, because she had hidden and protected the spies/men whom Joshua had sent to Jericho. The two men brought them all out and put them in a place outside the camp of the Israelis. Rahab still lives among us Israeli people. Then the soldiers gathered the articles made from silver, gold, bronze, and iron that they found and they put them all into Yahweh’s treasury. But they burned everything else that was in the city.<verse eid="JOS 6:23-25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 6:26"/>At that time, Joshua warned the people, “Yahweh will curse/punish anyone who tries to rebuild this city, Jericho. When that person lays/builds its foundation, his oldest son will die. And when he finishes building the city wall and sets up its gates, his youngest son will die.”<verse eid="JOS 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 6:27"/>Because of what happened that day, it was clear that Yahweh was with/helped Joshua, and Joshua became famous throughout the land.<verse eid="JOS 6:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="JOS 7"/>
  <para style="s1">The men of Ai defeated the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 7:1"/>Yahweh had commanded that all the things <char style="add">that they had captured in Jericho</char> should be <char style="add">destroyed to show that they belong</char> to him. But there was a man from the tribe of Judah named Achan. He was the son of Carmi and grandson of Zabdi and great-grandson of Zerah. He disobeyed <char style="add">what</char> Yahweh <char style="add">had commanded</char> and took for himself some of those things. So Yahweh was very angry with the Israelis.<verse eid="JOS 7:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 7:2"/>Joshua told some of his men to go from Jericho to Ai <char style="add">town</char>, which was east of Bethel <char style="add">city</char> and near Beth-Aven <char style="add">town</char>. He said to them, “Go to Ai and ◄spy out the area/see what the area is like►.” So the men went.<verse eid="JOS 7:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 7:3"/>When they returned to Joshua they said, “There are only a few people in Ai. So we do not need to send all of our soldiers to defeat them. Send 2.000 or 3,000 men to attack them. That will be enough.” <verse eid="JOS 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 7:4"/>So about 3,000 Israeli men went <char style="add">to attack Ai</char>. But the men of Ai defeated them badly. <verse eid="JOS 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 7:5"/>They killed about 36 Israelis and chased the rest of Israeli men from the city gate to the bottom of the hill. When the other Israelis saw that this had happened, they became very discouraged.<verse eid="JOS 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 7:6"/>Joshua and the other Israeli leaders tore their clothes <char style="add">because they were very sad about being defeated</char>. They prostrated themselves on the ground in front of <char style="add">the Sacred Tent in which was</char> the sacred chest. They stayed there until that evening. They also threw dirt on their heads <char style="add">to show that they were very sad about what had happened</char>. <verse eid="JOS 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 7:7"/>Then Joshua prayed and said, “Lord God, you brought us Israelis <char style="add">safely</char> across the Jordan River. So why are you now allowing the Amor people-group to defeat us [RHQ]? <char style="add">This would not have happened</char> if we had stayed on the other side of the Jordan River! <verse eid="JOS 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 7:8"/>Lord, we Israelis have been defeated by our enemies, so I do not know what to say now [RHQ]. <verse eid="JOS 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 7:9"/>The Canaan people-group and all the other people who are living in this land will hear about this. Then they will surround us and kill all of us! Then what will you do ◄to defend your reputation [MTY]/to show that you are a powerful God►?”<verse eid="JOS 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 7:10"/>But Yahweh said to Joshua, “Stand up! Stop lying there with your face on the ground [RHQ]! <verse eid="JOS 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 7:11"/>You Israelis have sinned! You have disobeyed the commands that I told you to obey. <char style="add">One of</char> your men has taken some of the things that I told you to destroy. He has stolen them and taken them for himself and lied <char style="add">about it</char>. <verse eid="JOS 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 7:12"/>That is why you Israelis have been unable to be strong when you went to attack your enemies. That is why you have run away from them. And now you yourselves may be destroyed. If you do not do as I commanded you and destroy everything <char style="add">that you captured in Jericho</char> I will not help you any more!”<verse eid="JOS 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Achan was punished for his sin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 7:13"/>“Now go and tell this to the people: ‘Tomorrow you must <char style="add">perform the rituals that will</char> cause yourselves to become acceptable to Yahweh again. Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, says that one of you has kept things that he told you to destroy. You will never defeat your enemies until you get rid of those things.<verse eid="JOS 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 7:14"/>‘Tomorrow morning you must present yourselves before Yahweh, tribe by tribe. Then Yahweh will indicate to which tribe <char style="add">the man who took those things belongs</char>. Then Yahweh will indicate to which clan from that tribe <char style="add">the guilty man belongs</char>. Then Yahweh will indicate to which family he belongs. And then he will indicate which person <char style="add">in that family took those things</char>. <verse eid="JOS 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 7:15"/>Then the one who has taken some of the things that should have been destroyed will be destroyed in a fire. And everything he owns will be destroyed with him, because he has disobeyed the command that Yahweh gave us and has done something that is disgraceful to us Israeli people.’”<verse eid="JOS 7:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 7:16"/>Early the next morning, Joshua told all the Israeli people to stand before the Sacred Tent, tribe by tribe. <char style="add">When they did that</char>, Yahweh indicated that a man from the tribe of Judah <char style="add">was the one who had taken the things</char>. <verse eid="JOS 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 7:17"/>Then the clans of Judah presented themselves, and Yahweh indicated that someone from the clan of Zerah was the guilty one. Then the families of Zerah’s clan presented themselves, and Yahweh indicated that someone from the family of Zabdi <char style="add">was the guilty one</char>. <verse eid="JOS 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 7:18"/>Then Joshua told the men from that family to present themselves. And Yahweh indicated that Achan was guilty.<verse eid="JOS 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 7:19"/>Then Joshua said to Achan, “Son, tell the truth [IDM]. Confess to Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship, what you have done</char>. And tell me what you did, and do not try to ◄conceal anything/prevent me from knowing what you did►.”<verse eid="JOS 7:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 7:20"/>Achan replied, “It is true. I have sinned against Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>. <verse eid="JOS 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 7:21"/>Among the things <char style="add">in Jericho</char> that I saw was a beautiful coat from Babylonia. I also saw 200 pieces of silver and some gold that weighed as much as 50 pieces of silver. I wanted those things very much for myself, so I took them. I buried them all in the ground under my tent. You will find them there. The silver is buried under the other things.”<verse eid="JOS 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 7:22"/>So Joshua sent some men <char style="add">to find those things</char>. They ran to Achan’s tent and found all the things hidden there. <verse eid="JOS 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 7:23"/>The men brought them all out of the tent and took them to Joshua and the rest of the Israeli people. Then they spread/laid them out on the ground, where Yahweh could see them.<verse eid="JOS 7:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 7:24"/>Then Joshua and the rest of the people led Achan down to the valley. They also took down there the silver, the coat, the gold, Achan’s <char style="add">wife and</char> sons and daughters, and his cattle and donkeys and sheep, and his tent, and everything else that he owned. <verse eid="JOS 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 7:25"/>Joshua said, “◄I do not know why you caused so much trouble for us/You have caused a lot of trouble for us► [RHQ], but now Yahweh will cause trouble for you.” Then all the people threw stones at Achan and his family until they all died. Then the people burned their corpses.<verse eid="JOS 7:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 7:26"/>They piled rocks over <char style="add">the ashes of</char> their <char style="add">corpses</char>, and those rocks are still there. That is why that valley is called Trouble Valley. After that, Yahweh was no longer angry <char style="add">with the Israeli people</char>.<verse eid="JOS 7:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="JOS 8"/>
  <para style="s1">The town of Ai is destroyed</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 8:1"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “Do not be afraid or discouraged <char style="add">because of what happened at</char> Ai. Lead all of your soldiers and go there again. I will help you to defeat the king of Ai, his people, and his city, and <char style="add">enable you to take</char> his land. <verse eid="JOS 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 8:2"/>Your army will do to the people of Ai and their king like what you did to the people of Jericho and their king. But this time <char style="add">I will permit you to</char> take all their possessions and keep them for yourselves. But first, tell some of your soldiers to <char style="add">hide behind</char> the city <char style="add">and</char> prepare to suddenly attack it.”<verse eid="JOS 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 8:3"/>So Joshua led all his army toward Ai. He chose 30,000 of his best fighters/warriors and prepared to send them out during the night. <verse eid="JOS 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 8:4"/>He said to them, “Listen carefully. Some of you must hide on the other side of the city. Do not go far from the city. Just be ready <char style="add">to attack</char>. <verse eid="JOS 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 8:5"/>I and the men who are with me will march toward the city <char style="add">in the morning</char>. The men in the city will come out to fight us, like they did before. Then we will turn around and start to run away from them. <verse eid="JOS 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 8:6"/>They will think that we are running away from them like we did before. So they will chase us away from the city. While we are running away, <verse eid="JOS 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 8:7"/><char style="add">those of you who are hiding come out and</char> rush into the city and capture it. Yahweh your God will enable you to conquer it. <verse eid="JOS 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 8:8"/>After you capture the city, burn it. Do what Yahweh has commanded us to do. Those are the orders I am giving to you.”<verse eid="JOS 8:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 8:9"/>Then Joshua <char style="add">prepared to</char> send some of them to <char style="add">hide and</char> wait between Ai and Bethel, which was west of Ai. But Joshua stayed with his other soldiers that night.<verse eid="JOS 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 8:10"/>Early the next morning, Joshua gathered his soldiers together. Then he and the other Israeli leaders led them up to Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 8:11"/>They all set up their tents close to Ai, just to the north of the city, where all the people of the city could see them. There was a valley between them and the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 8:12"/>Then Joshua chose about 5,000 men and told them to go and hide just west of the city, between Ai and Bethel. <verse eid="JOS 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 8:13"/>So those men did that. The main group of soldiers was north of the city, and the others were hiding west of the city. That night Joshua went down into the valley.<verse eid="JOS 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 8:14"/>When the king of Ai saw the Israeli army, he and his soldiers got up early the next morning and quickly went out of the city to fight them. They went to a place east of the city, but they did not know that some Israeli soldiers were hiding behind the city. <verse eid="JOS 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 8:15"/>Joshua and the Israeli soldiers <char style="add">who were with him</char> allowed the army of Ai to push them back. They ran toward the desert. <verse eid="JOS 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 8:16"/>The men in Ai were ordered to chase after Joshua and his men. So they left the city and started to pursue the Israelis. <verse eid="JOS 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 8:17"/>All the men of Ai and the men of Bethel pursued the Israeli army. They did not leave even one man in Ai to defend it. The <char style="add">gates of the</char> city were left wide open.<verse eid="JOS 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 8:18"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “<char style="add">Lift up</char> your spear <char style="add">and </char> point it toward Ai, because I am going to enable your soldiers to capture it!” So Joshua pointed <char style="add">his spear</char> toward Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 8:19"/>When the Israeli men who were hiding saw that, they rushed out from the places where they were hiding and ran into the city. They quickly captured it and set it on fire.<verse eid="JOS 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 8:20"/>When the men of Ai looked back, they saw smoke rising from their city. But they could not escape, because the Israeli troops stopped running away. <verse eid="JOS 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 8:21"/>Joshua and his men saw that the men who had been hiding had captured the city and were burning it, and they saw the smoke rising. So they turned around and started to attack the men of Ai. <verse eid="JOS 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 8:22"/>Meanwhile, the soldiers who had captured the city came out <char style="add">and attacked them from the rear</char>. So the men of Ai were caught between the two groups of Israeli soldiers. None of the men of Ai escaped. The Israelis fought until they killed all of them. Only the king of Ai was still alive. <verse eid="JOS 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 8:23"/>Then they seized the king of Ai and brought him to Joshua.<verse eid="JOS 8:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A summary of the battle</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 8:24"/>While they were fighting, the Israeli army pursued the men of Ai into the fields and into the desert, and killed all of them. Then they went to Ai and killed everyone who was there. <verse eid="JOS 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 8:25"/>They killed 12,000 men and women. <verse eid="JOS 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 8:26"/>Joshua continued to point his spear [LIT] toward Ai, until all the people in Ai had been killed. <verse eid="JOS 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 8:27"/>The Israeli soldiers took for themselves the animals and the other things that had belonged to the people of Ai, just like Yahweh had told Joshua that they should do.<verse eid="JOS 8:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 8:28"/>Joshua and his soldiers burned Ai city and caused it to become a pile of ruins. It is still like that today. <verse eid="JOS 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 8:29"/>Joshua hanged the king of Ai on a tree and left his corpse hanging there until the evening. At sunset Joshua told his men to take the king’s corpse down from the tree and to throw it on the ground at the city gate. <char style="add">After they did that</char>, they piled a lot of rocks on top of the corpse, and that pile of rocks is still there.<verse eid="JOS 8:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua repeated Yahweh’s agreement with the Israeli people</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 8:30"/>Joshua <char style="add">told his men to</char> build on Ebal Mountain an altar for Yahweh, the God <char style="add">who is worshiped by</char> the Israeli people. <verse eid="JOS 8:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 8:31"/>They built it just like Moses, the man who served God <char style="add">well</char>, had written previously in the laws <char style="add">that God had given to him</char>. They made it from stones that had not been cut using iron tools. The Israelis then offered sacrifices to Yahweh that were burned completely on the altar. They also offered sacrifices to restore fellowship with Yahweh. <verse eid="JOS 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 8:32"/>As the Israelis watched, Joshua wrote on stones the laws that <char style="add">Yahweh had given</char> to Moses previously. <verse eid="JOS 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 8:33"/>The Israeli leaders, the officials, the judges, and other Israelis were there, standing nearby. Many people who were not Israelis were also there. Half of the people stood <char style="add">on one side of the valley</char> below Ebal Mountain, and the other half of the people stood <char style="add">on the other side of the valley</char> below Gerizim Mountain. The sacred chest was <char style="add">in the valley</char> between the two groups. That was what Moses had previously commanded that the people should do when <char style="add">Yahweh was about to</char> bless them.<verse eid="JOS 8:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 8:34"/>Then Joshua read <char style="add">to the people</char> all that <char style="add">Moses</char> had written previously. That included what Yahweh had taught them and the ways <char style="add">that he promised</char> to bless them <char style="add">if they obeyed his commands</char>, or to curse them <char style="add">if they disobeyed them</char>. <verse eid="JOS 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 8:35"/>All the Israelis gathered together <char style="add">to listen</char>—the men, the women, and the children. The ◄foreigners/people who were not Israelis► who were living among them also listened, while Joshua read all the commands that Moses had written.<verse eid="JOS 8:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="JOS 9"/>
  <para style="s1">The Gibeonites tricked the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 9:1"/>There were several kings <char style="add">who ruled in lands that are</char> on the west side of the Jordan River. They were the kings of the Heth people-group, the Amor people-group, the Canaan people-group, the Periz people-group, the Hiv people-group, and the Jebus people-group. They lived in the hilly area, in the foothills further west, and <char style="add">on the plains</char> along the coast of the Mediterranean Sea. They heard <char style="add">about what happened at Ai</char>. <verse eid="JOS 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 9:2"/>So they all gathered <char style="add">their armies</char> to fight Joshua and the Israeli army.<verse eid="JOS 9:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 9:3"/>When the people who lived in Gibeon <char style="add">city</char> heard that Joshua’s army had defeated the people of Jericho and Ai, <verse eid="JOS 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 9:4"/>they decided to trick the Israelis. They gathered some old sacks and some old leather wine bags that had been mended after they were cracked, and they put these on the backs of their donkeys. <verse eid="JOS 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 9:5"/>They put on old sandals that had been patched, and wore old ragged clothes. And they took along bread that was dry and moldy. <verse eid="JOS 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 9:6"/>They traveled to where Joshua <char style="add">and the other Israelis</char> had set up their tents near Gilgal. They said to Joshua and the other Israeli leaders, “We have traveled from a distant land. We want you to make a peace agreement with us.”<verse eid="JOS 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 9:7"/>The Israeli leaders said to those men from <char style="add">Gilead who were from</char> the Hiv people-group, “<char style="add">We do not know if you truly live far from us</char>. If you live near us, we cannot [RHQ] make a peace agreement with you, <char style="add">because God has commanded us to get rid of the people that are living near us</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 9:8"/>They replied to Joshua, “<char style="add">If you make a peace agreement with us</char>, we will be your servants.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 9:8">But Joshua answered, “What people-group are you? Where do you come from?”<verse eid="JOS 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 9:9"/>The men from Gibeon answered, “<char style="add">We want to be</char> your servants<char style="add">. We</char> have come here from a distant land, because we have heard about the great things that your god has done. We have heard about everything that he did in Egypt <char style="add">to help you</char>. <verse eid="JOS 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 9:10"/>We have heard that he <char style="add">enabled you to</char> defeat <char style="add">the armies of</char> two kings of the Amor people-group, on the east side of the Jordan River—Sihon, the king who ruled in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char>, and Og, the king who ruled in Ashtaroth in the Bashan <char style="add">area</char>. <verse eid="JOS 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 9:11"/>So our leaders and the rest of our people said to us, ‘Take some food and go to talk with the Israelis. Tell them, “We want to be your servants. So make a peace agreement with us.”’ <verse eid="JOS 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 9:12"/>Look at our bread. It was fresh and warm <char style="add">from having been baked</char> on the day that we left our area, but now it is dry and moldy. <verse eid="JOS 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 9:13"/>Look at our leather wine bags. They were new when we filled them with wine <char style="add">before we left</char>, but now they are cracked and old. Our clothes and our sandals are worn out from traveling <char style="add">on the long road</char> to come here.”<verse eid="JOS 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 9:14"/>The Israeli leaders tasted the bread, but they did not ask Yahweh what to do. <verse eid="JOS 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 9:15"/>So Joshua agreed to make a peace agreement with the men from Gibeon to not kill them. All the Israeli leaders vowed to do what Joshua said in the agreement. <char style="add">Then the men from Gibeon returned home</char>.<verse eid="JOS 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 9:16"/>Three days later the Israelis found out that the men from Gibeon lived nearby. <verse eid="JOS 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 9:17"/>So they went to where the men from Gibeon lived. After traveling <char style="add">only</char> three days, they came to their cities: Gibeon, Kephirah, Beeroth, and Kiriath-Jearim. <verse eid="JOS 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 9:18"/>But the Israelis did not attack the people of those cities, because they had promised <char style="add">to live peacefully with them</char>, and Yahweh had heard them promise <char style="add">to do that</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 9:18">All the Israeli people grumbled against their leaders <char style="add">for doing that</char>. <verse eid="JOS 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 9:19"/>But the leaders answered, “We promised to <char style="add">live peacefully with them</char>, and Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, heard us promise <char style="add">to do that</char>. So now we cannot attack [EUP] them. <verse eid="JOS 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 9:20"/>This is what we will do: We will not kill them. If we kill them, God will be very angry with us <char style="add">and punish us</char> because of not doing what we promised to do. <verse eid="JOS 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 9:21"/>So we must allow them to live. But they will cut wood for us, and they will carry water for us.” So the Israeli leaders did what they had promised.<verse eid="JOS 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 9:22"/>Then Joshua summoned the men from Gibeon and asked them, “Why did you lie to us? Your land was near to where we had set up our tents, but you told us that you were from a distant land! <verse eid="JOS 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 9:23"/>So now you will become our slaves. You will always be forced to cut wood and carry water for <char style="add">us Israeli people who worship in</char> the temple of our God.”<verse eid="JOS 9:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 9:24"/>The men from Gibeon replied, “We lied to you because we were afraid that you would kill us. We heard that Yahweh, your God, declared to his servant Moses that he would enable you to conquer all the people in this land and to kill all the people who lived in it. <verse eid="JOS 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 9:25"/>So now you can decide what you will do with us. Do what you think is right.”<verse eid="JOS 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 9:26"/>So Joshua saved the lives of the people of Gibeon by not allowing the Israelis to kill them. <verse eid="JOS 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 9:27"/>Instead, he forced them to become the Israelis’ slaves. They cut wood and carried water for the Israelis. They also brought the wood and water <char style="add">that was needed for</char> the sacred altar of Yahweh, to whatever place Yahweh decided that they should build one. And the people of Gibeon are still doing that.<verse eid="JOS 9:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="JOS 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua’s army defeated the descendants of Amor when God made the sun stand still</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 10:1"/>Later, Adonizedek, the king of Jerusalem, heard that Joshua’s army had captured Ai <char style="add">town</char> and had destroyed everything in the town. He heard that they had done to the people of Ai and to their king the same thing that they had done to the people of Jericho and their king. He also heard that the people of Gibeon <char style="add">city</char> had made a peace treaty with the Israeli people, and that the people of Gibeon were now living near the Israelis and being protected by them. <verse eid="JOS 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 10:2"/>Because of that, he and the people whom he ruled became very afraid, because Gibeon was an important city, like the other cities that had kings. And <char style="add">even though</char> Gibeon was a larger city than Ai and all its soldiers were good fighters, <char style="add">they thought Joshua’s army might defeat them</char>. <verse eid="JOS 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 10:3"/>So King Adonizedek sent a message to Hosham the king of Hebron <char style="add">city</char>, to Piram the king of Jarmuth <char style="add">city</char>, to Jarmuth the king of Lachish <char style="add">city</char>, and to Debir the king of Eglon <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="JOS 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 10:4"/>In the message he said, “Please come up with your armies and help me to attack Gibeon, because the people of Gibeon have made a peace treaty with Joshua and the Israelis.”<verse eid="JOS 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 10:5"/>So those five kings who ruled all the groups who were descendants of Amor—the kings of Jerusalem, Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish, and Debir—came up with all of their soldiers and surrounded the city. Then they prepared to attack it.<verse eid="JOS 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 10:6"/>So the people of Gibeon sent a message to Joshua while he was in the camp at Gilgal. They said, “We are your servants. So do not forsake us. Come up to us quickly and save us! Help us, because the kings of all of the groups descended from Amor and their armies have joined their forces and have come from the hilly area to attack us!”<verse eid="JOS 10:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 10:7"/>So Joshua and all his army, including the soldiers who were his best fighting men, marched up from Gilgal. <verse eid="JOS 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 10:8"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “Do not be afraid of those armies! I will enable your army to defeat them [IDM]. None of them will be able to ◄resist/fight and defeat► your army.”<verse eid="JOS 10:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 10:9"/>Joshua’s army marched all night and arrived very early in the morning. <verse eid="JOS 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 10:10"/>They attacked their enemies before anyone knew that they had come. Yahweh caused their enemies to ◄become very confused/start running in all directions► when they saw the Israeli army. As a result, the Israeli army defeated them very severely at Gibeon <char style="add">and killed many of them</char>. The rest of them fled along the road that goes up to Beth-Horon. But the Israeli army pursued them and killed them all along the road that goes to Azekah and Makkedah towns. <verse eid="JOS 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 10:11"/>As they fled in front of the Israeli army, Yahweh threw down huge hailstones from the sky. As a result, more of them died from hailstones falling on them than died as a result of the Israeli army killing them with swords.<verse eid="JOS 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 10:12"/>On the day that Yahweh enabled the Israeli army to defeat the groups who were descendants of Amor, Joshua said to Yahweh while the Israeli people were listening, “Yahweh, cause the sun to stand still over Gibeon, and cause the moon to not move when it is over Aijalon Valley.” <verse eid="JOS 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 10:13"/>And that is what happened. The sun stood still, and the moon did not move, until the Israeli army defeated their enemies. That is what has been written in the book that Jashar wrote. The sun stopped while it was in the middle of the sky, and did not ◄set/go down► for about a whole day. <verse eid="JOS 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 10:14"/>On that day Yahweh did a great miracle that someone asked him to do. There was never a day like that previously, and there has never been a day like that since. Yahweh was certainly fighting for the Israeli people!<verse eid="JOS 10:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 10:15"/>After Joshua’s army defeated their enemies, they all returned to their camp at Gilgal.<verse eid="JOS 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua’s army defeated the armies of five kings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 10:16"/>While the enemy soldiers were fleeing from Joshua’s army, their five kings also fled and hid in a cave at Makkedah <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="JOS 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 10:17"/>Then someone told Joshua, “We found those five kings, hiding in a cave at Makkedah!” <verse eid="JOS 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 10:18"/>When Joshua heard that, he said, “Roll some very large rocks to the entrance of the cave so that the kings cannot escape, and leave some soldiers there to guard it. <verse eid="JOS 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 10:19"/>But do not stay there! Pursue our enemies! Attack them from behind! Do not allow them to escape to their cities, because Yahweh, our God, will enable you to defeat/kill them. [IDM]”<verse eid="JOS 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 10:20"/>So Joshua’s army did what he told them to do. They killed almost all of the enemy soldiers, but a few of them were able to reach their cities and be safe inside the walls of the cities. <verse eid="JOS 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 10:21"/>Then Joshua’s army returned to Joshua, who was still in their camp at Makkedah. No one in the land dared to criticize [MTY] the Israelis.<verse eid="JOS 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 10:22"/>Then Joshua said, “Open the entrance of the cave, and bring out to me those five kings!” <verse eid="JOS 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 10:23"/>So the soldiers brought those five kings out of the cave—the kings of Jerusalem, Hebron, Jarmuth, Lachish, and Eglon. <verse eid="JOS 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 10:24"/>When they brought those kings to Joshua <char style="add">and forced them to lie on the ground</char>, he summoned all the Israeli soldiers, and then he said to the army commanders, “Come here and put your feet on the necks of these kings!” So the commanders did that. <verse eid="JOS 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 10:25"/>Then Joshua said to them, “Do not be afraid of any of our enemies! Never be discouraged! Be strong and courageous. This is what Yahweh will do to all the enemies you will fight!” <verse eid="JOS 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 10:26"/>Then Joshua killed each of the five kings with his sword, and told his soldiers to hang the bodies of the five kings on trees. So they did that, and they left the bodies hanging on the trees until sunset. <verse eid="JOS 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 10:27"/>At sunset, Joshua told them to take the bodies down from the trees and throw them into the cave where they had been hiding. So the soldiers did that, and then they put those large rocks at the entrance of the cave again. Those rocks are still there.<verse eid="JOS 10:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 10:28"/>That is how Joshua’s army attacked and captured Makkedah. They killed the king and everyone else in the town. They did not leave anyone alive. They did to the king of Makkedah the same thing that they had done to the king of Jericho.<verse eid="JOS 10:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">They conquered the southern cities</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 10:29"/>That same day, Joshua and his Israeli army went <char style="add">southwest</char> from Makkedah to Libnah <char style="add">city</char> and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 10:30"/>Yahweh enabled the Israelis to conquer [MTY] that city and its king. They killed everyone in the city; they did not ◄spare anyone/allow anyone to remain alive►. They killed the king of Libnah just like they had killed the king of Jericho.<verse eid="JOS 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 10:31"/>Then Joshua and his army went <char style="add">south</char> from Libnah to Lachish <char style="add">city</char>. They surrounded the city and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 10:32"/>On the second day of the battle, Yahweh enabled the Israelis to conquer [MTY] the city. And like they had done at Libnah, they killed everyone [DOU] in the city. <verse eid="JOS 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 10:33"/>King Horam from Gezer <char style="add">city and his army</char> came to help <char style="add">the soldiers of</char> Lachish, but Joshua’s <char style="add">army</char> defeated Horam and his army, and did not allow any of them to remain alive.<verse eid="JOS 10:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 10:34"/>Then Joshua and his army went <char style="add">west</char> from Lachish to Eglon <char style="add">city</char>. They surrounded the city and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 10:35"/>On that day, they captured the city and killed [MTY] everyone in it [DOU], just like they had done at Lachish.<verse eid="JOS 10:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 10:36"/>Then Joshua and his army went <char style="add">west from Eglon</char> up <char style="add">into the hills</char> to Hebron <char style="add">city</char>. They attacked the city <verse eid="JOS 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 10:37"/>and captured it. They killed the king and everyone else, just like they had done at Eglon. They did not allow anyone to remain alive.<verse eid="JOS 10:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 10:38"/>Then Joshua and his army turned <char style="add">south</char> and went to Debir <char style="add">city</char> and attacked it. <verse eid="JOS 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 10:39"/>They captured the city and its king, and also captured the nearby towns. Then they killed everyone [DOU]; they did to the people there the same thing that they had done at Hebron and Libnah.<verse eid="JOS 10:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 10:40"/>That is how Joshua <char style="add">and his army</char> conquered the entire southern part of Canaan. They defeated the kings <char style="add">who ruled</char> the hilly area, the dry southern area, the <char style="add">western</char> foothills, and the <char style="add">eastern</char> slopes. They killed everyone [DOU] in those areas; they did not allow anyone to remain alive. <verse eid="JOS 10:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 10:41"/>Joshua’s soldiers captured all the cities from Kadesh-Barnea <char style="add">city</char> in the far south to Gaza <char style="add">city</char> near the coast, including all the Goshen area, and north to Gibeon <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="JOS 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 10:42"/>At that one time, Joshua’s army conquered all the kings and captured all the territory that they <char style="add">ruled</char>. They were able to do that because Yahweh, the God whom the Israeli people <char style="add">worship</char>, was fighting for them.<verse eid="JOS 10:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 10:43"/>Then Joshua and his army returned to their camp at Gilgal.<verse eid="JOS 10:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="JOS 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua’s army captured towns in the north</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 11:1"/>When King Jabin of Hazor <char style="add">city</char> heard <char style="add">about all those things that had happened</char>, he sent messages to Jobab, the king of Madon <char style="add">city</char>, to the king of Shimron <char style="add">city</char>, and to the king of Acshaph <char style="add">city</char>, <char style="add">requesting them to send their armies to come and help him fight against the Israelis</char>. <verse eid="JOS 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 11:2"/>He also sent messages to the kings in the northern hilly area and to the kings in the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley, south of Galilee <char style="add">Lake</char> and in the western hills. He sent a message to the king of Naphoth-Dor <char style="add">in the west</char> <verse eid="JOS 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 11:3"/>and to the kings of the Canaan people-group in the eastern and western parts of the land. He sent messages to the Amor people-group and the Heth people-group and the Periz people-group and the Jebus people-group who lived in the hilly area. He also sent a message to the Hiv people-group who lived below Hermon <char style="add">Mountain</char> in the Mizpah area. <verse eid="JOS 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 11:4"/>So the armies of all those kings gathered together, bringing their horses and chariots. <char style="add">There seemed to be</char> [HYP] as many soldiers as grains of sand on the seashore. <verse eid="JOS 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 11:5"/>All of those kings <char style="add">and their armies</char> gathered together at Merom Pond, <char style="add">and they set up their tents there</char>. Then they made plans to fight against the Israelis.<verse eid="JOS 11:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 11:6"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, “Do not be afraid of them, because at this time tomorrow I will enable your men to defeat them. Your men must also cripple their horses and burn their chariots.”<verse eid="JOS 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 11:7"/>So Joshua and his army traveled to Merom Pond and attacked their enemies ◄by surprise/before they were ready to fight►. <verse eid="JOS 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 11:8"/>Yahweh enabled the Israelis to defeat them. They pursued them to Sidon <char style="add">city in the far north</char>, and to Misrephoth-Maim <char style="add">in the northwest</char>, and to Mizpah Valley in the northeast. The Israelis fought them until ◄they were all dead/there were no survivors►. <verse eid="JOS 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 11:9"/>Then Joshua and his men did what Yahweh told them to do: They crippled their enemies’ horses and burned their chariots.<verse eid="JOS 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 11:10"/>The king of Hazor had ruled the people of all the kingdoms whose armies had fought against the Israelis. So Joshua’s army went back to Hazor and captured that city and killed their king. <verse eid="JOS 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 11:11"/>They killed everyone in Hazor; ◄they did not spare anyone/no one was left alive► [DOU]. Then they burned the city.<verse eid="JOS 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 11:12"/>Joshua’s army captured all of those cities and killed all of their kings. They did that like Moses, the man who served Yahweh <char style="add">well</char>, had commanded them to do. <verse eid="JOS 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 11:13"/>Joshua’s men burned Hazor <char style="add">city</char>, but they did not burn any of the other cities that were built on small hills. <verse eid="JOS 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 11:14"/>The Israelis took for themselves the animals that they found in those cities and everything else <char style="add">that was valuable</char> [DOU]. But they killed all the people. <verse eid="JOS 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 11:15"/><char style="add">Many years before</char>, Yahweh had told Moses to do that, and then Moses told Joshua to do it. So Joshua did everything that Yahweh had commanded Moses to do.<verse eid="JOS 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 11:16"/>Joshua’s <char style="add">army</char> defeated all the people who were living in that land. They took control over the hilly area and the area in the southern part of Canaan, all the area of Goshen, the western foothills, and the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley. They took control over all the mountains in Israel and all the hills near the mountains. <verse eid="JOS 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 11:17"/>They took control of all the land from Halak Mountain <char style="add">in the south</char> up to the Seir <char style="add">hilly area</char> as far as Baal-Gaal in Lebanon Valley <char style="add">in the north</char>, at the bottom of Hermon Mountain. They captured all the kings of those areas and killed them. <verse eid="JOS 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 11:18"/>Joshua’s men fought against those groups for many years. <verse eid="JOS 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 11:19"/>There was only one group that made a peace agreement with the Israelis; they were the people of the Hiv people-group who lived in Gibeon. The Israelis captured all the other towns in battles. <verse eid="JOS 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 11:20"/>Yahweh caused the people in all those other groups to be stubborn [IDM], with the result that they fought against the Israeli army, and the Israelis killed them all. They were not merciful to any of them. That is what Yahweh had commanded Moses to do.<verse eid="JOS 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 11:21"/>Joshua’s army also fought the Anak people-group who lived in the hills near Hebron, Debir, and Anah <char style="add">cities</char>. They also fought against the people who lived in the hilly area of Judah and Israel, and they killed all of those people and destroyed their cities. <verse eid="JOS 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 11:22"/>As a result, there were no descendants of Anak who remained alive in Israel. Only a few remained alive in Gaza, Gath, and Ashdod <char style="add">cities</char>. <verse eid="JOS 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 11:23"/>Joshua’s army took control of all the land, just as Yahweh <char style="add">long ago</char> had told Moses to do. Yahweh gave the land to the Israelis, because he had promised to give it to them. Then Joshua divided the land among the Israeli tribes. After that, there was ◄peace/no more battles► in the land.<verse eid="JOS 11:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="JOS 12"/>
  <para style="s1">The kings defeated by the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 12:1"/>The Israelis took control of the land that was east of the Jordan River, from the Arnon River gorge <char style="add">in the south</char> to Hermon Mountain <char style="add">in the north</char>, including all the land on the eastern side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley. That land previously belonged to the two kings whose armies the Israelis defeated.<verse eid="JOS 12:1"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 12:2"/>One of them was Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group. He lived in Heshbon <char style="add">city</char> and ruled over the area from Aroer <char style="add">town</char> along the Arnon River Gorge, north to the Jabbok River. His land started in the middle of the gorge, which was the border between his land and the land of the Ammon people-group. Sihon also ruled over <char style="add">the southern</char> half of the Gilead region, <verse eid="JOS 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 12:3"/>and over the land on the eastern side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley, from Galilee Lake <char style="add">south</char> to the Dead Sea. He also ruled over the land <char style="add">east of the Dead Sea</char> from Beth-Jeshimoth south to the side of Pisgah Mountain.<verse eid="JOS 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 12:4"/>The other king whom the Israeli army defeated was Og, the king of the Bashan <char style="add">region</char>. He was the last of the descendants of <char style="add">the giant</char> Rapha. He ruled that land, living alternately in Ashtaroth and Edrei <char style="add">cities</char>. <verse eid="JOS 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 12:5"/>He ruled over the area from Hermon Mountain and Salecah <char style="add">in the north</char>, and over all the Bashan area in the east, and to the borders of the kingdoms of Geshur and Maacah to the west. Og ruled <char style="add">the northern</char> half of the Gilead region, as far as the border of the land ruled by King Sihon.<verse eid="JOS 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 12:6"/>Moses, the man who served Yahweh <char style="add">well</char>, and all the Israeli army defeated the armies of those kings. Then Moses gave that land to the tribes of Reuben and Gad and half of the tribe of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 12:7"/>Joshua and the Israeli army also defeated kings who ruled over the land on the west side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. He gave that land to the Israeli people, dividing it among the other tribes. That land was between Baal-Gad <char style="add">city</char> in the Lebanon Valley <char style="add">in the far north all the way south</char> to Halak Mountain, which is near the land of the Edom people-group. <verse eid="JOS 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 12:8"/>That land included the mountains, the western hilly area, the Jordan <char style="add">River </char> Valley, the <char style="add">western</char> slopes of the mountains, the desert <char style="add">in Judea</char>, and the Negev <char style="add">desert in the south</char>. That whole area was the land where the Heth, Amor, Canaan, Periz, Hiv, and Jebus people-groups lived. The Israeli army defeated the armies of the kings of each of these cities: <verse eid="JOS 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 12:9"/>Jericho, Ai (which was near Bethel), <verse eid="JOS 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 12:10"/>Jerusalem, Hebron, <verse eid="JOS 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 12:11"/>Jarmuth, Lachish, <verse eid="JOS 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 12:12"/>Eglon, Gezer, <verse eid="JOS 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 12:13"/>Debir, Geder, <verse eid="JOS 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 12:14"/>Hormah, Arad, <verse eid="JOS 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 12:15"/>Libnah, Adullam, <verse eid="JOS 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 12:16"/>Makkedah, Bethel, <verse eid="JOS 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 12:17"/>Tappuah, Hepher, <verse eid="JOS 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 12:18"/>Aphek, Lasharon, <verse eid="JOS 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 12:19"/>Madon, Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 12:20"/>Shimron Meron, Acshaph, <verse eid="JOS 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 12:21"/>Taanach, Megiddo, <verse eid="JOS 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 12:22"/>Kedesh, Jokneam in the Carmel area, <verse eid="JOS 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 12:23"/>Dor in the Naphoth-Dor area, Goyim in the Gilgal area, <verse eid="JOS 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 12:24"/>and Tirzah.</para>
  <para style="m" vid="JOS 12:24">There was a total of 31 kings <char style="add">that the Israeli army defeated</char>.<verse eid="JOS 12:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="JOS 13"/>
  <para style="s1">The areas that the Israelis had not yet captured</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 13:1"/>When Joshua was very old, Yahweh said to him, “Joshua, you are now an old man, but there is still a lot of land <char style="add">for your army</char> to capture. <verse eid="JOS 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 13:2"/>Here is a list of the land that remains: The Geshur region and all the area where the Philistia people-group live; <verse eid="JOS 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 13:3"/>the area where the Canaan people-group live, from the Shihor River <char style="add">in the south</char> at the <char style="add">eastern</char> border of Egypt, to Ekron <char style="add">city</char> in the north; the rulers of the five <char style="add">cities</char> of Gaza, Ashdod, Ashkelon, Gath, and Ekron; the area where the Avva people-group live, <verse eid="JOS 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 13:4"/>which is south of the area where the Canaan people-group live; <verse eid="JOS 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 13:5"/>the area where the Gebal people-group live; and all the Lebanon area east of Baal-Gad <char style="add">city</char> at the bottom of Hermon Mountain, as far as Lebo-Hamath.<verse eid="JOS 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 13:6"/>All the people of the Sidon people-group live in the hilly area from Lebanon to Misrephoth-Maim, but I will force them to leave that area before you Israelis arrive there. Be sure to give that area to the Israeli people when you divide the land among them, like I told you to do. <verse eid="JOS 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 13:7"/>Divide all that land among the nine Israeli tribes and half of the tribe of Manasseh, <char style="add">the tribes that do not have land on the east side of the Jordan River</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The land east of the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 13:8"/>Half of the tribe of Manasseh and the tribes of Reuben and Gad had already been told what land they would receive, because Moses, the man who served Yahweh <char style="add">well</char>, had already assigned to them the land on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="JOS 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 13:9"/>Their land extended from Aroer <char style="add">town</char> at the Arnon River gorge to the town in the middle of the gorge. It included the whole plain from Medeba <char style="add">town south</char> to Dibon <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="JOS 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 13:10"/>All the towns ruled by King Sihon were in that area. The land extended to where the Ammon people-group lived. <verse eid="JOS 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 13:11"/>The Gilead area was also there, and the regions where the people of the Geshur and Maacah people-groups lived, and all of Hermon Mountain and all the Bashan region <char style="add">south</char> to Salecah. <verse eid="JOS 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 13:12"/>All the land ruled by Og, the king who ruled the Bashan <char style="add">region</char>, was in that land. Og was one of the last descendants of Repha; previously he had ruled in Ashtaroth and Edrei <char style="add">cities</char>, but <char style="add">the armies of</char> Moses had defeated their armies and had taken their land from them. <verse eid="JOS 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 13:13"/>But the Israelis did not force the people of the Geshur and Maacah <char style="add">people-groups</char> to leave their land, so they still live among the Israeli people.<verse eid="JOS 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 13:14"/>The tribe of Levi was the only tribe that did not get any land. Instead, just like Yahweh promised, they continued to receive <char style="add">food from</char> the sacrifices that were given to Yahweh, the God whom the Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, the sacrifices that were burned <char style="add">on the sacred altar</char>.<verse eid="JOS 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 13:15"/>Moses had allotted land to each clan in the tribe of Reuben. <verse eid="JOS 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 13:16"/>Their land extended from Aroer <char style="add">town</char> near the Arnon River gorge to Medeba <char style="add">town</char>. That included all of the plain <char style="add">that is near Medeba</char> and the town in the middle of the gorge. <verse eid="JOS 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 13:17"/>It also included Heshbon <char style="add">city</char> and all the nearby towns on the plain—Dibon, Bamioth-Baal, Beth-Baal-Meon, <verse eid="JOS 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 13:18"/>Jahaz, Kedemoth, Mephaath, <verse eid="JOS 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 13:19"/>Kiriathaim, Sibmah, Zereth-Shahar on the hill overlooking the valley, <verse eid="JOS 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 13:20"/>Beth-Peor, the hills in the Pisgah area, and Beth-Jeshimoth. <verse eid="JOS 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 13:21"/>That land included all the towns on the plain and all the area that King Sihon had previously ruled. But <char style="add">the army of</char> Moses had defeated him and the rulers of the Midian people-group: Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur, and Reba. The armies of all those rulers fought battles along with the army of Sihon, and they lived in that country. <verse eid="JOS 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 13:22"/>The Israeli army killed many people during those battles, including Balaam, <char style="add">the prophet</char> from Beor, who tried to use magic to predict/tell what would happen in the future. <verse eid="JOS 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 13:23"/>The <char style="add">western</char> boundary of the land that was allotted to the clans of the tribe of Reuben was the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>.<verse eid="JOS 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 13:24"/>Moses also allotted some land to each clan in the tribe of Gad. <verse eid="JOS 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 13:25"/>Their land included the Jazer <char style="add">area</char> and all the towns of the Gilead <char style="add">area</char>; half of the land where the Ammon people-group lived, as far as Aroer <char style="add">town which is</char> near Rabbah <char style="add">town</char>; <verse eid="JOS 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 13:26"/>the area from Heshbon <char style="add">city</char> to Ramath-Mizpah and Betonim <char style="add">towns; the area</char> from Mahanaim <char style="add">town</char> to the Debir region; <verse eid="JOS 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 13:27"/>Beth-Haram, Beth-Nimrah, Succoth, and Zaphon <char style="add">cities</char> in the valley; and the other area that King Sihon had ruled on the east side of the Jordan River. That area extended <char style="add">north </char> to the southern end of Galilee Lake. <verse eid="JOS 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 13:28"/>All this land, including the towns and villages, was allotted to the tribe of Gad.<verse eid="JOS 13:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 13:29"/>Moses also had allotted some of the land <char style="add">on the east side of the Jordan River</char> to half of the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 13:30"/>Their land extended <char style="add">north</char> from Mahanaim <char style="add">city</char>. It included all the Bashan region, all the land that King Og had ruled, and all the towns in the Jair area in Bashan. Altogether that area included 60 towns. <verse eid="JOS 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 13:31"/>Their area also included half of the Gilead region, and the cities of Ashtaroth and Edrei where King Og had ruled. All that area was allotted to the clans descended from Manasseh’s son Makir.<verse eid="JOS 13:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 13:32"/>Moses had allotted to those tribes the land that was on the plain of the Moab <char style="add">region</char>, on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, across from Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 13:33"/>But Moses did not allot any land to the tribe of Levi because Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis worship, promised that he himself would always provide for them.<verse eid="JOS 13:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="JOS 14"/>
  <para style="s1">The land west of the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 14:1"/>Eleazar the Supreme Priest, Joshua, and the leaders of the <char style="add">twelve</char> tribes repeated what land would be allotted to each of the Israeli tribes in Canaan. <verse eid="JOS 14:1"/><verse number="2-5" style="v" sid="JOS 14:2-5"/>Yahweh had told Moses many years previously in what way he wanted the division of the land to be decided. Moses had already declared that two and a half tribes would be allotted land on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. Joseph had two sons, Manasseh and Ephraim. <char style="add">Half of the tribe descended from Manasseh was allotted land on the east side of the Jordan, along with the tribes of Reuben and Gad</char>. The people belonging to the nine and a half other tribes <char style="add">on the west side of the Jordan River</char> threw ◄lots/stones that had been marked► to decide which land each tribe would receive. The tribe of Levi was not allotted any land. They received only towns <char style="add">that already existed</char>, towns in which to live, and ◄pastures/fields of grass► for their animals.<verse eid="JOS 14:2-5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for Caleb</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 14:6"/>One day some men from the tribe of Judah went to Joshua while he and all the Israelis were at Gilgal. Among those men was Jephunneh’s son Caleb. He said to Joshua, “<char style="add">I am sure that</char> you remember what Yahweh said to the prophet Moses about you and me when we were at Kadesh-Barnea. <verse eid="JOS 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 14:7"/>I was 40 years old at that time. Moses sent me <char style="add">and you and some other men</char> to explore this land. When we returned, I gave to Moses a true report [IDM] about what we had seen. <verse eid="JOS 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 14:8"/>The other men who went with us <char style="add">gave a report that</char> caused the people to be afraid [IDM]. But I fully/completely believed <char style="add">that</char> Yahweh <char style="add">would enable us to take the land from the people who lived there</char>. <verse eid="JOS 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 14:9"/>So on that day, Moses solemnly promised me, ‘<char style="add">Some of</char> the land on which you walked will become yours. It will belong to your descendants forever. I am giving it to you because you fully trusted in Yahweh, my God.’<verse eid="JOS 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 14:10"/>“Now Yahweh has done for me what he promised. Forty-five years have passed since Moses said that to me during the time that we were wandering around in the desert. And just like Yahweh promised, he has kept me alive and well all during that time. Now I am eighty-five years old. <verse eid="JOS 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 14:11"/>I am as strong today as I was on the day that Moses sent me <char style="add">to explore this land</char>. I am as ready to fight now as I was then. <verse eid="JOS 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 14:12"/>So please give me the hilly area that Yahweh promised to give to me at that time long ago. At that time, you heard <char style="add">me say</char> that the Amalek people-group lived there. You heard me say that their cities were large, and they had walls around them <char style="add">to protect them from attacks by their enemies</char>. But now, Yahweh will help me, and as a result I will force them to leave, just like Yahweh said would happen.”<verse eid="JOS 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 14:13"/>So Joshua <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless Caleb, and he gave to Caleb <char style="add">the city of</char> Hebron. <verse eid="JOS 14:13"/><verse number="14-15" style="v" sid="JOS 14:14-15"/>Previously that city was called Kiriath-Arba, because Arba was the greatest man among the Amalek people-group. Hebron still belongs to the descendants of Caleb, because Caleb completely/fully trusted in Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>, and obeyed him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 14:14-15">After that happened, there was ◄peace/no battles► in <char style="add">Canaan</char> land <char style="add">for many years</char>.<verse eid="JOS 14:14-15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="JOS 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribe of Judah</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 15:1"/>The land that was allotted to the tribe of Judah was divided among its clans. That land extended south along the border of the Edom region, as far as the Zin Desert.<verse eid="JOS 15:1"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 15:2"/>The southern border of the land that was allotted to the tribe of Judah started at the south end of the Dead Sea <char style="add">and extended west</char>. <verse eid="JOS 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 15:3"/>It extended south of Scorpion Pass to Zin <char style="add">Desert</char>, and from there west to a place south of Kadesh-Barnea, past Hezron <char style="add">town</char>, to Addar <char style="add">town</char>, and from there it turned <char style="add">northwest</char> to Karka <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="JOS 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 15:4"/>From there it continued to Azmon, and from there to the dry riverbed on the border of Egypt, and from there <char style="add">west </char> to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea. That was the southern border.<verse eid="JOS 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 15:5"/>The eastern border of the land of the tribe of Judah was the Dead Sea, and it extended <char style="add">north</char> to <char style="add">where the Jordan River ends at</char> the Dead Sea.<verse eid="JOS 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 15:6"/>The northern border started where the Jordan River ends at the Dead Sea. It extended <char style="add">north</char> to Beth-Hoglah <char style="add">town</char>, and from there it extended north of Beth-Arabah <char style="add">town</char> to the <char style="add">big</char> stone <char style="add">set up by</char> Reuben’s son Bohan. <verse eid="JOS 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 15:7"/>From there the border continued west through Achor Valley to Debir <char style="add">city</char>. From there it turned north to Gilgal <char style="add">city</char>. Gilgal is north of the road that goes through Adummim Pass, on the south side of the valley. From Gilgal the border extended west to the springs at En-Shemesh, and from there to En-Rogel. <verse eid="JOS 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 15:8"/>From there it extended through Ben-Hinnom Valley, south of the city where the Jebus people-group lived. (That city is now named Jerusalem.) From there the border extended to the top of the hill on the west side of Hinnom Valley, at the northern end of the valley where the Repha <char style="add">giants</char> lived. <verse eid="JOS 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 15:9"/>From there the border extended <char style="add">northwest</char> to Nephtoah Spring, and from there to the cities near Ephron Mountain. From there the border extended <char style="add">west</char> toward Baalah, which is now named Kiriath-Jearim. <verse eid="JOS 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 15:10"/>Then the border extended further west to Seir Mountain. Then it continued <char style="add">southwest</char> along the north side of Jearim Mountain, which is also named Kesalon, to Beth-Shemesh <char style="add">city</char>. From there it extended <char style="add">northwest</char> past Timnah <char style="add">city</char>, <verse eid="JOS 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 15:11"/>to the hill north of Ekron <char style="add">city</char>. From there it extended <char style="add">west</char> to Shikkeron <char style="add">town</char> and past Baalah Mountain to Jabneel <char style="add">town</char>, then <char style="add">northwest</char> to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea.<verse eid="JOS 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 15:12"/>The western border of the land that was allotted to the tribe of Judah was the Mediterranean Sea. All the clans of Judah lived inside those borders.<verse eid="JOS 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 15:13"/>Yahweh commanded Joshua to give part of the land for the tribe of Judah to Caleb. So he gave to Caleb Kiriath-Arba <char style="add">city</char>, which is now named Hebron. (Arba was the ancestor of the Anak people-group.) <verse eid="JOS 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 15:14"/>Caleb forced the three clans of the Anak people-group to leave Hebron. Those were the Sheshai, Ahiman, and Talmai clans. <verse eid="JOS 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 15:15"/>Then Caleb left there and went to fight against the people living in Debir <char style="add">city</char>, which was previously named Kiriath-Sepher. <verse eid="JOS 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 15:16"/>Caleb said, “If someone attacks <char style="add">the people in</char> Kiriath-Sepher and captures their city, I will give my daughter Acsah to him to be his wife.” <verse eid="JOS 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 15:17"/>Othniel, the son of Caleb’s brother Kenaz, captured the city. So Caleb gave his daughter to him.<verse eid="JOS 15:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 15:18"/>When Caleb’s daughter married Othniel, she told him to ask her father to give her a field. Then Acsah went to talk with her father Caleb. As she got down from her donkey, Caleb asked her, “Do you want something?”<verse eid="JOS 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 15:19"/>Acsah replied, “Yes, I want you to do something for me. You have given me some land in the southern part of Canaan, <char style="add">but there is no water there</char>. So please give me some <char style="add">land that has</char> springs.” So Caleb gave her the upper and lower springs <char style="add">near Hebron</char>.<verse eid="JOS 15:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 15:20"/>
    <char style="add">Here is a list of the towns in</char> the land <char style="add">that God had promised to</char> give to the tribe of Judah. Each clan was allotted some of the land.<verse eid="JOS 15:20"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 15:21"/>The tribe of Judah was allotted all these towns in the southern <char style="add">desert area of Canaan</char>, near the border of the Edom <char style="add">region</char>:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="JOS 15:21">Kabzeel, Eder, Jagur, <verse eid="JOS 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 15:22"/>Kinah, Dimonah, Adadah, <verse eid="JOS 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 15:23"/>Kedesh, Hazor, Ithnan, <verse eid="JOS 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 15:24"/>Ziph, Telem, Bealoth, <verse eid="JOS 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 15:25"/>Hazor-Hadattah, Kerioth-Hezron (which is also named Hazor), <verse eid="JOS 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 15:26"/>Amam, Shema, Molodah, <verse eid="JOS 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 15:27"/>Hazar-Gaddah, Heshmon, Beth-Pelet, <verse eid="JOS 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 15:28"/>Hazar-Shual, Beersheba, Biziothiah, <verse eid="JOS 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 15:29"/>Baalah, Iim, Ezem, <verse eid="JOS 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 15:30"/>Eltolad, Kesil, Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 15:31"/>Ziklag, Madmannah, Sansannah, <verse eid="JOS 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 15:32"/>Lebaoth, Shilhim, Ain, and Rimmon. There were 29 towns altogether and their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:32"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 15:33"/>The tribe of Judah was allotted these towns in the <char style="add">northern part of the western</char> foothills: Eshtaol, Zorah, Ashnah,<verse eid="JOS 15:33"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 15:34"/>Zanoah, En-Gannim, Tappuah, Enam, <verse eid="JOS 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 15:35"/>Jarmuth, Adullam, Socoh, Azekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 15:36"/>Shaaraim, Adithaim, and Gederah (which is also named Gederothaim). Altogether there were 14 towns and their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:36"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 15:37"/>
    <char style="add">The tribe of Judah was also allotted these towns in the southern part of the western foothills</char>: Zenan, Hadashah, Migdal-Gad, <verse eid="JOS 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 15:38"/>Dilean, Mizpah, Joktheel, <verse eid="JOS 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 15:39"/>Lachish, Bozkath, Eglon, <verse eid="JOS 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 15:40"/>Cabbon, Lahmas, Kitlish, <verse eid="JOS 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 15:41"/>Gederoth, Beth-Dagon, Naamah, and Makkedah.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="JOS 15:41">There were 16 towns altogether and their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:41"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 15:42"/>The tribe of Judah was also allotted these towns in <char style="add">the central part of</char> the western foothills: Libnah, Ether, Ashan, <verse eid="JOS 15:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 15:43"/>Iphtah, Ashnah, Nezib, <verse eid="JOS 15:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 15:44"/>Keilah, Aczib, and Mareshah. There were nine towns altogether, with their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:44"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="45-47" style="v" sid="JOS 15:45-47"/>The tribe of Judah was also allotted these towns <char style="add">close to the Mediterranean Sea</char> with their surrounding villages: Ekron and the towns between Ekron and the coast, Ashdod, and Gaza. The area extended south to the dry riverbed on the border of Egypt.<verse eid="JOS 15:45-47"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 15:48"/>The tribe of Judah was also allotted these towns in <char style="add">the southwest part of </char> the hilly region: Shamir, Jattir, Socoh, <verse eid="JOS 15:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 15:49"/>Dannah, Kiriath-Sannah (which is now named Debir), <verse eid="JOS 15:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 15:50"/>Anab, Eshtemoh, Anim, <verse eid="JOS 15:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 15:51"/>Goshen, Holon, and Giloh. There were eleven towns with their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:51"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="JOS 15:52"/>The tribe of Judah was also allotted these towns in <char style="add">the south-central part of</char> the hilly region: Arab, Dumah, Eshan, <verse eid="JOS 15:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="JOS 15:53"/>Janim, Beth-Tappuah, Aphekah, <verse eid="JOS 15:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="JOS 15:54"/>Humtah, Kiriath-Arba (which is now named Hebron), and Zior. There were nine towns altogether with their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:54"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="55" style="v" sid="JOS 15:55"/>The tribe of Judah was also allotted these towns <char style="add">in the southeastern part of the hilly region</char>: Maon, Carmel, Ziph, Juttah, <verse eid="JOS 15:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="JOS 15:56"/>Jezreel, Jokdeam, Zanoah, <verse eid="JOS 15:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="JOS 15:57"/>Kain, Gibeah, and Timnah. There were ten towns altogether with their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:57"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="58" style="v" sid="JOS 15:58"/>The tribe of Judah was also allotted these towns <char style="add">in the central part of the hilly region</char>: Halhul, Beth-Zur, Gedor, <verse eid="JOS 15:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="JOS 15:59"/>Maarath, Beth-Anoth, and Eltekon. There were six towns altogether with their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:59"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="JOS 15:60"/>The tribe of Judah was also allotted two towns <char style="add">in the northern part of the hilly region</char>, Rabbah and Kiriath-Baal (which is also named Kiriath-Jearim).<verse eid="JOS 15:60"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="61" style="v" sid="JOS 15:61"/>The tribe of Judah was also <char style="add">allotted these towns</char> in the desert <char style="add">near the Dead Sea</char>: Beth-Arabah, Middin, Secacah, <verse eid="JOS 15:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="JOS 15:62"/>Nibshan, Salt city, and En-Gedi. There were six towns altogether with their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 15:62"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" sid="JOS 15:63"/>
    <char style="add">The army of the tribe of</char> Judah was not able to force the people of the Jebus people-group to leave Jerusalem. So the people of that group are still living among the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 15:63"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="JOS 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 16:1"/>The land that was allotted to <char style="add">the two tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh that were descended from</char> Joseph started at the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, east of the springs at Jericho. <verse eid="JOS 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 16:2"/>It extended west from Jericho to the hilly area near Bethel, which is also called Luz. It extended as far as Ataroth, at the border of the land where the Arki people-group lived. <verse eid="JOS 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 16:3"/>From there it extended west to the border of the land where the Japhleti people-group lived, and then it extended west to the area near Lower Beth-Horon. From there it extended west to Gezer <char style="add">city</char> and from there to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea.<verse eid="JOS 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 16:4"/>That is the land that the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh were allotted.<verse eid="JOS 16:4"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 16:5"/>The border of the land that was allotted to the clans of the tribe of Ephraim started at Ataroth-Addar <char style="add">city</char> in the east. It extended to Upper Beth-Horon <verse eid="JOS 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 16:6"/>and from there to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea. <verse eid="JOS 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 16:7"/>From Michmethath <char style="add">on the north</char> it extended east to Taanath and from there on to Janoah. From there it extended <char style="add">south</char> to Ataroth <char style="add">city</char> and to Naarah <char style="add">town</char>. From there it extended to Jericho and from there to the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="JOS 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 16:8"/>The <char style="add">northern</char> border extended from Tappuah west to Kanah Ravine, and ended at the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea. That was the land that was allotted to the tribe of Ephraim. <verse eid="JOS 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 16:9"/>Many of those towns were really within the area allotted to the tribe of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 16:10"/>The people of the tribe of Ephraim could not force the Canaan people-group to leave Gezer, so the Canaan people-group still live among the people of the tribe of Ephraim, but the Israelis forced the people of the Canaan people-group to become their slaves.<verse eid="JOS 16:10"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="JOS 17"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 17:1"/>
    <char style="add">This is a list of</char> the land that was allotted to the tribe of Manasseh. Manasseh’s oldest son was Makir and his grandson was Gilead. Makir’s descendants were great warriors, so the lands in the Gilead and Bashan regions were allotted to their clan. <verse eid="JOS 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 17:2"/>Land was also allotted to the other clans of the tribe of Manasseh: The clans of Abiezer, Helek, Asriel, Shechem, Hepher, and Shemida.<verse eid="JOS 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 17:3"/>Hepher’s son Zelophehad had no sons, but he had five daughters: Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. <verse eid="JOS 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 17:4"/>They went to Eleazar the Supreme Priest, and to Joshua and to the other Israeli leaders. They said, “<char style="add">We want you to give us some land, because</char> Yahweh told Moses that he should give to us some land, just like you gave to the men.” So Eleazar did what Yahweh had commanded, and he allotted to them some land, just like he allotted to their uncles. <verse eid="JOS 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 17:5"/>So the tribe of Manasseh eventually had ten sections <char style="add">of land west of the Jordan River</char> and <char style="add">two sections,</char> Gilead and Bashan, on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="JOS 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 17:6"/>So those female descendants of Manasseh also were allotted land <char style="add">on the west side of the river</char> just like the men were allotted. The other parts of the Gilead area were allotted to the male descendants of Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 17:7"/>The land allotted to the tribe of Manasseh was between the land where the tribe of Asher lives and Michmethath <char style="add">town</char>, near Shechem <char style="add">city</char>. The border extended south to the Tappuah Spring. <verse eid="JOS 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 17:8"/>The land near the Tappuah area belonged to the tribe of Manasseh, but the town of Tappuah, which was at the border of the land that was allotted to the tribe of Manasseh, was allotted to the tribe of Ephraim. <verse eid="JOS 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 17:9"/>The border <char style="add">of the land allotted to the tribe of Manasseh</char> extended south to Kanah Gorge. From there it extended <char style="add">west</char> along the north side of the gorge and ended at the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea. <verse eid="JOS 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 17:10"/>The land on the south side of the gorge belonged to the tribe of Ephraim, and the land on the north side belonged to the tribe of Manasseh. The western border of the land allotted to the tribe of Manasseh was the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea. To the north, the border of their land extended from the land allotted to the tribe of Asher <char style="add">at the northwest</char> to the land allotted to the tribe of Issachar <char style="add">at the northeast.</char><verse eid="JOS 17:10"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 17:11"/>But there are cities inside the area allotted to the tribes of Issachar and Asher. Those cities, along with their surrounding villages, were allotted to people from the tribe of Manasseh. These cities are Beth-Shan, Ibleam, Dor (which is also named Naphoth-Dor,) Endor, Taanach, and Megiddo.<verse eid="JOS 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 17:12"/>The men of the tribe of Manasseh were not able to force the people who lived in those cities to leave, so the people of the Canaan people-group continued to live in those cities. <verse eid="JOS 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 17:13"/>But <char style="add">years later</char> when the Israelis became better <char style="add">warriors</char>, they forced the Canaan people-group to work for them as slaves, although they did not force them to leave the land.<verse eid="JOS 17:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 17:14"/>The people of the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh said to Joshua, “You allotted to us only one area of land, but there are a lot of us. Yahweh has blessed us very much <char style="add">with the result that our tribe has grown very large</char>. So why did you give us only a small part of the land [RHQ]?”<verse eid="JOS 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 17:15"/>Joshua replied to them, “<char style="add">I agree that</char> you do not have enough land in the hilly area of the tribe of Ephraim. So, since you have a lot of people, I will allot more land to you, in the hilly region. But you will have to <char style="add">cut down the trees</char> in the forest <char style="add">and </char> make a place for yourselves in the land where the Periz and Repha people-groups live.”<verse eid="JOS 17:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 17:16"/>The people of the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh replied, “It is true that the land in the hilly area is not big enough for us, but the Canaan people-group who live in the lowlands, in Beth-Shan and the surrounding villages in that area, and in the Jezreel Valley, have iron chariots, <char style="add">so we will not be able to defeat them</char>!”<verse eid="JOS 17:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 17:17"/>Joshua replied to them, “Your tribe is very numerous and very powerful. So I will allot more land for you in the hilly area, <verse eid="JOS 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 17:18"/>but you will have to cut down the trees in order to make a place for you to live. <char style="add">It is true that</char> the Canaan people-group are strong and have iron chariots, but you will be able to force them to leave that valley.”<verse eid="JOS 17:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="JOS 18"/>
  <para style="s1">The rest of the land was allotted</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-2" style="v" sid="JOS 18:1-2"/>The Israeli people captured all the land <char style="add">that they were able to</char>, but there were still seven tribes that had not been allotted any land. The Israeli people all gathered at Shiloh, and they set up the Sacred Tent there. <verse eid="JOS 18:1-2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 18:3"/>Joshua said to them, “Why are you waiting a long time to take control of <char style="add">the rest of</char> the land that Yahweh, the God whom your ancestors <char style="add">worshiped</char>, has promised to give to you [RHQ]?<verse eid="JOS 18:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 18:4"/>Choose three men from each of your seven tribes. Then I will send them to explore <char style="add">the parts of</char> the land <char style="add">which you have not occupied yet. When they finish exploring it</char>, they must write a report, in which they will ◄make a map/show the boundaries► of the land that each tribe wants to receive. <verse eid="JOS 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 18:5"/>They will divide the remaining land into seven parts. The tribe of Judah will keep its land in the south, and the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh will keep their land in the north. <verse eid="JOS 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 18:6"/>But in their report, the men from the seven tribes should describe the seven parts of the remaining land <char style="add">that they wish to receive</char>, and bring the report to me. While Yahweh is watching, I will ◄cast lots/throw marked stones► <char style="add">to decide which land should be allotted to each tribe</char>. <verse eid="JOS 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 18:7"/>But the tribe of Levi will not be allotted any land, because their <char style="add">reward is that they will be</char> Yahweh’s priests. The tribes of Gad, Reuben, and half the tribe of Manasseh have already been allotted their land on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, just as Moses, the man who served God <char style="add">well</char>, decided, <char style="add">so they will not get any more land</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 18:8"/>When the men who were chosen <char style="add">got ready to</char> leave, Joshua told them, “Go and explore the land. Then write a report of what you have seen, and bring it back to me. Then while Yahweh is watching, I will ◄cast lots/throw marked stones► here at Shiloh, <char style="add">to determine what area each tribe will receive</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 18:9"/>So the men left and walked through the area. Then they described in a scroll each town that was in the seven parts <char style="add">into which they had divided</char> the land. Then they returned to Joshua, who was still at Shiloh. <verse eid="JOS 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 18:10"/><char style="add">After Joshua read their report</char>, while Yahweh was watching, he ◄cast lots/threw marked stones► to choose which land would be allotted to each of the seven Israeli tribes.<verse eid="JOS 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The land for the tribe of Benjamin</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 18:11"/>The first tribe that was allotted land was the tribe of Benjamin. Each clan in that tribe was allotted some of the land that was between the area that was allotted to the tribe of Judah and the area that was allotted to the tribes of Ephraim and Manasseh.<verse eid="JOS 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 18:12"/>The northern border started at the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and extended west along the northern side of Jericho, into the hilly area. From there the border extended west to the desert near Beth-Aven <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="JOS 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 18:13"/>From there it extended southwest to Luz (which is <char style="add">now named</char> Bethel). From there it extended southwest to Ataroth-Addar <char style="add">town</char>, which is on the hill south of Lower Beth-Horon <char style="add">city</char>.<verse eid="JOS 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 18:14"/>At the hill south of Beth-Horon, the border turned and extended south to Kiriath-Baal <char style="add">town</char>, which is <char style="add">also named</char> Kiriath-Jearim. That is a town where people of the tribe of Judah live. That was the western border of the land allotted to the tribe of Benjamin.<verse eid="JOS 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 18:15"/>The southern border of their land started near Kiriath-Jearim and extended west to Nephtoah Springs. <verse eid="JOS 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 18:16"/>From there it extended south to the bottom of the hill, near Ben-Hinnom Valley, on the north side of Repha Valley. The border extended south along the Hinnom Valley, south of the city where the Jebus people-group lived, to En-Rogel. <verse eid="JOS 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 18:17"/>From there the border extended west to En-Shemesh, and continued to Geliloth near Adummim Pass. Then it extended to the great stone of Reuben’s son Bohan. <verse eid="JOS 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 18:18"/>From there the border extended to the northern edge of Beth-Arabah <char style="add">town</char> and down into the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> Valley. <verse eid="JOS 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 18:19"/>From there it extended east to the northern edge of Beth-Hoglah <char style="add">town</char> and ended at the north end of the Dead Sea, where the Jordan <char style="add">River flows into the Dead Sea</char>. That was the southern boundary <char style="add">of the land allotted to the tribe of Benjamin</char>.<verse eid="JOS 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 18:20"/>The Jordan <char style="add">River</char> was the eastern boundary of the land allotted to the tribe of Benjamin. Those were the boundaries of the land allotted to them.<verse eid="JOS 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 18:21"/>The cities in the land allotted to the tribe of Benjamin were Jericho, Beth-Hoglah, Emek-Keziz, <verse eid="JOS 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 18:22"/>Beth-Arabah, Zemaraim, Bethel, <verse eid="JOS 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 18:23"/>Avvim, Parah, Ophrah, <verse eid="JOS 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 18:24"/>Kephar-Ammoni, Ophni, and Geba. Altogether there were fourteen towns and the surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 18:25"/>The tribe of Benjamin also had the towns of Gibeon, Ramah, Beeroth, <verse eid="JOS 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 18:26"/>Mizpah, Kephirah, Mozah, <verse eid="JOS 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 18:27"/>Rekem, Irpeel, Taralah, <verse eid="JOS 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 18:28"/>Zelah, Haeleph, the city where the Jebus people-group lived (which is <char style="add">now named</char> Jerusalem), Gibeah, and Kiriath. Altogether there were 14 towns and the surrounding villages. All that area was allotted to the clans of the tribe of Benjamin.<verse eid="JOS 18:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="JOS 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribe of Simeon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 19:1"/>The second/next tribe that was allotted land was the tribe of Simeon. Each clan in that tribe was allotted some land that was inside the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="JOS 19:1"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 19:2"/>Their land included the towns of Beersheba (<char style="add">which is also named</char> Sheba), Moladah, <verse eid="JOS 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 19:3"/>Hazar-Shual, Balah, Ezem, <verse eid="JOS 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 19:4"/>Eltolad, Bethul, Hormah, <verse eid="JOS 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 19:5"/>Ziklag, Beth-Marcaboth. Hazar-Susah, <verse eid="JOS 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 19:6"/>Beth-Lebaoth, and Sharuhen. Altogether there were 13 towns and the surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 19:7"/>The land allotted to them also included the four cities of Ain, Rimmon, Ether, and Ashan, and their surrounding villages. <verse eid="JOS 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 19:8"/>They were also allotted some very small villages in an area that extended south to Baalath-Beer (which is <char style="add">also named</char> Ramah, in the southern desert). That was the land allotted to the clans of the tribe of Simeon.<verse eid="JOS 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 19:9"/>The tribe of Judah had been allotted much more land than they needed, so part of their land was given to the tribe of Simeon.<verse eid="JOS 19:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribe of Zebulun</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 19:10"/>The third/next tribe that was allotted land was the tribe of Zebulun. Each clan of that tribe was allotted some of the land.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="JOS 19:10">The southern border started at Sarid <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="JOS 19:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 19:11"/>It extended west to Maralah <char style="add">city</char> and on to Dabbesheth <char style="add">city</char>, and on to the brook just north of Jokneam <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="JOS 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 19:12"/>The border extended east from Sarid to the area near Kisloth-Tabor <char style="add">city</char> and on to Daberath <char style="add">town</char> and on to Japhia <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="JOS 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 19:13"/>From there it extended east to Gath-Hepher <char style="add">city</char> and Eth-Kazin <char style="add">town</char>, and north to Rimmon <char style="add">city</char>. From there the border extended <char style="add">west</char> to Neah <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="JOS 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 19:14"/>From Neah it extended south to Hannathon <char style="add">city</char> and from there to Iphtah-El Valley. <verse eid="JOS 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 19:15"/>Their area included the towns of Kattath, Nahalal, Shimron, Idalah, and Bethlehem. Altogether there were twelve towns and the surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 19:16"/>That was the land that was allotted to the clans of the tribe of Zebulun.<verse eid="JOS 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribe of Issachar</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 19:17"/>The fourth/next tribe that was allotted land was the tribe of Issachar. Each of the clans of that tribe was allotted some of the land. <verse eid="JOS 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 19:18"/>Their land included the cities of Jezreel, Kesulloth, Shunem, <verse eid="JOS 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 19:19"/>Hapharaim, Shion, Anaharath, <verse eid="JOS 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 19:20"/>Rabbith, Kishion, Ebez, <verse eid="JOS 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 19:21"/>Remeth, En-Gannim, En-Haddah, and Beth-Pazzez. <verse eid="JOS 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 19:22"/>The border of the area that was allotted to the tribe of Issachar was close to Tabor, Shahazumah, and Beth-Shemesh <char style="add">cities</char>, and ended <char style="add">in the east</char> at the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. Altogether there were 16 cities and the surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 19:23"/>Those cities and villages were in the land allotted to the clans of the tribe of Issachar.<verse eid="JOS 19:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribe of Asher</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 19:24"/>The fifth/next tribe that was allotted land was the tribe of Asher. Each of the clans in that tribe was allotted some of the land.<verse eid="JOS 19:24"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 19:25"/>Their land included the towns of Helkath, Hali, Beten, Acshaph, <verse eid="JOS 19:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 19:26"/>Allammelech, Amad, and Mishal. The western border started at Carmel <char style="add">Mountain</char> and Shihor-Libnath. <verse eid="JOS 19:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 19:27"/>From there it extended <char style="add">southeast</char> to Beth-Dagon <char style="add">town</char>, and then to <char style="add">the area that was allotted to the tribe of</char> Zebulun and Iphtah-El Valley. From there the border extended east and then north to Beth-Emek <char style="add">town</char> and Neiel and Cabul <char style="add">towns</char>. <verse eid="JOS 19:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 19:28"/>From there it extended west to Abdon, Rehob, Hammon, and Kanah <char style="add">cities</char>, and continued to Sidon, which is a big city. <verse eid="JOS 19:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 19:29"/>From there the border extended south toward Ramah and to the big city of Tyre that had strong walls around it. From there the border extended <char style="add">west</char> to Hosah <char style="add">town</char> and ended at the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea. Within their area were the towns of Aczib, <verse eid="JOS 19:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 19:30"/>Ummah, Aphek, and Rehob. Altogether there were 22 towns and their surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 19:31"/>Those cities and villages were within the land that was allotted to the clans of the tribe of Asher.<verse eid="JOS 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribe of Naphtali</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 19:32"/>The sixth/next tribe that was allotted land was the tribe of Naphtali. Each of the clans in that tribe was allotted some of the land.<verse eid="JOS 19:32"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 19:33"/>The border of their land started <char style="add">in the west</char> at the <char style="add">huge</char> oak tree at Zaanannim, near Heleph <char style="add">town</char>. It extended <char style="add">east</char> through Adami-Nekeb <char style="add">city</char> and Jabneel, and then to Lakkum, and ended at the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="JOS 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 19:34"/>The western boundary extended through Aznoth-Tabor as far as Hukkok <char style="add">city</char>. It extended to the borders of <char style="add">the tribe of</char> Zebulun at the south, to <char style="add">the border of the tribe of</char> Asher on the west, and the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> at the east. <verse eid="JOS 19:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 19:35"/><char style="add">Within their land were</char> several cities with strong walls around them. They were Ziddim, Zer, Hammath, Rakkath, Kinnereth, <verse eid="JOS 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 19:36"/>Adamah, Ramah, Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 19:37"/>Kedesh, Edrei, En-Hazor, <verse eid="JOS 19:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 19:38"/>Iron, Migdal-El, Horem, Beth-Anath, and Beth-Shemesh. Altogether there were 19 cities and the surrounding villages.<verse eid="JOS 19:38"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 19:39"/>Those cities and surrounding villages were in the land that was allotted to the clans of the tribe of Naphtali.<verse eid="JOS 19:39"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for the tribe of Dan</para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 19:40"/>The seventh/last tribe that was allotted land was the tribe of Dan. Each of the clans in that tribe was allotted some of the land. <verse eid="JOS 19:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 19:41"/>Their land included the towns of Zorah, Eshtaol, Ir-Shemesh, <verse eid="JOS 19:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 19:42"/>Shaalabbin, Aijalon, Ithlah, <verse eid="JOS 19:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 19:43"/>Elon, Timnah, Ekron, <verse eid="JOS 19:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 19:44"/>Eltekeh, Gibbethon, Baalath, <verse eid="JOS 19:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 19:45"/>Jehud, Bene-Berak, Gath-Rimmon, <verse eid="JOS 19:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="JOS 19:46"/>Me-Jarkon, Rakkon, and the area near Joppa.<verse eid="JOS 19:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="JOS 19:47"/>But the people of the tribe of Dan were unable to take control of the land that had been allotted to them. So they went <char style="add">northeast</char> and fought against the people in Leshem <char style="add">city</char>. They defeated and killed all the people who lived there. Then they began to live in Leshem, and changed the name of the city to Dan, the man from whom their tribe descended.<verse eid="JOS 19:47"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="JOS 19:48"/>All of those towns and surrounding villages were in the land that was allotted to the clans in the tribe of Dan.<verse eid="JOS 19:48"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Land for Joshua</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="JOS 19:49"/>After the Israeli leaders divided the land among the tribes, they allotted some land to Joshua. <verse eid="JOS 19:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="JOS 19:50"/>They allotted to him Timnath-Serah. Yahweh had said that he could have whatever city he wanted, and that was the city that he chose. It was in the hilly region which was allotted to the tribe of Ephraim. Joshua rebuilt the city and lived there.<verse eid="JOS 19:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="JOS 19:51"/>Those were the areas that were allotted to the various tribes of Israel. Eleazar the Supreme Priest and Joshua and the leaders of each tribe divided up the land while they were all at Shiloh, by ◄casting lots/throwing marked stones► <char style="add">to decide which area each tribe would receive</char>. They did that while Yahweh was watching, at the entrance of the Sacred Tent. In that way they completed dividing up the land.<verse eid="JOS 19:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="JOS 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Cities of refuge</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 20:1"/>Then Yahweh said to Joshua, <verse eid="JOS 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 20:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people that they should choose some cities to which people <char style="add">can run</char> in order to be safe/protected, like I told Moses that they should do. <verse eid="JOS 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 20:3"/>If someone kills another person accidentally, not intending to kill that person, the one who killed that person may run/escape to one of these cities and be safe/protected from someone trying to get revenge for that person’s death [MTY].<verse eid="JOS 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 20:4"/>When the one who killed someone arrives at the gate of one of those cities, he must stop there and tell the leaders of the city what happened. <char style="add">If they believe him</char>, they must allow him to enter the city, and they must give him a place to live among them. <verse eid="JOS 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 20:5"/>If some relative of the one who was killed comes to that city to get revenge, the leaders of that city must not allow the relative to take the killer, because what happened was accidental. He did not hate that person and as a result deliberately kill him. <verse eid="JOS 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 20:6"/>But the person who killed someone must stay in that city until the city judges put him on trial. <char style="add">Only if the judges decide that the person who has run/escaped to their city did not deliberately kill the other person will they allow him to stay in that city</char>, and he must stay there until the Supreme Priest dies. Then he may safely go back to his own town, <char style="add">because the death of the Supreme Priest will be considered to atone/pay for the death of the person who was killed</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 20:7"/>So the Israelis chose these cities to be cities to which people could run to be safe/protected: Kedesh in the Galilee district in the hilly area where the tribe of Naphtali lived; Shechem in the hilly area where the tribe of Ephraim lived; Kiriath-Arba (which is <char style="add">now named</char> Hebron) in the hilly area where the tribe of Judah lived; <verse eid="JOS 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 20:8"/>Bezer, on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> near Jericho, in the flat land in the desert where the tribe of Reuben lived; Ramoth in the Gilead <char style="add">region</char> in the land where the tribe of Gad lived; and Golan in the Bashan region where the tribe of Manasseh lived. <verse eid="JOS 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 20:9"/>Any Israeli or any foreigner who lived among us, anyone who killed someone ◄accidentally/without planning to do it►, was allowed to run to one of those cities, and be safe/protected from some relative of the person who died coming there and killing him to get revenge. He could stay in that city until there was a trial there <char style="add">to decide whether he was telling the truth or not when he said that he did not plan to kill that person</char>.<verse eid="JOS 20:9"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="JOS 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Towns for the Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-2" style="v" sid="JOS 21:1-2"/>While Eleazar the Supreme Priest and Joshua and the leaders of all the Israeli tribes were at Shiloh, the leaders of the clans of the tribe of Levi went to them and said, “Yahweh commanded Moses that you should give us towns where we can have pasture/fields/grassland for our animals, <char style="add">but you have not done these things yet</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 21:1-2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 21:3"/>So the Israeli leaders obeyed this command from Yahweh. They agreed to give towns and pasturelands to the tribe of Levi.<verse eid="JOS 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 21:4"/>
    <char style="add">First</char> they allotted some cities to the Kohath clans, who belonged to the tribe of Levi. To those who were descendants of the first Supreme Priest Aaron, they allotted 13 towns in the areas that had been allotted to the tribes of Judah, Simeon, and Benjamin. <verse eid="JOS 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 21:5"/>To the other members of the Kohath clan they allotted ten cities in the areas that had been allotted to the tribes of Ephraim, Dan, and the part of the tribe of Manasseh <char style="add">that lives on the west side of the Jordan River</char>.<verse eid="JOS 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 21:6"/>The people from the Gershon clans were allotted 13 cities in the areas that had been allotted to the tribes of Issachar, Asher, Naphtali, and the part of the tribe of Manasseh that lives on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>.<verse eid="JOS 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 21:7"/>The people from the Merari clans were allotted twelve cities in the areas that had been allotted to the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and Zebulun.<verse eid="JOS 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 21:8"/>So the Israeli leaders gave cities and pastureland to the tribe of Levi, just as Yahweh had commanded Moses that they should do.<verse eid="JOS 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 21:9"/>These are the names of the cities and surrounding pasturelands that were allotted to them, that were in the areas where the tribes of Judah and Simeon lived.<verse eid="JOS 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 21:10"/>First, they allotted cities to the members of the Kohath clans.<verse eid="JOS 21:10"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 21:11"/>They allotted to them Kiriath-Arba (which is <char style="add">now named</char> Hebron), in the hilly area of Judah. Arba received its name because Arba was the ancestor of <char style="add">the giants of</char> the Anak people-group. <verse eid="JOS 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 21:12"/>But the fields and villages surrounding Arba had already been allotted to Caleb.<verse eid="JOS 21:12"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 21:13"/>They allotted to them Hebron, which was one of the cities to which people could run/escape to be safe/protected. They also allotted to the Kohath clan the cities of Libnah, <verse eid="JOS 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 21:14"/>Jattir, Eshtemoa, <verse eid="JOS 21:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 21:15"/>Holon, Debir, <verse eid="JOS 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 21:16"/>Ain, Juttah, and Beth-Shemesh. Altogether they were allotted those nine cities which were located in the areas that had been allotted to the tribes of Judah and Simeon.<verse eid="JOS 21:16"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 21:17"/>The Kohath clan was also allotted these four cities: Gibeon, Geba, <verse eid="JOS 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 21:18"/>Anathoth, and Almon. Those cities were in the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Benjamin.<verse eid="JOS 21:18"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 21:19"/>Altogether those 13 towns and surrounding pastureland were allotted to the priests who were descended from Aaron.<verse eid="JOS 21:19"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 21:20"/>The other members the Kohath clan were allotted four cities and the surrounding pastureland in the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Ephraim.<verse eid="JOS 21:20"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 21:21"/>Those cities were Shechem (which was one of the cities to which people could run/escape to be safe/protected), Gezer, <verse eid="JOS 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 21:22"/>Kibzaim, and Beth-Horon.<verse eid="JOS 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 21:23"/>They were also allotted four cities and surrounding pastureland in the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Dan. Those cities were Eltekeh, Gibbethon, <verse eid="JOS 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 21:24"/>Aijalon, and Gath-Rimmon.<verse eid="JOS 21:24"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 21:25"/>They were also allotted two towns and surrounding pastureland that had been allotted to <char style="add">the </char> part of the tribe of Manasseh <char style="add">that lived on the west side of the Jordan River</char>. Those cities were Taanach and Gath-Rimmon.<verse eid="JOS 21:25"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 21:26"/>Those were the ten cities and surrounding pastureland that were allotted to the other members of the Kohath clan.<verse eid="JOS 21:26"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 21:27"/>They also allotted towns and the surrounding pastureland to the Gershon clans. Those clans were also descended from Levi.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="JOS 21:27">They were allotted two cities from the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Manasseh <char style="add">that is on the east side of the Jordan River</char>. Those cities were Golan in the Bashan region, which was one of the cities to which people could run/escape to be safe/protected, and Be-Eshtarah.<verse eid="JOS 21:27"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 21:28"/>From the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Issachar they were allotted four cities. Those cities were Kishion, Daberath, <verse eid="JOS 21:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 21:29"/>Jarmuth, and En-Gannim.<verse eid="JOS 21:29"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 21:30"/>From the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Asher they were allotted four cities. Those cities were Mishal, Abdon, <verse eid="JOS 21:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 21:31"/>Helkath, and Rehob.<verse eid="JOS 21:31"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 21:32"/>From the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Naphtali they were allotted three cities. Those cities were Kedesh in the Galilee region (it was one of the cities to which people could run/escape to be safe/protected), Hammoth-Dor, and Kartan.<verse eid="JOS 21:32"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 21:33"/>So altogether the Gershon clans were allotted 13 cities and the surrounding pasturelands.<verse eid="JOS 21:33"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 21:34"/>The other descendants of Levi, the ones who belonged to the Merari clans, were also allotted towns and their surrounding pasturelands.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="JOS 21:34">From the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Zebulun they were allotted four cities. They were Jokneam, Kartah, <verse eid="JOS 21:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="JOS 21:35"/>Dimnah, and Nahalal.<verse eid="JOS 21:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="JOS 21:36"/>From the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Reuben they were allotted four cities. They were Bezer, Jahaz, <verse eid="JOS 21:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="JOS 21:37"/>Kedemoth, and Mephaath.<verse eid="JOS 21:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="JOS 21:38"/>From the area that had been allotted to the tribe of Gad they were allotted four cities. They were Ramoth, which was one of the cities in the Gilead region to which people could run/escape to be safe/protected, Mahanaim, <verse eid="JOS 21:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="JOS 21:39"/>Heshbon, and Jazer.<verse eid="JOS 21:39"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="JOS 21:40"/>Altogether twelve cities were allotted to the Merari clans.<verse eid="JOS 21:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="JOS 21:41"/>So altogether 48 cities were allotted to the tribe of Levi, <verse eid="JOS 21:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="JOS 21:42"/>and each city had surrounding pastureland.<verse eid="JOS 21:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="JOS 21:43"/>In that way Yahweh allotted to the Israeli people all the land that he had promised to give to their/our ancestors. The Israeli people took control of <char style="add">most of</char> those areas and started to live there. <verse eid="JOS 21:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="JOS 21:44"/>Just like he had promised our ancestors, Yahweh allowed them/us to have peace with the enemies that surrounded them/us. Yahweh enabled the Israelis/us to defeat their/our enemies. <verse eid="JOS 21:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="JOS 21:45"/>Yahweh did all the things that he had promised to the Israeli people/us. Everything that he said would happen did happen.<verse eid="JOS 21:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="JOS 22"/>
  <para style="s1">The tribes east of the Jordan went home</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 22:1"/>Joshua then summoned the leaders of the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and half of the tribe of Manasseh. <verse eid="JOS 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 22:2"/>He said to them, “You have done everything that Moses, who served Yahweh <char style="add">well</char>, told you to do. You have also done what I told you to do. <verse eid="JOS 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 22:3"/>For a long time you have helped the other tribes <char style="add">to defeat their enemies</char>. You have obeyed everything that Yahweh your God commanded you to do. <verse eid="JOS 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 22:4"/>He promised to give peace to us Israelis, and he has done what he promised. So now you may go back to your homes, to the land that Moses gave to you, on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="JOS 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 22:5"/>Moses also commanded you to love Yahweh your God and to obey his commands, and to continue to worship him and serve him by everything that you think and everything that you do.”<verse eid="JOS 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 22:6"/>Then Joshua blessed them and said goodbye to them, and they <char style="add">prepared to</char> leave and return to their homes <char style="add">on the east side of the Jordan River</char>. <verse eid="JOS 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 22:7"/>Moses had given the Bashan region to half the tribe of Manasseh, and land on the west side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> to the other half of the tribe. Before they left, he <char style="add">asked God to</char> bless them. <verse eid="JOS 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 22:8"/>He said, “Go back to your homes and to all the things that you have taken from your enemies—the many animals and silver and gold and <char style="add">things made of</char> bronze and iron, and many beautiful clothes. But you should share some of those things with other people of your tribe.”<verse eid="JOS 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 22:9"/>So the people of the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh left the other Israelis at Shiloh in Canaan land, to return to their homes in the Gilead region. That was the area that belonged to them. It had been allotted to them by Moses as Yahweh had commanded.<verse eid="JOS 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 22:10"/>The people from those three tribes arrived near the western side of the Jordan River, at a town called Geliloth. There they built a large altar. <char style="add">Then they crossed the Jordan River to the Gilead region</char>. <verse eid="JOS 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 22:11"/>But the other Israelis who were still at Shiloh heard about the altar that those men had built. <verse eid="JOS 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 22:12"/>They became very angry with the men of those tribes, so they decided to fight them.<verse eid="JOS 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 22:13"/>The Israelis sent Phinehas, who was the son of Eleazar the Supreme Priest, to <char style="add">talk with</char> the people of those three tribes. <verse eid="JOS 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 22:14"/>They also sent one leader from each of the ten tribes that were still at Shiloh. Each of them was a leader of his clan.<verse eid="JOS 22:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 22:15"/>Those leaders went to the Gilead region to talk to the people of the tribes of Reuben, Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh. They said, <verse eid="JOS 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 22:16"/>“All the other Israelis are asking, ‘Why have you rebelled against the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char> by building an altar for yourselves? <verse eid="JOS 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 22:17"/>Have you forgotten what happened at Peor, <char style="add">when some Israelis sinned by worshiping the god that the Moab people-group worship</char>? Many Israelis became very sick and died because of that sin, and we are still suffering because of their sin. <verse eid="JOS 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 22:18"/>Are you now turning away from obeying Yahweh and refusing to do what he wants? If you do not stop rebelling against Yahweh today, he will be angry with all of us Israelis tomorrow.’<verse eid="JOS 22:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 22:19"/>“If <char style="add">you think that Yahweh considers</char> that your land here is not suitable for worshiping him, come back to our land where Yahweh’s Sacred Tent is. We can share our land with you. But do not rebel against Yahweh and against us by building another altar for Yahweh our God. <verse eid="JOS 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 22:20"/>Do you remember what happened when Zerah’s son Achan refused to obey <char style="add">Yahweh’s command to destroy everything in Jericho</char>? That one man disobeyed God’s command, but many [HYP] other Israelis were punished. Achan died because of his sin, but other Israelis also died.”<verse eid="JOS 22:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 22:21"/>The <char style="add">leaders of the</char> tribes of Reuben, Gad, and half the tribe of Manasseh replied, <verse eid="JOS 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 22:22"/>“Yahweh, the Almighty God, knows <char style="add">why we did that</char>, and we want you to know, too. If we have done something wrong <char style="add">against Yahweh</char>, you may kill us. <verse eid="JOS 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 22:23"/>If we have disobeyed one of Yahweh’s laws, we request that he should punish us. We did not build that new altar to completely burn animals as sacrifices to Yahweh, or to offer on it sacrifices of grain or sacrifices to maintain fellowship with God.<verse eid="JOS 22:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 22:24"/>“This is the reason that we built that altar: We were afraid/worried that some day your descendants would say that our descendants are not true Israelis. We were afraid that then they would say, ‘You are not allowed to worship Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">worship</char>. <verse eid="JOS 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 22:25"/>Yahweh caused the Jordan River to be a boundary between us and you people of the tribes of Reuben and Gad. So you are not allowed to worship Yahweh.’ We were worried that your descendants would force our descendants to stop worshiping Yahweh.<verse eid="JOS 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 22:26"/>“That is the reason that we decided to build that <char style="add">new</char> altar. But it is not an altar for completely burning sacrifices of animals and <char style="add">burning other</char> sacrifices. <verse eid="JOS 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 22:27"/>We built that new altar to prove/show to you and to us and to all of our descendants that we worship Yahweh by completely burning animal sacrifices and offerings of grain and offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh <char style="add">only at the place Yahweh chooses</char>. We do not want your descendants to say to our descendants, ‘You do not belong to Yahweh.’<verse eid="JOS 22:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 22:28"/>“In the future, if your descendants say that, our descendants can say, ‘Look at the altar that our ancestors made! It is exactly like Yahweh’s altar <char style="add">that our ancestors built</char>, but we do not burn sacrifices on it. It only shows that we are Israelis!’ <verse eid="JOS 22:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 22:29"/>We certainly do not want to rebel against Yahweh or stop doing what he desires, by building an altar for completely burning some sacrifices and burning grain offerings and making <char style="add">other</char> sacrifices. <char style="add">We know that</char> there is only one true altar for Yahweh our God, and it is in front of the Sacred Tent <char style="add">at Shiloh</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 22:30"/>When Phinehas the priest and the other <char style="add">ten</char> leaders heard what they said, they were pleased. <verse eid="JOS 22:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 22:31"/>So Phinehas said to them, “Now we know that Yahweh is with all of us Israelis, and that you were not rebelling against him <char style="add">when you built that altar</char>. And we know that Yahweh will not punish us Israelis <char style="add">because of your having done that</char>.”<verse eid="JOS 22:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 22:32"/>Then Phinehas and the Israeli leaders left the people of the tribes of Reuben and Gad in the Gilead region, and returned to Canaan. There they told the other Israelis what had happened. <verse eid="JOS 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 22:33"/>They were pleased, and they thanked God. And they did not talk any more about fighting against the people of the tribes of Reuben and Gad and destroying everything in their land.<verse eid="JOS 22:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="JOS 22:34"/>The people of the tribes of Reuben and Gad named their new altar ‘A reminder to us all that Yahweh is God’.<verse eid="JOS 22:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="JOS 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua’s final speech</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 23:1"/>Yahweh enabled the Israelis to live peacefully <char style="add">for many years</char> with the people-groups that were around them.<verse eid="JOS 23:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 23:2"/>Joshua was now very old. <char style="add">One day</char> he summoned the leaders of the tribes of Israel, the leaders of the clans, the judges, and <char style="add">other</char> officials. He said to them, “I am now very old. <verse eid="JOS 23:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 23:3"/>You people have seen what Yahweh our God has done to help you defeat the people-groups <char style="add">that lived in this land</char>. Yahweh our God has fought for you. <verse eid="JOS 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 23:4"/>But do not forget that he has given to you all this land, from the Jordan <char style="add">River in the east</char> to the Mediterranean Sea in the west, all this land that I have allotted to you. <verse eid="JOS 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 23:5"/>Yahweh our God will compel the people who are still living there to leave. He will push them out as you advance. Then the land will be yours, as Yahweh has promised you.<verse eid="JOS 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 23:6"/>“Be sure that you obey all the laws that are in the book that Moses wrote. Do not disobey any part of it [IDM]. <verse eid="JOS 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 23:7"/>Do not associate with the people who live among us <char style="add">who are not Israelis and who worship other gods</char>. Do not mention the names of their gods, and do not use the names of their gods when you promise to do something. Do not serve their gods or worship them. <verse eid="JOS 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 23:8"/>You must continue to do what Yahweh our God wants us to do, as you have been doing.<verse eid="JOS 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 23:9"/>“Yahweh has forced <char style="add">many</char> very powerful people-groups to leave as you advanced. No people-group has been able to defeat you. <verse eid="JOS 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 23:10"/>Each of you will be able to cause 1,000 of them to run away, because Yahweh your God will fight for you, just like he promised to do. <verse eid="JOS 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 23:11"/>So be sure that you continue to love Yahweh our God.<verse eid="JOS 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 23:12"/>“If you turn away from doing what Yahweh desires and you associate with the people who are not Israelis, and if you marry them, <verse eid="JOS 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 23:13"/>then you can be sure that Yahweh our God will not help you to expel those people-groups from your land. They will be <char style="add">like</char> traps [DOU, MET] <char style="add">that will catch you</char>. They will be <char style="add">like</char> whips <char style="add">that strike</char> your backs, and like thorns <char style="add">that will scratch</char> your eyes. As a result, none of you will be left in this good land that Yahweh our God is giving to you.<verse eid="JOS 23:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 23:14"/>“It is almost time for me to die, like everyone does [EUP]. You know in your hearts [DOU] that Yahweh has done for you [LIT] everything that he promised to do. <verse eid="JOS 23:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 23:15"/>He has given to you all the good things that he promised. In the same way, the other things that he promised, <char style="add">things that are not good</char>, will also happen. He said that if you do what is evil, he will get rid of you and send you away from this good land that he has given to you. <verse eid="JOS 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 23:16"/>That will happen if you do not obey the commands that Yahweh our God told you to obey. If you serve other gods and worship them, Yahweh will become very angry with you. Very quickly <char style="add">he will expel you from</char> this good land that he has given to you, <char style="add">and</char> none of you will be left here.”<verse eid="JOS 23:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="JOS 24"/>
  <para style="s1">Joshua encouraged the Israeli people to worship only Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="JOS 24:1"/>
    <char style="add">Many years later</char>, Joshua summoned representatives of all the tribes of Israel. He gathered together the elders, the leaders, the judges, and the other officials at Shechem <char style="add">city</char>. He told them to listen to what God wanted to tell them. <verse eid="JOS 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="JOS 24:2"/>Joshua said to all of them, “This is what Yahweh, the God we Israeli people worship, is saying: ‘Long ago, your ancestors, including Abraham’s father Terah and Abraham’s younger brother Nahor, lived on the east side of the Euphrates River. <verse eid="JOS 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="JOS 24:3"/>But I took your ancestor Abraham from that land east of the Euphrates River, and I led him as he lived in various places in this land of Canaan, and I enabled him to have many descendants. First, I enabled him to have a son, Isaac. <verse eid="JOS 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="JOS 24:4"/>When Isaac grew up, I enabled him to have twin sons, Jacob and Esau. I enabled Esau to live in the hilly area in Seir region, but many years later Jacob and his sons and their families went down to live in Egypt.<verse eid="JOS 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="JOS 24:5"/>“<char style="add">Many years later</char>, I sent Moses and his older brother Aaron to help your people, and I caused <char style="add">the people of</char> Egypt to suffer very much because of what I did there. Then I enabled your ancestors to leave Egypt. <verse eid="JOS 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="JOS 24:6"/>When I brought your ancestors out of Egypt, they came to the Red Sea. The Egyptian army pursued them, some riding in chariots and others on horses, and they also arrived at the Red Sea. <verse eid="JOS 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="JOS 24:7"/>Then <char style="add">your ancestors</char> pleaded with me to help them. So he caused ◄darkness/a very dark cloud► to come between your ancestors and the Egyptian army, so that the Egyptian army could not see your ancestors. I separated the water in the Red Sea so that your ancestors could cross it, but when the Egyptian army tried to cross in the same way to pursue them, I caused the water to come back and cover them, and the Egyptian soldiers all drowned, as your ancestors watched and were amazed [IDM]. But after that, you lived in the desert for many years.<verse eid="JOS 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="JOS 24:8"/>“Then I brought your <char style="add">ancestors</char> to the area where the groups who were descendants of Amor lived, east of the Jordan River. They fought against you, but I enabled you to defeat them [IDM]. I <char style="add">enabled you to</char> destroy them so that you could live in their land [IDM]. <verse eid="JOS 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="JOS 24:9"/>Then, Zippor’s son Balak, the King of Moab, ◄decided that his army would fight against/opposed► the Israelis. He summoned Beor’s son Balaam and asked him to curse you. <verse eid="JOS 24:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="JOS 24:10"/>But I would not do what Balaam asked, so he ◄blessed/said that I would do great things for► you four times, and I did not enable the army of Moab to defeat you [IDM].<verse eid="JOS 24:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="JOS 24:11"/>“Then you all crossed the Jordan River and came to Jericho. The people of Jericho prepared to fight against you, <char style="add">and the armies of</char> the descendants of Amor, Periz, Canaan, Heth, Girgash, Hiv, and Jebus <char style="add">all prepared to do the same thing</char> but I enabled you to defeat [IDM] them all. <verse eid="JOS 24:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="JOS 24:12"/>I am the one who caused them to panic as you advanced and enabled you to defeat them, as I had enabled you to do earlier to the two kings of the groups who were descendants of Amor. You did not defeat them by using your own bows and arrows and swords; <char style="add">it was I who defeated them</char>. <verse eid="JOS 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="JOS 24:13"/>So I gave you a land that you had not tilled/planted, and I gave you cities that you did not build. <char style="add">Now</char> you live in those <char style="add">cities</char> and you eat the grapes from the grapevines that you did not plant, and you eat olives from trees that you did not plant.’ ”<verse eid="JOS 24:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="JOS 24:14"/>
    <char style="add">Then Joshua said to the people</char>, “<char style="add">Because of all that</char> Yahweh <char style="add">has done for you</char>, revere him, and serve/worship him very faithfully. Throw away the idols that your ancestors worshiped on the east/other side of the Euphrates River and in Egypt. Serve only Yahweh. <verse eid="JOS 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="JOS 24:15"/>But if you do not want to serve/worship Yahweh, you should decide today what <char style="add">gods</char> you will serve/worship. You should decide whether you will serve/worship the gods that your ancestors who lived on the other/east side of the Euphrates River served, or whether you will serve/worship the gods that the descendants of Amor, who previously lived in the land where you are now living, <char style="add">serve/worship</char>. But as for me and my family [MTY], we will serve/worship Yahweh!”<verse eid="JOS 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="JOS 24:16"/>The Israeli people answered, “We will never quit <char style="add">serving/worshiping</char> Yahweh! We would never <char style="add">think of</char> [IDM] serving/worshiping other gods! <verse eid="JOS 24:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="JOS 24:17"/>It was our God, Yahweh, who brought our parents and grandparents up out of Egypt. <char style="add">He rescued them</char> from that land where they were slaves. As he rescued them, they saw him perform great miracles. He protected them all the time when they were traveling. He protected them from all the people-groups through whose territory they traveled. <verse eid="JOS 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="JOS 24:18"/>As our forefathers advanced, Yahweh expelled the descendants of Amor and the other people-groups who lived in this land. Yahweh is our God, so <char style="add">we are saying that</char> we also will serve/worship him.”<verse eid="JOS 24:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="JOS 24:19"/>Joshua replied to the people, “<char style="add">I think that</char> you are not able to serve/worship Yahweh, because he is a holy God. He will not forgive your sinning and rebelling <char style="add">against him</char>. He demands that you serve/worship only him [IDM]. <verse eid="JOS 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="JOS 24:20"/>He has been good to you <char style="add">in the past</char>, but if you turn away from him and serve/worship foreign/other gods, he will turn <char style="add">against you</char> and he will cause you to experience disasters. He will punish [IDM] you severely!” <verse eid="JOS 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="JOS 24:21"/>But the people replied to Joshua, “No, <char style="add">we will not turn away from worshiping/serving Yahweh</char> We will serve/worship Yahweh!”<verse eid="JOS 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="JOS 24:22"/>Then Joshua said, “You yourselves are saying that you have decided to serve/worship Yahweh.” They replied, “Yes, we are saying that.” <verse eid="JOS 24:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="JOS 24:23"/>Then Joshua said, “Since <char style="add">you have decided</char> that, you must throw away all the other gods/idols that you have among you. You must also promise that you will wholeheartedly give yourselves to Yahweh, the God whom we Israelis <char style="add">serve/worship</char>.” <verse eid="JOS 24:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="JOS 24:24"/>The people replied, “We will serve/worship Yahweh, our God, and obey him.”<verse eid="JOS 24:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="JOS 24:25"/>That day, Joshua established an agreement between the people and Yahweh. He wrote for them all the laws that they were required to obey. <verse eid="JOS 24:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="JOS 24:26"/>He wrote all those laws on a scroll. He called it ‘The laws of God’. Then he <char style="add">told some men to</char> set up a large stone there at Shechem, under the <char style="add">large</char> oak tree near the place where <char style="add">they worshiped</char> Yahweh. <verse eid="JOS 24:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="JOS 24:27"/>He said to all the people, “Look! <char style="add">It is as though</char> this stone has heard everything that Yahweh said to you <char style="add">and that you promised Yahweh</char>. It will serve as a witness against you if you rebel against your God!”<verse eid="JOS 24:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="JOS 24:28"/>Then Joshua sent the people away, and all of them returned to their own areas/homes.<verse eid="JOS 24:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">
    <char style="add">Joshua died</char></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="JOS 24:29"/>Some time after that, Nun’s son Joshua, the faithful servant of Yahweh, died. He was 110 years old when he died. <verse eid="JOS 24:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="JOS 24:30"/>The Israeli people buried his body on his own property in Timnath-Serah <char style="add">town</char> town. It is north of Gaash Mountain in the hilly area of the tribe who were descendants of Ephraim. <verse eid="JOS 24:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="JOS 24:31"/>The Israeli people served/worshiped Yahweh as long as Joshua was alive. After Joshua died, they continued serving/worshiping Yahweh while the elders who had experienced everything that Yahweh had done for the Israeli people were still alive. <verse eid="JOS 24:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="JOS 24:32"/>Joseph’s bones, which the Israeli people had brought with them from Egypt, were also buried at Shechem. The people buried them in the piece of land that Jacob had bought long ago for 100 pieces of silver from Hamor, the father of Shechem. That piece of land was in the area that was given to the people who were descendants of Ephraim and Manasseh, Joseph’s sons. <verse eid="JOS 24:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="JOS 24:33"/>Eleazar, the Supreme Priest, the son of Aaron, also died. They buried his body at Gibeah, in the area that had been given to Eleazar’s son Phinehas, in the hilly area that belonged to the people who were descendants of Ephraim.<verse eid="JOS 24:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="JOS 24"/>
</usx>
