<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="LEV" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">LEVITICUS</para>
  <para style="toc1">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="toc2">Leviticus</para>
  <para style="toc3">Lev</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of God giving some more laws for his people</para>
  <para style="mt1">Leviticus</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="LEV 1"/>
  <para style="s1">The burnt offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 1:1"/>While Moses/I was <char style="add">standing near the entrance</char> to the Sacred Tent, Yahweh called to him/me from inside the tent. He said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 1:2"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: ‘When any of you brings an offering to Yahweh, bring one of your sheep or goats or cattle.<verse eid="LEV 1:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 1:3"/>‘If what you are offering is a bull that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, it must not have any defects. You must take it to the entrance to the Sacred Tent, in order that it will be acceptable to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 1:4"/>You must lay your hands on the head of the bull. When you do that, Yahweh will accept <char style="add">its death in your place</char> to forgive/pardon you for the sins that you have committed. <verse eid="LEV 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 1:5"/>You must slaughter the bull in front of Yahweh. Then Aaron’s sons, who are priests, will bring the blood and sprinkle it against all sides of the altar near the entrance to the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 1:6"/>You must remove the skin of the animal and cut the animal into pieces. You must wash the inner parts and the legs of the bull. <verse eid="LEV 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 1:7"/>Then Aaron’s sons will put wood on the altar and light a fire. <verse eid="LEV 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 1:8"/>Then they will arrange the pieces, including the head and the fat, on the burning wood. <verse eid="LEV 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 1:9"/>Then one of the priests will completely burn all of it on the altar. And the aroma will be pleasing to Yahweh.<verse eid="LEV 1:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 1:10"/>‘If you are offering a sheep or a goat, it must be a male without any defect. <verse eid="LEV 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 1:11"/>You must slaughter it in front of Yahweh, on the north side of the altar, <char style="add">and drain all the blood into a bowl</char>. Then Aaron’s sons will sprinkle the blood against all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 1:12"/>You must cut the animal into pieces. You must wash the inner parts and the legs of the animal. Then the priests will arrange the pieces, including the head and the fat, on the burning wood. <verse eid="LEV 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 1:13"/>Then one of the priests will take all of it and completely burn all of it on the altar. And the aroma as it burns will be pleasing to Yahweh.<verse eid="LEV 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 1:14"/>‘If what you are offering to Yahweh is a bird, you must offer a dove or a young pigeon. <verse eid="LEV 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 1:15"/>The priest will take it to the altar and wring/twist off its head. Then he will burn the head on the altar. He will drain out the bird’s blood onto the side of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 1:16"/>Then he will remove the bird’s ◄craw/food-grinding pouch► and what is inside it, and throw it on the east side of the altar, where the ashes are thrown. <verse eid="LEV 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 1:17"/>Then he will grasp the bird’s wings and partially tear the bird open. Then he will burn it completely in the fire on the altar. And the aroma will be pleasing to Yahweh.’<verse eid="LEV 1:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="LEV 2"/>
  <para style="s1">The grain offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 2:1"/>‘If you bring to Yahweh an offering of grain, it must consist of finely-ground flour. You must pour olive oil on it, and put some incense on it, <verse eid="LEV 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 2:2"/>and take it to one of the priests. The priest will take a handful of the flour and the oil with the incense and burn it on the altar. That part will symbolize <char style="add">that all of the offering truly belongs to Yahweh</char>. And the aroma will be pleasing to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 2:3"/>The part of that offering that is not burned will belong to Aaron and his sons. It is a very holy part of the offerings that are given to Yahweh by <char style="add">burning them</char> in a fire.<verse eid="LEV 2:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 2:4"/>‘If you bring an offering that is made from grain, something that is baked in an oven, it must be made from finely-ground flour. You may bring loaves made from flour mixed with olive oil but without yeast, or you may bring wafers with olive oil smeared on them, but also made without yeast. <verse eid="LEV 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 2:5"/>If your offering is cooked ◄on a griddle/in a shallow pan►, it must be made from finely-ground flour mixed with olive oil and without yeast. <verse eid="LEV 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 2:6"/>You must crumble it and pour olive oil on it. That will be your offering made from grain. <verse eid="LEV 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 2:7"/>If your offering that is made from grain is cooked in a pan, it must be made of finely-ground flour mixed with olive oil. <verse eid="LEV 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 2:8"/>Bring to Yahweh your grain offering. Give it to the priest, and he will take it to the altar. <verse eid="LEV 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 2:9"/>He will take a part of it that will symbolize that all the offering belongs to Yahweh. He will burn that part on the altar, and the aroma as it burns will be pleasing to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 2:10"/>The part that is not burned will belong to Aaron and his sons. It is a very holy part of the offerings given to Yahweh by <char style="add">burning them</char> in a fire.<verse eid="LEV 2:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 2:11"/>‘Every offering that is made from grain and that you bring to Yahweh must be made without yeast, because you must not put any yeast or honey in any offering to Yahweh that is burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 2:12"/>You may bring to Yahweh an offering of the first part of your harvest, but that is not to be burned on the altar to produce an aroma that will be pleasing to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 2:13"/>Put salt on all your offerings that are made from grain. The salt represents the agreement that your God <char style="add">made with</char> you, so be sure that you do not forget to put salt on those offerings.<verse eid="LEV 2:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 2:14"/>‘If you bring to Yahweh an offering of the first part of your harvest of grain, offer some new grain that has been crushed and roasted in a fire. <verse eid="LEV 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 2:15"/>Put olive oil and incense on it, and that will be your offering made from grain. <verse eid="LEV 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 2:16"/>The priest will take a part of the flour and oil along with the incense. <char style="add">That will symbolize that all the offering truly belongs to Yahweh</char>. He will burn that part on the altar, to be an offering given to Yahweh by <char style="add">burning it</char> in a fire.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 2:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="LEV 3"/>
  <para style="s1">The fellowship offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 3:1"/>
    <char style="add">“Also tell the people</char>, ‘When the offering that you bring to Yahweh is to maintain good fellowship <char style="add">with him</char>, you may bring a bull or a cow from your herd <char style="add">of cattle</char>, but what you present to Yahweh must be an animal that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 3:2"/>You must bring the animal to the entrance to the Sacred Tent. You must lay your hands on its head. Then you must slaughter it <char style="add">and drain some of its blood in a bowl</char>. Then one of Aaron’s sons, one of the priests, will sprinkle the blood against all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 3:3"/>From that offering, you must offer to Yahweh, as a sacrifice that will be burned in the fire, all the fat that covers the inner parts of the animal, or which is attached to them— <verse eid="LEV 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 3:4"/>the kidneys and the fat that is attached to them near the lower back muscle, and the fat that covers the liver. <verse eid="LEV 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 3:5"/>Then one of the priests will burn those things on the altar, along with the other parts of the animal that will be completely burned to be an offering <char style="add">to Yahweh</char>. And the aroma while it burns will be pleasing to Yahweh.<verse eid="LEV 3:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 3:6"/>If that offering to maintain good fellowship with Yahweh is a sheep or a goat, it must also be an animal that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 3:7"/>If you offer a lamb, you must present it to Yahweh <char style="add">at the entrance to the Sacred Tent</char>. You must lay your hands on the lamb’s head and then slaughter it. <char style="add">‘You must drain some of its blood in a bowl</char>. <verse eid="LEV 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 3:8"/>Then one of the priests will sprinkle that blood against all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 3:9"/>You must dedicate these things to be a sacrifice to Yahweh that is burned: Its fat, the fat tail that you must cut off close to the backbone, and all the fat that covers the inner parts of the lamb or which is attached to them— <verse eid="LEV 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 3:10"/>the kidneys with the fat that is on them near the lower back muscle, and the fat that covers the liver. <verse eid="LEV 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 3:11"/>One of the priests will burn those things on the altar to be an offering to Yahweh; <char style="add">it will be as though</char> they will be a special food <char style="add">given to Yahweh</char>.<verse eid="LEV 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 3:12"/>‘If your offering is a goat, you must take/present it to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 3:13"/>You must lay your hands on its head. Then you must slaughter it in front of the Sacred Tent. Then one of Aaron’s sons will sprinkle the blood against all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 3:14"/>From that offering you must dedicate these things to be a sacrifice to Yahweh that is burned: All the fat that covers the inner parts of the animal or which is attached to them, <verse eid="LEV 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 3:15"/>the kidneys with the fat that is on them near the lower back muscle, and the fat that covers the liver. <verse eid="LEV 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 3:16"/>The priest will burn those things on the altar to be an offering to Yahweh; <char style="add">it will be as though</char> they will be a special food <char style="add">given to Yahweh</char>. And the aroma while it burns will be pleasing to Yahweh. All the fat <char style="add">of the animals that are sacrificed</char> belongs to Yahweh.<verse eid="LEV 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 3:17"/>‘This is a command that must be obeyed by you and your descendants forever, wherever you live: You must not eat the fat or the blood <char style="add">of any animal</char>.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 3:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="LEV 4"/>
  <para style="s1">The sin offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 4:1"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 4:2"/>“Say this to the Israeli people: This is what must be done if someone sins without intending to sin, doing something that is forbidden in any of Yahweh’s commands.<verse eid="LEV 4:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 4:3"/>'If the Supreme [MTY] Priest sins, and that causes all the people to be guilty, he must bring to Yahweh a young bull that has no defects. That will be an offering for the sin that he has committed. <verse eid="LEV 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 4:4"/>He must bring the bull to the entrance to the Sacred Tent. He must lay his hands on its head. Then he must slaughter it in front of Yahweh <char style="add">and drain some of the blood into a bowl</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 4:5"/>Then the Supreme Priest must take some of that blood into the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 4:6"/>He must dip <char style="add">one of</char> his fingers into the blood and sprinkle it seven times in the presence of Yahweh, in front of the curtain <char style="add">that separates the Holy Place from the Very Holy Place</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 4:7"/>Then he must put some of the blood on the projections at the corners of the altar where fragrant incense is burned in the Sacred Tent in the presence of Yahweh. The remaining part of the bull’s blood <char style="add">that is still in the bowl</char>, he must pour out at the base of the altar, where sacrifices are burned, at the entrance to the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 4:8"/>From that offering the Supreme Priest must separate these things from the bull that is to be burned: The fat that covers the inner parts of the bull or which is attached to them— <verse eid="LEV 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 4:9"/>the kidneys and the fat that is attached to them near the lower back muscle, and the fat that covers the liver. <verse eid="LEV 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 4:10"/>Then the Supreme Priest must completely burn those things on the altar. That will be just like when the fat is removed from an animal that is sacrificed to maintain good fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 4:11"/>But all the other parts of the animal—its skin/hide and all its other meat, its head and its legs, its inner parts and the intestines, <verse eid="LEV 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 4:12"/>he must take outside the camp and throw them in a place that is acceptable to Yahweh, where the ashes are thrown, and he must burn them in a fire on the pile of ashes.<verse eid="LEV 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 4:13"/>‘If all the Israeli people sin without intending to sin, doing something that is forbidden in any of Yahweh’s commands, they will be guilty, even if they do not realize that they have sinned. <verse eid="LEV 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 4:14"/>When they realize that they have committed a sin, together they must bring a young bull to be an offering for their sin, to the front of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 4:15"/>The elders must lay their hands on the bull’s head in the presence of Yahweh and slaughter it <char style="add">and catch some of the blood in a bowl</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 4:16"/>Then the Supreme [MTY] Priest must take some of that blood into the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 4:17"/>‘He must dip <char style="add">one of</char> his fingers into the blood and sprinkle it seven times in the presence of Yahweh, in front of the curtain <char style="add">that separates the Holy Place from the Very Holy Place</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 4:18"/>Then he must put some of the blood on the projections at the corners of the altar that is in the presence of Yahweh in the Sacred Tent. The remaining part of the bull’s blood, he must pour out at the base of the altar where sacrifices are burned, at the entrance of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 4:19"/>He must remove all the animal’s fat and burn it on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 4:20"/>He must do with this bull the same things that he did with the bull that was an offering for his own sins, and they will be forgiven {Yahweh will forgive them}. <verse eid="LEV 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 4:21"/>Then the priest must take <char style="add">the other parts of</char> the bull outside the camp and burn them, like he does when he himself has sinned. That will be the offering for the sin that all the people have committed, and they will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 4:22"/>‘When one of the leaders sins without intending to sin, doing something that is forbidden in any of the commands of Yahweh his God, he will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 4:23"/>When he realizes that he has committed a sin, he must bring as his offering a male goat that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 4:24"/>He must lay his hands on the goat’s head in the presence of Yahweh and slaughter it at the place where they slaughter {are slaughtered} the animals that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. That will be an offering for his sin. <verse eid="LEV 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 4:25"/>Then the priest must put some of the animal’s blood <char style="add">into a bowl</char> and dip <char style="add">one of</char> his fingers in it and put some of the blood on the corners of the projections of the altar. Then he must pour out the rest of the blood at the base of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 4:26"/>Then he must burn all the fat on the altar, as was done with the fat of the offering to maintain good fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>. As a result of the priest’s doing that, the leader will no longer be guilty for his sin and he will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 4:27"/>‘If one of the Israeli people who is not a priest sins without intending to sin, and does something that is forbidden in any of the commands of Yahweh his God, he will be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 4:28"/>When he realizes that he has committed a sin, he must bring as his offering a female goat that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 4:29"/>He must lay his hands on the goat’s head and slaughter it at the place where they slaughter the animals that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar, and catch some of the blood in a bowl</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 4:30"/>Then the priest must dip <char style="add">one of</char> his fingers in the blood, and put some of it on the projections at the corners of the altar. Then he must pour out the rest of the blood at the base of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 4:31"/>Then he must remove all the goat’s fat, and burn all the fat on the altar, like was done with the fat of the offering to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>. And the aroma while it burns will be pleasing to Yahweh. As a result of the priest doing that, the person will no longer be guilty for his sin, and he will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 4:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 4:32"/>‘If that person brings a lamb to be his offering for sin, he must bring a female lamb that has no defects. <verse eid="LEV 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 4:33"/>He must lay his hands on the lamb’s head and slaughter it at the place where they slaughter the animals that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar, and catch some of the blood in a bowl</char>. <verse eid="LEV 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 4:34"/>Then the priest must dip <char style="add">one of</char> his fingers in the blood and put some of it on the projections at the corners of the altar. Then he must pour out the rest of the blood at the base of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 4:35"/>Then he must remove all the lamb’s fat, and burn all the fat on the altar, like was done with the fat of the offering to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>. He must burn it on top of the other offerings to Yahweh that are being burned. As a result, the priest will request God to forgive that person for his sin, and he will be forgiven.’”<verse eid="LEV 4:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="LEV 5"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 5:1"/>
    <char style="add">Yahweh also said to tell the people</char>, “If <char style="add">a judge</char> orders any of you to tell <char style="add">in court</char> something that you have seen or something that you heard someone say, if you refuse to say what you know is true, you must ◄pay a penalty/be punished► [MTY] for refusing to tell what you know.<verse eid="LEV 5:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 5:2"/>If you accidentally touch something which God considers impure [DOU], such as the carcass of a wild animal or the carcass of a bull or cow, or of an animal that scurries across the ground, you must ◄pay a penalty/be punished►.<verse eid="LEV 5:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 5:3"/>If you touch any human feces, even if you do not intend to do that, when you realize what you have done, you must ◄pay a penalty/be punished►.<verse eid="LEV 5:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 5:4"/>If you carelessly make a solemn promise <char style="add">to do something</char> that is good or that is bad, when you realize what you have done, you must ◄pay a penalty/be punished►.<verse eid="LEV 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 5:5"/>If you are guilty of committing any of those sins, you must confess what you have done. <verse eid="LEV 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 5:6"/>And for a penalty you must bring to Yahweh a female lamb or female goat, to be an offering for the sin that you have committed, and the priest will sacrifice it, and then you will no longer be guilty for your sin.<verse eid="LEV 5:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 5:7"/>If you <char style="add">are poor and</char> cannot afford to bring a lamb, you must bring to Yahweh two doves or two young pigeons. One will be an offering for your sin and one will be an offering that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 5:8"/>You must bring them to the priest. First he will offer one of them to be an offering for your sin. He will wring/twist its neck <char style="add">to kill it</char>, but he must not pull off its head completely. <verse eid="LEV 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 5:9"/>Then he must sprinkle some of the blood against the side of the altar. The remaining blood must be drained out at the base of the altar. That will be an offering for your sin. <verse eid="LEV 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 5:10"/>The priest will then do what I have commanded and offer the other bird to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. Then you will no longer be guilty for the sin you have committed, and Yahweh will forgive you.<verse eid="LEV 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 5:11"/>However, if you <char style="add">are very poor and</char> cannot afford two doves or two young pigeons, you must bring to be an offering for your sin ◄2 pounds/1 kg.► of fine flour. You must not put olive oil or incense on it, because it is an offering for sin. <verse eid="LEV 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 5:12"/>You must take it to the priest. He will take a handful of it, to symbolize that the whole offering truly belongs to Yahweh, and burn it on the altar, on top of the other offerings. <verse eid="LEV 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 5:13"/>And by doing that, the priest will enable you to no longer be guilty for any of the sins that you have committed, and you will be forgiven. The part of the offering that is not burned will belong to the priest, like was true for the offerings made from grain.”<verse eid="LEV 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The guilt offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 5:14"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 5:15"/>“When you sin, without intending to, by not giving to Yahweh the things that you are required to give to him, you must pay a penalty by bringing to Yahweh a ram that has no defects. You must determine how much silver it is worth, by using the official standard in the temple. It will be an offering to cause you to no longer be guilty. <verse eid="LEV 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 5:16"/>But you must also make restitution for what you failed to give to Yahweh, adding one-fifth of its value. You must give that to the priest. He will offer the ram as a sacrifice for the sin that you have committed, and cause you to no longer be guilty; and you will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 5:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 5:17"/>If you sin by doing something that is forbidden by any of Yahweh’s commands, even if you do not know that you have disobeyed one of my commands, you are guilty and must pay a penalty <char style="add">to me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 5:18"/><char style="add">When you realize what you have done</char>, you must bring a ram to the Supreme Priest to be an offering in order that you will no longer be guilty. You must bring one that has no defects. He will offer the ram to be a sacrifice to me, and as a result you will no longer be guilty for the sin that you have committed, and you will be forgiven. <verse eid="LEV 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 5:19"/>It is an offering to cause you to no longer be guilty for sinning against me.”<verse eid="LEV 5:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="LEV 6"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 6:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 6:2"/>“If any one of you you sins against me by deceiving someone—if you refuse to return what someone has lent you, or if you steal something of his, or if you find something and claim that you do not have it, <verse eid="LEV 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 6:3"/>you are guilty. You must return to its owner what you have stolen or what someone has lent you and you have not returned, or what you found that someone else had lost, <verse eid="LEV 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 6:4"/>or whatever you lied about. <verse eid="LEV 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 6:5"/>You must not only return anything like that to its owner, but you must also pay to the owner one-fifth of its value. <verse eid="LEV 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 6:6"/>You must also bring to the Supreme Priest a ram to be an offering to me in order that you will no longer be guilty. The ram that you bring must be one that has no defects, one that has the value that has been officially determined. <verse eid="LEV 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 6:7"/>Then he will offer that ram to be a sacrifice that will cause you to no longer be guilty, and you will be forgiven for the wrong things that you did.”<verse eid="LEV 6:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Other instructions concerning the burnt offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 6:8"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 6:9"/>“Tell this to Aaron and his sons: These are the regulations concerning the offerings that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>: The offering must remain on the altar all during the night, and the fire on the altar must always be kept burning. <verse eid="LEV 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 6:10"/><char style="add">The next morning</char> the priest must put on his linen under-clothes and linen outer clothes. Then he must remove the ashes of the offering from the fire and put them beside the altar. <verse eid="LEV 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 6:11"/>Then he must take off those clothes and put on other clothes, and take the ashes outside the camp, to a place that is acceptable to me. <verse eid="LEV 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 6:12"/>The fire on the altar must always be kept burning; the priest must not allow it to ◄go out/quit burning►. Each morning the priest must put more firewood on the fire. Then he must arrange more offerings on the fire, and burn on the altar the fat of the offerings to be burned to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 6:13"/>The fire on the altar must be kept burning continually; the priest must not allow it to go out.”<verse eid="LEV 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Other instructions concerning the grain offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 6:14"/>“These are the regulations concerning the offerings made from grain: Aaron’s sons must bring them to me in front of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 6:15"/>The priest must take a handful of fine flour mixed with olive oil and incense and burn that on the altar. That handful will signify that the whole offering truly belongs to me. And the aroma while it burns will be pleasing to me. <verse eid="LEV 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 6:16"/>Aaron and his sons may eat the remaining part of the grain offering. But they must eat it in a holy place, in the courtyard of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 6:17"/>It must not have yeast mixed with it. Like the offerings for sin and the offerings to cause people to no longer be guilty of sin, that offering is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 6:18"/>Any male descendants of Aaron are permitted to eat it, because it is forever their regular share of the offerings given to me and burned in the fire <char style="add">on the altar</char>. Anyone else who touches those offerings made from grain will be punished by God.”<verse eid="LEV 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 6:19"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 6:20"/>“Tell Aaron and his sons that this is the offering that they must bring to Yahweh on the day that any of them ◄is ordained/becomes a priest►: That person must bring two quarts/liters of fine flour as an offering made from grain. He must bring half of it in the morning and half of it in the evening. <verse eid="LEV 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 6:21"/>He must mix it well with olive oil and bake it in a shallow pan. He must then break it into small pieces to be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. And the aroma while it burns will be pleasing to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 6:22"/>I have commanded that the descendants of Aaron who are appointed in turn to become the Supreme Priests after Aaron dies are the ones who must prepare those things. These offerings must be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> to be sacrifices to me, Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 6:23"/>Every offering that a priest gives that is made from grain must be completely burned; none of it is to be eaten.”<verse eid="LEV 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Other instructions concerning the sin offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 6:24"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 6:25"/>“Tell Aaron and his sons: These are the regulations concerning the offerings that people must bring to me so that I will forgive the people for the sins they have committed: <verse eid="LEV 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 6:26"/>The animals must be slaughtered in my presence in the same place that the animals that are to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> are slaughtered, in the courtyard in front of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 6:27"/>Any other person who touches any of its meat will be punished by God. And if its blood is splattered on your clothes, you must wash the clothes in a holy place. <verse eid="LEV 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 6:28"/>If the meat is cooked in a clay pot, the pot must be broken <char style="add">afterwards</char>. But if it is cooked in a bronze pot, the pot must be scoured <char style="add">afterwards</char> and rinsed with water. <verse eid="LEV 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 6:29"/>Any male in a priest’s family may eat some of the cooked meat; that meat is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 6:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 6:30"/>But if the blood of those sin offerings is brought into the Sacred Tent to enable the people to be forgiven for having sinned, the meat of those animals must not be eaten. The meat must be completely burned.”<verse eid="LEV 6:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="LEV 7"/>
  <para style="s1">The guilt offering</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 7:1"/>“These are the regulations concerning the offerings to be made by people who are guilty of not giving to me the things that are required to be given to me. Those are very sacred offerings. <verse eid="LEV 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 7:2"/>Each animal that is to be offered by such people must be slaughtered in the same place where the animals that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> are slaughtered, and their blood must be sprinkled against all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 7:3"/>All their fat, the fat tails that are cut close to the backbone, and all the fat that covers the inner parts of the animals or which is attached to them, must be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 7:4"/>That includes the kidneys with their fat near the lower back muscle, and the protruding lobe that is attached to the liver. <verse eid="LEV 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 7:5"/>The priest must burn them on the altar to be offerings to me, Yahweh. They are an offering for the people to be forgiven for not doing what they were required to do. <verse eid="LEV 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 7:6"/>All the males in the priest’s family are permitted to eat its meat, but it must be eaten in a sacred place, because it is very sacred.<verse eid="LEV 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 7:7"/>“The regulation is the same for the offerings <char style="add">to enable people to be forgiven for the sins they have committed </char> and the offerings for when they are guilty of not giving to me the things that are required to be given to me. The meat of those offerings belongs to the priest who offers them in order that the people will be forgiven. <verse eid="LEV 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 7:8"/>The priest who slaughters an animal that will be completely burned on the altar is permitted to keep the animal’s hide for himself. <verse eid="LEV 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 7:9"/>Offerings of things made from grain that are baked in an oven or cooked in a pan or ◄in a shallow pan/on a griddle► belong to the priest who makes those offerings <char style="add">for another person</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 7:10"/>And offerings of things made from grain, whether they were mixed with olive oil or not, also belong to the sons of Aaron.”<verse eid="LEV 7:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 7:11"/>These are the regulations concerning the offerings that people make to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>:<verse eid="LEV 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 7:12"/>“If you bring an offering to thank <char style="add">Yahweh</char>, along with <char style="add">the animal that you slaughter</char> you must offer loaves of bread made with olive oil mixed <char style="add">with the flour</char> but without yeast, and wafers that are made without yeast but with olive oil smeared on them, and loaves made from fine flour with olive oil well mixed with the flour. <verse eid="LEV 7:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 7:13"/>Along with that offering to thank Yahweh, you must bring an offering of loaves made with yeast. <verse eid="LEV 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 7:14"/>You must bring one of each kind for an offering to Yahweh, but they belong to the priest who sprinkles against the altar the blood of the animal that is <char style="add">slaughtered as an offering</char> to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 7:15"/>The meat of that offering must be eaten on the day that it is offered; none of it should be left to <char style="add">be eaten on</char> the next day.<verse eid="LEV 7:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 7:16"/>“However, if your offering is the result of a solemn promise that you made to Yahweh, or if it is an offering that you make ◄voluntarily/without being required to►, you are permitted to eat some of the meat on the day it is offered, but anything that is left may be eaten on the next day. <verse eid="LEV 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 7:17"/>But any meat that is left until the third day must be completely burned. <verse eid="LEV 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 7:18"/>If any meat from the offering to maintain fellowship with Yahweh is eaten on the third day, Yahweh will not accept that offering; it will be useless to offer it, because Yahweh will consider that it is worthless. Anyone who eats some of it will have to pay a penalty <char style="add">to Yahweh</char>.<verse eid="LEV 7:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 7:19"/>“Meat that touches something <char style="add">that God considers to be</char> impure must not be eaten; it must be completely burned. Anyone who has performed the rituals to become acceptable to God is allowed to eat other meat <char style="add">which has been offered as a sacrifice</char>. <verse eid="LEV 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 7:20"/>But if anyone who has not performed those rituals eats some of the meat of the offering to maintain fellowship with Yahweh, meat that belongs to Yahweh, he must no longer be allowed to associate with God’s people. <verse eid="LEV 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 7:21"/>If anyone touches something that God considers to be impure and very displeasing to him, whether it is from a human or from an animal, and then he eats any of the meat of the offering to maintain fellowship with Yahweh, meat that belongs to Yahweh, he must no longer be allowed to associate with God’s people.”<verse eid="LEV 7:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Eating fat or blood is forbidden</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 7:22"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me: <verse eid="LEV 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 7:23"/>“Say this to the Israeli people: ‘Do not eat any of the fat of cattle or sheep or goats. <verse eid="LEV 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 7:24"/>The fat of an animal that is found dead or that has been killed by a wild animal may be used for other purposes, but you must not eat it. <verse eid="LEV 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 7:25"/>Anyone who eats the fat of an animal from which an offering has been made to Yahweh must no longer be allowed to associate with God’s people. <verse eid="LEV 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 7:26"/>And wherever you live, you must not eat the blood of any bird or animal. <verse eid="LEV 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 7:27"/>If anyone eats blood, he must no longer be allowed to associate with God’s people.’”<verse eid="LEV 7:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The portions for the priests</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 7:28"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 7:29"/>“Tell the Israeli people this: ‘Anyone who brings an offering to maintain fellowship with Yahweh must bring part of it to be a sacrifice to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 7:30"/>He himself must bring the offering that will be burned in the fire. He must bring the fat along with the breast of the animal and lift it up in front of Yahweh to indicate that it is an offering to him. <verse eid="LEV 7:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 7:31"/>The Supreme Priest must burn the fat on the altar, but the breast belongs to Aaron and all his sons. <verse eid="LEV 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 7:32"/>You must give to the Supreme Priest the right thigh of the animal that is sacrificed to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 7:33"/>The son of Aaron who offers the blood and the fat of that sacrifice must be given the right thigh of the animal as his share. <verse eid="LEV 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 7:34"/>From the offerings that the Israeli people give to maintain fellowship with Yahweh, he has declared that he has given to Aaron and his sons the breast that is lifted up and the right thigh that is offered; those portions must always be their regular share from the Israeli people.’”<verse eid="LEV 7:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 7:35"/>Those are the portions of the offerings brought/given to Yahweh and burned in fire that are allotted to Aaron and his sons on the day that they are set apart to serve Yahweh as priests. <verse eid="LEV 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 7:36"/>Yahweh commands that on the day that the priests are appointed [MTY], the Israeli people must always give those portions to the priests.<verse eid="LEV 7:36"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 7:37"/>Those are the regulations for the offerings that are to be completely burned on the altar, the offerings made from grain, the offerings to enable people to become acceptable to God again, the offerings for when people are guilty of not giving to Yahweh the things that are required to be given to him, the offerings given when the priests are appointed, and the offerings to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 7:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 7:38"/>They are regulations that Yahweh gave to Moses/me on Sinai Mountain in the Sinai Desert, on the day that he commanded the Israeli people to start bringing their offerings to him.<verse eid="LEV 7:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="LEV 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Aaron and his sons were appointed to be priests</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 8:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 8:2"/>“Bring Aaron and his sons, and bring their ◄special clothes/clothes <char style="add">that they will wear while they do the work of priests►</char>, the oil for anointing them, the bull to be offered to cause them to become forgiven for the sins they have committed, the two rams <char style="add">to be slaughtered</char>, and the basket containing bread made without yeast. <verse eid="LEV 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 8:3"/>Then gather all the people at the entrance to the Sacred Tent.” <verse eid="LEV 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 8:4"/>Moses/I did what Yahweh told him/me to do, and all the people gathered there.<verse eid="LEV 8:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 8:5"/>Then Moses/I said to the people, “This is what Yahweh has commanded us to do.” <verse eid="LEV 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 8:6"/>Then he/I brought Aaron and his sons forward and washed them. <verse eid="LEV 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 8:7"/>He/I put the special tunic/shirt on Aaron, tied the sash/waistband around him, put on him the special robe, and put on him the sacred vest/apron. He/I fastened the sacred vest/apron around him, using the skillfully woven sash. <verse eid="LEV 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 8:8"/>He/I put the sacred pouch on his chest and put into it the two stones for him to use to find out what God wants. <verse eid="LEV 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 8:9"/>Then he/I wrapped the turban around Aaron’s head, and fastened on the front of it the gold ornament, the object that showed that he was dedicated to God, like Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="LEV 8:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 8:10"/>Then Moses/I took the olive oil and anointed the sacred tent and everything in it, and dedicated them <char style="add">to Yahweh</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 8:11"/>He/I sprinkled some of the oil on the altar seven times. He/I anointed the altar and all the things used with it, and its huge washbasin and its stand, to dedicate them to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 8:12"/>He/I poured some of the oil on Aaron’s head and anointed him to dedicate him to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 8:13"/>Then he/I brought forward Aaron’s sons. He/I put tunics/shirts on them, tied sashes/waistbands around them, and wrapped turbans around their heads, like Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="LEV 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 8:14"/>Then he/I brought the bull for the offering to cause people to be forgiven for the sins that have committed. Then Aaron and his sons put their hands on the bull’s head. <verse eid="LEV 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 8:15"/>Then Moses/I slaughtered the bull, <char style="add">caught some of its blood in a bowl</char>, and with his/my finger put some of that blood on the projections at the corners of the altar, to purify the altar. He/I poured the rest of the blood at the base of the altar. By doing that, he/I caused it to be a suitable place for burning sacrifices for sin. <verse eid="LEV 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 8:16"/>Moses/I took all the fat that covers the inner parts of the animal, including the liver and kidneys, and burned them on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 8:17"/>He/I took the rest of the bull, including the hide and intestines, and burned them outside the camp, like Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="LEV 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 8:18"/>Then he/I brought the ram for the offering that would be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on its head. <verse eid="LEV 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 8:19"/>Then Moses/I slaughtered the ram and sprinkled its blood on all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 8:19"/><verse number="20-21" style="v" sid="LEV 8:20-21"/>He/I cut the ram into pieces and washed the inner parts and hind legs.Then he/I put the head, the fat, and the other parts of the ram on the altar. As it burned, the aroma of the smoke was pleasing to Yahweh. It was an offering to Yahweh that was burned, as Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="LEV 8:20-21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 8:22"/>Then he/I brought the other ram, the one for consecrating the priests, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on its head. <verse eid="LEV 8:22"/><verse number="23-24" style="v" sid="LEV 8:23-24"/>Moses/I slaughtered that ram, <char style="add">drained some of its blood in a bowl</char>, and put some of that blood on the lobes of the right ears, the thumbs of the right hands, and the big toes of the right feet of Aaron and his sons <char style="add">to indicate that what they listened to and what they did and where they went should be directed by Yahweh</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:23-24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 8:25"/>He/I picked up all the fat of the ram, its fat tail, the fat that covered the inner parts, including the fat that covered the liver and kidneys, and the right thigh of the ram. <verse eid="LEV 8:25"/><verse number="26-27" style="v" sid="LEV 8:26-27"/>Then from the basket containing the bread that was made without yeast, the bread which had been dedicated to Yahweh, he/I picked up one loaf of bread <char style="add">made without olive oil</char>, and one loaf that was <char style="add">made by mixing the flour</char> with olive oil, and one wafer. He/I put those on top of the portions of fat, and put them into the hands of Aaron and his sons. Then they lifted them up in the presence of Yahweh <char style="add">to indicate that it was an offering that belonged to him</char>. <verse eid="LEV 8:26-27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 8:28"/>Then Moses/I took those things from their hands and burned them on the altar. That was the offering that was burned to appoint Aaron and his sons as priests. And the aroma while it burned was pleasing to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 8:29"/>Moses/I also took the breast of the second ram and lifted it up, as Yahweh had commanded. The breast was Moses’/my share of the ram that was sacrificed to dedicate the priests.<verse eid="LEV 8:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 8:30"/>Then Moses/I took some of the olive oil for anointing <char style="add">Aaron and his sons</char>, and some of the blood that was on the altar and sprinkled it on Aaron and his sons and on their clothes. By doing that, he/I consecrated Aaron and his sons and their clothes.<verse eid="LEV 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 8:31"/>Then Moses/I said to Aaron and his sons, “Boil the meat <char style="add">of the second ram</char> at the entrance of the Sacred Tent, and eat it there with the bread that is in the basket, like I told you to do. <verse eid="LEV 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 8:32"/>Burn up any of the meat and bread that remains. <verse eid="LEV 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 8:33"/>The time for you to be set apart as priests will be seven days, so do not leave the entrance of the Sacred Tent for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 8:34"/>What we have done today is what Yahweh commanded to cause that you will be forgiven for your sins. <verse eid="LEV 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 8:35"/>You must stay at the entrance of the Sacred Tent for seven days and seven nights and do what Yahweh requires, in order that you will not die <char style="add">because of disobeying him. I am telling you that</char> because that is what Yahweh has commanded me to tell you.”<verse eid="LEV 8:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 8:36"/>So Aaron and his sons did everything that Yahweh told Moses/me to tell them.<verse eid="LEV 8:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="LEV 9"/>
  <para style="s1">Aaron and his sons started to offer sacrifices</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 9:1"/>Eight days later, Moses/I summoned the elders of Israel. <verse eid="LEV 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 9:2"/>Then he/I said to Aaron, “Take a young bull for the offering to enable you leaders to be forgiven for the sins you have committed, and a ram to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, both of them without any defects, and offer them to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 9:3"/>Then say to the Israeli people, ‘Take one male goat for the offering to enable you all to be forgiven for the sins you have committed. Also take a calf and a lamb that have no defects, to be an offering completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 9:4"/>Also take an ox and a ram to be an offering to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>, along with an offering of flour mixed with olive oil. Do this because today Yahweh is going to appear to you.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 9:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 9:5"/>
    <char style="add">After Moses/I told this to the Israeli people, some of them</char> took the things that Moses/I had commanded them to take, and went to the courtyard in front of the Sacred Tent. Then all the people came near and stood in front of Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 9:6"/>Then Moses/I said, “This is what Yahweh has commanded you to do, in order that his glory will appear to you.”<verse eid="LEV 9:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 9:7"/>Then Moses/I said to Aaron, “Come to the altar and sacrifice the animal that is your offering to enable you to be forgiven for the sins you have committed, and the animal that will be completely burned there. Because of those offerings, God will forgive you and the people for the sins that you have committed [DOU]. Do those things that Yahweh has commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 9:8"/>So Aaron came close to the altar and slaughtered the calf to be an offering for his sins. <verse eid="LEV 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 9:9"/>His sons brought its blood to him <char style="add">in a bowl</char>. He dipped his finger into the blood and put some of it on the projections at the corners of the altar. He poured out the rest of the blood at the base of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 9:10"/>He/I burned the fat, including that which covered the kidneys and the liver, as Yahweh had commanded him/me. <verse eid="LEV 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 9:11"/>Then Aaron burned <char style="add">the rest of</char> the meat and the hide/skin outside the camp.<verse eid="LEV 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 9:12"/>Then Aaron slaughtered the animal that would be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. His sons handed him <char style="add">the bowl containing</char> its blood, and he sprinkled the blood on all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 9:13"/>Then they handed him the head and the pieces of the animal that would be burned, and he burned them on the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 9:14"/>He washed the inner parts and the legs of the animal, and burned them on the altar, on top of the other pieces of the animal.<verse eid="LEV 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 9:15"/>Then Aaron brought the animals that would be sacrifices for the Israeli people. He took the goat and slaughtered it to be an offering to enable them to be forgiven for the sins they had committed, like he had done with the goat for his own offering.<verse eid="LEV 9:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 9:16"/>Then he brought the animal for the offering to be completely burned. He slaughtered it and offered it in the way that Yahweh had commanded him to do. <verse eid="LEV 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 9:17"/>He also brought the offering of grain. He took a handful of it and burned it on the altar, like he had done for the animal that he had slaughtered and completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> in the morning.<verse eid="LEV 9:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 9:18"/>Then he slaughtered the ox and the ram, to be an offering for the Israeli people to maintain fellowship with Yahweh. His sons handed him <char style="add">the bowl containing</char> the blood, and he sprinkled the blood against all sides of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 9:19"/>But he took the fat from the ox and the ram, including their fat tails that were cut close to the backbone, and all the fat that covered the livers and the kidneys. <verse eid="LEV 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 9:20"/>He put them on top of the breasts of those animals and carried them to the altar to be burned. <verse eid="LEV 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 9:21"/>Then, doing what Moses/I had commanded, he lifted up in front of Yahweh the breast and the right thigh of those animals, to signify that those two animals completely belonged to Yahweh.<verse eid="LEV 9:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 9:22"/>Then Aaron lifted his arms toward the people and <char style="add">asked Yahweh to</char> bless them. Then having finished making all those offerings, he stepped down <char style="add">from the place where the altar was</char>.<verse eid="LEV 9:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 9:23"/>Then Aaron and Moses/I entered the Sacred Tent. When they/we later came out, they/we <char style="add">asked Yahweh to</char> bless the people. And suddenly the glory/brightness of Yahweh appeared to all the people. <verse eid="LEV 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 9:24"/>A fire from Yahweh appeared and burned up the offering that was to be completely burned and the fat that was on the altar. And when all the people saw that, they shouted joyfully and prostrated themselves on the ground <char style="add">to worship Yahweh</char>.<verse eid="LEV 9:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="LEV 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Nadab and Abihu died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 10:1"/>
    <char style="add">Two of</char> Aaron’s sons, Nadab and Abihu, took the pans in which they burned incense. They put some burning coals in them and put incense on top of the coals, but this fire was not acceptable <char style="add">to Yahweh</char> because it was not the kind that he had commanded them to burn. <verse eid="LEV 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 10:2"/>So suddenly a fire from Yahweh appeared and burned them up [DOU] in the presence of Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 10:3"/>Then Moses/I said to Aaron, “That is what Yahweh predicted. He said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LEV 10:3">‘Those priests who come near to me,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LEV 10:3">I will show them that they must ◄respect me/treat me as being holy►;</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="LEV 10:3">in the presence of all the people</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="LEV 10:3">I am the one who must be honored.’”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="LEV 10:3">But Aaron said nothing.<verse eid="LEV 10:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 10:4"/>Then Moses/I summoned Mishael and Elzaphan, who were the sons of Aaron’s uncle Uzziel, and said to them, “Take <char style="add">the corpses of</char> your cousins outside the camp, away from the front of the Sacred Tent.” <verse eid="LEV 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 10:5"/>So they carried the corpses, which still had their special gowns on, outside the camp, <char style="add">and buried them</char>.<verse eid="LEV 10:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 10:6"/>Then Moses/I said to Aaron and his <char style="add">other two</char> sons Eleazar and Ithamar, “<char style="add">You are sad because Nadab and Abihu died, but you must act like you always do</char>. Do not allow the hair on your <char style="add">heads</char> to remain uncombed, and do not tear your clothes. But your relatives and all your fellow Israelis are allowed to mourn for those whom Yahweh destroyed by fire. <verse eid="LEV 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 10:7"/>But you must not leave the entrance of the Sacred Tent <char style="add">to join those who are mourning</char>, because if you do that, you also will die, and Yahweh will punish [MTY] all the people of Israel. Do not forget that Yahweh has set you apart [MTY] to work for him here, <char style="add">and he does not want you to become defiled by touching a corpse</char>.” So they did what Moses/I told them to do.<verse eid="LEV 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 10:8"/>Then Yahweh said to Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 10:9"/>“You and your <char style="add">two</char> sons <char style="add">who are still alive</char> must not drink wine or other fermented drinks before you enter the Sacred Tent; if you do that, you will die. That is a command that you and your descendants must obey forever. <verse eid="LEV 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 10:10"/>You must do that in order to learn what things are holy and what things are ◄not holy/common►, and <char style="add">from the things that are not holy</char> you must learn what things are acceptable to me and what things are not. <verse eid="LEV 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 10:11"/>And you must teach to the Israeli people all the laws that I gave to the Israeli people by telling them to Moses.”<verse eid="LEV 10:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 10:12"/>Moses/I said to Aaron and his two sons who were still alive, Eleazar and Ithamar, “Take the offering made from grain that is left after a portion of it has been offered to Yahweh to be burned, and eat it alongside the altar. <char style="add">It should not be eaten elsewhere</char>, because it is very holy. <verse eid="LEV 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 10:13"/>Eat it in a holy place; it is the share for you and your sons from the offerings that were burned; I have commanded that it be your share. <verse eid="LEV 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 10:14"/>But you and your sons and daughters are permitted to eat the breast and the thigh that were lifted up in front of Yahweh. Eat them in any place that is ◄holy/acceptable to him►. They have been given to you and your descendants as your share of the offerings to enable the Israelis to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with Yahweh</char>. <verse eid="LEV 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 10:15"/>The thigh and the breast that were lifted up in front of Yahweh must be brought with the portions of fat to be burned, to be lifted up in his presence. They will be the regular share for you and your descendants, as Yahweh has commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 10:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 10:16"/>When Moses/I inquired about the goat that had been sacrificed to enable the people to be forgiven by Yahweh for the sins they had committed, he/I found out that it had been completely burned. So he/I was angry with Eleazar and Ithamar and asked them, <verse eid="LEV 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 10:17"/>“Why did you not eat near the Sacred Tent the meat of the offering for sin? It was very holy, and it was given to you to enable the Israeli people to no longer be guilty for their sins and to be forgiven for their sins. <verse eid="LEV 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 10:18"/>Since its blood was not taken into the holy place inside the Sacred Tent, you should have eaten the <char style="add">meat of</char> the goat near the Sacred Tent, as I commanded.”<verse eid="LEV 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 10:19"/>Aaron replied to Moses/me, “Today the people brought to Yahweh their offering to be forgiven for the sins they had committed, and the offering to be completely burned, <char style="add">and surely that pleased Yahweh</char>, but <char style="add">think about the terrible thing</char> that happened to my other two sons! Would [RHQ] Yahweh have been pleased if I had eaten some of the offering to cause the people to become acceptable to God?” <verse eid="LEV 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 10:20"/>When Moses/I heard that, he/I was satisfied.<verse eid="LEV 10:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="LEV 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Food that is acceptable to God and food that is not</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 11:1"/>Yahweh said to Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 11:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people that <char style="add">this is what Yahweh says</char>: From all the animals that live on the land, these are the ones that you are permitted to eat: <verse eid="LEV 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 11:3"/>The ones that have hooves that are completely split and that ◄chew their cuds/bring their food up from their stomachs to chew it again►.<verse eid="LEV 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 11:4"/>There are some animals that chew their cuds but do not have split hooves, and some animals that have split hooves but do not chew their cuds. You must not eat any of those animals. <char style="add">For example</char>, camels chew their cuds but do not have split hooves, so they are unacceptable for you to eat. <verse eid="LEV 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 11:5"/>Rock badgers chew their cuds but do not have split hooves, so they are unacceptable for you to eat. <verse eid="LEV 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 11:6"/>Rabbits chew their cuds but do not have split hooves, so they are unacceptable for you to eat. <verse eid="LEV 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 11:7"/>Pigs have completely split hooves but they do not chew their cuds, so they are unacceptable for you to eat. <verse eid="LEV 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 11:8"/>All of those animals are unacceptable for you, so you must not eat their meat or even touch their carcasses.<verse eid="LEV 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 11:9"/>From all the creatures that live in the oceans and the streams, you are permitted to eat any that have fins and scales. <verse eid="LEV 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 11:10"/>But you must detest <char style="add">and not eat</char> those that do not have fins and scales. That includes ones that are very small. <verse eid="LEV 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 11:11"/>You must despise them, and you must not eat their meat, and you must detest their carcasses. <verse eid="LEV 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 11:12"/>You must detest everything that lives in the water that does not have fins and scales.<verse eid="LEV 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 11:13"/>There are some birds that you must detest <char style="add">and not eat</char>. They include eagles, bearded vultures, black vultures, <verse eid="LEV 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 11:14"/>kites, any kind of falcon/buzzard, <verse eid="LEV 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 11:15"/>any kind of raven, <verse eid="LEV 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 11:16"/>horned owls, screech owls, seagulls, any kind of hawk, <verse eid="LEV 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 11:17"/>small owls, cormorants, large owls, <verse eid="LEV 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 11:18"/>white owls, desert owls, vultures that eat dead animals, <verse eid="LEV 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 11:19"/>storks, any kind of heron, hoopoes, and bats.<verse eid="LEV 11:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 11:20"/>You must detest <char style="add">and not eat</char> flying insects that <char style="add">sometimes</char> walk on the ground [MTY]. <verse eid="LEV 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 11:21"/>But you are permitted to eat creatures with wings that sometimes walk on the ground if they have jointed legs for hopping around. <verse eid="LEV 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 11:22"/>They include locusts, crickets, and grasshoppers. <verse eid="LEV 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 11:23"/>But you must detest <char style="add">and not eat</char> other insects with wings that have four legs.<verse eid="LEV 11:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 11:24"/>‘There are certain creatures that if you touch their carcasses you will become defiled. Anyone who touches their carcasses must not touch other people until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 11:25"/>Anyone who picks up one of their carcasses must wash his clothes and not touch other people until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 11:26"/>‘The animals whose carcasses you must not touch are those that have hooves that are not completely divided or animals that do not chew their cuds. Anyone who touches the carcasses of any of those animals becomes ◄defiled/unacceptable to me►. <verse eid="LEV 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 11:27"/>From all the animals that walk on the ground, you must not touch the carcasses of those that have paws to walk on. Anyone who touches one of their carcasses must not touch other people until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 11:28"/>Anyone who picks up one of their carcasses must wash his clothes and not touch other people until that evening, because touching their carcasses ◄defiles you/causes you to become unacceptable to me►.<verse eid="LEV 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 11:29"/>‘From all the animals that walk on the ground, these are the ones that ◄defile you/cause you to become unacceptable to me► <char style="add">if you touch them</char>: Moles, rats, any kind of lizard, <verse eid="LEV 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 11:30"/>geckos, skinks, and chameleons. <verse eid="LEV 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 11:31"/>Those creatures that scurry across the ground ◄defile you/cause you to become unacceptable to me►; anyone who touches one of their carcasses must not touch other people until the evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 11:32"/>When one of those creatures dies and falls on something, the thing that it falls on, whatever it is used for, will become ◄defiled/unacceptable to me►, whether it is made of wood or cloth or the hide of some animal or from rough cloth. You must put it in water. Then you must not use it until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 11:33"/>If one of them falls into a clay pot, everything in it becomes defiled, and you must break that pot into pieces. <verse eid="LEV 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 11:34"/>If you pour water from that pot on any food, you must not eat that food. And you must not drink any water from that pot. <verse eid="LEV 11:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 11:35"/>Anything that one of the carcasses of those creatures falls on becomes ◄defiled/unacceptable to me►; even if it falls on an oven or a cooking pot, anything that it falls on must be broken into pieces. It becomes unacceptable to me and you must not use it again. <verse eid="LEV 11:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 11:36"/>If one of their carcasses falls into a spring or a pit for storing water, the water may still be drunk, but anyone who touches one of those carcasses becomes unacceptable to me. <verse eid="LEV 11:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 11:37"/>If one of those carcasses falls on seeds that are to be planted, those seeds are still acceptable to be planted. <verse eid="LEV 11:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 11:38"/>But if water has been put on the seeds and then a carcass falls on them, the seeds must be thrown away.<verse eid="LEV 11:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 11:39"/>‘If an animal <char style="add">whose meat</char> you are permitted to eat dies, anyone who touches its carcass must not touch other people until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 11:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 11:40"/>Anyone who eats some meat from that carcass must wash his clothes, and then he must not touch anyone until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 11:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41-42" style="v" sid="LEV 11:41-42"/>‘All creatures that scurry across the ground, including those that move on their bellies and those that crawl, are detestable, and they must not be eaten. <verse eid="LEV 11:41-42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 11:43"/>Do not ◄defile yourselves/cause you to become unacceptable to me► by <char style="add">eating</char> any of those creatures [DOU]. <verse eid="LEV 11:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 11:44"/>I am Yahweh your God, and I am holy, so you must consecrate yourselves and be holy. You must avoid eating things that cause you to be unacceptable to me. Do not cause yourselves to become unacceptable to me by eating creatures that scurry across the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 11:45"/>I am Yahweh, the one who freed you from <char style="add">being slaves in</char> Egypt, in order to be your God. Therefore, because I am holy, you must be holy.<verse eid="LEV 11:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 11:46"/>'Those are the regulations concerning animals and birds, all the living creatures that live in water or scurry across the ground. <verse eid="LEV 11:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 11:47"/>You must learn what things <char style="add">I say</char> are acceptable to me and what things are not, and learn what things you are permitted to eat and what things you are not permitted to eat.’”<verse eid="LEV 11:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="LEV 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Purifying women after they give birth</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 12:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 12:2"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: ‘If a woman gives birth to a son, she must be avoided for seven days, like she must be avoided when she is menstruating each month. <verse eid="LEV 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 12:3"/>The baby son must be circumcised on the eighth day after he is born. <verse eid="LEV 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 12:4"/>Then the woman must wait 33 days to be purified from her bleeding <char style="add">during childbirth</char>. She must not touch anything that is sacred or enter the Sacred Tent area until that time is ended. <verse eid="LEV 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 12:5"/>If a woman gives birth to a daughter, she must be avoided for two weeks, like she must be avoided when she is menstruating each month. Then she must wait 66 days to be purified from the bleeding that occurred <char style="add">when her baby was born</char>.<verse eid="LEV 12:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 12:6"/>‘Then that time for her to be purified is ended, that woman must bring to the priest at the entrance of the Sacred Tent a one-year-old lamb to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and a dove or a young pigeon <char style="add">to be sacrificed</char> to enable her to become acceptable to Yahweh again. <verse eid="LEV 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 12:7"/>The priest will offer them to Yahweh in order that she may be forgiven for any sins she has committed. Then she will be purified from her loss of blood <char style="add">when the baby was born</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 12:7">‘Those are the regulations for women who give birth to a son or daughter. <verse eid="LEV 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 12:8"/>If a woman who gives birth to a child cannot afford a lamb, she must bring two doves or two young pigeons. One will be burned completely <char style="add">on the altar</char>, and one will be an offering to enable her to become acceptable to God again. By doing that, the priest will cause that she will be forgiven for any sins she has committed, and she no longer will need to be avoided.’”<verse eid="LEV 12:8"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="LEV 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Regulations concerning contagious skin diseases</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 13:1"/>Yahweh said this to Aaron and Moses/me: <verse eid="LEV 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 13:2"/>“When someone has on his skin a swelling or a rash or a shiny/bright spot that may become ◄contagious/a dreaded skin disease►, he must be brought to Aaron or to one of his sons who are also priests. <verse eid="LEV 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 13:3"/>The priest must examine that part of the person’s skin. If the hair in that area has become white and it appears that the sore is deeper than just on the skin, it is a contagious skin disease. When the priest sees that, he must declare that the person must stay away from other people [MTY]. <verse eid="LEV 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 13:4"/>If the spot on the person’s skin is white but it does not appear that the sore is deeper than just on the skin, the priest must tell him to stay away from other people for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 13:5"/>Then the priest must examine the person again. If the priest sees that the sore has not changed and has not spread, he must tell the person to stay away from people for seven more days. <verse eid="LEV 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 13:6"/>Then the priest must examine him again. If the sore has faded and has not spread, the priest will allow him to be with other people again; it is only a rash. After the person washes his clothes, he will be allowed to be with other people again. <verse eid="LEV 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 13:7"/>But if the sore spreads after the priest has examined him, he must go to the priest again. <verse eid="LEV 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 13:8"/>The priest will examine him; and if the sore has spread to more of the skin, it is a contagious skin disease, and the priest will declare that he must stay away from other people.<verse eid="LEV 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 13:9"/>When anyone has a contagious skin disease, he must be brought to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 13:10"/>The priest must examine him. And if there is a white swelling in the skin that has caused the hair in that swelling to become white, and if the flesh in that area is painful/sensitive, <verse eid="LEV 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 13:11"/>it is a permanent skin disease, and the priest will declare that he must stay away from other people. The priest does not need to tell that person that he must avoid other people, because other people already are wanting to stay away from him.<verse eid="LEV 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 13:12"/>‘If the disease spreads all over someone’s body, and the priest examines that person and sees that it is covering his skin from his head to his feet, <verse eid="LEV 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 13:13"/>and it has caused all his skin to become white <char style="add">which will indicate that the disease has ended</char>, the priest will declare that the person does not have to stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 13:14"/>But if the person has open sores and they are very painful/sensitive, he has a contagious skin disease, <verse eid="LEV 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 13:15"/>and when the priest sees that, he will declare that the person must stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 13:16"/>But if the person’s flesh changes and becomes white, he must go to the priest again. <verse eid="LEV 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 13:17"/>The priest must examine him again; and if the sores have become white, the priest will declare that the person who had been infected is now permitted to be with other people again.<verse eid="LEV 13:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 13:18"/>‘Then someone has a boil on his skin and it has healed, <verse eid="LEV 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 13:19"/>but in the place where the boil was a white swelling or a bright/shiny spot appears, he must go to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 13:20"/>The priest must examine it. And if it seems to be deeper than just on the skin, and if the hair in that spot has become white, it is a contagious skin disease that has appeared where the boil had been. And the priest will declare that the person must stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 13:21"/>But when the priest examines it, if there is no white hair in that spot and it is only on the surface of the skin and has become less bright/shiny, then the priest will order him to stay away from other people for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 13:22"/>But if it is spreading, it is contagious and the priest will declare that the person must stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 13:23"/>But if that spot is unchanged and has not spread, it is only a scar from the boil, and the priest will declare that the person is permitted to be with other people again.<verse eid="LEV 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 13:24"/>‘Then someone has a burn on his skin and a bright/shiny or white spot appears, and the flesh in that area is sensitive/painful, <verse eid="LEV 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 13:25"/>the priest must examine the spot. If the hair in that spot has turned white and it seems to be deeper than just on the surface of the skin, it is a contagious skin disease that has appeared where the burn was, and that person must stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 13:26"/>But when the priest examines it and sees that there is no white hair in that spot and it is only on the surface of the skin, and has faded, the priest will declare that the person must stay away from people for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 13:27"/>On the seventh day, the priest will examine him again. If the sore is spreading, it is a contagious skin disease, and the priest will declare that the person must stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 13:28"/>However, if the spot is not changed and has not spread but has faded, it is only a scar from the burn, and the priest will declare that the person is permitted to be with other people again.<verse eid="LEV 13:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 13:29"/>‘If a man or a woman has a sore on his head or on his chin, <verse eid="LEV 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 13:30"/>the priest must examine it. If it appears to be deeper than <char style="add">just on the surface of</char> the skin, and the hair in that spot has thinned out and has become yellowish, it is a contagious skin disease that causes itching. And the priest will declare that the person must stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 13:31"/>But when the priest examines that kind of sore, if it seems to be only on the surface of the skin and there is no healthy hair in it, the priest will tell the person to stay away from other people for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 13:32"/>On the seventh day, the priest will examine the sore again. If it has not spread and if there is no yellow hair in that spot and if it appears to be only on the surface of the skin, <verse eid="LEV 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 13:33"/>the person must shave the hair near the sore but not the hair on the sore. And the priest will tell him to stay away from other people for seven more days. <verse eid="LEV 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 13:34"/>On the seventh day, the priest will examine that spot again. If it has not spread and it appears to be only on the surface of the skin, the priest will declare that the person is permitted to be with people again. The person must wash his clothes, and then he can be with other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 13:35"/>But if the sore later spreads, <verse eid="LEV 13:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 13:36"/>the priest must examine him again. If the itch/sore has spread, the priest does not need to look for yellow hair, because it is clear that the person has a contagious skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 13:37"/>However, if the priest thinks that the spot has not changed, and healthy hair is growing in that area, it is clear that the itch has healed, and the priest will declare that the person is permitted to be with other people again.<verse eid="LEV 13:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 13:38"/>‘Then a man or a woman has white spots on the skin, <verse eid="LEV 13:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 13:39"/>the priest should examine them. But if the spots are dull white, it is only a rash, and <char style="add">the priest will declare that</char> the person is permitted to be with other people.<verse eid="LEV 13:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40-41" style="v" sid="LEV 13:40-41"/>‘If a man loses the hair on any part of his head, he does not need to stay away from other people. <verse eid="LEV 13:40-41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 13:42"/>But if he gets a bright/shiny sore on his bald head or on his forehead, he has a contagious skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 13:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 13:43"/>The priest must examine him. If the swollen sore is a bright spot like <char style="add">the spot on someone who has</char> a contagious skin disease, <verse eid="LEV 13:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 13:44"/>the priest will declare that the man has a contagious skin disease and must not be with other people.<verse eid="LEV 13:44"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 13:45"/>‘Anyone who has a contagious skin disease must wear torn clothes and not comb his hair. <char style="add">When he is near other people</char>, he must cover the lower part to his face and call out, “Do not come near me! I have a contagious skin disease!” <verse eid="LEV 13:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 13:46"/>He is not allowed to be with other people as long as he has the disease. He must live alone, outside the camp.’”<verse eid="LEV 13:46"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Regulations concerning mildew</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47-48" style="v" sid="LEV 13:47-48"/>“Sometimes a person’s clothing gets mildew on it. It may be clothing that is woven from wool or made from linen or from leather. <verse eid="LEV 13:47-48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 13:49"/>If the contaminated/mildewed part is greenish or reddish, it is a spreading mildew, and it must be shown to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 13:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 13:50"/>The priest will examine it, and then put it in a separate place by itself for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 13:51"/>On the seventh day he must examine it again. If the mildew has spread, it is clear that it is a type of mildew that destroys clothing, and that clothing must not be worn again. <verse eid="LEV 13:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 13:52"/>The owner must burn completely the item that has the mildew in it, whatever kind of item it is.<verse eid="LEV 13:52"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 13:53"/>But when the priest examines it, if the mildew has not spread, <verse eid="LEV 13:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 13:54"/>he will tell the person <char style="add">who owns it</char> to wash it. Then he must put it in a separate place for another seven days. <verse eid="LEV 13:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 13:55"/>Then the priest will examine it again. If the color of the mildew has not changed, even though it has not spread, that item must not be worn again. It does not matter if the mildew is on the inside of the clothing or on the outside; it must be burned. <verse eid="LEV 13:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LEV 13:56"/>But when the priest examines it <char style="add">after it has been washed</char>, if the mildew has faded, he must tear out that part that had the mildew in it. <verse eid="LEV 13:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LEV 13:57"/>But if the mildew reappears in that item, it is clear that it is spreading, and the whole item must be burned. <verse eid="LEV 13:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="LEV 13:58"/>But after the clothing is washed and the mildew disappears, it must be washed again, and then it can be worn again.<verse eid="LEV 13:58"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="59" style="v" sid="LEV 13:59"/>Those are the regulations concerning mildew on things made of wool or linen or leather, for deciding whether those things can continue to be worn or not.”<verse eid="LEV 13:59"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="LEV 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Rituals for those healed of contagious skin diseases</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 14:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 14:2"/>“These are the regulations for anyone who has been healed of a contagious skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 14:3"/>The person must be brought to a priest. The priest will take him outside the camp <char style="add">to where that person has been staying</char>, and examine him. If the skin disease has been healed, <verse eid="LEV 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 14:4"/>the priest will say that someone must bring two living birds that are acceptable to Yahweh, along with some cedar wood, some scarlet/red yarn, and some sprigs of ◄hyssop/a very leafy plant►. <verse eid="LEV 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 14:5"/>Then the priest will command that one of the birds be killed while <char style="add">it is being held</char> over a clay pot containing water from a spring. <verse eid="LEV 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 14:6"/>Then the priest will dip the other bird, along with the cedar wood, the scarlet/red yarn and the hyssop, into the blood of the bird that was killed. <verse eid="LEV 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 14:7"/>Then he must sprinkle some of the blood on the person who was healed; he must sprinkle it on him seven times. Then he will declare that the person is permitted to be with other people again. And the priest will release the other bird and allow it to fly away.<verse eid="LEV 14:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 14:8"/>“Then the person who was healed must wash his clothes, shave off all his hair, and bathe. Then he is allowed to return to the camp, but he must stay outside his tent for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 14:9"/>On the seventh day, he must again shave off all his hair, including his beard and his eyebrows. Then he must again wash his clothes and bathe, and then he will be allowed to be with other people again.<verse eid="LEV 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 14:10"/>“The next day that person must bring two male lambs and one female lamb that is one year old, all of them with no defects. He must also bring six quarts/liters of fine flour, mixed with olive oil, to be an offering, and ◄0.6 pint/0.3 liter► of olive oil. <verse eid="LEV 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 14:11"/>The priest who declares that the person’s skin disease is ended must bring that person, and his offerings, to me, Yahweh, at the entrance of the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="LEV 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 14:12"/>“Then the priest must take one of the male lambs and lift it up, along with the olive oil, in front of me, to be a guilt offering—<char style="add">an offering for his being guilty for not giving to me the things that he was required to give me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 14:13"/>Then the priest must slaughter the lamb in the sacred place where the other sacrifices are offered. Like the offering to enable people to be forgiven, this guilt offering is holy, and belongs to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 14:14"/>The priest must take some of the blood of that animal and pour it on the lobe/tip of the right ear and on the thumb of the right hand and on the big toe of the right foot of the one who has been healed of the skin disease. <verse eid="LEV 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 14:15"/>Then the priest must take some of the olive oil and pour it in the palm of his own left hand. <verse eid="LEV 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 14:16"/>Then he must dip the forefinger of his right hand into the oil in his palm, and sprinkle it in front of me seven times. <verse eid="LEV 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 14:17"/>Then he must put some of the oil that is still in the palm of his hand on the lobe/tip of the right ear and the thumb of the right hand and on the big toe of the right foot of the person who has been healed of the skin disease. He must put it on top of the blood that he has already put on those places. <verse eid="LEV 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 14:18"/>The remaining oil in his palm must be put on the person’s head, <char style="add">to indicate that I declare that</char> the person has been forgiven for having sinned.<verse eid="LEV 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 14:19"/>“Then the priest must slaughter one of the other two animals, to show that the one who has been healed of the skin disease has been forgiven for having sinned, and that he has become acceptable to Yahweh. Then the priest will slaughter the animal that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 14:20"/>He will also put on the altar the offering of grain, to indicate that the person has been forgiven for having sinned. Then that person will be allowed to be with other people again.<verse eid="LEV 14:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 14:21"/>“But if the person who has been healed of a skin disease is poor and cannot afford to bring all those animals, he must take to the priest one male lamb to be lifted up to be an offering for his not giving to me the things that he was required to give me. He must also take two quarts/liters of fine flour mixed with olive oil to be an offering made from grain, ◄0.6 pint/0.3 liter► of olive oil, <verse eid="LEV 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 14:22"/>and two doves or two young pigeons, one for him to be forgiven for the sins he has committed, and one to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>.<verse eid="LEV 14:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 14:23"/>“On that same day, that person must take those things to the priest at the entrance of the Sacred Tent, to offer them to Yahweh. <verse eid="LEV 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 14:24"/>The priest will take the lamb for the offering for that person not giving to me the things that he was required to give me, along with the olive oil, and lift them up in front of me. <verse eid="LEV 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 14:25"/>Then the priest will slaughter that lamb <char style="add">and drain some of the blood in a bowl</char>, and take some of that blood and put it on the lobe/tip of the person’s right ear and on the thumb of his right hand and on the big toe of his right foot. <verse eid="LEV 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 14:26"/>Then the priest will pour some of the oil into the palm of his left hand, <verse eid="LEV 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 14:27"/>and with his right forefinger he must sprinkle some of the oil from his palm there in my presence. <verse eid="LEV 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 14:28"/>He must put some of the oil in his palm on the same places where he put the blood. <verse eid="LEV 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 14:29"/>He must put the rest of the oil that is in his hand on the head of the person who has been healed of a skin disease, to indicate that I have forgiven him for having sinned. <verse eid="LEV 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 14:30"/>Then the priest must sacrifice the doves or the pigeons, whichever that person has brought. <verse eid="LEV 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 14:31"/>One will be an offering for sin and the other will be completely burned on the altar, along with the offering of grain. By doing that, the priest will declare that the person is no longer guilty for having sinned.<verse eid="LEV 14:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 14:32"/>“Those are the regulations for anyone who has a contagious skin disease and who is poor and cannot afford the usual offerings, in order that he can be with people again.”<verse eid="LEV 14:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Instructions regarding mildew in a house</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 14:33"/>Yahweh also said to Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 14:34"/>“I am about to give you Canaan land to belong to your people permanently. When you enter that land, there will be times when I cause/allow mildew to appear inside one of your houses. <verse eid="LEV 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 14:35"/>If that happens, the owner of that house must go to the priest and tell him, ‘There is something in my house that looks like mildew.’ <verse eid="LEV 14:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 14:36"/>“Then the priest will say to him, ‘Take everything out of the house before I enter the house to examine the mildew. If you do not do that, I will declare that everything in the house is contaminated.’ <verse eid="LEV 14:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 14:37"/><char style="add">After the owner takes everything outside of his house</char>, the priest will go in and inspect the house. If the mildew has caused greenish or reddish spots/depressions on the walls that seem to be deeper than only on the surface of the walls, <verse eid="LEV 14:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 14:38"/>the priest will go outside the house and lock it up for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 14:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 14:39"/>On the seventh day, he must go into the house and inspect it again. If the mildew on the walls has spread, <verse eid="LEV 14:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 14:40"/>the priest will tell someone to tear out and throw in the dump outside the town all the stones in the walls that have mildew on them. <verse eid="LEV 14:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 14:41"/>Then the owner must scrape all the walls inside the house, and everything that is scraped off must be thrown into a dump outside the town. <verse eid="LEV 14:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 14:42"/>Then the owner must get new/other stones to replace the ones that had mildew on them, and take new clay and plaster <char style="add">to cover the stones in the walls of</char> the house.<verse eid="LEV 14:42"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 14:43"/>“If the mildew appears again in the house after that is done, <verse eid="LEV 14:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 14:44"/>the priest must go and examine the house again. If the mildew has spread inside the house, it will be clear that the mildew is the kind that destroys <char style="add">houses</char>, and no one will be allowed to live in it. <verse eid="LEV 14:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 14:45"/>It must be completely torn down—the stones, the timber and the plaster—and all those things must be thrown into a dump outside the town.<verse eid="LEV 14:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 14:46"/>“Anyone who goes into that house while it is locked up will not be allowed to be with other people until sunset of that day. <verse eid="LEV 14:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 14:47"/>Anyone who sleeps in that house or eats in that house <char style="add">during that time</char> must wash his clothes.<verse eid="LEV 14:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 14:48"/>“But when the priest comes to examine the house after it has been plastered, if the mildew has not spread, he shall declare that people may live in it, because the mildew is gone. <verse eid="LEV 14:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 14:49"/>But before people are allowed to live in it, the priest must take two small birds and some cedar wood and some red/scarlet yarn and some hyssop. <verse eid="LEV 14:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 14:50"/>He must kill one of the birds while <char style="add">holding it</char> over a clay pot containing water from a spring. <verse eid="LEV 14:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 14:51"/>Then he must take the cedar wood, the hyssop, the red/scarlet yarn, and the other/living bird, and dip them into the blood of the dead bird, and sprinkle some of that blood on the house seven times. <verse eid="LEV 14:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 14:52"/>By doing all those things he will cause the house to be acceptable to be lived in again. <verse eid="LEV 14:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 14:53"/>Then he must release the other bird and allow it to fly away. By doing that, he will <char style="add">finish the ritual for</char> causing the house to be acceptable for people to live in it again.<verse eid="LEV 14:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 14:54"/>“Those are the regulations for contagious diseases, for itching sores, <verse eid="LEV 14:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 14:55"/>for mildew [DOU] on clothes or in a house, <verse eid="LEV 14:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="LEV 14:56"/>and for swellings, rashes, or bright spots <char style="add">on sores</char>, <verse eid="LEV 14:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="LEV 14:57"/>to find out whether a person has a contagious disease or not, and whether people will still be permitted to touch their clothing or their house, or not.”<verse eid="LEV 14:57"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="LEV 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Discharges from bodies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 15:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me and Aaron, <verse eid="LEV 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 15:2"/>“Tell this to the Israelis: When an infected discharge comes out of a man’s sexual organs [EUP], that fluid should not be touched. <verse eid="LEV 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 15:3"/>Whether that fluid is blocked or continues to drip, it causes him to be someone who should not be touched.<verse eid="LEV 15:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 15:4"/>“And any bed that such a man lies on should not be touched, and anything that he sits on should not be touched. <verse eid="LEV 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 15:5"/>Anyone who touches that person’s bed must wash his clothes and bathe, and no one should touch him until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 15:6"/>Anyone who sits on something that man has sat on must wash his clothes and bathe, and no one should touch him until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 15:7"/>“Anyone who touches such a man must wash his clothes and bathe, and no one should touch him until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 15:8"/>“If such a man spits on someone else, that person who is spit upon should not be touched. He must wash his clothes, and no one should touch him until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 15:9"/>“Everything that a man who has such a discharge of fluid sits on while he is riding <char style="add">a horse or a donkey</char> should not be touched, <verse eid="LEV 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 15:10"/>and anyone who touches the seat or saddle that he was sitting on also should not be touched until that evening. And anyone who picks up the seat or saddle must wash his clothes and bathe, and no one should touch him until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 15:11"/>Anyone whom the man with such a discharge of fluid from his body touches without first rinsing his hands in water must wash his clothes and bathe, and no one should touch him until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 15:12"/>“If such a man touches a clay pot, that pot must be broken into pieces. Anything made from wood that he touches must be rinsed in water.<verse eid="LEV 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 15:13"/>“If such a man is healed from his flow of fluid, he must wait for seven days. Then he must wash his clothes and bathe in water from a spring. Then he will be able to be with others. <verse eid="LEV 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 15:14"/>On the eighth/next day, he must take two doves or two young pigeons and come in front of Yahweh at the entrance of the Sacred Tent, and give them to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 15:15"/>The priest will sacrifice them. One will be an offering for the man to become acceptable to God, and the other one will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. As a result of the priest doing that, the man will be forgiven for having sinned.<verse eid="LEV 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 15:16"/>“Then semen accidentally flows from a man’s sexual organs [EUP], he must bathe his whole body, and no one should touch him until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 15:17"/>Any clothing or leather that has semen on it must be washed, and no one should touch it until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 15:18"/>When a man has sex with a woman and some semen spills, both of them must bathe, and no one should touch them until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 15:19"/>“Then a woman has her monthly menstrual period, no one should touch her for seven days. If anyone touches her <char style="add">during that time</char>, no one should touch the person who touched her until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 15:20"/>No one should touch anything that she lies on or sits on during that time. <verse eid="LEV 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 15:21"/>Anyone who touches her bed must wash his clothes and bathe, and no one should touch that person until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 15:21"/><verse number="22-23" style="v" sid="LEV 15:22-23"/>Anyone who touches something that she has been sitting on, a bed or anything else, must wash his clothes, and no one should touch that person until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:22-23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 15:24"/>“If a man has sex with a woman <char style="add">during that time</char> and some of the menstrual blood touches him, no one should touch him for seven days, and no one should touch the bed that he lies on.<verse eid="LEV 15:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 15:25"/>“Then a woman has a vaginal discharge of blood for ◄many days/a long time►, which is not her monthly flow of blood, or if her flow of blood continues after her monthly flow ends, no one should touch her until it stops. <verse eid="LEV 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 15:26"/>And no one should touch the bed that she lies on or anything that she sits on while that flow of blood continues, just like during her monthly menstrual period. <verse eid="LEV 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 15:27"/>Anyone who touches those things should not touch anyone else; he must wash his clothes and bathe, and he should not touch anyone else until that evening.<verse eid="LEV 15:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 15:28"/>“After a woman’s monthly menstrual flow ends, she must wait seven days before she touches anyone. <verse eid="LEV 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 15:29"/>On the eighth/next day, she must take two doves or two pigeons to the priest at the entrance of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 15:30"/>The priest will sacrifice one of them to be an offering to enable her to become acceptable to Yahweh again, and completely burn the other one <char style="add">on the altar</char>. By doing that he will cause me, Yahweh, to forgive her for having sinned [DOU].<verse eid="LEV 15:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 15:31"/>“You must warn the Israeli people not to do things that ◄defile them/cause them to be unacceptable to me►. If they become ◄unacceptable to me/defiled►, they will cause my Sacred Tent which is among them to become an unacceptable place to worship me, and as a result they will die.”<verse eid="LEV 15:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 15:32"/>“Those are the regulations for a man who has a fluid that flows from his sexual organs or who should not be touched because some of his semen spills out while having sex <char style="add">with a woman</char>, <verse eid="LEV 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 15:33"/>and for any woman during her monthly menstrual period, and for any man who has sex with a woman during her menstrual period.”<verse eid="LEV 15:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="LEV 16"/>
  <para style="s1">The Day of Atonement</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 16:1"/>After the two sons of Aaron died because they burned incense to Yahweh <char style="add">in a manner that was contrary to what Yahweh commanded</char>, Yahweh spoke to Moses/me. <verse eid="LEV 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 16:2"/>He said to him/me, “Warn your <char style="add">older</char> brother Aaron that he must not enter the Very Holy Place inside the curtain that is in the Sacred Tent whenever he wants to, because the cover of the sacred chest is there. That is the place where the priest ◄makes atonement for/requests me to forgive► sins. I am present in the cloud that is over the cover of the sacred chest. If Aaron goes in that room when it is not the proper time, he will die!<verse eid="LEV 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 16:3"/>“When Aaron enters the Sacred Tent area, he must bring a bull that <char style="add">will be killed</char> to become an offering/sacrifice for sins, and a ram <char style="add">to be killed</char> to be an offering that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 16:4"/>Then he must bathe his whole body, and put on the linen underwear/undershorts and the linen gown. He must tie the linen sash/waistbands around his waist and wrap the turban around his head. Those are his sacred garments. <verse eid="LEV 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 16:5"/>The Israeli people must then bring to him two male goats <char style="add">to be killed</char> as an offering/sacrifice for sin, and a ram to be <char style="add">killed and</char> burned completely <char style="add">on the altar</char>.<verse eid="LEV 16:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 16:6"/>“Aaron must offer the bull <char style="add">to me</char> to be a sacrifice in order that ◄I will forgive his sins and the sins of his family/his sins and the sins of his family will be forgiven►. <verse eid="LEV 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 16:7"/>Then he must bring the two male goats to me at the entrance to the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 16:8"/>He must ◄cast lots/throw down stones that have been marked► to determine which goat will be <char style="add">sacrificed</char> to me, and which will be the goat that will be set free. <verse eid="LEV 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 16:9"/>Aaron must bring to me the goat that was chosen to be sacrificed. It will be an offering for the people’s sins. <verse eid="LEV 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 16:10"/>Aaron must also bring to me the other goat, but it is not to be killed. It will be freed while it is still alive. As a result of Aaron sending it into the desert, the people’s sins will be forgiven.<verse eid="LEV 16:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 16:11"/>“Then Aaron must bring the young bull to me, to be an offering/sacrifice for himself and for his family. He must slaughter that bull to be an offering for their sins, <char style="add">and he must drain the blood into a basin</char>. <verse eid="LEV 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 16:12"/>Then he must take some burning coals from the <char style="add">bronze</char> altar and put them in the incense burner. Then he must fill his hands with fragrant finely-ground incense. Then he must take the incense and the incense burner inside the curtain into the Very Holy Place <char style="add">of the Sacred Tent</char>. <verse eid="LEV 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 16:13"/>There he must put the incense on the burning coals, with the result that a cloud of burning incense will rise up over the lid of the sacred chest. If he obeys these instructions, he will not die <char style="add">like Korah’s two sons did because of offering incense incorrectly</char> (OR, <char style="add">because of being in God’s presence</char>). <verse eid="LEV 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 16:14"/>Then he must dip his finger into <char style="add">the basin</char> and sprinkle some blood on the lid of the sacred chest, and also sprinkle some blood seven times against the front of the chest.<verse eid="LEV 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 16:15"/>
    <char style="add">“Aaron must then go outside the Sacred Tent</char> and slaughter the goat to be an offering for the sins of the people. Then he must bring its blood into the Very Holy Place behind the curtain. There he must sprinkle <char style="add">some of</char> that blood on the lid of the sacred chest and against the front of the chest, like he did with the bull’s blood. <verse eid="LEV 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 16:16"/>By doing that, he will purify the Very Holy Place. And he must sprinkle more of the blood on the Sacred Tent, because the tent is in the midst of the camp of the Israeli people who have become unacceptable to me <char style="add">because of their sins</char>. <verse eid="LEV 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 16:17"/>When Aaron goes into the Very Holy Place <char style="add">in the Sacred Tent</char> to purify it, no one else is permitted to enter <char style="add">the other part of</char> the Sacred Tent. Only after Aaron has performed rituals to enable me to forgive him and his family, and all the Israeli people, is any priest permitted to enter the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="LEV 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 16:18"/>“Then Aaron must go outside the tent to purify my altar. He must do this by smearing some of the blood from the bull and some of the blood from the goat on each of the projections at the corners of the altar. <verse eid="LEV 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 16:19"/>Then Aaron must dip his finger into the <char style="add">basin of</char> blood and sprinkle some of the blood over the altar seven times. By doing that, he will cleanse it from being unholy <char style="add">because of the sins</char> of the Israeli people, and it will become holy again.<verse eid="LEV 16:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 16:20"/>“When Aaron has finished purifying the Very Holy Place <char style="add">inside the Sacred Tent</char> and all of the Sacred Tent and the altar, he must bring the goat that was chosen to be set free. <verse eid="LEV 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 16:21"/>He must put both of his hands on the head of the goat and confess all the sins [DOU] of the Israeli people. By doing that, he will put <char style="add">the guilt of</char> their sins on the head of the goat. Then he must give the goat to a man who is chosen, and that man will send the goat out into the desert. <verse eid="LEV 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 16:22"/><char style="add">It is as though</char> the goat will carry away into the desert <char style="add">the guilt for</char> the sins of all the people.<verse eid="LEV 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 16:23"/>“When Aaron approaches the Sacred Tent, he must take off the linen clothes that he wore when he <char style="add">previously</char> entered the Very Holy Place, and he must leave those clothes there. <verse eid="LEV 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 16:24"/>Then he must bathe in a sacred place, put on his regular/ordinary clothes, and sacrifice the animals that will be burned completely on the altar for his own sins and for the sins of the Israeli people. By doing that he will enable me to forgive him and them. <verse eid="LEV 16:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 16:25"/>He must also burn on the altar all the fat of the bull and the goat that were sacrificed.<verse eid="LEV 16:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 16:26"/>“The man who was chosen to send the other goat into the desert and free it there must afterwards wash his clothes and bathe. Then he may return to the camp. <verse eid="LEV 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 16:27"/>The carcasses of the bull and the goat that were slaughtered to be an offering/sacrifice for the people’s sins, whose blood was taken inside the Very Holy Place to enable Yahweh to forgive the Israeli people, must be carried outside the camp and burned. The hides/skins of the animals, the inner organs, and the dung must also be burned. <verse eid="LEV 16:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 16:28"/>The man who burns those things must then wash his clothes and bathe before he returns to the camp.<verse eid="LEV 16:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 16:29"/>“On ◄October/the month after the dry season ends►, on the day that I have appointed, you all must ◄fast/abstain from eating food► and not do any work. This is a rule/law that will never end. It must be obeyed by you people who have been Israelis all your lives, and also by foreigners who are living among you. <verse eid="LEV 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 16:30"/>On that day, Aaron will perform rituals to enable me to forgive you all, and then I will cleanse/free you all from <char style="add">the guilt of</char> all your sins and you will become acceptable to me. <verse eid="LEV 16:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 16:31"/>That will be a day for you to rest and not do any work, like the Sabbath days, and you must ◄fast/abstain from eating food► all that day. That is a permanent command/law for you all to obey. <verse eid="LEV 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 16:32"/>In future years, <char style="add">after Aaron has died</char>, this ritual/ceremony to enable me to forgive you all [DOU] will be performed by the Supreme Priest who is anointed <char style="add">with olive oil</char> and appointed to serve instead of his ancestor Aaron. He must put on the sacred clothes made of linen <verse eid="LEV 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 16:33"/>and offer sacrifices to purify the Very Holy Place, all of the Sacred Tent, the altar, the priests, and all the Israel people <char style="add">like Aaron did</char>. <verse eid="LEV 16:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 16:34"/>This will be a permanent command/law for you to obey once every year, to enable me to forgive you Israeli people for the sins that you have committed.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 16:34">Moses/I obeyed all those instructions/commands that Yahweh had given to him/me.<verse eid="LEV 16:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="LEV 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Where sacrifices are to be offered</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 17:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 17:2"/>“Speak to Aaron and his sons and to all the other Israeli people, and say this to them: ‘This is what Yahweh has commanded: <verse eid="LEV 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 17:3"/>If you sacrifice an ox or a lamb or a goat, you must bring it <char style="add">to the priest</char> at the entrance of the Sacred Tent <char style="add">area</char>, to present/offer it to me there. <verse eid="LEV 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 17:4"/>If you slaughter it to be a sacrifice anywhere else in the camp or outside the camp, you will be guilty of killing an animal <char style="add">in an unacceptable place</char>. As a result you will no longer be allowed to be/associate with my people. <verse eid="LEV 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 17:5"/>That rule is in order that you Israeli people, instead of offering sacrifices in the open fields, will offer them to me by taking them to the priest at the entrance of the Sacred Tent <char style="add">area</char>, to be offerings to maintain fellowship <char style="add">with me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 17:6"/><char style="add">After the animal is slaughtered</char>, the priest must sprinkle some of its blood against the altar at the entrance of the Sacred Tent, and burn its fat to be an aroma that is pleasing to me. <verse eid="LEV 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 17:7"/>You people must no longer give sacrifices to the demons that resemble goats which you are worshiping. You people must obey this command forever.’<verse eid="LEV 17:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 17:8"/>“And tell this to the people: ‘If any Israeli or any foreigner who is living among them brings an offering that is to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, or any other sacrifice, <verse eid="LEV 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 17:9"/>and does not bring it to the entrance of the Sacred Tent <char style="add">area</char> to be a sacrifice to me, that person will no longer be allowed to associate with my people.<verse eid="LEV 17:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 17:10"/>‘I will reject [IDM] any Israeli or any foreigner who is living among you who eats any blood, and I <char style="add">will command that he</char> no longer be allowed to associate with my people. <verse eid="LEV 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 17:11"/>That is because the life of every creature is in its blood; I have declared that it is blood that is to be offered on the altar to enable people to be forgiven for their sins. <verse eid="LEV 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 17:12"/>That is why I say that you Israelis must not eat blood, and the foreigners who live among you must also not eat blood.<verse eid="LEV 17:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 17:13"/>‘Any Israeli or any foreigner who is living among you who hunts any animal or bird that is permitted for you to eat, must drain out the blood <char style="add">of the animal or bird that he kills</char>, and cover the blood with dirt. <verse eid="LEV 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 17:14"/>This is because the life of every creature is in its blood. And that is why I have said [DOU] to you Israelis that anyone who eats blood must no longer <char style="add">be allowed to associate with my people</char>.<verse eid="LEV 17:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 17:15"/>‘Anyone in Israel, including foreigners, who eats any of the meat of any creature that is found dead, or that had been killed by wild animals, must wash his clothes and bathe. Then he must not touch anyone until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 17:16"/>If he does not do those things, he will be punished for what he did.’”<verse eid="LEV 17:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="LEV 18"/>
  <para style="s1">Forbidden sexual behavior</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 18:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 18:2"/>“Speak to the Israeli people and tell them <char style="add">that I, Yahweh, say this</char> this: I am Yahweh, your God. <verse eid="LEV 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 18:3"/><char style="add">So you must do what I want you to do</char>; you must not do the things that the people in Egypt, where you lived previously, do; and you must not do what is done by the people in Canaan, the land to which I am taking you. Do not imitate their behavior. <verse eid="LEV 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 18:4"/>You must obey all of my laws [DOU], because it is I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">who am commanding those laws</char>. <verse eid="LEV 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 18:5"/>If you obey all my laws and decrees, you will continue to remain alive <char style="add">for a long time</char>. I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am the one who is promising that to you</char>. <char style="add">These are some of my laws</char>:<verse eid="LEV 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 18:6"/>“Do not have sex with any of your close relatives. It is I, Yahweh, <char style="add">who am commanding that</char>.<verse eid="LEV 18:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 18:7"/>“Do not disgrace your father by having sex with your mother [DOU].<verse eid="LEV 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 18:8"/>“Do not have sex with any of your father’s <char style="add">other</char> wives, because that would disgrace your father.<verse eid="LEV 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 18:9"/>“Do not have sex with your sister or your stepsister; it does not matter whether she was born in your house or somewhere else.<verse eid="LEV 18:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 18:10"/>“Do not have sex with your granddaughter, because that would disgrace you.<verse eid="LEV 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 18:11"/>“Do not have sex with your half-sister, because she is your sister.<verse eid="LEV 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 18:12"/>“Do not have sex with your father’s sister, because she is your father’s close relative.<verse eid="LEV 18:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 18:13"/>“Do not have sex with your mother’s sister, because she is your mother’s close relative.<verse eid="LEV 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 18:14"/>“Do not disgrace your ◄uncle/father’s brother► by having sex with his wife, because she is your aunt.<verse eid="LEV 18:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 18:15"/>“Do not have sex with [DOU] your daughter-in-law, because she is your son’s wife.<verse eid="LEV 18:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 18:16"/>“Do not have sex with your brother’s wife, because that would disgrace your brother.<verse eid="LEV 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 18:17"/>“Do not have sex with the daughter or granddaughter of any woman whom you have previously had sex with; they are <char style="add">her</char> (OR, <char style="add">your</char>) close relatives. Having sex with any of them would be a wicked thing to do.<verse eid="LEV 18:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 18:18"/>“While your wife is still living, do not marry your wife’s sister and have sex with her.<verse eid="LEV 18:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 18:19"/>“Do not have sex with any woman while she is having her monthly menstrual period.<verse eid="LEV 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 18:20"/>“Do not ◄defile yourself/make yourself unacceptable to me► by having sex with someone else’s wife.<verse eid="LEV 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 18:21"/>“Do not give any of your children to be burned to be a sacrifice to the god Molech, because that would show that you do not revere me [MTY], Yahweh, your God.<verse eid="LEV 18:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 18:22"/>“No man should have sex with another man; that is detestable.<verse eid="LEV 18:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 18:23"/>“No one, man or woman, should ◄defile himself/cause himself to become unacceptable to me► by having sex with an animal; that is a perverse act.<verse eid="LEV 18:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 18:24"/>“Do not ◄defile yourselves/cause yourselves to become unacceptable to me► in any of those ways, because doing those things is how the people of the nations that I expelled as you advanced became ◄unacceptable to me/defiled►. <verse eid="LEV 18:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 18:25"/>They even caused the land to become defiled, so I punished them for their sins, and <char style="add">it was as though</char> the land vomited out the people who lived there. <verse eid="LEV 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 18:26"/>You must all obey my laws and decrees. That includes you people who were born here and the foreigners who live among you. <verse eid="LEV 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 18:27"/>All those detestable things were done by the people who lived in this land before you came here, and they caused the land to become defiled. <verse eid="LEV 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 18:28"/>So if you defile the land, I will get rid of [MET] you like I got rid of the people of those nations that were here before you came.<verse eid="LEV 18:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 18:29"/>“You must not allow people who do any of those detestable things to associate with you who are my people. <verse eid="LEV 18:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 18:30"/>Obey everything that I command you to do, and do not defile yourselves by practicing any of the detestable customs that were practiced <char style="add">by the people who were there</char> before you came. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am the one who is commanding these things</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 18:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="LEV 19"/>
  <para style="s1">Other laws</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 19:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 19:2"/>“Speak to all the people of Israel and tell them this: You must be holy, because I, Yahweh your God, am holy, <char style="add">and I want you to be like me</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 19:3"/>‘Each of you must respect your father and your mother. And you must ◄honor/treat respectfully► the Sabbath days. I am Yahweh, your God, <char style="add">and that is what I am commanding you to do</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 19:4"/>‘Do not worship idols or make metal statues of gods for yourselves. I am Yahweh, your God, <char style="add">and I am the only one you must worship</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 19:5"/>‘Then you bring an offering to maintain fellowship with me, offer it in a way that will cause me to accept it. <verse eid="LEV 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 19:6"/>The meat should be eaten on the day that you sacrifice it, but you are permitted to eat some of it on the next day. Anything that remains until the third/next day must be completely burned. <verse eid="LEV 19:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 19:7"/>For any of it to be eaten on the third day is very displeasing to me, and I will not accept that offering. <verse eid="LEV 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 19:8"/>I will punish anyone who eats it <char style="add">after the second day</char>, because he will not have respected that what I say is holy. And that person must no longer be allowed to associate with my people.<verse eid="LEV 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 19:9"/>‘Then you harvest your grain, leave the grain at the very edge of the field, and do not pick up the grain that has fallen on the ground. <verse eid="LEV 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 19:10"/>And when you harvest your grapes, do not go back a second time to try to harvest some more, and do not pick up the grapes that have fallen on the ground. Leave those things for the poor people and for foreigners who are living among you. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am commanding those things</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 19:11"/>‘Do not steal anything.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:11">‘Do not tell lies.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:11">‘Do not deceive each other.<verse eid="LEV 19:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 19:12"/>‘Do not show that you do not respect me by using/saying my name to falsely promise that you will do something. <char style="add">Do not forget that</char> I am Yahweh, your God.<verse eid="LEV 19:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 19:13"/>‘Do not cheat anyone or steal from anyone.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:13">
    <char style="add">‘If you have agreed to</char> pay your workers at the end of the day, <char style="add">do what you have promised</char>; do not keep those wages until the next day.<verse eid="LEV 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 19:14"/>‘Do not curse deaf people, and do not put things in the path of blind people to cause them to stumble.<verse eid="LEV 19:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 19:15"/>‘Always [LIT] judge people fairly [DOU]. Do not do special favors for either poor people or rich people.<verse eid="LEV 19:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 19:16"/>‘Do not spread false rumors about other people.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:16">‘Do not say anything <char style="add">in court</char> that would result in some <char style="add">innocent</char> person being executed. I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am commanding this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 19:17"/>‘Do not hate anyone. Instead, honestly rebuke those who ought to be rebuked, in order that you also will not be guilty.<verse eid="LEV 19:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 19:18"/>‘Do not try to get revenge against someone or be angry with someone for a long time. Instead, love other people like you love yourself. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am commanding this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 19:19"/>‘Obey my laws.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:19">‘Do not allow two different kinds of animals to mate with each other.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:19">‘Do not plant two different kinds of seed in the <char style="add">same</char> field.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:19">‘Do not wear clothing made from two different kinds of material.<verse eid="LEV 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 19:20"/>‘If a man has sex with a slave woman who has been promised to marry some other man, but she has not been bought by that man and is still a slave, the man who had sex with her must be punished. But because she is still a slave, she and the man who had sex with her must not be killed. <verse eid="LEV 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 19:21"/>However, that man must bring a ram to <char style="add">be slaughtered at</char> the entrance of the Sacred Tent area, to be an offering in order that he no longer be guilty for his sin. <verse eid="LEV 19:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 19:22"/>The priest will offer that ram to me in order that the man will be forgiven for the sin that he committed, and I will forgive him.<verse eid="LEV 19:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 19:23"/>‘When you enter the land <char style="add">that I have promised to give to you</char>, and when you plant various kinds of fruit trees, you must not eat any of their fruit for three years [DOU]. <verse eid="LEV 19:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 19:24"/>In the fourth year all of their fruit must be set aside to belong to me; it must be brought to me to be an offering to praise me. <verse eid="LEV 19:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 19:25"/>But in the fifth/next year, you will be permitted to eat their fruit. If you do that, your trees will produce much fruit. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am promising that</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 19:26"/>‘Do not eat any meat that still has <char style="add">the animal’s</char> blood in it.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="LEV 19:26">‘Do not consult spirits to find out what will happen in the future, and do not practice sorcery.<verse eid="LEV 19:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 19:27"/>‘Do not shave the hair at the sides of your heads <char style="add">like pagan people do</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 19:28"/>‘Do not cut your bodies <char style="add">when you are mourning</char> for people who have died, and do not put tattoos on your bodies. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am commanding this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 19:29"/>‘Do not disgrace your daughters by forcing them to become prostitutes. If you cause them to become prostitutes, soon the land will be filled with prostitutes and all other kinds of people’s wicked behavior.<verse eid="LEV 19:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 19:30"/>‘Honor my Sabbath days and revere my Sacred Tent, because I, Yahweh, <char style="add">live there</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 19:31"/>‘Do not seek advice from those who ◄consult/talk with► the spirits of dead people [DOU], because if you do that, they will defile you. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am the one you should consult</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 19:32"/>‘Stand up when old people <char style="add">enter the room</char>, and show that you respect them, and also revere me, your God; <char style="add">that is what</char> I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am commanding</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 19:33"/>‘When foreigners live among you <char style="add">in your land</char>, do not mistreat them. <verse eid="LEV 19:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 19:34"/>You must treat them like you treat your fellow-citizens. Love them like you love yourselves, and do not forget that once, when you were foreigners in Egypt, <char style="add">you were badly mistreated by the people of Egypt</char>. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am commanding you to do this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 19:35"/>‘When you are measuring things, to see how long they are or how much they weigh or how many there are, <verse eid="LEV 19:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 19:36"/>use correct <char style="add">measuring sticks and</char> scales and weights <char style="add">on the scales</char> and measuring baskets and other measuring containers. I Yahweh, your God, who brought you out of Egypt, <char style="add">am giving you these laws</char>.<verse eid="LEV 19:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 19:37"/>‘Obey carefully [DOU] all my laws and decrees, because I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am the one who am commanding them</char>.’ ”<verse eid="LEV 19:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="LEV 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Punishments for various sins</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 20:1"/>Yahweh also said this to Moses/me: <verse eid="LEV 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 20:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people, ‘<char style="add">This is what Yahweh says</char>: Any Israeli or any foreigner who is living in Israel who sacrifices any of his children to be an offering to the god Molech must be executed. The people of the town must kill him by throwing stones at him. <verse eid="LEV 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 20:3"/>I will reject [IDM] such people and command that they no longer be allowed to associate with my people. <verse eid="LEV 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 20:4"/>If the people of that man’s town ignore it when he kills one of his children to offer him as a sacrifice to Molech, and if they do not execute that person, <verse eid="LEV 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 20:5"/>I myself will punish that person and his family, and I will command that he no longer be able to associate with my people. And I will do the same thing to any others who do the same thing that he did to worship Molech.<verse eid="LEV 20:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 20:6"/>‘ will reject [IDM] those who go to those who ◄consult/talk with► the spirits of dead people and fortune-tellers to seek advice from them. I will command that they no longer be allowed to associate with my people.<verse eid="LEV 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 20:7"/>‘Set yourselves apart and be holy, because I, Yahweh your God, am holy, <char style="add">and I want you to be like me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 20:8"/>Obey carefully [DOU] all my laws. I am Yahweh, the one will cause you to be holy.<verse eid="LEV 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 20:9"/>‘If anyone curses his father or his mother, he must be executed. He himself will be responsible for his own death [MTY].<verse eid="LEV 20:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 20:10"/>‘If a man commits adultery with some other man’s wife, both of them, the man and the woman, must be executed.<verse eid="LEV 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 20:11"/>‘If a man has sex with [EUP] one of his father’s wives, he has disgraced his father. So both that man and that woman must be executed, they will be responsible for their own deaths [MTY].<verse eid="LEV 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 20:12"/>‘If a man has sex with [EUP] his daughter-in-law, both of them must be executed. What they have done is very perverse; and they will be responsible for their own deaths [MTY].<verse eid="LEV 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 20:13"/>‘If two men have sex together, they have done something detestable. They must both be executed, they will be responsible for their own deaths [MTY].<verse eid="LEV 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 20:14"/>‘If a man marries both a woman and her mother, that is a wicked thing. All three of them must be burned to death, in order that such a wicked practice will not <char style="add">continue to be done</char> among you.<verse eid="LEV 20:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 20:15"/>‘If a man has sex with an animal, he must be executed, and you must also kill that animal.<verse eid="LEV 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 20:16"/>‘<char style="add">Similarly</char>, if a woman has sex with an animal, both the woman and that animal must be killed [DOU]; they are responsible for their own deaths [MTY].<verse eid="LEV 20:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 20:17"/>‘If a man marries his sister, the daughter of either his mother or his father, and they have sex together, that is disgraceful. They must not be allowed to continue to associate with my people. And because he has disgraced his sister, he must be punished.<verse eid="LEV 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 20:18"/>‘If a man has sex with [EUP, DOU] a woman during her monthly menstrual period, they have both revealed why she was bleeding, so both of them must not be allowed to associate with my people any more.<verse eid="LEV 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 20:19"/>‘Do not have sex with the sister of either your father or your mother, because that would be disgracing someone who is a close relative. And you and the woman must both be punished.<verse eid="LEV 20:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 20:20"/>‘If a man has sex [EUP] with his aunt, he has dishonored his uncle. I will punish both of them by causing them to die without having any children.<verse eid="LEV 20:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 20:21"/>‘If a man marries his brother’s wife <char style="add">while his brother is still living</char>, that is disgraceful. He has dishonored his brother; and they both will die without having any children.<verse eid="LEV 20:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 20:22"/>‘Obey all my laws/decrees [DOU] carefully, in order that you will not be forced to leave [MET] the land to which I am bringing you. <verse eid="LEV 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 20:23"/>Do not imitate/adopt the customs of the people of the land from which I will expel them as you advance. I hated them because they did all those things. <verse eid="LEV 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 20:24"/>But I said to you, “You will take their land from them; I will give it to you to be yours, a land that is very fertile [IDM]. I am Yahweh your God, who has set you apart from the people of other nations.”<verse eid="LEV 20:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 20:25"/>‘So you must distinguish between birds and animals that are unacceptable to me and those that are acceptable to me. Do not defile yourselves by <char style="add">eating</char> birds or animals, or anything that scurries across the ground, that I have said are unacceptable for you. <verse eid="LEV 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 20:26"/>You must behave in ways that I consider to be holy, because I, Yahweh, am holy, and I have set you apart from the <char style="add">ungodly people of other</char> nations to belong to me.<verse eid="LEV 20:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 20:27"/>‘You must execute any man or woman among you who ◄consults/talks with► the spirits of dead people or who is a fortune-teller. Kill them by <char style="add">throwing</char> stones at them; but they will be responsible for their own deaths.’”<verse eid="LEV 20:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="LEV 21"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules for priests</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 21:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, “Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron, and say to them, <verse eid="LEV 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 21:2"/>‘You priests must not cause yourselves to become unfit to do my work by <char style="add">touching</char> corpses. Priests are permitted to touch only the corpses of close relatives, such as the priest’s mother or father or his son or daughter or his brother. <verse eid="LEV 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 21:3"/>Priests are also permitted to touch the corpse of a sister if she is not married, because she has no husband <char style="add">to bury her body</char>. <verse eid="LEV 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 21:4"/>Priests must not cause themselves to become unfit to do my work [DOU] by <char style="add">touching corpses of</char> people who were married to one of their close relatives.<verse eid="LEV 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 21:5"/>You priests must not shave your heads or shave the edges of your beards or cut your bodies <char style="add">to show that you are mourning for someone who has died</char>. <verse eid="LEV 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 21:6"/>You must act in ways that I, your God, consider to be holy, and not disgrace my name/reputation. You are the ones who present to me the offerings that are burned. <char style="add">It is as though</char> those offerings are food for me, your God; so you must act in ways that are holy.<verse eid="LEV 21:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 21:7"/>You priests must not marry women who have been prostitutes or who have been divorced from their husbands, because you priests are ◄set apart for me/holy►. <verse eid="LEV 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 21:8"/>You must consider that you are holy, because you offer food to me, your God. Consider yourselves to be holy because I, Yahweh, <char style="add">the one who caused you to be priests and </char> the one who enables you to be holy, am holy.<verse eid="LEV 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 21:9"/>If a priest’s daughter disgraces herself by becoming a prostitute, she disgraces her father; and she must be killed by being burned in a fire.<verse eid="LEV 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 21:10"/>The Supreme Priest is the one among his relatives who has been <char style="add">appointed for that work</char> by having his head anointed with olive oil. He is also the one who has been appointed to wear the special garments that priests wear. He must not allow the hair on his <char style="add">head</char> to remain uncombed, and he must not tear his clothes <char style="add">when he is mourning for someone</char>. <verse eid="LEV 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 21:11"/>He must not enter some place where there is a corpse. He must not do that and cause himself to become unfit for his work, even if it is his father or his mother who has died. <verse eid="LEV 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 21:12"/>He must not leave the Sacred Tent <char style="add">to join those who are mourning</char>, because he would cause himself to become unfit for his work and would also defile/desecrate the Sacred Tent. He must not leave the Sacred Tent <char style="add">at that time</char>, because by being anointed with olive oil he has been ◄appointed/set apart► to serve his God <char style="add">in the Sacred Tent</char>. I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am the one who am commanding this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 21:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 21:13"/>Women whom you priests marry must be virgins. <verse eid="LEV 21:13"/><verse number="14-15" style="v" sid="LEV 21:14-15"/>You priests must not marry widows or prostitutes or divorced women, because if you did that, <char style="add">if you later have</char> sons, they would not be acceptable to be priests among your people. You must marry only virgins from among your own people. I am Yahweh, who sets priests apart to be holy.’”<verse eid="LEV 21:14-15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 21:16"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 21:17"/>“Say this to Aaron: 'For all future time, none of your descendants who has any defects <char style="add">on his body</char> will be allowed to come near <char style="add">the altar</char> to offer <char style="add">sacrifices to me which will be like</char> [MET] my food: <verse eid="LEV 21:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 21:18"/>No one who is blind or lame or deformed, or whose <char style="add">face is</char> disfigured, <verse eid="LEV 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 21:19"/>no man with a crippled foot or a crippled hand, <verse eid="LEV 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 21:20"/>no man who is a hunchback or a dwarf, no man whose eyes are defective, no man who has a skin disease [DOU] or whose testicles have been damaged is allowed to brings sacrifices. <verse eid="LEV 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 21:21"/>No descendant of Aaron, the <char style="add">first Supreme</char> Priest, who has any defect is allowed to come to the altar to offer to me, his God, sacrifices that will be burned. <verse eid="LEV 21:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 21:22"/>Priests who have defects are permitted to eat the various kinds of holy food offered to me. <verse eid="LEV 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 21:23"/>But because of their defects, they must not go near the curtain <char style="add">in the Sacred Tent</char> or near the altar, because if they did that, they would desecrate my Sacred Tent. I am Yahweh, the one who sets those places apart as being holy.' ”<verse eid="LEV 21:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 21:24"/>So Moses/I told this to Aaron and to his sons and to all the Israeli people.<verse eid="LEV 21:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="LEV 22"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 22:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 22:2"/>“Tell Aaron and his sons to greatly respect the sacred offerings that the Israeli people bring to me; by doing that you will respect me [MTY], Yahweh.<verse eid="LEV 22:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 22:3"/>“Tell them that for all future time, if any of their descendants comes near to the sacred offerings that the Israeli people dedicate to me while he is unfit to work for me, that person will no longer be allowed to work for me. I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am commanding this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 22:4"/>“If any descendant of Aaron has a contagious skin disease or a discharge from his sexual organs, he is not allowed to eat any of the sacred offerings until he is cured. He will also be unfit for his work if he touches anything which has become unacceptable to me because it has touched a corpse, or if he touches anyone who as an emission of semen, <verse eid="LEV 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 22:5"/>or if he touches anything that crawls on the ground, or if he touches any person who causes him to be unfit for his work. <verse eid="LEV 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 22:6"/>Any priest who touches such things must bathe, and he must not touch anyone else until that evening. <verse eid="LEV 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 22:7"/>After the sun sets, he will be permitted to eat some of the sacred offerings that are for him to eat. <verse eid="LEV 22:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 22:8"/>He must not eat anything that is found dead or that has been killed by wild animals, because if he did that, he would be unfit to work for me. I, Yahweh <char style="add">am commanding those things</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 22:9"/>“The priests must obey my commandments in order that they will not become guilty and die as a result of ◄despising/not obeying► them.<verse eid="LEV 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 22:10"/>“Anyone who is not a member of a priest’s family is not permitted to eat any of a sacred offering, and no one who is visiting the priest or whom the priest has hired is permitted to eat it. <verse eid="LEV 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 22:11"/>But if a priest buys a slave, or if a slave is born in his house, that slave is permitted to eat such food. <verse eid="LEV 22:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 22:12"/>If a priest’s daughter marries a man who is not a priest, she no longer is permitted to eat the sacred food. <verse eid="LEV 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 22:13"/>But if a priest’s daughter who has no children becomes a widow or becomes divorced, if she returns to her father’s house to live there like she did when she was young, she may eat the same food that her father eats. But no other person is permitted to eat any of it.<verse eid="LEV 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 22:14"/>“If anyone who is not permitted to eat a sacred offering eats it without realizing that it is sacred, he must pay the priest for the offering, and pay him an extra one-fifth of its value. <verse eid="LEV 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 22:15"/>When the priests bring offerings to me, the sacred offerings that the Israeli people bring to them, they must not treat those offerings as though they are not sacred <verse eid="LEV 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 22:16"/>by allowing those who are not priests to eat any of those offerings. If they did that, they would become guilty and must make a payment. I am Yahweh, the one who causes those offerings to be sacred.”<verse eid="LEV 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Offerings that are not acceptable</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 22:17"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 22:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 22:18"/>“Speak to Aaron and his sons and to all the Israeli people and tell them that I command this: ‘If any of you Israelis or foreigners who live in Israel brings to me an animal that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, either as a result of a solemn promise that you made to me or to be an offering that is given voluntarily, <verse eid="LEV 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 22:19"/>it must be an animal that has no defects, in order that it will be accepted by me. <verse eid="LEV 22:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 22:20"/>Do not bring any animals that have defects, because I will not accept them as an offering from you. <verse eid="LEV 22:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 22:21"/><char style="add">Similarly</char>, when someone brings from his cattle or sheep or goats an offering to maintain fellowship with me, either to fulfill a promise that he made to me or to be a voluntary offering, in order that I will accept it, it must have no defects [DOU] or blemishes. <verse eid="LEV 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 22:22"/>Do not offer to me animals that are blind or injured or maimed/crippled, or any animal that has warts or a festering sore [DOU]. <verse eid="LEV 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 22:23"/>You may present to me to be a voluntary offering an ox or a sheep that is injured or stunted, but it will not be accepted to fulfill a promise made to me. <verse eid="LEV 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 22:24"/>You must not offer to me animals whose testicles are bruised or crushed or torn or cut. You must not injure the testicles of any animal in your land, <verse eid="LEV 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 22:25"/>and you must not accept such animals that are sold/given to you by a foreigner. You must not offer them to me as a sacrifice for me. Such animals will not be accepted by me, because they are deformed or have defects.’”<verse eid="LEV 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 22:26"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 22:27"/>“When a calf or lamb or goat is born, it must remain with its mother for seven days. After that, it will be acceptable as an offering to me that will be burned. <verse eid="LEV 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 22:28"/>Do not slaughter a cow or a sheep and its baby on the same day.<verse eid="LEV 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 22:29"/>“Then you sacrifice an animal to thank <char style="add">me for what I have done</char>, sacrifice it in a way that is acceptable to me. <verse eid="LEV 22:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 22:30"/>The meat must be eaten on that day; do not leave any of it until the next morning. I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am the one who am commanding this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 22:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 22:31"/>“Obey all my commands [DOU]. I, Yahweh, <char style="add">am commanding them</char>; <verse eid="LEV 22:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 22:32"/>do not dishonor me [MTY] <char style="add">by disobeying them</char>. You Israeli people must acknowledge that I, Yahweh, am holy, and I am the one who causes you to be holy. <verse eid="LEV 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 22:33"/>And I am the one who brought you out of Egypt in order to show that that I, Yahweh, am <char style="add">and will always be</char> your God.”<verse eid="LEV 22:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="LEV 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Religious celebrations</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 23:1"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 23:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people about the festivals that I have chosen, the days when you all must gather together <char style="add">to worship me</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Sabbath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 23:3"/>“You may work for six days <char style="add">each week</char>, but on the seventh day you must not do any work. You must rest. It is a sacred/holy day when you must gather together <char style="add">to worship me</char>. Wherever you live, you must rest on that day.”<verse eid="LEV 23:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festivals of Passover and Unleavened Bread</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 23:4"/>“There are festivals that I have established for you. Those will also be sacred/holy days when you must gather together <char style="add">to worship me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 23:5"/><char style="add">The first festival is</char> ◄the Passover/when you remember that I spared your ancestors when I killed all the firstborn Egyptian sons►. That festival will begin at twilight/dusk/sunset on the chosen day ◄each spring/in March or April each year►, <char style="add">and end on the following day</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 23:6"/>The next day, the Festival of Eating Bread That Has No Yeast will begin. That festival will continue for seven days. During that time, the bread that you eat must be made without yeast. <verse eid="LEV 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 23:7"/>On the first day of that festival, you all must stop your regular work and you must gather together <char style="add">to worship me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 23:8"/>On each of the seven days, you must present to me <char style="add">several animals to be</char> an offering/sacrifice to be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. On the seventh day, you all must again stop your regular work and gather to worship me.”<verse eid="LEV 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festival of the Beginning of the Harvest</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 23:9"/>Yahweh also told Moses/me <verse eid="LEV 23:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 23:10"/>to tell the Israeli people <char style="add">about other festivals</char>. He said, “When you arrive in the land which I am giving to you, and you harvest your crops <char style="add">for the first time</char> there, bring to the priest some of the first grain that you harvest. <verse eid="LEV 23:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 23:11"/>On the day after the <char style="add">next</char> Sabbath/rest day, the priest will lift it up <char style="add">high to dedicate it</char> to me, in order that I will accept it as your <char style="add">gift</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 23:12"/>That same day, you must sacrifice to me a one-year-old male lamb that has no defects. You must burn it <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 23:13"/>You must also burn an offering of grain. That offering must consist of ◄three quarts/3.5 liters► of good flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. The smell <char style="add">of those things burning</char> will be very pleasing to me. Along with that, you must also offer one quart/liter of wine, which will be a liquid offering. <verse eid="LEV 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 23:14"/>Do not eat any bread or any roasted grain or unroasted grain on that day until after you have brought those offerings to me, your God. You must always obey [LIT] those commands, wherever you live.”<verse eid="LEV 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festival of the End of the Harvest</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 23:15"/>“Seven weeks after the priest offers that grain to me, <verse eid="LEV 23:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 23:16"/>on the next/50th day after he offers it, <char style="add">each family</char> must bring to me an offering from the new crop of grain. <verse eid="LEV 23:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 23:17"/>From your homes, bring two loaves of bread <char style="add">to the priest</char>. He will lift them up <char style="add">high to dedicate them</char> as an offering to me. Those loaves must be baked from three quarts/liters of good flour that has yeast mixed with it. That bread will be an offering to me from the first wheat that you harvest <char style="add">each year</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 23:18"/>Along with this bread, you must present to me seven one-year-old lambs with no defects, one young bull, and two rams. They must all be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. All those offerings, with the grain offering and the wine offering, will be burned, and the smell <char style="add">of all those things burning</char> will be very pleasing to me. <verse eid="LEV 23:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 23:19"/>Then you must also kill one male goat to be an offering/sacrifice for your sins, and two one-year-old male lambs to be an offering to enable you to maintain fellowship with me. <verse eid="LEV 23:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 23:20"/>The priest will lift up these offerings <char style="add">high to dedicate them</char> to me. He will also offer the loaves of bread that were baked from the first wheat that you harvest. Those offerings are sacred to me, but they are for the priests <char style="add">to eat</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 23:21"/>On that day, you must stop your regular work and gather to worship me. You must always obey those instructions/commands, and you must obey them wherever you live.<verse eid="LEV 23:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 23:22"/>“When you harvest the grain in your fields, do not harvest the grain along the edges of the fields, and do not pick up the grain that the harvesters drop. Leave that grain for the poor people and for the foreigners who are living among you. <char style="add">Do not forget that it is</char> I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">who am commanding those things</char>!”<verse eid="LEV 23:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festival of Trumpets</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 23:23"/>Yahweh also told Moses/me <verse eid="LEV 23:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 23:24"/>to give these instructions/commands to the Israeli people: “<char style="add">Each year</char> in September, on the day that I have chosen, you all must celebrate it by completely resting. You must not do any work on that day. When <char style="add">the priests</char> blow their trumpets loudly, you all must gather together to worship me. <verse eid="LEV 23:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 23:25"/>All of you must not do your regular work on that day. Instead, you must present offerings to me that will be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festival of Atonement</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 23:26"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 23:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 23:27"/>“You must celebrate a day <char style="add">on which you request that I</char> forgive you for the sins that you have committed. That day will be nine days after the festival <char style="add">when the priests blow</char> the trumpets. On that day you must ◄fast/abstain from eating food►. You must gather together to worship me and present offerings to me that will be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 23:28"/>You must not do any work on that day, because it is the day when the priests will offer sacrifices to me to ◄atone for/ask me to forgive► your sins. <verse eid="LEV 23:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 23:29"/>You must expel from your group anyone who does not ◄fast/abstain from eating food► on that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 23:30"/>I will get rid of anyone who does any kind of work on that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 23:31"/>You must not work at all! You must always obey those instructions/commands, and you must obey them wherever you live. <verse eid="LEV 23:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 23:32"/>That day will be a day of complete rest for all of you, and on that day you must ◄fast/abstain from eating food► <char style="add">to show that you are sorry for having sinned</char>. That day of rest and ◄fasting/abstaining from eating food► will begin on the evening before the day in which you ask me to forgive you for your sins, and it will end on the evening of the following day.”<verse eid="LEV 23:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festival of Shelters</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 23:33"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 23:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 23:34"/>“Tell the Israeli people that <char style="add">each year</char> they must also celebrate a festival of living in temporary shelters. That festival will begin five days after the day in which they request me to forgive them for their sins. It will last for seven days. <verse eid="LEV 23:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 23:35"/>On the first day of that festival, the people must gather together to worship me, and they must not do any regular work on that day. <verse eid="LEV 23:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 23:36"/>On each of the seven days of the festival, they must present to me an offering <char style="add">of animals</char> that will be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. On the next day, they must gather again to worship me and present to me another animal that will be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. That also will be a sacred gathering, and they must not work on that day, either.<verse eid="LEV 23:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 23:37"/>“<char style="add">To summarize</char>, those are the festivals that I have appointed. Celebrate those sacred festivals by gathering together to present to me all the various offerings that will be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>—animals that will be burned completely, and offerings of grain, and offerings to enable the Israeli people to maintain fellowship with me, and offerings of wine. Each offering must be brought on the day that I have indicated. <verse eid="LEV 23:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 23:38"/>◄Those festivals must be celebrated/You must celebrate those festivals► in addition to <char style="add">worshiping on</char> the ◄Sabbath days/days of rest►. And all those offerings must be given in addition to the offerings that people personally decide to give, and in addition to the offerings that people make to accompany the solemn promises that they have made, or offerings that people make ◄voluntarily/because they themselves want to►.<verse eid="LEV 23:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 23:39"/>“<char style="add">Returning to my instructions about</char> the Festival of Living in Temporary Shelters, you must celebrate this festival after you have harvested all the crops. On the first day and on the last day of that festival, you must rest completely. <verse eid="LEV 23:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 23:40"/>But on the first day, you are permitted to pick fruit from trees. Cut palm fronds/branches and other leafy branches from trees or from bushes that grow by the streams, <char style="add">and make shelters/huts to live in for that week</char>. Then rejoice in my presence for those seven days. <verse eid="LEV 23:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 23:41"/>You must celebrate this festival for seven days every year. You must never stop obeying my commands/instructions for that festival. You must celebrate it in September. <verse eid="LEV 23:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 23:42"/>During the seven days of that festival, all of you people who have been Israelis your entire lives must live in shelters/huts. <verse eid="LEV 23:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 23:43"/>That will remind your descendants that their ancestors lived in shelters <char style="add">for many years</char> after I rescued them from Egypt. <char style="add">Do not forget that</char> I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am the one who is commanding this</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 23:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 23:44"/>So Moses/I gave to the Israeli people all those instructions concerning the festivals that Yahweh <char style="add">wanted them to celebrate</char> each year.<verse eid="LEV 23:44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="LEV 24"/>
  <para style="s1">Taking care of the lamps</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 24:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 24:2"/>“Command the Israeli people to continually bring to you clear oil made from pressed olives to burn in the lamps <char style="add">in the Sacred Tent</char>, in order that those lamps will burn all the time. <verse eid="LEV 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 24:3"/>Outside the curtain of the Very Holy Place, Aaron must take care of the lamps in my presence continually, in order that they will burn all during the night. That regulation must be obeyed forever. <verse eid="LEV 24:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 24:4"/>Those lampstands that burn in my presence must be taken care of continually.<verse eid="LEV 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 24:5"/>“Also, <char style="add">each week</char> you must take some fine flour and bake twelve <char style="add">very big</char> loaves of bread, using about four quarts/liters of flour for each loaf. <verse eid="LEV 24:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 24:6"/>Put the loaves in two rows, with six loaves in each row, on the table covered with pure gold, in my presence. <verse eid="LEV 24:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 24:7"/>Along each row, place <char style="add">in some gold cups</char> some pure incense to be burned to be an offering to me instead of the bread. <verse eid="LEV 24:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 24:8"/>New/Fresh loaves of bread must be put <char style="add">on the table</char> each Sabbath day, to signify the agreement that will never end, that I have made with you Israeli people. <verse eid="LEV 24:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 24:9"/>The bread <char style="add">that is taken off the table</char> belongs to Aaron and his sons. They must eat it in a holy place, because it is a very holy part of the offerings that are given to me by being burned.”<verse eid="LEV 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">An example of fair punishment</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10-11" style="v" sid="LEV 24:10-11"/>There was a man whose mother’s name was Shelomith; she was an Israeli whose father was Dibri from the tribe of Dan. And that man’s father was from Egypt. One day that man and another Israeli man started to fight inside the camp. And while they were fighting, that man cursed Yahweh [MTY]. <verse eid="LEV 24:10-11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 24:12"/>So the Israeli people seized him and guarded him until they could find out what Yahweh would reveal to them <char style="add">that they should do to that man</char>.<verse eid="LEV 24:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 24:13"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 24:14"/>“<char style="add">Tie up and</char> take outside the camp the man who has cursed me. There all those who heard what he said must put their hands on his head <char style="add">to indicate that he is guilty</char>, and then all the people must <char style="add">kill him by</char> throwing stones at him. <verse eid="LEV 24:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 24:15"/>Tell the Israelis, ‘If anyone curses me, he must ◄endure the consequences/be punished►. <verse eid="LEV 24:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 24:16"/>So anyone who curses me [MTY] must be executed. All the people must throw stones at him. It does not matter if he is a foreigner or an Israeli citizen; anyone who curses me must be executed.’<verse eid="LEV 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 24:17"/>“Also, If anyone murders another person, he must be executed. <verse eid="LEV 24:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 24:18"/>And anyone who kills <char style="add">another person’s</char> animal must give that person a live animal to replace the one that he killed. <verse eid="LEV 24:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 24:19"/>And if one person injures another person, the injured person is allowed to injure the person who injured him in the same way: <verse eid="LEV 24:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 24:20"/>If someone breaks one of another person’s bones, that person is allowed to break one of the bones of the person who injured him. If someone gouges out an eye of another person, that person is allowed to gouge out the eye of the person who injured him. If someone knocks out the tooth of another person, that person is allowed to knock out one of his teeth. What is done to the offender must be the same as what he did to the other person. <verse eid="LEV 24:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 24:21"/>Whoever kills <char style="add">another person’s</char> animal must give that person a live animal to replace the one that he killed, but anyone who murders another person must be executed. <verse eid="LEV 24:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 24:22"/>That law applies to you Israelis and and also to the foreigners who live among you; I, Yahweh your God <char style="add">am the one who has commanded it</char>.”<verse eid="LEV 24:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 24:23"/>Then Moses/I told the Israelis <char style="add">what they must do to the man who cursed Yahweh</char>, so they took the man outside the camp and <char style="add">killed him by</char> throwing stones at him. They did what Yahweh commanded Moses/me <char style="add">to tell them to do</char>.<verse eid="LEV 24:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="LEV 25"/>
  <para style="s1">The seventh year</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 25:1"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me on Sinai Mountain, <verse eid="LEV 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 25:2"/>“Tell the Israelis <char style="add">that I, Yahweh, say this</char>: When you enter the land that I am about to give you, every seventh year you must honor me by <char style="add">not planting any seeds. You will be</char> allowing the ground to rest. <verse eid="LEV 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 25:3"/>For six years you are to plant seeds in your fields and prune your grapevines and harvest the crops. <verse eid="LEV 25:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 25:4"/>But the seventh/next year you must <char style="add">dedicate</char> to me, and allow your fields to rest. Do not plant seeds in your fields or prune your grapevines <char style="add">during that year</char>. <verse eid="LEV 25:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 25:5"/>Do not reap <char style="add">the grain</char> that grows in your fields without having been planted, or harvest the grapes that grow <char style="add">without the vines being pruned</char>; you must allow the land to rest for that one year. <verse eid="LEV 25:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 25:6"/>But you are permitted to eat whatever crops grow by themselves during that year without having been planted. You and your male and female servants, and workers whom you have hired, and people who are living among you temporarily are permitted to eat it. <verse eid="LEV 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 25:7"/>Also, <char style="add">during that year</char> your livestock and the wild animals in your land are permitted to eat it.’<verse eid="LEV 25:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The fiftieth year</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8-9" style="v" sid="LEV 25:8-9"/>‘Also, after every 49 years has ended, you must do this: ◄On the tenth day of the seventh month/At the end of September► <char style="add">of the next/50th year</char>, blow trumpets throughout the country, to declare that it will be a day on which you request that I forgive you for the sins that you have committed. <verse eid="LEV 25:8-9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 25:10"/>Set apart that year, and proclaim that throughout the country, it will be a year of restoring the land and freeing people: All the people <char style="add">who sold their property</char> will receive back the property that they previously owned, and slaves must be ◄freed/allowed to return to <char style="add">their property and</char> their families►. <verse eid="LEV 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 25:11"/>That year will be a Year of Celebration; <char style="add">during that year</char> do not plant anything, and do not harvest <char style="add">in the usual way</char> the grain/wheat that grows without having been planted, or the grapes that grow without the vines being pruned. <verse eid="LEV 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 25:12"/>It will be a Year of Celebration, so eat <char style="add">only</char> what grows in the fields ◄by itself/without any work being done to produce anything►.<verse eid="LEV 25:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 25:13"/>‘In that Year of Celebration, everyone must return to their own property.<verse eid="LEV 25:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 25:14"/>‘If you sell some of your land to a fellow Israeli or if you buy some land from one of them, you must treat that person fairly: <verse eid="LEV 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 25:15"/>If you buy land, the price that you will pay will depend on the number of years there will be until the next Year of Celebration. If someone sells land to you, he will charge a price that is determined by the number of years until the next Year of Celebration. <verse eid="LEV 25:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 25:16"/>If there will be many years before the next Year of Celebration, the price will be higher; if there will be only a few years until the next Year of Celebration, the price will be lower. <char style="add">You could say that</char> what he is really selling you is the number of crops <char style="add">which you can harvest before the next Year of Celebration</char>. <verse eid="LEV 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 25:17"/>Do not cheat each other; instead, revere me. I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">am the one who am commanding this</char>.<verse eid="LEV 25:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 25:18"/>‘Obey all my laws [DOU] carefully. If you do that, you will continue to live safely in your country [DOU]. <verse eid="LEV 25:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 25:19"/>And crops will grow well on the land, and you will have plenty to eat. <verse eid="LEV 25:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 25:20"/>But you may ask, “If we do not plant or harvest our crops during the seventh year, what will we have to eat?” <verse eid="LEV 25:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 25:21"/><char style="add">My answer is that</char> I will bless you very much during the sixth/previous year, with the result that during that year there will be enough crops to provide food for you for three years! <verse eid="LEV 25:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 25:22"/>Then, after you plant seed during the eighth/next year <char style="add">and wait for the crops to grow</char>, you will eat the food grown in the sixth year, and continue to eat it until more food is harvested in the ninth year!<verse eid="LEV 25:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 25:23"/>‘You must not sell any of your land to belong to someone else permanently, because the land <char style="add">is not yours, it</char>; is really mine, and you are only living on it temporarily and ◄farming/taking care of► it for me. <verse eid="LEV 25:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 25:24"/>Throughout the country that you will possess, you must remember that if someone sells some of his land to you, he is permitted to buy it back from you <char style="add">if he wants to</char>.<verse eid="LEV 25:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 25:25"/>‘So, if one of your fellow Israelis becomes poor and sells some of his property <char style="add">to obtain some money</char>, the person who is most closely related to him is permitted to come and buy that land for him. <verse eid="LEV 25:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 25:26"/>However, if a man has no one to buy the land for him, and he himself prospers again and saves enough money to buy that land back, <verse eid="LEV 25:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 25:27"/>he must calculate how many years there will be until the next Year of Celebration. Then he must pay to the man who bought the land the money that he would have earned by continuing to grow crops on that land for those years. <verse eid="LEV 25:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 25:28"/>But if the original owner does not have any money to buy the land that he sold, it will continue to belong to the man who bought it, until the next Year of Celebration. In that year it must be returned to its original owner, and he will be able to live on it again.<verse eid="LEV 25:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 25:29"/>‘If someone who lives in a city that has a wall around it sells a house there, during the next year he will be permitted to buy it from the man who bought it. <verse eid="LEV 25:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 25:30"/>If he does not buy it during that year, it will belong permanently to the man who bought it and to his descendants. It must not be returned to the original owner in the Year of Celebration. <verse eid="LEV 25:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 25:31"/>But houses that are in villages that do not have walls around them are considered to be as though they are in a field. So if someone sells one of those houses, he is permitted to buy it back at any time. And <char style="add">if he does not buy it</char>, it must be returned to him in the Year of Celebration.<verse eid="LEV 25:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 25:32"/>‘If any descendants of Levi sell their houses in the towns in which they live, they are permitted to buy them back at any time. <verse eid="LEV 25:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 25:33"/>And because the houses in their towns are on land that <char style="add">was given to them by</char> other Israelis, that land will become theirs again in the Year of Celebration <char style="add">if they do not buy it back before then</char>. <verse eid="LEV 25:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 25:34"/>But the pastureland near their towns must not be sold. It must belong to the original owners permanently/forever.<verse eid="LEV 25:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 25:35"/>‘If one of your fellow Israelis becomes poor and is unable to buy what he needs [IDM], others of you must help him like you would help a foreigner who is living among you [DOU] temporarily. <verse eid="LEV 25:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 25:36"/><char style="add">If you lend money to him</char>, do not charge any kind of interest [DOU]. Instead, <char style="add">show by what you do that you</char> revere me, your God, and help that man, in order that he will be able to continue to live among you. <verse eid="LEV 25:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 25:37"/>If you lend him money, do not charge interest; and if you sell food to him, <char style="add">charge him only what you paid for it</char>; do not get a profit from it. <verse eid="LEV 25:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 25:38"/><char style="add">Do not forget that</char> I am Yahweh your God, who brought you out of Egypt to be your God and to give you the land of Canaan, <char style="add">and I did not charge you for doing that</char>.<verse eid="LEV 25:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 25:39"/>‘If one of your fellow Israelis becomes poor and sells himself to you, do not force him to work like a slave. <verse eid="LEV 25:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="LEV 25:40"/>Treat him like you treat workers that you hire or like someone who is living on your land temporarily. But he must work for you <char style="add">only</char> until the Year of Celebration. <verse eid="LEV 25:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="LEV 25:41"/>During that year, you must free him, and he will go back to his family and to the property that his ancestors owned. <verse eid="LEV 25:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 25:42"/><char style="add">It is as though</char> you Israelis are my slaves/servants, whom I <char style="add">freed from being slaves</char> in Egypt. So none of you should be sold to become slaves. <verse eid="LEV 25:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 25:43"/>And do not treat the Israelis whom you buy cruelly; instead, revere me, your God.<verse eid="LEV 25:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 25:44"/>‘If you want to have slaves, you are permitted to buy them from nearby countries. <verse eid="LEV 25:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 25:45"/>You are also permitted to buy some of the foreigners who are living among you, and members of their clans that were born in your country. Then you will own them. <verse eid="LEV 25:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 25:46"/>They will be your slaves for the remaining years of your life, and after you die, it is permitted for your children to own them. But you must not act in brutal ways toward your fellow Israelis.<verse eid="LEV 25:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="LEV 25:47"/>‘If a foreigner who is living among you [DOU] becomes rich, and if one of your fellow Israelis becomes poor and sells himself to that foreigner or to a member of his clan/family, <verse eid="LEV 25:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="LEV 25:48"/>it is permitted for someone to pay for him to be freed. It is permitted for one of his relatives to pay for him to be released: <verse eid="LEV 25:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="LEV 25:49"/>An uncle or a cousin or another relative in his clan may pay for him to be released. Or, if he prospers <char style="add">and gets enough money</char>, he is permitted to pay for his own release. <verse eid="LEV 25:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="LEV 25:50"/>The man who wants to pay for his own release must count the number of years until the next Year of Celebration. The price he pays to the man who bought him will depend on the pay that would be given to a hired worker for that number of years. <verse eid="LEV 25:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="LEV 25:51"/>If there are a lot of years that remain until the Year of Celebration, he must pay for his release a larger amount of the money. <verse eid="LEV 25:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="LEV 25:52"/>If there are only a few years that remain until the Year of Celebration, he must pay a smaller amount to be released. <verse eid="LEV 25:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="LEV 25:53"/>During the years that he is working for the man who bought him, the man who bought him must treat him like he would treat a hired worker, and all of you must make sure that his owner does not treat him cruelly.<verse eid="LEV 25:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="LEV 25:54"/>‘And even if a fellow Israeli who has sold himself to a rich man is not able to pay for himself to be freed by any of these ways, he and his children must be freed in the Year of Celebration, <verse eid="LEV 25:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="LEV 25:55"/>because <char style="add">it is as though</char> you Israelis are my slaves/servants, whom I, Yahweh your God, freed from <char style="add">being slaves in</char> Egypt.’”<verse eid="LEV 25:55"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="LEV 26"/>
  <para style="s1">Promised blessings for obeying Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 26:1"/>
    <char style="add">Yahweh also said this to Moses/me on Sinai Mountain</char>: “Do not make idols or set up statues of false gods or sacred stones <char style="add">to worship other gods</char>. And do not put on your property a stone that has been shaped <char style="add">to resemble a false god</char> and bow down to <char style="add">worship</char> it. <char style="add">You must worship only</char> me, Yahweh, your God.<verse eid="LEV 26:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 26:2"/>“Honor the Sabbath days and revere my Sacred Tent, because I, Yahweh, <char style="add">live there</char>.<verse eid="LEV 26:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 26:3"/>“If you carefully obey all my commands [DOU], <verse eid="LEV 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 26:4"/>I will send rain for you at the proper/right times, in order that crops will grow on your land and there will be plenty of fruit on your trees. <verse eid="LEV 26:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 26:5"/>You will continue <char style="add">harvesting and</char> threshing <char style="add">grain</char> until it is time to harvest grapes, and you will continue to harvest grapes until it is time to start planting <char style="add">things in the following year</char>. And you will have all the food that you want to eat, and you will live safely in your land.<verse eid="LEV 26:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 26:6"/>“<char style="add">If you obey all my laws</char>, there will be peace in your country, and when you lie down <char style="add">to sleep</char>, nothing will cause you to be afraid. I will get rid of the dangerous animals in your country, and there will no wars [MTY] in your country. <verse eid="LEV 26:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 26:7"/>You will pursue your enemies and kill them with your swords: <verse eid="LEV 26:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 26:8"/>Five of you will pursue 100 of them, and 100 of you will pursue 1,000 of them and kill them with your swords.<verse eid="LEV 26:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 26:9"/>“<char style="add">If you obey all my laws</char>, I will bless you and cause you to have many children [DOU]. And I will do what I said that I would do in the agreement that I made with you. <verse eid="LEV 26:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 26:10"/>When you are still eating food from the harvest from the previous year, it will be necessary for you to throw away some of it to make space for the new harvest. <verse eid="LEV 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 26:11"/>I will live among you in my Sacred Tent, and I will never reject you. <verse eid="LEV 26:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 26:12"/>I will walk among you and continue to be your God, and you will continue to be my people. <verse eid="LEV 26:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 26:13"/>I am Yahweh your God, the one who brought you out of Egypt in order that you would no longer be slaves of the people of Egypt. <char style="add">When you were there, you were treated as though you were animals that worked for the people of Egypt, but</char> [MET] I broke the bars of the ◄yokes/frames that were put around your necks► and enabled you to walk with your heads up.”<verse eid="LEV 26:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Threatened punishments for disobeying Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 26:14"/>“But if you will not heed me and obey all these commands, <verse eid="LEV 26:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 26:15"/>and if you reject [DOU] my decrees and laws, and do not do [DOU] what I commanded you to do in the agreement that I made with you, <verse eid="LEV 26:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 26:16"/>these are the things that I will do to you: I will suddenly cause there to be disasters that will ruin you. You will have diseases that cannot be cured, and fevers that will cause you to become blind and will slowly kill you. It will be useless for you to plant seeds, because your enemies will eat the crops that grow. <verse eid="LEV 26:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 26:17"/>I will reject/abandon you [IDM], with the result that you will be defeated by your enemies. Then those who hate you will rule you, and <char style="add">you will be so terrified that</char> you will run away even when no one is pursuing you.<verse eid="LEV 26:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 26:18"/>“If you still will not heed me after all those things happen to you, I will continue to punish you again and again for the sins that you have committed. <verse eid="LEV 26:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 26:19"/>I will cause you to no longer be stubborn and proud; I will cause <char style="add">no rain to fall; it will be as though</char> [MET] the sky is made of iron; and the ground will be <char style="add">as hard as</char> brass [MET]. <verse eid="LEV 26:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 26:20"/>You will uselessly work very hard <char style="add">to plant seeds</char>, because crops will not grow in the hard soil in your fields, and fruit will not grow on your trees.<verse eid="LEV 26:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 26:21"/>“If you continue to oppose me and refuse to heed me, I will cause you to experience disasters again and again, like you deserve to experience because of your sins. <verse eid="LEV 26:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 26:22"/>I will send wild animals to attack you, and they will kill your little children and destroy your cattle. There will be very few of you who will remain alive, with the result that there will be very few [HYP] people walking on the roads in your country.<verse eid="LEV 26:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 26:23"/>“When you experience those things that I do to punish you, if you still do not pay attention to me, and if you continue to oppose me, <verse eid="LEV 26:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 26:24"/>I myself will oppose you, and I will punish you for your sins again and again. <verse eid="LEV 26:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 26:25"/>I will send <char style="add">foreign </char>armies [MTY] to punish you for not doing the things that I commanded you to do in the agreement that I made with you. If you <char style="add">try to escape from your enemies by</char> shutting yourselves in your cities <char style="add">that have walls around them</char>, I will cause you to experience plagues, and I will allow your enemies to capture [IDM] you. <verse eid="LEV 26:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 26:26"/>When I cut off your food supply, there will be very little flour with which to make bread. As a result, ten women will be able to bake all their bread in <char style="add">only</char> one oven. <char style="add">When the bread is baked</char>, each woman will divide it <char style="add">among the members of her family, but there will be very little for each one</char>, and when they have eaten all of it, they will still be hungry.<verse eid="LEV 26:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 26:27"/>“After all those things happen, if you still do not heed me, if you still oppose me, <verse eid="LEV 26:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 26:28"/>I will be very angry with you, and I will oppose you, and I myself will punish you for your sins again and again. <verse eid="LEV 26:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 26:29"/><char style="add">You will be extremely hungry, with the result that</char> you will <char style="add">kill</char> your sons and daughters and eat their flesh. <verse eid="LEV 26:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 26:30"/>I will cause the shrines <char style="add">where you worship idols</char> on hilltops to be destroyed. I will smash the altars where you burn incense <char style="add">to worship your gods</char>, and I will cause your corpses to be piled on the lifeless statues of your gods. And I will detest you. <verse eid="LEV 26:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 26:31"/>I will cause your cities to become heaps of ruins, and I will cause the buildings that are dedicated to the worship of your gods to be smashed. And I will not be pleased at all with the aroma of your offerings <char style="add">that are burned on the altar</char>. <verse eid="LEV 26:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 26:32"/>I will completely ruin your country, with the result that even your enemies who capture it will be shocked/appalled <char style="add">when they see it</char>. <verse eid="LEV 26:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 26:33"/>I will enable <char style="add">your enemies to kill you with</char> their swords, and I will cause the rest of you to be scattered among other nations. Your country will be ruined and your cities will become ruins. <verse eid="LEV 26:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 26:34"/>After that happens, as long as you are living in your enemies’ countries, your land will be allowed to rest, like you should have allowed it to rest every seven years. <verse eid="LEV 26:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="LEV 26:35"/>All the time that your land is desolate, it will be able to rest, like you did not enable it to rest during all the years that you lived there.<verse eid="LEV 26:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="LEV 26:36"/>“As for you people who will remain alive in the countries to which your enemies <char style="add">will have taken you</char>, I will cause you to become so afraid that when you hear the sound of leaves being blown by the wind, you will run away. You will run like [SIM] you are running from <char style="add">a man carrying</char> a sword, and you will fall down, even though no one is pursuing you. <verse eid="LEV 26:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="LEV 26:37"/>You will stumble over each other. So you will not be able to stand and fight your enemies. <verse eid="LEV 26:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="LEV 26:38"/>Many of you will die in the countries that belong to your enemies [DOU]. <verse eid="LEV 26:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="LEV 26:39"/>And those of you who remain alive will slowly die and rot in the countries of your enemies because of your sins and because of the sins of your ancestors.<verse eid="LEV 26:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40-41" style="v" sid="LEV 26:40-41"/>“But your descendants must confess their sins and the sins that their ancestors committed. Their ancestors acted unfaithfully toward me and were hostile to me, with the result that I forced them to go to the countries that belonged to their enemies. But when your descendants humble themselves [SYN] and stop being very stubborn [IDM] and accept being punished for their sins, <verse eid="LEV 26:40-41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="LEV 26:42"/>I will remember the agreement that I made with <char style="add">your ancestors</char> Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, and <char style="add">what I promised them about </char> this land. <verse eid="LEV 26:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="LEV 26:43"/>But <char style="add">before that happens</char>, you will be forced to leave your land, with the result that the land will be able to rest while it is desolate and while the people are being punished for rejecting my laws and hating my decrees [DOU]. <verse eid="LEV 26:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="LEV 26:44"/>But when that happens, I will still not reject them or hate them and destroy them completely. I will not cancel the agreement that I made with them; for I am still Yahweh their God. <verse eid="LEV 26:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="LEV 26:45"/>I will ◄remember/never forget► the agreement that I made with your ancestors when I brought them out of Egypt, in order that the people of all nations will know that I, Yahweh, <char style="add">will continue to</char> be your God.”<verse eid="LEV 26:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="LEV 26:46"/>Those are the decrees, the laws, and the regulations [DOU] that Yahweh established on Sinai Mountain between himself and the Israeli people by <char style="add">giving them to</char> Moses/me <char style="add">to tell to them</char>.<verse eid="LEV 26:46"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="LEV 27"/>
  <para style="s1">Making promises about gifts to Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="LEV 27:1"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="LEV 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="LEV 27:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people <char style="add">that this is what I am saying to them</char>: If anyone solemnly promises to dedicate another person to <char style="add">work solely</char> for me, the person who is dedicated to me is allowed to be free from having to do that by someone paying <char style="add">to the priest</char> a fixed amount of money. The money that is given must be calculated by comparing it with the official pieces of silver in the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="LEV 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="LEV 27:3"/><char style="add">These are the amounts that must be paid</char>:</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="LEV 27:3">50 pieces of silver for men who are between 20 and 60 years old,<verse eid="LEV 27:3"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="LEV 27:4"/>30 pieces of silver for adult women <char style="add">who are between 20 and 60 years old</char>,<verse eid="LEV 27:4"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="LEV 27:5"/>20 pieces of silver for young men who are between five and 20 years old,</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="LEV 27:5">ten pieces of silver for young women who are between five and 20 years old,<verse eid="LEV 27:5"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="LEV 27:6"/>five pieces of silver for boys who are between one month and five years old,</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="LEV 27:6">three pieces of silver for girls who are between one month and five years old,<verse eid="LEV 27:6"/></para>
  <para style="li2">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="LEV 27:7"/>15 pieces of silver for men who are more than 60 years old,</para>
  <para style="li2" vid="LEV 27:7">ten pieces of silver for women who are more than 60 years old.<verse eid="LEV 27:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="LEV 27:8"/>‘If anyone who has made such a solemn promise is very poor and unable to pay, to free that person from doing what he had promised, he must take that person to the priest. The priest will set the price <char style="add">for freeing him</char> to be what the person who made that solemn promise is able to pay.<verse eid="LEV 27:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="LEV 27:9"/>‘If someone solemnly promises to give an animal that is acceptable to be an offering to me, that animal becomes sacred <char style="add">and belongs to me</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="LEV 27:10"/>The person who promised to give it must not give another animal instead of the one that he promised; he must not substitute a bad animal for a good one or even a better one than the one offered. If he would substitute one animal for the other, both animals would belong to me. <verse eid="LEV 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="LEV 27:11"/>If the animal that he wishes to dedicate to me is a kind that is unacceptable to be an offering to me, he must take that animal to the priest. <verse eid="LEV 27:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="LEV 27:12"/>The priest will then decide what its value is, according to the animal’s good and bad points. Whatever value the priests sets will be the value of the animal, <char style="add">and that is the price that the priest must pay for the animal</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="LEV 27:13"/>If the man who gave the animal later decides that he wants to buy it back, he must pay <char style="add">to the priest</char> that price plus an additional 20 percent.<verse eid="LEV 27:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="LEV 27:14"/>‘<char style="add">Similarly</char>, if someone dedicates his house to be a sacred gift to belong to me, the priest will decide how much it is worth, which will depend on whether the house is in good condition. Whatever the priest says that it is worth, that will be its value <char style="add">and that is the price that the priest must pay for it</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="LEV 27:15"/>If the man who dedicated his house to me later wants to buy it back, he must pay that price plus an additional 20 percent, and then the house will belong to him again.<verse eid="LEV 27:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="LEV 27:16"/>‘If someone dedicates to me some of the property that belongs to him and his family, its value will be determined by the number of bushels of seed that will be needed to plant seeds on that land: Its value will be ten pieces of silver for each bushel of seed. <verse eid="LEV 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="LEV 27:17"/>If he dedicates the land during the Year of Celebration, its full value will be that amount. <verse eid="LEV 27:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="LEV 27:18"/>But if he dedicates the field after the Year of Celebration, the priest will count the number of years until the next Year of Celebration, and if there are not many years that remain, the price will be much lower <char style="add">than the full price</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="LEV 27:19"/>If the person who dedicated the field later wants to buy it back, he must pay <char style="add">to the priest</char> the price that the priest says it is worth, plus an added one-fifth, and then the field will belong to that man again. <verse eid="LEV 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="LEV 27:20"/>However, if he does not buy it back, or if it has been sold (OR, the priest has sold it) to someone else, that person will never be permitted to buy it back again. <verse eid="LEV 27:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="LEV 27:21"/>In the Year of Celebration, it will become sacred again, and it will be given to the priest.<verse eid="LEV 27:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="LEV 27:22"/>‘If someone dedicates to me some land that he has bought, land which is not part of the land that his family has always owned, <verse eid="LEV 27:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="LEV 27:23"/>the priest will count the number of years until the next Year of Celebration to determine how much it is worth, and the man must pay that amount to the priest on that day, <char style="add">and then that land will belong to that man again</char>. <verse eid="LEV 27:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="LEV 27:24"/>But in the Year of Celebration, the land will again be owned by the person from whom he bought it, the person whose family had always owned that land. <verse eid="LEV 27:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="LEV 27:25"/>All the silver that is paid must be compared with the official pieces of silver in the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="LEV 27:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="LEV 27:26"/>‘No one is permitted to dedicate to me the firstborn of any cow or sheep, because the firstborn already belongs to me [DOU]. <verse eid="LEV 27:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="LEV 27:27"/>If someone gives to me a kind of animal that is not acceptable to me, that person may later buy it back by paying what it is worth plus an additional 20 percent of its value. If he does not buy it back, it must be sold (OR, the priest must sell it) for its standard price.<verse eid="LEV 27:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="LEV 27:28"/>‘However, no slave or animal or family land that someone owns can be sold or bought back after it has been dedicated to me <char style="add">and no price has been paid for it</char>. That kind of gift belongs to me permanently/forever.<verse eid="LEV 27:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="LEV 27:29"/>‘No person who has <char style="add">done something that I consider to be very wicked</char> is permitted to be freed <char style="add">from being punished</char>; that person must surely be executed.<verse eid="LEV 27:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="LEV 27:30"/>‘One tenth of all the crops and grain or fruit that is produced on anyone’s land is sacred and belongs to me. <verse eid="LEV 27:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="LEV 27:31"/>If anyone wants to buy back any of that tenth, he must pay <char style="add">to the priest</char> what it is worth plus an additional 20 percent. <verse eid="LEV 27:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="LEV 27:32"/>One of every ten domestic animals belongs to me. When a shepherd counts his animals [MTY] <char style="add">to decide which ones he will give to me</char>, he must mark every tenth one as belonging to me. <verse eid="LEV 27:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="LEV 27:33"/>When he does that, he must not pick out the good ones for himself or leave the bad ones, or substitute bad ones for good ones. If he substitutes one animal for another, both animals will belong to me, and he will not be permitted to buy them back (OR, the shepherd cannot buy them back).’ ”<verse eid="LEV 27:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="LEV 27:34"/>Those are the commands that Yahweh gave to Moses/me on Sinai Mountain <char style="add">to tell to the people</char>.<verse eid="LEV 27:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="LEV 27"/>
</usx>
