<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="MRK" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">MARK</para>
  <para style="toc1">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc2">Mark</para>
  <para style="toc3">Mrk</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book is the Gospel that Mark wrote. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Mark</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="MRK 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Mark 1:1-8</para>
  <para style="s1">The good message about Jesus the Messiah, the Son of God, began when John, the Baptizer, as was prophesied long ago, announced the coming of Jesus.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-2" style="v" sid="MRK 1:1-2"/>◄<char style="add">This is/I want to tell you</char>► the good message about Jesus Christ, the Son of God (OR, the man who was also God). <char style="add">What I want to tell you</char> begins just like the prophet Isaiah <char style="add">said it would begin, when</char> he wrote <char style="add">these words that God said to Jesus:</char></para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="MRK 1:1-2">Listen! I am sending my messenger ahead of you. He will prepare <char style="add">people for</char> your <char style="add">coming</char>. <verse eid="MRK 1:1-2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 1:3"/>He will call out to people <char style="add">who pass by where he is</char> in the desolate area, “As people improve and straighten out pathways <char style="add">before an important official arrives</char> [MET], make <char style="add">yourselves</char> ready [DOU] <char style="add">in order that you will be prepared when</char> the Lord <char style="add">comes</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 1:4"/>
    <char style="add">The messenger that Isaiah predicted was</char> John. <char style="add">People called him</char> ‘The Baptizer’. In the desolate area near the Jordan River he kept telling people, “If you want God to forgive you for having sinned, you must turn away from your sinful behavior <char style="add">before you ask me to</char> baptize <char style="add">you</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 1:5"/>A great number [HYP] of people who lived in Jerusalem <char style="add">city</char> and <char style="add">elsewhere</char> in the Judea <char style="add">district</char> were going out to where John was. There, <char style="add">after hearing John’s message</char>, they <char style="add">responded by</char> confessing the sinful things <char style="add">that they had done</char>. Then they were being baptized by John {John was baptizing them} in the Jordan River. <verse eid="MRK 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 1:6"/>John wore <char style="add">rough</char> clothes made of camel’s hair. And <char style="add">as the prophet Elijah had done</char>, he wore a leather belt around his waist; and what he ate was <char style="add">only</char> grasshoppers and honey <char style="add">that he found</char> in that desolate area. <verse eid="MRK 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 1:7"/>He was preaching, “Very shortly a man will come who is very great. I <char style="add">am nothing compared to him. Because he is so superior to me</char>, I am not even worthy to <char style="add">serve him like a slave</char> by stooping down and untying his sandals. <verse eid="MRK 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 1:8"/>I used <char style="add">only</char> water when I baptized you <char style="add">because you said that you wanted to change your lives</char>, but he will put his Holy Spirit <char style="add">within</char> you <char style="add">to truly change your lives</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God showed Jesus to be the Son of God by God’s Spirit descending upon him; by Himself, God the Father, declaring it; by Satan testing him; and by the angels taking care of him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:9-13">Mark 1:9-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 1:9"/>During that time <char style="add">when John was preaching</char>, Jesus came from Nazareth <char style="add">town</char>, which is in Galilee <char style="add">district</char>. He went to <char style="add">where John was preaching</char> and he was baptized by John {John baptized him} in the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. <verse eid="MRK 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 1:10"/>Immediately after <char style="add">Jesus</char> came up out of the water, he saw heaven opened up <char style="add">and he saw</char> the Spirit <char style="add">of God</char> descending on himself. He came in the form of a dove. <verse eid="MRK 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 1:11"/>And <char style="add">God</char> [MTY] spoke to him from heaven saying, “You are my Son, whom I love dearly. I am very pleased with you.” <verse eid="MRK 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 1:12"/>◄Then/Right away► the Spirit <char style="add">of God</char> sent Jesus into the desolate area. <verse eid="MRK 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 1:13"/>He was there for 40 days. During that time, he was tempted by Satan {Satan tempted him}. There were wild animals <char style="add">there</char> also. But angels took care of him.<verse eid="MRK 1:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After John was arrested, Jesus came and preached the good message that came from God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:14-15">Mark 1:14-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 1:14"/>Later, after John was put in prison {after <char style="add">soldiers</char> put John in prison} <char style="add">because he had rebuked the governor Herod Antipas for his sins</char>, Jesus went to Galilee <char style="add">district</char>. There he was preaching the good message <char style="add">that came</char> from God. <verse eid="MRK 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 1:15"/>He was repeatedly saying, “Now is the time when God will begin to rule people’s lives <char style="add">in a new way</char>. <char style="add">So</char> turn away from your sinful behavior! Believe the good message <char style="add">in order</char> ◄<char style="add">to belong to him/to become those whose lives he will rule</char>►!”<verse eid="MRK 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus showed his authority when he summoned four men, and they immediately went with him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:16-20">Mark 1:16-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 1:16"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char>, while Jesus was walking along by Galilee Lake, he saw <char style="add">two men</char>, Simon and Simon’s <char style="add">younger</char> brother, Andrew. They were casting their <char style="add">fishing</char> net into the lake. They <char style="add">earned money by</char> catching <char style="add">and selling</char> fish. <verse eid="MRK 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 1:17"/>Then Jesus said to them, “<char style="add">Just like you have been</char> gathering fish, come with me and I will <char style="add">teach</char> you how to <char style="add">gather people to become my disciples</char>” [MET]. <verse eid="MRK 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 1:18"/>Immediately they abandoned <char style="add">the work that they were doing with</char> their nets, and they went with him. <verse eid="MRK 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 1:19"/>After they had gone on a little further, Jesus saw <char style="add">two other men</char>, James and James’ <char style="add">younger</char> brother, John. They were the sons of <char style="add">a man named</char> Zebedee. They were both in a boat mending <char style="add">fishing</char> nets. <verse eid="MRK 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 1:20"/>As soon as Jesus saw them, he told them that <char style="add">they should leave their work and to come with him</char>. So they left their father, <char style="add">who remained</char> in the boat with the hired servants, and they went away with Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 1:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">People were amazed as a result of Jesus expelling a demon from a man.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:21-28">Mark 1:21-28</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 1:21"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char> Jesus <char style="add">and those disciples</char> arrived at Capernaum <char style="add">town</char>. On the next ◄Sabbath/Jewish rest day►, after Jesus had entered ◄the synagogue/the Jewish meeting place►, he began teaching <char style="add">the people who had gathered there</char>. <verse eid="MRK 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 1:22"/>They were continually amazed at the way he taught. <char style="add">He did</char> not <char style="add">just teach what others had taught</char>, like the men who teach the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws did. <char style="add">They habitually just repeated what other people had taught</char>. Instead, he taught with <char style="add">his own</char> authority. <verse eid="MRK 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 1:23"/>Suddenly, <char style="add">while he was teaching</char>, a man <char style="add">appeared</char> in their worship place who had an evil spirit in him, and he shouted, <verse eid="MRK 1:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 1:24"/>“Jesus, from Nazareth <char style="add">town, since</char> we <char style="add">evil spirits</char> have nothing in common with you, ◄<char style="add">do not interfere with us</char>!/what do you want with us <char style="add">evil spirits</char>?► [RHQ] ◄Do not destroy us <char style="add">now</char>!/Have you come to destroy us <char style="add">now</char>?► [RHQ] I know who you are. I know that you are the holy one <char style="add">who has come</char> from God!” <verse eid="MRK 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 1:25"/>Jesus rebuked <char style="add">the evil spirit</char>, saying, “Be quiet! And come out <char style="add">of the man</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 1:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 1:26"/>The evil spirit shook the man hard. He screamed loudly, and then he came out of the man <char style="add">and left</char>. <verse eid="MRK 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 1:27"/>All <char style="add">the people who were there</char> were amazed. As a result, they discussed this among themselves, <char style="add">exclaiming</char>, “◄This is <char style="add">amazing</char>!/What is this?► [RHQ] Not only does he teach in a new and authoritative way, but also the evil spirits obey him <char style="add">when</char> he commands <char style="add">them</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 1:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 1:28"/>The people very soon told <char style="add">many others</char> throughout the whole Galilee district what Jesus <char style="add">had done</char>.<verse eid="MRK 1:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus healed Simon’s mother-in-law.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:29-31">Mark 1:29-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 1:29"/>After they left ◄the synagogue/the Jewish meeting place►, <char style="add">Jesus, Simon and Andrew</char>, along with James and John went directly to Simon and Andrew’s house. <verse eid="MRK 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 1:30"/>Simon’s mother-in-law was lying in bed because she had a <char style="add">high</char> fever. Right away someone told Jesus about her <char style="add">being sick</char>. <verse eid="MRK 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 1:31"/>He went to her, and helped her up by taking hold of her hand. She recovered <char style="add">at once</char> from the fever, and then she <char style="add">got up and</char> served them <char style="add">some food</char>.<verse eid="MRK 1:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus healed many people and expelled many evil spirits from people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:32-34">Mark 1:32-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 1:32"/>That evening, after the sun had gone down <char style="add">and restrictions about travel on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day</char>► <char style="add">were ended</char>, some people brought to Jesus many people who were sick and others whose lives evil spirits were controlling. <verse eid="MRK 1:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 1:33"/><char style="add">It seemed as though</char> everyone [HYP, MTY] <char style="add">who lived in</char> the town was gathered at the doorway <char style="add">of Simon’s house</char>. <verse eid="MRK 1:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 1:34"/>Jesus healed many people who were ill with various diseases. He also expelled many demons <char style="add">from people</char>. He did not allow the demons to tell people <char style="add">about him</char>, because they knew that he <char style="add">had come from God, and for various reasons he did not want everyone to know that yet</char>.<verse eid="MRK 1:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus traveled throughout Galilee, preaching and expelling evil spirits from people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:35-39">Mark 1:35-39</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 1:35"/>Jesus got up very early <char style="add">the next morning</char> while it was still dark. He left <char style="add">the house</char> and went away <char style="add">from the town</char> to a place where there were no people. Then he prayed there. <verse eid="MRK 1:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 1:36"/>Simon and his companions searched for him. When they found him, <char style="add">wanting him to go back to town to help other people</char>, they said to him, <verse eid="MRK 1:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 1:37"/>“<char style="add">Come back to the town with us, because</char> many [HYP] people <char style="add">in Capernaum</char> are looking for you!” <verse eid="MRK 1:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 1:38"/>He said to them, “<char style="add">No</char>, let’s go on to the neighboring towns in order that I can preach there also, because the reason that I came <char style="add">into the world</char> was to <char style="add">preach to people</char> in many places!” <verse eid="MRK 1:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 1:39"/>So they went throughout Galilee <char style="add">district. As they did so, each ◄Sabbath/Jewish rest day</char>► he preached in ◄synagogues/Jewish meeting places►. He was also expelling evil spirits <char style="add">from people</char>.<verse eid="MRK 1:39"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus cured a leper and arranged for him to be able to associate with people again.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 1:40-45">Mark 1:40-45</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 1:40"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char> a man who had <char style="add">a bad skin disease called</char> leprosy came to Jesus. He knelt down in front of Jesus and then he pleaded with him saying, “<char style="add">Please heal me, because I know</char> you are able to heal me if you want to!” <verse eid="MRK 1:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 1:41"/>Jesus felt very sorry for him. <char style="add">So he ignored the religious laws about coming close to people who had that disease</char>. He reached out his hand and touched the man. Then he said to him, “Since I am willing <char style="add">to heal you</char>, be healed {I heal you} <char style="add">now</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 1:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 1:42"/>Immediately the man was healed! He was no longer a leper! <verse eid="MRK 1:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 1:43"/>Jesus spoke sternly to him before he sent him away. <verse eid="MRK 1:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 1:44"/>What Jesus said was, “Go to a local priest and show yourself to him <char style="add">in order that he may examine you and verify that you are healed</char>. Then, <char style="add">after the priest tells the local people</char>, they will know <char style="add">that you have been healed, and you will be able to associate with them again</char>. Make sure that you do not tell others <char style="add">about what happened</char> Then go to <char style="add">Jerusalem and take to the priest what Moses commanded that people who have been healed from leprosy should offer, in order that he</char> may offer it <char style="add">as a sacrifice to God</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 1:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 1:45"/>The man went <char style="add">and presented himself to the priest. But then</char> he began to tell many people about <char style="add">how Jesus had healed him</char> [DOU]. As a result, Jesus was no longer able to enter any town publicly <char style="add">because the crowds would surround him</char>. Instead, he remained outside <char style="add">the towns</char> in places <char style="add">where no people lived</char>. But people kept coming to him from all over that region.<verse eid="MRK 1:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="MRK 2"/>
  <para style="s1">By healing a paralyzed man Jesus demonstrated his authority to forgive sins as well as to heal.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 2:1-12">Mark 2:1-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 2:1"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus and his disciples</char> returned to Capernaum <char style="add">town</char>. A few days later, because it was {people} heard that Jesus was in <char style="add">his</char> house, <verse eid="MRK 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 2:2"/>many people gathered there. As a result, <char style="add">after the people filled the house</char>, there was no longer space to stand <char style="add">in the house or outside</char> around the doorway. Jesus preached <char style="add">God’s</char> message to them. <verse eid="MRK 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 2:3"/>Some people came to the house bringing to Jesus a man who was paralyzed. He was carried by four men {Four men carried <char style="add">him</char>} <char style="add">on a sleeping pad</char>. <verse eid="MRK 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 2:4"/>They were not able to bring the man to Jesus because there was a crowd there. So they <char style="add">went up the steps to the flat roof and</char> removed <char style="add">some of</char> the tiles <char style="add">above</char> where Jesus was. Then, after they made a <char style="add">big</char> hole in the roof, they lowered <char style="add">by ropes</char> the sleeping pad on which the paralyzed man lay. They lowered <char style="add">it through the hole, down in front of Jesus</char>. <verse eid="MRK 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 2:5"/>After Jesus perceived that the men believed <char style="add">that he could heal this man</char>, he said to the paralyzed man, “My friend, <char style="add">I</char> forgive your sins!” <verse eid="MRK 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 2:6"/>There were some men who taught <char style="add">the Jewish</char> laws sitting there. They started thinking like this: <verse eid="MRK 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 2:7"/>“◄Who does this man think he is, talking like that/This man shouldn’t talk like that!► [RHQ]? ◄He is insulting God!/Does he think he is God?► [RHQ] ◄No person can forgive sins!/Who can forgive sins?► [RHQ] Only God can forgive sins!” <verse eid="MRK 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 2:8"/>Jesus sensed that they were deliberating like that within themselves. So he said to them, “◄You should not question within yourselves <char style="add">whether I have the right to forgive this man’s sins</char>!/Why do you question <char style="add">whether I have the right to forgive this man’s sins</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 2:9"/>It is <char style="add">not risky</char> [RHQ] for someone to tell the man who is paralyzed, ‘Your sins are forgiven {<char style="add">I</char> forgive your sins},’ <char style="add">because no one can prove that it has happened</char>. But no one would say to him, ‘Get up, pick up your stretcher, and then walk away’, <char style="add">unless he really had the power to heal him, because people can easily see whether it happens or not</char>. <verse eid="MRK 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 2:10"/>So I <char style="add">will do something</char> in order that you may know that <char style="add">God</char> has authorized me, the one who came from heaven, to forgive sins on earth <char style="add">as well as to heal people</char>.” Then he said to the paralyzed man, <verse eid="MRK 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 2:11"/>“To you I say, ‘Get up! Pick up your sleeping pad! And then go home!’” <verse eid="MRK 2:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 2:12"/><note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">2:12 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">COL 5:1</char></note> The man stood up immediately! He picked up the sleeping pad, and then he went away, while all the people <char style="add">there</char> were watching. They were all amazed, and they praised God and said, “We have never before seen anything like <char style="add">what happened</char> just now!”<verse eid="MRK 2:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus invited Levi to be his disciple and refuted those who objected to his associating with such people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 2:13-17">Mark 2:13-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 2:13"/>Jesus left <char style="add">Capernaum town again and walked with his disciples</char> alongside <char style="add">Galilee</char> lake. A large crowd came to him. Then he taught them. <verse eid="MRK 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 2:14"/>As he walked on further, he saw a man named Levi, whose other name was Matthew, and whose father’s name was Alpheus. He was sitting in his office where he collected taxes <char style="add">for the Roman government</char>. Jesus said to him, “Come with me <char style="add">and become my disciple</char>!” So he got up and went with Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 2:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 2:15"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char>, Jesus was eating a meal in Levi’s house. Many men who collected taxes and <char style="add">other</char> people who were <char style="add">considered to be</char> sinning regularly were eating with Jesus and his disciples. <char style="add">This was not surprising</char>, for there were many people like this who were going <char style="add">everywhere</char> with Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 2:16"/>The <char style="add">men who taught the Jewish</char> laws <char style="add">who were there</char> and who were members of the Pharisee <char style="add">sect</char> saw that Jesus was eating with men who collected taxes and <char style="add">others who were considered</char> {<char style="add">whom they considered</char>} <char style="add">to be</char> sinners. So they said to his disciples, “◄It is disgusting that he eats with <char style="add">such disgusting</char> men as those who collect taxes, and with <char style="add">other</char> sinners!/Why is it that he eats with <char style="add">such disgusting</char> men as those who collect taxes, and with <char style="add">other</char> sinners?►” [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 2:17"/>After Jesus heard <char style="add">what they were saying</char>, he said to the men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws, “People who <char style="add">consider that they</char> are well do not seek a doctor. On the contrary, it is those who are sick <char style="add">who seek a doctor</char> [MET]!” <char style="add">This he said to indicate that it was those who knew that they had sinned who were coming to him in order that he might help them spiritually</char>. And he said, “I did not come to invite people <char style="add">who think that</char> [IRO] they are righteous <char style="add">to come to me and turn from their sinful behavior</char>. On the contrary, I came <char style="add">from heaven to invite</char> people who <char style="add">know that they</char> are sinners, <char style="add">in order that they might turn from their sins and come to me</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told them it was inappropriate for his disciples to show sorrow by fasting while he was with them, and that requiring people to perform rituals like fasting was inconsistent with the new way of life he was bringing.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 2:18-22">Mark 2:18-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 2:18"/>The disciples of John <char style="add">the Baptizer</char> and some men who belonged to the Pharisee <char style="add">sect</char> used to abstain from food <char style="add">to show that they wanted to please God</char>. One day, some people came <char style="add">to Jesus</char> and asked him <char style="add">critically</char>, “The disciples of John and the Pharisees ◄fast/abstain from food► <char style="add">from time to time</char>, but your disciples do not. <char style="add">We think they should abstain from food also. What do you say about that</char> [RHQ]?” <verse eid="MRK 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 2:19"/><char style="add">Jesus wanted them to understand that it was not appropriate for his disciples to show sorrow by abstaining from food while he was still with them</char>. So he said to them, “When a man is marrying a woman, his friends will certainly not abstain from food while he is still with them, will they [RHQ]? No. During the time that he is with them, they will not abstain from food <char style="add">because they are happy together</char>. <verse eid="MRK 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 2:20"/>But some day, he will be taken away {his <char style="add">enemies</char> will take him away} from them. Then, in those days, they will abstain from food, <char style="add">because they will be sad</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 2:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 2:21"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus wanted to show that those who desire to live in accordance with his new message should not try to continue to obey the old religious traditions like fasting. So he also said to them</char>, “People do not sew a patch of unshrunken cloth on an old garment <char style="add">in order to mend a hole</char>. If they did that, <char style="add">when they washed the garment, the patch would shrink</char> and the new <char style="add">piece of cloth</char> would tear off more of the old cloth. As a result, the hole would become bigger! <verse eid="MRK 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 2:22"/><char style="add">Similarly</char>, people do not put newly <char style="add">squeezed</char> grape juice into old skin bags <char style="add">to store it</char>. If they did that, that juice will burst the skin bags <char style="add">because they would not stretch when the wine ferments and expands</char>. As a result both the wine and the skin bags would be ruined! On the contrary, people must put new wine into new skin bags!” [MET]<verse eid="MRK 2:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When the Pharisees complained about Jesus’ disciples plucking grain on the Sabbath day, Jesus replied that there was Scriptural precedent for ignoring religious laws if there was a physical need, and that he is the one to decide what people should do on the Sabbath.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 2:23-28">Mark 2:23-28</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 2:23"/>On one ◄Sabbath/Jewish day of rest► Jesus was walking through some grain fields with his disciples. As they were walking along <char style="add">through the grain fields</char>, the disciples were plucking some of the heads of grain. <char style="add">They rubbed them in their hands to remove the chaff, and were eating the grain. The laws of Moses permitted people to do that if they were hungry</char>. <verse eid="MRK 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 2:24"/><char style="add">Some of</char> the Pharisees <char style="add">saw them doing what they considered to be work. So they</char> said to him, “Look! ◄They should not be doing on our ◄Sabbath day/day of rest► <char style="add">work</char> that our laws forbid!/Why are they doing on our ◄Sabbath day/day of rest► <char style="add">work</char> that our laws forbid?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 2:25"/><char style="add">Jesus wanted to show them that the record in the Scriptures indicated that God permitted people to disobey certain religious laws when they needed food</char>. So he said to them, “<char style="add">It is written in the Scriptures</char> what <char style="add">our revered ancestor, King</char> David, did when he needed food, and both he and the men with him were hungry. You have read about that, but ◄<char style="add">you do not think about what it implies./why do you not think about what it implies</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 2:26"/>During the time Abiathar was high priest, David entered the big tent <char style="add">where people worshipped</char> God <char style="add">and asked for some bread. The high priest gave him some</char> of the loaves of bread. That bread was the bread he had presented to God. It was permitted in one of Moses’ laws that only the priests could eat that bread! But David ate some of it. Then he also gave some of it to the men who were with him. <char style="add">But God did not consider that was wrong!</char>” <verse eid="MRK 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 2:27"/>Jesus said to them further, “<char style="add">God</char> established ◄the day of rest/the Sabbath day► <char style="add">to help</char> people! He did not create people to <char style="add">obey rules about</char> ◄the Sabbath/the day of rest►! <verse eid="MRK 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 2:28"/>And <char style="add">think about this</char>: I am the one who came from heaven. So I have the authority <char style="add">to determine what is right for my disciples to do</char> ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day►!”<verse eid="MRK 2:28"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="MRK 3"/>
  <para style="s1">After Jesus healed a man with a withered arm on the Sabbath, Jewish leaders began to plan to kill him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 3:1-6">Mark 3:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 3:1"/>
    <char style="add">On another</char> ◄<char style="add">Sabbath/Jewish day of rest</char>►, Jesus entered ◄the synagogue/the Jewish meeting place► again. There was a man there whose hand was shriveled. <verse eid="MRK 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 3:2"/><char style="add">Some men of the Pharisee sect</char> watched him carefully in order to see whether he would heal the man ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day►. They did this in order that <char style="add">if he healed the man</char>, they would accuse him of disobeying <char style="add">their Jewish laws, because he worked</char> ◄<char style="add">on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day</char>►. <verse eid="MRK 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 3:3"/>Jesus said to the man whose hand was shriveled, “Stand up here in front of everyone!” <char style="add">So the man stood up</char>. <verse eid="MRK 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 3:4"/>Then Jesus said <char style="add">to the Pharisees</char>, “Do the laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char> permit people to do good ◄<char style="add">on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day</char>►, or do they permit people to do evil? Specifically, do his laws permit us to save a person’s life ◄on the Sabbath/on the Jewish rest day►, or <char style="add">do they permit us</char> to let him die <char style="add">by refusing to help him</char>?” But they did not reply. <verse eid="MRK 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 3:5"/>He looked around at them angrily. He was very distressed that they were stubbornly <char style="add">not wanting to help the man</char>. So he said to the man, “Reach out your hand!” When the man reached out his withered hand, his hand became all right again! <verse eid="MRK 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 3:6"/>Then the Pharisees <char style="add">decided to get rid of Jesus. So</char> after they left <char style="add">the meeting house</char>, they <char style="add">immediately met with some of</char> the Jews who supported Herod <char style="add">Antipas, who ruled Galilee district</char>. Together they planned how they could kill Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Many people came from various areas to hear Jesus, because he had healed many.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 3:7-12">Mark 3:7-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 3:7"/>Jesus and his disciples left <char style="add">that</char> town and went to an area further along <char style="add">Galilee Lake in order to get away from the people</char>. But a great crowd of people followed him. They were people who came from Galilee <char style="add">district</char>, <verse eid="MRK 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 3:8"/>from Jerusalem <char style="add">city</char>, from <char style="add">other towns of</char> Judea <char style="add">district</char>, from Idumea <char style="add">district</char>, from <char style="add">the region on</char> the <char style="add">east</char> side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, and from <char style="add">the region</char> around Tyre and Sidon <char style="add">cities</char>. This great crowd of people came to him because they heard about what he was doing. <verse eid="MRK 3:8"/><verse number="9-10" style="v" sid="MRK 3:9-10"/>Because he had healed many people, many <char style="add">other</char> people who had various illnesses pushed forward in order that by touching him <char style="add">they would come well</char>. So he told his disciples that they should get a small boat ready for him <char style="add">to get in and teach from it</char>. He wanted to do this in order that the crowd would not crush him <char style="add">when they pushed forward to touch him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 3:9-10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 3:11"/>Whenever the evil spirits saw Jesus, <char style="add">they caused the people whom they controlled</char> to fall down in front of Jesus <char style="add">in recognition of Jesus’ power</char>. Then they exclaimed, “You are ◄the Son of God/the man who is also God►!” <verse eid="MRK 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 3:12"/>He commanded the <char style="add">evil spirits</char> strongly that they should not tell anyone who he was.<verse eid="MRK 3:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus appointed the twelve apostles.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 3:13-19">Mark 3:13-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 3:13"/>Jesus went <char style="add">with many other people</char> up into the hills. After he picked out <char style="add">from among them</char> the men whom he wanted <char style="add">to accompany him</char>, they came <char style="add">close</char> to him. <verse eid="MRK 3:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 3:14"/>He appointed twelve men in order that they might be with him and in order that he might send them out to preach. He called them apostles. <verse eid="MRK 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 3:15"/>He also gave them power in order that they might expel evil spirits <char style="add">from people</char>. <verse eid="MRK 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 3:16"/>These were the twelve men he appointed: Simon, to whom he gave the <char style="add">new</char> name Peter; his <char style="add">younger</char> brother Andrew; <verse eid="MRK 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 3:17"/>James, <char style="add">the son</char> of Zebedee, and John, the <char style="add">younger</char> brother of James, to <char style="add">both of</char> whom he added the <char style="add">new</char> name, ‘Men who are like Thunder’. <char style="add">because of their fiery zeal</char>; <verse eid="MRK 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 3:18"/>Philip; Bartholomew; Levi, whose other name was Matthew; Thomas; <char style="add">another</char> James, the son of Alphaeus; Thaddeus; <char style="add">another</char> Simon, who was a <char style="add">member of the party that wanted</char> to overthrow <char style="add">the Roman government</char>; <verse eid="MRK 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 3:19"/>and Judas Iscariot (OR, Judas, the man from Kerioth <char style="add">Town</char>). He was the one who <char style="add">later</char> ◄betrayed Jesus/helped Jesus’ enemies seize him►.<verse eid="MRK 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus explained why their claim that he was expelling evil spirits by Satan’s power was ridiculous, and that such a claim was an unforgivable sin.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 3:20-30">Mark 3:20-30</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 3:20"/>Jesus <char style="add">along with his disciples</char> went to the house where he was staying <char style="add">in Capernaum. Again a crowd gathered where he was</char>. There were many people crowding around him, so that he and his disciples had no time when they could eat or <char style="add">when they could do anything else</char>. <verse eid="MRK 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 3:21"/>After his relatives heard about this, they went to take him home <char style="add">with them</char> because ◄some people/they► were saying that he was insane.<verse eid="MRK 3:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 3:22"/>
    <char style="add">Around that time</char> some men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws came down from Jerusalem <char style="add">city. They heard that Jesus was expelling demons</char>. So they were telling <char style="add">people</char>, “Beelzebub, who rules the evil spirits, controls him. He is the one who enables this man to expel evil spirits <char style="add">from people</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 3:23"/>Jesus summoned those men. <char style="add">Then he spoke to them</char> in parables <char style="add">to enable them to realize that Satan would not oppose his own evil spirits. He also wanted them to realize that by expelling evil spirits, he was demonstrating that he was much more powerful than Satan</char>. So he said, “◄<char style="add">It is ridiculous</char> to suggest that Satan would expel his own <char style="add">evil spirits</char>!/Why would Satan expel his own <char style="add">evil spirits</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 3:24"/>If <char style="add">people who live in the same</char> country are fighting one another, they will cease to be a single group under one ruler. <verse eid="MRK 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 3:25"/>And if <char style="add">people who live in the same</char> house fight each other, they will certainly not remain <char style="add">as one family</char>. <verse eid="MRK 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 3:26"/>Similarly, if Satan and his <char style="add">evil spirits</char> were fighting one another, instead of remaining strong, he would become powerless. <verse eid="MRK 3:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 3:27"/>Contrary to <char style="add">what you say about me</char>, someone can enter the house of a strong man <char style="add">like Satan</char> and carry off his possessions only if he first ties up the strong man. Then <char style="add">and only then</char> will he <char style="add">be able to</char> steal the things in that man’s house.” <verse eid="MRK 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 3:28"/><char style="add">Jesus also said</char>, “Consider this carefully! People may sin in many ways and they may speak evilly about God, but <char style="add">if</char> they <char style="add">then are sorry and ask God to</char> forgive <char style="add">them</char>, <char style="add">God</char> will forgive them for doing that. <verse eid="MRK 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 3:29"/>But if anyone speaks evil words about what the Holy Spirit <char style="add">does</char>, <char style="add">God</char> will never forgive that. That person’s guilt will remain with him forever.”<verse eid="MRK 3:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 3:30"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus told them that</char> because <char style="add">they refused to admit that the Holy Spirit was helping him to expel demons. Instead</char>, they were saying, “An evil spirit is controlling him!”<verse eid="MRK 3:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told them that those who obey God are as dear to him as his close relatives.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 3:31-35">Mark 3:31-35</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 3:31"/>Jesus’ mother and <char style="add">younger</char> siblings arrived. While they stood outside, they sent <char style="add">someone inside</char> in order to call him <char style="add">outside</char>. <verse eid="MRK 3:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 3:32"/>A crowd was sitting around Jesus. One of them said to him, “Listen/Hey, your mother and your <char style="add">younger</char> brothers and sisters are outside, and they are wanting ◄to see/to talk with► you!” <verse eid="MRK 3:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 3:33"/>Jesus replied to them, “◄<char style="add">I will tell you something about</char> my mother and my brothers.<char style="add">/Do you know whom I consider to be like</char> my mother and my brothers?►” [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 3:34"/>After he looked around at <char style="add">the disciples</char> who were sitting around him <char style="add">in a circle</char>, he said, “Look here! I <char style="add">love these men as much as</char> I <char style="add">love</char> my mother and my brothers. <verse eid="MRK 3:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 3:35"/>Those who habitually do what God wants are <char style="add">as dear to me</char> [MET] as my brother, my sister, or my mother!”<verse eid="MRK 3:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="MRK 4"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught the crowds by parables about the various ways that people who hear his message react.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 4:1-25">Mark 4:1-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 4:1"/>Another time Jesus began to teach <char style="add">people</char> alongside Lake <char style="add">Galilee. As he was doing that, a very large crowd gathered around him. Because people were jostling him</char>, he got into a boat in the lake <char style="add">so that he could speak to the crowd better. Then he sat in it and began to teach the crowd from the boat</char>. At the same time, the crowd was on the shore close to the lake. <verse eid="MRK 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 4:2"/>Then he taught them many parables. While he was teaching them, he told them <char style="add">this</char>: <verse eid="MRK 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 4:3"/>“Consider <char style="add">well the meaning of this illustration</char>: A man/farmer went out <char style="add">to his field</char> to sow <char style="add">some seeds</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 4:4"/>As he was scattering them <char style="add">over the soil</char>, some <char style="add">of the</char> seeds fell on the path. Then some birds came and ate those seeds. <verse eid="MRK 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 4:5"/>Other <char style="add">seeds</char> fell on ground where there was not much soil <char style="add">on top of</char> rock. Very soon the <char style="add">seeds</char> sprouted because <char style="add">the sun warmed</char> the moist soil quickly where it was not deep. <verse eid="MRK 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 4:6"/>But after the sun shone <char style="add">on those young plants</char>, they became scorched. Then they withered because they did not have <char style="add">deep</char> roots. <verse eid="MRK 4:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 4:7"/>As the farmer sowed, other <char style="add">seeds</char> fell on <char style="add">ground that contained roots of</char> thorny plants. <char style="add">The</char> seeds <char style="add">grew, but</char> the thorny plants also grew up and crowded out <char style="add">the</char> good <char style="add">plants. So the plants</char> produced no grain. <verse eid="MRK 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 4:8"/>But as the farmer sowed, other <char style="add">seeds</char> fell on good soil. As a result, they sprouted, they grew well, and then they produced <char style="add">plenty of</char> grain. <char style="add">Some</char> plants bore 30 <char style="add">grains</char>. <char style="add">Some</char> bore 60 <char style="add">grains</char>. <char style="add">Some</char> bore 100 <char style="add">grains</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 4:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 4:9"/>Then Jesus said, “If you want to understand this [MTY], you should consider <char style="add">carefully what I have just said</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 4:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 4:10"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char>, when only the twelve <char style="add">disciples</char> and a few <char style="add">other</char> people were with him, they asked him about the parables. <verse eid="MRK 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 4:11"/>He said to them, “People have not understood before <char style="add">the new message</char> about how God wants to rule people’s lives. It is to you that this is being made known {that I am making this known}. But I tell about this <char style="add">only</char> ◄in parables/figuratively► to those who have not <char style="add">yet invited God to rule their lives</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 4:12"/>As a result <char style="add">it is true what a prophet has written</char>,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="MRK 4:12">Although they see <char style="add">what I do</char>, they do not perceive <char style="add">what it means</char> [DOU]. Although they hear <char style="add">what I say</char>, they do not understand <char style="add">what it means</char> [DOU]. So they do not ◄repent/turn away from their sinful behavior► in order that they would be forgiven {<char style="add">God</char> would forgive them}.”<verse eid="MRK 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 4:13"/>He also said to them, “◄<char style="add">I am disappointed that</char> you do not understand this illustration!/Can you not understand this illustration?► [RHQ] <char style="add">If you do not understand</char> this, ◄you will certainly not understand any of the <char style="add">other</char> illustrations!/how will you understand any of the <char style="add">other</char> illustrations?► [RHQ] <char style="add">Nevertheless, I will explain it to you</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 4:14"/><char style="add">In the illustration that I told you</char>, the man who sows <char style="add">seeds represents someone who</char> declares God’s message [DOU]. <verse eid="MRK 4:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 4:15"/><char style="add">Some people are like</char> the path on which <char style="add">some of</char> the seeds fell. When they hear <char style="add">the message</char>, Satan comes at once and causes them to forget what they have heard. <verse eid="MRK 4:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 4:16"/><char style="add">Some people are like the ground where the soil was not very deep over</char> rock. When they hear <char style="add">God’s</char> message, they immediately accept it with joy. <verse eid="MRK 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 4:17"/>But, because <char style="add">the message does not penetrate deeply</char> [MET] <char style="add">into their hearts/inner beings, they</char> believe it for <char style="add">only a short time. They are like the plants that</char> did not have deep roots. When others treat such people badly or cause them to suffer because <char style="add">they believe</char>, those people <char style="add">who are suffering</char> soon stop believing God’s message. <verse eid="MRK 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 4:18"/><char style="add">Some people are like</char> the <char style="add">soil that had roots of</char> thorny weeds in it. <char style="add">Although</char> those people hear <char style="add">God’s</char> message, <verse eid="MRK 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 4:19"/>they desire to be rich, and they desire to own many other things. So they worry <char style="add">only</char> about material things. The result is that they forget <char style="add">God’s</char> message and they do not do <char style="add">the things that God wants them to do</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 4:20"/><char style="add">But some people</char> are like the good soil. They hear <char style="add">God’s</char> message and they accept it <char style="add">and they believe</char> it. <char style="add">Then they do the things that God wants them to do. They are like the good plants that produced</char> 30, 60 or 100 <char style="add">grains</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 4:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 4:21"/>He also told them <char style="add">another parable</char>, saying, “◄People certainly do not <char style="add">light</char> an oil lamp and then bring it <char style="add">in the house</char> in order that it may be put {someone may put it} under a container or under a bed./Would anyone <char style="add">light</char> an oil lamp and then bring it <char style="add">in the house</char> in order that it may be put {someone may put it} under a container or under a bed?► [RHQ] ◄No, <char style="add">they light it</char> in order that it may be put {someone may put it} in a place <char style="add">where it lights the house</char>.<char style="add">/Wouldn’t they light it</char> in order that it may be put {someone may put it} in a place <char style="add">where it lights the house</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 4:22"/><char style="add">Similarly</char>, there are some <char style="add">parts of God’s message</char> that people do not know. <char style="add">But he intends that</char> people will understand all the things that they do not know <char style="add">now</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 4:23"/>If you want to understand this, you should consider <char style="add">carefully</char> what you <char style="add">have just heard</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 4:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 4:24"/>Then he said to them, “Consider carefully what you hear <char style="add">me say to you</char>, for <char style="add">God</char> will let you <char style="add">understand</char> to the same degree that you <char style="add">consider what I say</char>. <char style="add">He</char> will let you <char style="add">understand</char> even more than that. <verse eid="MRK 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 4:25"/>Those who <char style="add">consider what I say</char> and understand it, <char style="add">God</char> will enable them to understand more. But those who do not <char style="add">consider carefully what I say</char>, they will forget even what they already know.”<verse eid="MRK 4:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told them two parables to show them how the number of people who will submit to God’s rule over their lives will greatly increase.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 4:26-34">Mark 4:26-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 4:26"/>Jesus also said, “God <char style="add">has the power to change</char> people who let him rule their lives. I <char style="add">will illustrate how that can happen</char> [MET]. A man planted seeds in the ground. <verse eid="MRK 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 4:27"/>Afterwards he slept each night and rose each day <char style="add">without worrying about the seeds</char>. <char style="add">During that time</char> the seeds sprouted and grew in a way that he did not understand, because by itself the soil <char style="add">caused the plants to grow and produce grain</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 4:28"/>First the stalks <char style="add">appeared</char>. Then the heads <char style="add">appeared</char>. Then the full kernels in the heads <char style="add">appeared</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 4:29"/>As soon as the grain was ripe he sent <char style="add">people</char> [MTY] to harvest it because it was time to harvest <char style="add">the grain</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 4:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 4:30"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus told them</char> another <char style="add">parable. He</char> said, “I will tell you [RHQ] how the <char style="add">number of people</char> whose lives God rules in a new way <char style="add">will continue to grow</char> (OR, each continue to have more and more influence in this world). I hope [RHQ] that this illustration will show this <char style="add">to you</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 4:31"/><char style="add">You know what happens to</char> mustard seeds when we plant them. Though mustard seeds are among the smallest of seeds, <char style="add">here in Israel</char> they become large plants. <verse eid="MRK 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 4:32"/>After they are planted, they grow up and become larger than the other garden plants. They put out big branches so that birds are able to make nests in their shade.”<verse eid="MRK 4:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 4:33"/>Jesus used many such illustrations when he talked to the people about God. If they were able to understand <char style="add">some, he kept telling them more</char>. <verse eid="MRK 4:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 4:34"/>He always used parables when he spoke to them. But he explained all <char style="add">the illustrations</char> to his own disciples when he was alone with them.<verse eid="MRK 4:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">While Jesus and his disciples crossed the lake in a boat and while Jesus slept, a storm arose, so the disciples woke him and he calmed the storm.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 4:35-41">Mark 4:35-41</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 4:35"/>On that same day, when the sun was setting, Jesus said to <char style="add">his disciples</char>, “Let’s cross over to the opposite side of <char style="add">Lake Galilee in the boat</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 4:36"/>So they left the crowd, <char style="add">got in</char> the boat where Jesus <char style="add">already</char> was, and left. <char style="add">Other people</char> went with them in other boats. <verse eid="MRK 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 4:37"/>A strong wind came up and the waves started coming into the boat! The boat was soon nearly full <char style="add">of water</char>! <verse eid="MRK 4:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 4:38"/>Jesus was in the back part of the boat. He was sleeping, <char style="add">with his head</char> on a cushion. So they woke him up and said to him, “Teacher! ◄You ought to be concerned that we are about to die!/Are you not concerned that we are about to die?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 4:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 4:39"/>So Jesus got up and rebuked the wind. Then he said to the lake, “Be quiet! Be still! [DOU]” The wind <char style="add">immediately </char>stopped blowing and then <char style="add">the lake</char> became very calm. <verse eid="MRK 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 4:40"/>He said to the disciples, “◄<char style="add">I am disappointed that</char> you are afraid <char style="add">like that</char>!/Why are you afraid <char style="add">like that</char>?► [RHQ] Do you not yet believe <char style="add">that I can protect you</char>?” <verse eid="MRK 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 4:41"/>They were very awestruck. They said to one another, “<char style="add">Not only do the demons obey this man, but </char> even the wind and the waves obey him! “◄What kind of man is he?/This man is <char style="add">not like ordinary </char> people!► [RHQ]”<verse eid="MRK 4:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="MRK 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus expelled evil spirits from a Gerasene man and then allowed them to enter a herd of pigs, which then ran down a hill and drowned. As a result, the local people asked Jesus to leave the area.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 5:1-20">Mark 5:1-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 5:1"/>Jesus and his disciples arrived on the <char style="add">east</char> side of Lake <char style="add">Galilee. They landed near</char> where the Gerasene <char style="add">people lived</char>. <verse eid="MRK 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 5:2"/>There was a man in that region whom evil spirits controlled. <verse eid="MRK 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 5:3"/><char style="add">Because that man was violent and people were afraid of him</char>, they had tied him up many times. <char style="add">As he grew more violent</char>, no one was able to tie him up any longer, not even with chains, <verse eid="MRK 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 5:4"/>because the chains would be broken by him {he would break the chains} whenever he was bound {they bound him} with them. The iron shackles would also be smashed by him {He would also smash the iron shackles} whenever they were fastened {they fastened them} <char style="add">on his feet</char>. <verse eid="MRK 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 5:5"/>He lived in one of the caves <char style="add">where they bury dead people</char>. During both night and day he would scream among the caves and in the hills. He would also cut himself with <char style="add">sharp</char> stones. <char style="add">That day</char> he came out of the caves. <verse eid="MRK 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 5:6"/>As Jesus <char style="add">and his disciples got</char> out of the boat, that man saw Jesus from a distance. He immediately ran to Jesus, and then he knelt before him. <verse eid="MRK 5:6"/><verse number="7-8" style="v" sid="MRK 5:7-8"/>Jesus said to the evil spirit, “You evil spirit, come out of this man!” <char style="add">But the demon did not leave quickly</char>. It shouted very loudly, “Jesus, I <char style="add">know that you are the</char> ◄Son of/man who is also► God, so ◄we have nothing in common./what do we have in common?► [IDM, RHQ] <char style="add">So leave me alone</char> I ask you to promise, knowing God is listening, that you will not torture me <char style="add">now</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 5:7-8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 5:9"/><char style="add">So, in order to expel the demon more easily</char>, Jesus asked him, “What is your name?” He replied, “My name is Crowd/Mob because there are many of us <char style="add">evil spirits in this man</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 5:10"/>Then the evil spirits fervently kept begging Jesus that he not send them out of the region. <verse eid="MRK 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 5:11"/><char style="add">At the same time</char>, a large herd of pigs was ◄grazing/rooting for food► nearby on the hillside. <verse eid="MRK 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 5:12"/>So the evil spirits pleaded with Jesus, “Allow us to go to the pigs in order that we might enter them!” <verse eid="MRK 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 5:13"/>He permitted them <char style="add">to do that</char>. So the evil spirits left the man and entered the pigs. The herd, <char style="add">which numbered</char> about 2,000, rushed down the cliff into the lake, and drowned in the lake.<verse eid="MRK 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 5:14"/>The men who had been tending the pigs ran and reported in the town and the countryside <char style="add">what had happened. Many people</char> went to see what had happened. <verse eid="MRK 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 5:15"/>They came to <char style="add">the place where</char> Jesus <char style="add">was</char>. Then they saw the man whom evil spirits had <char style="add">previously</char> controlled. He was sitting there with clothes on and mentally sound. <char style="add">As a result</char>, they became afraid <char style="add">because they thought that Jesus might destroy more of their property</char>. (OR, <char style="add">they realized that Jesus must be very powerful</char>.) <verse eid="MRK 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 5:16"/>The people who had seen what had happened described what had happened to the man whom the evil spirits <char style="add">previously</char> controlled. They also described <char style="add">what had happened to</char> the pigs. <verse eid="MRK 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 5:17"/>Then the people pleaded with Jesus to leave their region.<verse eid="MRK 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 5:18"/>As Jesus got in the boat <char style="add">in order to leave</char>, the man whom the evil spirits <char style="add">previously</char> controlled begged Jesus, “<char style="add">Please let me</char> go with you!” <verse eid="MRK 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 5:19"/>But Jesus did not let him <char style="add">go with him</char>. On the contrary, he said to him, “Go home to your family and tell them how much the Lord <char style="add">God</char> has done for you, and tell them how <char style="add">God</char> was kind to you.” <verse eid="MRK 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 5:20"/>So the man left <char style="add">and traveled around</char> the Ten Towns <char style="add">district</char>. He told people how much Jesus had done for him. All the people <char style="add">who heard what the man said</char> were amazed.<verse eid="MRK 5:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus cured a woman who had been suffering from hemorrhaging, and brought Jairus’ daughter back to life.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 5:21-43">Mark 5:21-43</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 5:21"/>Jesus <char style="add">and his disciples</char> went in a boat back around Lake <char style="add">Galilee</char> to where they were before. When they arrived at the shore of the lake, a large crowd gathered around Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 5:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 5:22"/>One of the men who presided over a ◄synagogue/Jewish meeting place►, whose name was Jairus, came there. When he saw Jesus, he prostrated himself at his feet. <verse eid="MRK 5:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 5:23"/>Then he pleaded with Jesus earnestly, “My twelve-year old daughter is <char style="add">sick and</char> nearly dead! <char style="add">Please</char> come <char style="add">to my house</char> and place your hands on her in order that she will be healed {to heal her}, so that she will not die!” <verse eid="MRK 5:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 5:24"/>So Jesus <char style="add">and the disciples</char> went with him.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="MRK 5:24">A large crowd followed <char style="add">Jesus</char> and <char style="add">many</char> pushed close to him. <verse eid="MRK 5:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 5:25"/>There was a woman <char style="add">in the crowd</char> who had vaginal bleeding [EUP] <char style="add">every day</char> for twelve years. <verse eid="MRK 5:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 5:26"/>She had suffered much while many doctors <char style="add">treated her</char>. But although she had spent all <char style="add">her money</char> to pay the doctors, she had not been helped {they had not helped her}. Instead, she had become worse [EUP]. <verse eid="MRK 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 5:27"/>After she heard that Jesus <char style="add">healed people</char>, she came <char style="add">to where he was and pushed</char> in the crowd <char style="add">close</char> behind Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 5:28"/>She did that because she was thinking, “If I <char style="add">touch him or</char> even if I touch his clothes, I will be healed {his power will heal me}.” So she touched Jesus’ clothes. <verse eid="MRK 5:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 5:29"/>At once her bleeding stopped. At the same time, she sensed that she had been cured of {that <char style="add">he</char> had cured} her illness. <verse eid="MRK 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 5:30"/>Jesus <char style="add">also</char> immediately sensed that his power had healed someone. So he turned around in the crowd and asked, “Who touched my clothes?” <verse eid="MRK 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 5:31"/><char style="add">One of</char> his disciples replied, “You can see that many people are crowding close to you! <char style="add">Probably many people touched you</char>! So ◄why do you ask ‘Who touched me?’<char style="add">/We are surprised</char> that you ask ‘Who touched me?’ [RHQ]►” <verse eid="MRK 5:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 5:32"/>But Jesus kept looking around in order to see the one who had done it. <verse eid="MRK 5:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 5:33"/>The woman was very afraid and trembling. <char style="add">She thought that Jesus might be angry because she had violated the law that women who had such a</char> sickness <char style="add">should not touch other people. But</char> she knew <char style="add">that Jesus had healed her</char>. So she prostrated herself before him. Then she told him truthfully <char style="add">about what she had done</char>. <verse eid="MRK 5:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 5:34"/>He said to her, “◄Ma’am/Young lady►, because you have believed <char style="add">that I could heal you</char>, I <char style="bd">have</char> healed you. You may go home with peace <char style="add">in your heart/inner being</char>, <char style="add">because I promise that </char> you will not be sick <char style="add">this way any more</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 5:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 5:35"/>While Jesus was still speaking <char style="add">to that woman</char>, some people arrived who had come from Jairus’ house. They said <char style="add">to Jairus</char>, “Your daughter has <char style="add">now</char> died. So ◄it is useless that you bother the teacher any longer <char style="add">by urging him to go to your house</char>!/why do you bother the teacher any longer <char style="add">by urging him to go to your house</char>?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 5:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 5:36"/>But when Jesus heard what these men said, he said to Jairus, “Do not think that the situation is hopeless! Just keep believing <char style="add">that she will live</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 5:36"/><verse number="37-38" style="v" sid="MRK 5:37-38"/>Then he allowed only <char style="add">his three closest disciples</char>, Peter, James, and John, to go with him <char style="add">to Jairus’ house</char>. He did not allow any other people to go with him. After they arrived near the house, Jesus saw that the people there were in turmoil. They were weeping and wailing [DOU] loudly. <verse eid="MRK 5:37-38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 5:39"/>He entered the house and then he said to them, knowing that <char style="add">he was going to cause her to live again</char>, “◄Do not make such a disturbance!/Why are you making such a disturbance?► [RHQ] Stop crying, for the child is not dead! On the contrary, she is <char style="add">only</char> sleeping [HYP, EUP]!” <verse eid="MRK 5:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 5:40"/>The people laughed at him, <char style="add">because they knew that she was dead</char>. But he sent all the other people outside the house. Then he took the child’s father and mother and the <char style="add">three disciples</char> who were with him. He went into <char style="add">the room</char> where the child was <char style="add">lying</char>. <verse eid="MRK 5:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 5:41"/>He took hold of the child’s hand and said to her <char style="add">in her own language</char>, “Talitha, Koum!” That means, “Little girl, get up!” <verse eid="MRK 5:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 5:42"/>At once the girl got up and walked around. (<char style="add">It was not surprising that she could walk</char>, because she was twelve years old.) <char style="add">When this happened, all who were present</char> were very astonished. <verse eid="MRK 5:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 5:43"/>Jesus ordered them strictly, “Do not tell anyone about <char style="add">what I have done</char>!” Afterwards he told them that something to eat should be brought to the girl {that they should bring the girl something to eat}.<verse eid="MRK 5:43"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="MRK 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught in the synagogue, and the people who heard him were amazed and offended.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 6:1-6a">Mark 6:1-6a</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 6:1"/>Jesus left <char style="add">Capernaum city and went to his hometown, Nazareth</char>. His disciples went with him. <verse eid="MRK 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 6:2"/>◄On the Sabbath/On the Jewish rest day►, <char style="add">he entered</char> the Jewish worship house and taught <char style="add">the people</char>. Many who were listening to him were astonished. <char style="add">But some</char> were saying, “<char style="add">This man is just an ordinary person like we are! So ◄we cannot believe that</char> this man <char style="add">is able to teach us</char> about these things and that he has been made very wise {that <char style="add">God</char> has made him very wise} and that he is performing such miracles!<char style="add">/how is it that</char> [RHQ] this man <char style="add">is able to teach us</char> about these things and that he has been made very wise {that <char style="add">God</char> has made him very wise} and that he is performing such miracles?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 6:3"/>◄<char style="add">We know that</char> he is <char style="add">just an ordinary</char> carpenter!/Isn’t he <char style="add">just an ordinary</char> carpenter [RHQ]?► <char style="add">We know him and his family! We know</char> Mary his mother! ◄<char style="add">We know</char> his <char style="add">younger</char> brothers James, Joses, Judas and Simon!/Are not his <char style="add">younger</char> brothers James, Joses, Judas and Simon?► [RHQ] And ◄his <char style="add">younger</char> sisters also live here in this town!/do not his <char style="add">younger</char> sisters also live here in this town?► [RHQ]” So they despised him. <verse eid="MRK 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 6:4"/>Jesus <char style="add">knew that they refused to believe in him</char>. So he said to them, “<char style="add">It is certainly true that</char> people honor <char style="add">me and other</char> prophets <char style="add">in other places, but</char> not in our hometowns! Even our relatives and the people who live in our own houses do not honor us!”<verse eid="MRK 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 6:5"/>
    <char style="add">So</char>, although he healed a few sick people there by touching them, he <char style="add">decided</char> not to perform many <char style="add">other</char> miracles <char style="add">in Nazareth</char> because the people there did not believe that he was the Messiah. <verse eid="MRK 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 6:6"/>He was amazed that they did not believe <char style="add">in him</char>.</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="MRK 6:6">Jesus began to send out his disciples two-by-two and gave them power and instructions.</para>
  <para style="sr" vid="MRK 6:6">
    <ref loc="MRK 6:6b-13">Mark 6:6b-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p" vid="MRK 6:6">Jesus <char style="add">and his disciples</char> went from town to town <char style="add">in that region</char> teaching <char style="add">the people</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 6:7"/><char style="add">One day</char> he summoned the twelve <char style="add">disciples</char>, and then he <char style="add">told them that</char> he was going to send them out two-by-two <char style="add">to teach people in various towns</char>. He gave them power <char style="add">to expel</char> evil spirits <char style="add">from people</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:7"/><verse number="8-9" style="v" sid="MRK 6:8-9"/>He also instructed them to wear sandals and to take along a walking stick when they were traveling. He told them not to take food, nor a bag <char style="add">in which travelers carry supplies</char>, nor any money for their journey. He also did not allow them to take extra clothing. <char style="add">He wanted the people who heard their message to give them what they needed</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:8-9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 6:10"/>He also instructed them, “After you enter a town, <char style="add">if someone invites you to stay in his house</char>, go into his house. Eat and sleep in that same home until you leave that town. <verse eid="MRK 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 6:11"/>Wherever the people do not welcome you and wherever the people do not listen to you, shake off the dust from your feet as you leave <char style="add">that place</char>. By doing that, you will warn them <char style="add">that God will punish them for rejecting your message</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 6:12"/><char style="add">So</char> after the disciples went out <char style="add">to various towns</char>, they were preaching that people should stop their sinful behavior. <verse eid="MRK 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 6:13"/>They were also expelling many evil spirits <char style="add">from people</char>, and they were anointing many sick people with <char style="add">olive</char> oil and healing them.<verse eid="MRK 6:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">King Herod heard about Jesus and wondered if he was John the Baptizer, come back after King Herod had ordered John to be executed due to the insistence of his wife, Herodias.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 6:14-29">Mark 6:14-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 6:14"/>
    <char style="add">King</char> Herod <char style="add">Antipas</char> heard about <char style="add">what</char> Jesus <char style="add">was doing</char>, because many people were talking <char style="add">about it. Some</char> people were saying <char style="add">about Jesus</char>, “<char style="add">He must be</char> John the Baptizer! He has come back to life! That is why he <char style="add">has God’s</char> power to perform these miracles!” <verse eid="MRK 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 6:15"/>Others were saying <char style="add">about Jesus</char>, “He is <char style="add">the former prophet</char> Elijah, <char style="add">whom God promised to send back again</char>.” Others were saying <char style="add">about Jesus</char>, “<char style="add">No</char>, he is a <char style="add">different</char> prophet, like one of the <char style="add">other</char> prophets <char style="add">who lived long ago</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 6:16"/>Having heard <char style="add">what the people were saying, King</char> Herod <char style="add">Antipas</char> himself repeatedly said, “The man <char style="add">performing those miracles</char> must be John! I <char style="add">commanded my soldiers to</char> cut off his head, but he has come back to life again <char style="add">to get revenge for my killing him</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 6:17"/>The reason <char style="add">King Herod concluded that John wanted revenge is as follows: Some time before this</char>, Herod married Herodias, while she was <char style="add">still</char> the wife of his <char style="add">younger</char> brother, Philip. <verse eid="MRK 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 6:18"/>John kept telling Herod, “<char style="add">God’s</char> law does not permit you to marry the wife of your brother <char style="add">while he is still alive</char>.” Then, because Herodias <char style="add">urged him to put John in prison</char>, Herod himself sent <char style="add">soldiers to John</char>. They seized John and put him in prison. <verse eid="MRK 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 6:19"/>But because Herodias wanted to get <char style="add">further</char> revenge on John, she wanted <char style="add">someone</char> to execute him. But she could not do that because <char style="add">while John was in prison</char>, Herod kept John safe <char style="add">from her</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 6:20"/>Herod did this because he respected/feared John, because he knew that he was a righteous and holy man. The king did not know what he should do, but he liked to listen to him. <verse eid="MRK 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 6:21"/>But <char style="add">Herodias was able to have someone execute John when they honored/celebrated</char> the day when Herod was born. On that day, he invited the <char style="add">most important</char> government officials, the <char style="add">most important</char> army leaders, and the most important men in Galilee <char style="add">district</char> in order that they might eat <char style="add">and celebrate with him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 6:22"/><char style="add">While they were eating</char>, Herodias’ daughter came into the room and danced, and that pleased <char style="add">King</char> Herod and his guests. So the king said to her, “Ask me for whatever you desire and I will give it to you!” <verse eid="MRK 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 6:23"/>He said to her, “Whatever you ask, I will give it to you! I will give you up to half of what I own and rule, if you ask for it. May God punish me <char style="add">if I do not do what I have promised</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 6:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 6:24"/>The girl immediately left the room and went to her mother. She <char style="add">told her what the king had said, and</char> asked her, “What shall I ask for?” Her mother replied, “<char style="add">Ask the king to give you</char> the head of John the Baptizer!” <verse eid="MRK 6:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 6:25"/>The girl quickly entered the room again. She went to the king and she requested, “I want you to command someone to <char style="add">cut off</char> the head of John the Baptizer <char style="add">and</char> give it to me at once on a platter, <char style="add">so that my mother can know he is dead</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 6:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 6:26"/>The king became very distressed <char style="add">when he heard what she asked for</char>, because he knew John was a very righteous man (OR, because he now knew that he should not have made that promise to her). But he could not refuse <char style="add">what she requested because</char> he had promised <char style="add">that he would give her anything she asked for</char>, and because his guests <char style="add">had heard him promise that</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 6:27"/>So the king at once ordered the man who executes prisoners to go and <char style="add">cut off</char> John’s head and bring it <char style="add">to the girl</char>. That man went to the prison and cut off John’s head. <verse eid="MRK 6:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 6:28"/>He <char style="add">put it on</char> a platter, brought it back, and gave it to the girl. The girl took it to her mother. <verse eid="MRK 6:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 6:29"/>After John’s disciples heard <char style="add">what happened</char>, they went <char style="add">to the prison</char> and took John’s body and then they buried <char style="add">it in a burial cave</char>.<verse eid="MRK 6:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The apostles returned to Jesus to report what they had done. Then they all went off to a lonely place, but many people followed them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 6:30-34">Mark 6:30-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 6:30"/>The <char style="add">twelve</char> apostles returned to Jesus <char style="add">from the places to which they had gone</char>. They reported to him what they had done and what they had taught <char style="add">to people</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 6:31"/>He said to them, “Come <char style="add">with me</char> to a place where no people are living, in order that we can be alone and rest a little while!” <char style="add">He said this</char> because many people were continually coming to them and going <char style="add">away again</char>, with the result that <char style="add">Jesus and</char> his disciples did not have time to eat <char style="add">or do anything else</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 6:32"/>So they went away by themselves in a boat to a place where no people were living. <verse eid="MRK 6:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 6:33"/><char style="add">But many</char> people saw them leaving. They also recognized <char style="add">that they were Jesus and the disciples, and they saw where they were going</char>. So they ran <char style="add">ahead on land</char> from all the <char style="add">nearby</char> towns to the place <char style="add">where Jesus and his disciples were going</char>. They <char style="add">actually</char> arrived there before <char style="add">Jesus and the disciples</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 6:34"/>As Jesus <char style="add">and his disciples</char> got out of the boat, Jesus saw this large crowd. He felt sorry for them because they were <char style="add">confused</char>, like sheep that do not have a shepherd. So he taught them many things.<verse eid="MRK 6:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When it became late in the afternoon the people became hungry and there was no place to obtain food; as a result, Jesus miraculously provided food for them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 6:35-44">Mark 6:35-44</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 6:35"/>Late <char style="add">in the afternoon</char>, the disciples came to him and said, “This is a place where no people live and it is very late. <verse eid="MRK 6:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 6:36"/><char style="add">So </char> send the people away in order that they may go to the surrounding farms and villages in order that they can buy for themselves something to eat!” <verse eid="MRK 6:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 6:37"/>But he replied, “<char style="add">No</char>, you <char style="add">yourselves</char> give them something to eat!” They replied, “◄We could not buy enough bread to feed <char style="add">this crowd</char>, even if we had as much money as a man earns by working 200 days!/How could we buy enough bread to feed <char style="add">this mob</char>, even if we had as much money as a man earns by working 200 days?►” [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 6:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 6:38"/>But he replied to them, “How many loaves of bread do you have? Go and find out!” They <char style="add">went and</char> found out and then they told him, “We have <char style="add">only</char> five flat loaves and two <char style="add">cooked</char> fish!” <verse eid="MRK 6:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 6:39"/>He instructed <char style="add">the disciples to tell</char> all the people to sit down on the green grass. <verse eid="MRK 6:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 6:40"/>So the people sat in groups. There were 50 people in some groups and 100 people in other groups. <verse eid="MRK 6:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 6:41"/>Jesus took the five flat loaves and the two fish. He looked up towards heaven and thanked <char style="add">God</char> for them. Then he broke the loaves and fish into pieces and kept giving them to the disciples in order that they would distribute them to the people. <verse eid="MRK 6:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 6:42"/>Everyone ate <char style="add">this food</char> until they all had enough to eat! <verse eid="MRK 6:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 6:43"/>The disciples then collected twelve baskets full of pieces <char style="add">of bread</char> and of the fish <char style="add">that were left over</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 6:44"/>There were approximately 5,000 men who ate the bread <char style="add">and fish. They did not even count the women and children</char>.<verse eid="MRK 6:44"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus sent his disciples ahead of him to Bethsaida by boat while he stayed to pray. Later he saw that they were in difficulty due to a wind blowing against them, so he went to them, walking on the water.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 6:45-52">Mark 6:45-52</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 6:45"/>Right away Jesus told his disciples to get into the boat and then go ahead of him to Bethsaida <char style="add">town, which was</char> further around <char style="add">Lake Galilee. He stayed and</char> dismissed the many people who were there. <verse eid="MRK 6:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 6:46"/>After he said goodbye to the people, he went up into the hills in order to pray. <verse eid="MRK 6:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 6:47"/>When it was evening, the <char style="add">disciples’</char> boat was in the middle of the lake and Jesus was by himself on the land. <verse eid="MRK 6:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 6:48"/>He saw that the wind was <char style="add">blowing</char> against them as they rowed. As a result, they were having great difficulty. He approached them early in the morning, when it was still dark, by walking on the water. He intended to walk by them. <verse eid="MRK 6:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 6:49"/>They saw him walking on the water, but they thought that he was a ghost. They screamed <verse eid="MRK 6:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 6:50"/>because they all were terrified when they saw him. But he talked to them. He said to them, “Be calm! Do not be afraid, <char style="add">because</char> it is I!” <verse eid="MRK 6:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 6:51"/>He got into the boat <char style="add">and sat down</char> with them and the wind <char style="add">immediately </char>stopped blowing. They were completely amazed <char style="add">about what he had done</char>. <verse eid="MRK 6:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 6:52"/><char style="add">Although they had seen Jesus multiply</char> the <char style="add">bread and the fish</char>, they did not understand <char style="add">from that how powerful he was, as they should have</char>. They did not think clearly about it.<verse eid="MRK 6:52"/></para>
  <para style="s1">As soon as Jesus and his disciples reached land and disembarked, people began to come to Jesus, bringing sick people in order that he might heal them, and he healed all who touched him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 6:53-56">Mark 6:53-56</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 6:53"/>After they went further around <char style="add">Lake Galilee in a boat, they came to the shore at Gennesaret town</char>. Then they tied up the boat there. <verse eid="MRK 6:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 6:54"/>As soon as they got out of the boat, <char style="add">the people there</char> recognized Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 6:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 6:55"/>So they ran throughout the whole district <char style="add">in order to tell others that Jesus was there</char>. Then the people <char style="add">placed</char> those who were sick on stretchers and carried them to any place where they heard <char style="add">people say</char> that Jesus was. <verse eid="MRK 6:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 6:56"/>In whatever village, town or other place where he entered, they would bring to the marketplaces those who were sick. Then the <char style="add">sick people</char> would beg Jesus to let them touch <char style="add">him or</char> even the edge of his clothes <char style="add">in order that Jesus might heal them</char>. All those who touched <char style="add">him or his robe</char> were healed.<verse eid="MRK 6:56"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="MRK 7"/>
  <para style="s1">Some Pharisees and scribes criticized Jesus about his disciples disobeying the traditions of the elders. Jesus replied, showing that their attitudes and practices were mistaken.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 7:1-23">Mark 7:1-23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 7:1"/>
    <char style="add">One day some</char> Pharisees and some men who teach the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws gathered around Jesus. They had come from Jerusalem <char style="add">to investigate him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 7:1"/><verse number="2-4" style="v" sid="MRK 7:2-4"/>The Pharisees and all of the <char style="add">other</char> Jews <char style="add">strictly</char> observe the traditions that their ancestors <char style="add">taught. For example, they refuse to</char> eat until they first wash their hands <char style="add">with a special ritual</char>, especially after they <char style="add">return</char> from <char style="add">buying things in</char> the marketplace. <char style="add">They think that God will be angry with them if they do not do that, because some person or thing unacceptable to God might have touched</char> ◄<char style="add">them/the things they bought</char>►. There are many other such <char style="add">traditions</char> that they accept and try to obey. Specifically, they wash <char style="add">in a special way</char> their cups, pots, kettles, containers, and beds <char style="add">in order that using these things will not make God reject them</char>.<verse eid="MRK 7:2-4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 7:5"/>That day, those Pharisees and men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws saw that some of his disciples were eating food with hands that they had not washed <char style="add">using the special ritual</char>. So they questioned Jesus, saying, “<char style="add">Your</char> disciples disobey the traditions of our ancestors! ◄You should not <char style="add">let them</char> eat food if they have not washed their hands <char style="add">using our special ritual</char>!/Why do you <char style="add">let them</char> eat food if they have not washed their hands <char style="add">using our special ritual</char>?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 7:6"/>Jesus said to them, “Isaiah <char style="add">rebuked your ancestors</char>, and his words describe very well you people who only pretend to be good! He wrote these words <char style="add">that God said</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="MRK 7:6">These people speak <char style="add">as if they</char> honor me, but they [SYN] really do not think about honoring me at all. <verse eid="MRK 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 7:7"/>It is useless for them to worship me, because they teach only what people have commanded <char style="add">as if I myself had commanded them</char>.<verse eid="MRK 7:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 7:8"/>You, <char style="add">like your ancestors</char>, refuse <char style="add">to do</char> what God has commanded. Instead, you follow only the traditions that ◄others/your ancestors► have <char style="add">taught</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 7:9"/>Jesus also said to them, “<char style="add">You think</char> [IRO] that you are clever in refusing to do what God commanded just so that you can obey your own traditions! <verse eid="MRK 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 7:10"/><char style="add">For example, our ancestor</char> Moses <char style="add">wrote God’s</char> command, ‘Honor your fathers and your mothers’. He also wrote, ‘<char style="add">The authorities must</char> execute a person who speaks evil about his father or mother.’ <verse eid="MRK 7:10"/><verse number="11-12" style="v" sid="MRK 7:11-12"/>But you <char style="add">teach people that it is all right that people no longer must help their parents. You teach people that it is all right if people</char> give their things to God <char style="add">instead of giving them to their parents</char>. You allow them to say to their parents, ‘What I was going to give to you <char style="add">to provide for you, I have now promised to</char> give to God. So I <char style="add">cannot any longer help you</char>!’ As a result, you are <char style="add">actually telling people</char> that they no longer have to help their parents! <verse eid="MRK 7:11-12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 7:13"/>And, by doing that, you disregard what God commanded! You teach your own traditions to others <char style="add">and tell them strongly that they should obey them</char> And you do many other things like that.”<verse eid="MRK 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 7:14"/>Then Jesus again summoned the crowd <char style="add">to come closer. Then</char> he said to them <char style="add">figuratively</char>, “All of you people listen to me! <char style="add">Try to</char> understand [DOU] <char style="add">what I am about to tell you</char>. <verse eid="MRK 7:14"/><verse number="15-16" style="v" sid="MRK 7:15-16"/>Nothing that people eat causes <char style="add">God to</char> consider them to be unacceptable. On the contrary, it is that which comes from people’s ◄inner beings/hearts► that causes God to reject them.”<verse eid="MRK 7:15-16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 7:17"/>After Jesus had left the crowd and then entered a house with the disciples, they asked him about the parable <char style="add">that he had just spoken</char>. <verse eid="MRK 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 7:18"/>He replied, “◄<char style="add">I am disappointed that</char> you also do not understand <char style="add">what it means</char>!/Why can you not understand <char style="add">what it means</char>?► [RHQ] ◄You ought to understand that nothing that <char style="add">enters us from</char> outside can cause <char style="add">God to</char> consider us unacceptable to him./Can you not understand that nothing that <char style="add">enters us from</char> outside of us can cause <char style="add">God to</char> consider us unacceptable to him?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 7:19"/>Instead of entering <char style="add">and ruining</char> our minds/souls, it goes into our stomachs, and afterwards the refuse passes out <char style="add">of our bodies</char>.” By saying this, Jesus was declaring that people <char style="add">can eat</char> any food without causing <char style="add">God</char> to reject them. <verse eid="MRK 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 7:20"/>He also said, “It is the <char style="add">thoughts and actions</char> that come from within people that cause <char style="add">God</char> to consider them unacceptable to him. <verse eid="MRK 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 7:21"/>Specifically, it is people’s innermost being <char style="add">that causes them to</char> think things that are evil; they act immorally, they steal <char style="add">things</char>, they commit murder. <verse eid="MRK 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 7:22"/>They <char style="add">commit</char> adultery, they are greedy, they <char style="add">act</char> maliciously, they deceive <char style="add">people</char>. They <char style="add">act</char> indecently, they envy <char style="add">people</char>, they speak evil about others, they are proud, and they <char style="add">act</char> foolishly. <verse eid="MRK 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 7:23"/>People think <char style="add">these thoughts</char> and then they do these evil actions, and that is what causes <char style="add">God to</char> consider them unacceptable to him.”<verse eid="MRK 7:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus went to the region around Tyre to be away from people, but they learned of it, and a woman came to ask him to expel an evil spirit from her daughter.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 7:24-30">Mark 7:24-30</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 7:24"/>After Jesus <char style="add">and his disciples</char> left <char style="add">Galilee district</char>, they went to the region around Tyre. While he stayed at a certain house, he desired that no one know <char style="add">it</char>, but people soon found out <char style="add">that he was there</char>. <verse eid="MRK 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 7:25"/>A certain woman, whose daughter had an evil spirit <char style="add">within her</char>, heard about Jesus. At once she came to him and prostrated herself at his feet. <verse eid="MRK 7:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 7:26"/>This woman <char style="add">was not a Jew. Her ancestors came</char> from Greece <char style="add">country</char>, but she was born in <char style="add">the region around</char> Phoenicia <char style="add">town</char> in Syria district. She pleaded with Jesus that he expel the evil spirit from her daughter. <verse eid="MRK 7:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 7:27"/>But he <char style="add">wanted to see how strongly she believed in him. So, suggesting that he should help the Jews first and not the non-Jews whom some Jews called dogs</char> [MET], <char style="add">he</char> spoke to her saying, “First let the children eat all they want, because it is not good for someone to take the food <char style="add">the mother has prepared</char> for the children and then throw it to the <char style="add">little</char> dogs.” <verse eid="MRK 7:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 7:28"/>But <char style="add">to show that she believed that non-Jews could also receive help from God</char> [MET], she replied to him, “Sir, <char style="add">what you say is</char> correct, but even the <char style="add">little</char> dogs, which lie under the table, eat the crumbs that the children <char style="add">drop</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 7:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 7:29"/><char style="add">Jesus</char> said to her, “Because of what you have said, <char style="add">you have shown me that you believe in what I can do for you</char>. So I will help you. Now you may go <char style="add">home, because I have caused</char> the evil spirit to leave your daughter.” <verse eid="MRK 7:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 7:30"/>The woman returned to her house and saw that her child was lying <char style="add">quietly</char> on the bed and that the evil spirit had left.<verse eid="MRK 7:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When Jesus went back to Lake Galilee, some people brought a deaf-mute man to Jesus and asked him to heal the man, which he did.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 7:31-37">Mark 7:31-37</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 7:31"/>Jesus <char style="add">and his disciples</char> left the region around Tyre <char style="add">city</char> and went <char style="add">north</char> through Sidon <char style="add">city</char>, then <char style="add">toward the east</char> through the district of the Ten Towns, and then <char style="add">south</char> to <char style="add">the towns near</char> Lake Galilee. <verse eid="MRK 7:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 7:32"/><char style="add">There</char>, people brought to him a man who was deaf and who could hardly talk. They begged <char style="add">Jesus</char> to lay his hands on him <char style="add">in order to heal him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 7:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 7:33"/><char style="add">So Jesus</char> took him away from the crowd <char style="add">in order that the two of them could be</char> alone. Then he put <char style="add">one of</char> his fingers into <char style="add">each of</char> the man’s ears. After he spat <char style="add">on his fingers</char>, he touched the man’s tongue <char style="add">with his fingers</char>. <verse eid="MRK 7:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 7:34"/>Then he looked up toward heaven, he sighed <char style="add">because he was concerned for the man</char>, and then <char style="add">in his own language</char> he said to the man’s <char style="add">ears</char>, “Ephphatha”, which means, “Be opened {Open up}!”. <verse eid="MRK 7:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 7:35"/>At once the man could hear plainly [MTY]. He also began to speak clearly because <char style="add">what was causing him to be unable to speak</char> was healed {Jesus healed <char style="add">what was causing him to be unable to speak</char>}. <verse eid="MRK 7:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 7:36"/>Jesus told ◄<char style="add">the people/his friends</char>► not to tell anyone <char style="add">what he had done</char>. But, although he ordered them <char style="add">and others</char> repeatedly <char style="add">not to tell anyone about it</char>, they kept talking about it very much. <verse eid="MRK 7:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 7:37"/><char style="add">People who heard about it</char> were utterly amazed and were saying <char style="add">enthusiastically</char>, “Everything he has done is wonderful! <char style="add">Besides doing other amazing things</char>, he enables deaf people to hear! And he enables those who cannot speak to speak!”<verse eid="MRK 7:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="MRK 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Again Jesus provided food miraculously for a great crowd who gathered to hear him and became hungry.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 8:1-10">Mark 8:1-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 8:1"/>During those days, a large crowd of people gathered again. <char style="add">After they had been there a couple days</char>, they had no food to eat. So Jesus summoned the disciples <char style="add">to come closer</char> and then he said to them, <verse eid="MRK 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 8:2"/>“This is the third day that these people have been with me, and they have nothing <char style="add">left</char> to eat, so now I feel very sorry for them. <verse eid="MRK 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 8:3"/>Furthermore, if I send them home <char style="add">while they are still</char> hungry, <char style="add">some of</char> them will faint on the way home, because some of them have come from far away.” <verse eid="MRK 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 8:4"/><char style="add">Knowing that he was suggesting that they give the people something to eat, one of</char> his disciples replied, “◄We cannot possibly find food to satisfy this crowd, here in this place where no people live!/How can we find food to satisfy this crowd, here in this place where no people live?►” [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 8:5"/>Jesus asked them, “How many loaves of bread do you have?” They replied, “<char style="add">We have</char> seven <char style="add">flat loaves</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 8:6"/>Jesus commanded the crowd, “Sit down on the ground!” <char style="add">After they sat down</char>, he took the seven loaves, he thanked <char style="add">God for them</char>, he broke them <char style="add">into pieces</char> and started giving them to his disciples in order that they might distribute them <char style="add">to the people</char>. <verse eid="MRK 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 8:7"/><char style="add">They found that</char> they <char style="add">also</char> had a few small <char style="add">dried</char> fish. So after he thanked God for these, he told the disciples, “Distribute these also.” <char style="add">After they distributed the bread and fish to the crowd</char>, <verse eid="MRK 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 8:8"/>the people ate this food and they had plenty <char style="add">to</char> satisfy <char style="add">them</char>. <char style="add">The disciples</char> collected the pieces of food that were left over. <char style="add">They filled</char> seven large baskets full of those pieces. <verse eid="MRK 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 8:9"/><char style="add">They estimated that</char> there were about 4,000 people <char style="add">who ate on that day</char>. <verse eid="MRK 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 8:10"/>Then Jesus dismissed the crowd. Immediately after that, he got into the boat along with his disciples, and they went <char style="add">around Lake Galilee</char> to Dalmanutha district.<verse eid="MRK 8:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus rebuked those who insisted on him performing more miracles, and rebuked the disciples when they worried about not having enough food with them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 8:11-21">Mark 8:11-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 8:11"/>
    <char style="add">In those days some</char> Pharisees came to Jesus. They asked him <char style="add">to perform</char> a miracle <char style="add">that would show that</char> God <char style="add">had sent him</char>. They wanted to <char style="add">find a way by which they could</char> convince the people to reject him. <char style="add">So</char> they started to argue with him. <verse eid="MRK 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 8:12"/>Jesus sighed quietly to himself, and then he said, “I am disgusted that [RHQ], <char style="add">even though</char> you people have seen how I <char style="add">have healed people</char>, you keep asking me to perform miracles! Note this: Such a miracle will certainly not be shown {I will certainly not show such a miracle} <char style="add">just</char> for you people!” <verse eid="MRK 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 8:13"/>Then he left them.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="MRK 8:13">He got into the boat again, along <char style="add">with his disciples</char>, and they went further around <char style="add">Lake Galilee</char>. <verse eid="MRK 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 8:14"/>The disciples had forgotten to bring along <char style="add">enough</char> food. Specifically, they had only one flat loaf of bread with them in the boat. <verse eid="MRK 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 8:15"/><char style="add">As they were going</char>, Jesus warned them against <char style="add">the attitudes the Pharisees and Herod Antipas had, attitudes that were having a bad effect on other people. He did this by telling them a parable</char>. He said, “Be careful! Beware of the yeast of the Pharisees and the yeast of Herod!” <verse eid="MRK 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 8:16"/><char style="add">The disciples misunderstood him</char>. So they said to one another, “<char style="add">He must have said that</char> because we have no bread.” <verse eid="MRK 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 8:17"/>Jesus knew <char style="add">what they were discussing among themselves</char>. So he said to them, “◄<char style="add">I am disappointed that you are</char> discussing about your not having enough bread!/Why are you discussing about your not having enough bread?► [RHQ] ◄You should understand by now <char style="add">that I can provide miraculously for you if you need food!/Why do you not yet perceive or understand that I can provide miraculously for you if you need food</char>?► [RHQ] ◄You are not thinking!/Why are you not thinking?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 8:18"/>◄I am also disappointed that, although you have eyes, you do not <char style="add">understand what you</char> see!/Why is it that, although you have eyes, you do not <char style="add">understand what you</char> see?► [RHQ] You have ears, but you do not understand <char style="add">what I say</char> [RHQ]!” <char style="add">Then he asked</char>, “Do you not remember <char style="add">what happened</char> <verse eid="MRK 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 8:19"/>when I broke <char style="add">only</char> five loaves <char style="add">and fed</char> the 5.000 people [RHQ]? <char style="add">Not only was everyone satisfied, but there was food left over</char> How many baskets full of pieces of bread <char style="add">that were left over</char> did you collect?” They replied, “We collected twelve baskets full.” <verse eid="MRK 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 8:20"/>Then he asked, “When I broke the seven loaves in order to <char style="add">feed</char> the 4,000 people, <char style="add">again when everyone had plenty to eat</char>, how many large baskets <char style="add">of pieces of bread that were left over</char> did you collect?” They replied, “<char style="add">We collected</char> seven <char style="add">large baskets full</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 8:21"/>Then he kept saying to them, “◄<char style="add">I am disappointed that</char> you do not understand yet <char style="add">that you should never worry that you do not have enough food</char>!/Why do you not understand yet <char style="add">that you should never worry that you do not have enough food</char>?►” [RHQ]<verse eid="MRK 8:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus healed a blind man.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 8:22-26">Mark 8:22-26</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 8:22"/>They arrived <char style="add">in the boat</char> at Bethsaida <char style="add">town</char>. People brought to Jesus a blind man and earnestly requested that Jesus touch him <char style="add">in order to heal him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 8:23"/>Jesus took the hand of the blind man, led him outside the town, he put his saliva on the man’s eyes, he put his hands on the man, and then he asked him, “Do you see anything?” <verse eid="MRK 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 8:24"/>The man looked up and then he said, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, I see people! They are walking around, but I cannot see them <char style="add">clearly</char>. They look like trees!” <verse eid="MRK 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 8:25"/>Then Jesus again touched the eyes of the blind man. The man looked intently and at that moment he was completely healed! He could see everything clearly. <verse eid="MRK 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 8:26"/>Jesus said to him, “Do not go into the town! <char style="add">First go straight home and tell the people there about what I did</char>!” Then he sent the man to his home.<verse eid="MRK 8:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">On the way to the villages near the city of Caesarea Philippi, Jesus asked his disciples what people were saying about who he was and, then, what they thought.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 8:27-30">Mark 8:27-30</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 8:27"/>Jesus and the disciples <char style="add">left Bethsaida town and went to the villages near Caesarea Philippi town</char>. On the way he questioned them, “Who do people say that I <char style="add">really</char> am?” <verse eid="MRK 8:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 8:28"/>They replied, “<char style="add">Some people say</char> that you are John the Baptizer, <char style="add">who has come back to life again</char>. Others say <char style="add">that you are the prophet</char> Elijah <char style="add">who has returned from heaven as God promised</char>. And others say that you are one of the <char style="add">other former</char> prophets <char style="add">who has come back to life again</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 8:29"/>He asked them, “What about you? Who do you say that I am?” Peter replied to him, “<char style="add">We believe that</char> you are the Messiah!” <verse eid="MRK 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 8:30"/>Then Jesus warned them strongly that they should not tell anyone <char style="add">yet that he was the Messiah</char>.<verse eid="MRK 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus spoke plainly to his disciples about his coming death and resurrection.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 8:31-33">Mark 8:31-33</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 8:31"/>Then Jesus began to teach them, “<char style="add">Even though</char> I am the one who came from heaven, it is necessary that I suffer very much. It is also necessary that I be rejected by the elders, the chief priests, and the men who teach the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws {that the elders, the chief priests, and the men who teach the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws reject me}, and that I be killed {they kill me}. But on the third day <char style="add">after I am killed I</char> will become alive again.” <verse eid="MRK 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 8:32"/>He said this to them clearly. But Peter took Jesus aside and then, <char style="add">because he assumed that the Messiah would never die</char>, he started to rebuke Jesus <char style="add">for talking about dying</char>. <verse eid="MRK 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 8:33"/>Jesus turned around and looked at his disciples. Then he rebuked Peter, saying, “Stop thinking like that! Satan <char style="add">is causing you to talk like that! Instead</char> of wanting what God wants <char style="add">me to do, you are wanting</char> me to do <char style="add">only</char> what <char style="add">most</char> people <char style="add">would want me to do</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 8:33"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus explained to the crowd and his disciples what is required if anyone wants to be Jesus’ disciple.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 8:34-9:1">Mark 8:34—9:1</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 8:34"/>Then he summoned the crowd along with his disciples <char style="add">so that they might listen to him</char>. He told them, “If any one <char style="add">of you</char> wants to be my disciple, you must not do <char style="add">only</char> what you yourself want to do. Specifically, you must <char style="add">be willing to allow people to hurt you and to disgrace you. That is what they do to criminals</char> who are forced to carry crosses [MET] <char style="add">to the places where they will be crucified</char>. That is what anyone who wants to be my disciple must do. <verse eid="MRK 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 8:35"/><char style="add">You must do that</char>, because those who try to save their lives <char style="add">by denying that they belong to me when people want to kill them for believing in me</char> will not live <char style="add">eternally</char>, but those who are killed because of being my <char style="add">disciples</char> and <char style="add">because of telling others my</char> good message will live <char style="add">forever with me</char>. <verse eid="MRK 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 8:36"/>People might get everything <char style="add">they want</char> in this world, but ◄they are really gaining nothing if they do not get eternal life <char style="add">because they do not become my disciples!</char>/what will they gain if they do not get eternal life <char style="add">because they do not become my disciples</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 8:37"/>◄<char style="add">Think carefully about the fact that</char> there is absolutely nothing that people can give <char style="add">to God</char> that would enable them to gain eternal life!/Is there anything that a person can give <char style="add">to God</char> in order to gain eternal life?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 8:38"/>And think about this: Those who refuse <char style="add">to say that they belong to</char> me and who reject what I say in these days when many people have turned away <char style="add">from God</char> and are very sinful, I, the one who came from heaven, will also refuse <char style="add">to say that they belong to me</char> when I come back with the holy angels and have the glorious brightness that my Father has!”<verse eid="MRK 8:38"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="MRK 9"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 9:1"/>He also said to <char style="add">his disciples</char>, “Listen carefully! Some of you who are here now will see God ruling powerfully in <char style="add">many ways</char>. You will see it before you die!”<verse eid="MRK 9:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus took Peter, James and John up a high mountain where his appearance changed, and Moses and Elijah appeared and talked to Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:2-8">Mark 9:2-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 9:2"/>A week later Jesus took Peter, James and <char style="add">James’ younger brother</char> John and led them up a high mountain. <char style="add">While they were</char> alone up there, he appeared very different to them. <verse eid="MRK 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 9:3"/>His clothes became dazzling white. They were whiter than anyone on earth could make them by bleaching them. <verse eid="MRK 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 9:4"/><char style="add">Two prophets who had lived long ago</char>, Moses and Elijah, appeared to them. Then the two of them began talking with Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 9:5"/><char style="add">After a short time</char>, Peter <char style="add">interrupted by</char> exclaiming, “Teacher, it is wonderful to be here! So allow us to make three shelters. One <char style="add">will be</char> for you, one <char style="add">will be</char> for Moses, and one <char style="add">will be</char> for Elijah!” <verse eid="MRK 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 9:6"/><char style="add">He said this</char> because <char style="add">he wanted to say something, but</char> he did not know what to say, because he and the other <char style="add">two disciples</char> were very awestruck. <verse eid="MRK 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 9:7"/>Then a <char style="add">shining</char> cloud appeared that covered them. <char style="add">God</char> [EUP] spoke to them from the cloud saying, “This is my Son. I love him. <char style="add">Therefore</char>, listen to him!” <verse eid="MRK 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 9:8"/>When <char style="add">the three disciples</char> looked around, they saw that suddenly Jesus was alone with them, and that there was no longer anyone <char style="add">else</char> there.<verse eid="MRK 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told them that the one like Elijah has already come and been evilly treated, but that the Messiah would also be evilly treated.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:9-13">Mark 9:9-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 9:9"/>While they were coming down the mountain, Jesus told them that they should not tell anyone <char style="add">yet</char> what had just happened to him. He said, “You may tell them after I, the one who came from heaven, ◄rise from the dead/become alive again► after I die.” <verse eid="MRK 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 9:10"/>So they did not tell others about it <char style="add">for a long time</char>. But they discussed among themselves what it meant when he said that he would ◄rise from the dead/become alive again► after he died.<verse eid="MRK 9:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 9:11"/>
    <char style="add">The three disciples had just seen Elijah, but Elijah had not done anything to prepare people to accept Jesus. So</char> they asked Jesus, “The men who teach the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws say that Elijah must come back to the earth before <char style="add">the Messiah comes to earth. But you have been here a long time and Elijah came just today. So is what they are teaching wrong?</char>” <verse eid="MRK 9:11"/><verse number="12-13" style="v" sid="MRK 9:12-13"/><char style="add">Jesus wanted them to know that John the Baptizer was the one who represented Elijah. So</char> he answered them, “It is true that <char style="add">God promised to send Elijah to come</char> first <char style="add">so that people would be ready when I came</char>. Elijah’s representative has already come, and our leaders treated him very badly, just like they wanted to do, just like it was prophesied {<char style="add">the prophets</char> prophesied} long ago. But, ◄I also want you to consider what is written {what <char style="add">the prophets</char> wrote} in the Scriptures about me, the one who came from heaven./why have you not thought about what is written {what <char style="add">the prophets</char> wrote} about me, the one who came from heaven?► [RHQ] It is written {They wrote} that I would suffer much and that I would be rejected {that <char style="add">many people</char> would reject me}.”<verse eid="MRK 9:12-13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus expelled an evil spirit and later explained to the disciples why they had failed to do that.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:14-29">Mark 9:14-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 9:14"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus and those three disciples</char> returned to where the <char style="add">other</char> disciples were. They saw a large crowd around the other disciples and <char style="add">some</char> men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws arguing with them. <verse eid="MRK 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 9:15"/>As soon as the crowd saw Jesus, they were very surprised <char style="add">to see him come</char>. So they ran to him and greeted him. <verse eid="MRK 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 9:16"/>He asked them, “What are you arguing about?” <verse eid="MRK 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 9:17"/>A man in the crowd answered him, “Teacher, I brought my son <char style="add">here in order that</char> you <char style="add">would heal him</char>. There is an evil spirit in him <char style="add">that makes him</char> unable to talk. <verse eid="MRK 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 9:18"/>Whenever the spirit attacks him, it throws him down. He foams at the mouth, he grinds his teeth together, and he becomes stiff. I asked your disciples to expel the spirit, but they were not able to do it.” <verse eid="MRK 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 9:19"/>Jesus replied by saying to those people, “◄I am very disappointed that <char style="add">although you</char> have observed how I help people, you do not believe <char style="add">that you are able to do anything</char>!/Why is it that <char style="add">although you</char> have observed how I help people, you do not believe <char style="add">that you are able to do anything</char>?► [RHQ] ◄I have been with you a long time, <char style="add">and you still cannot do what I do</char>!/How long do I have to be with you <char style="add">before you can do what I do</char>?► [RHQ] Bring the boy to me!” <verse eid="MRK 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 9:20"/>So they brought the boy to Jesus. As soon as the evil spirit saw Jesus, it shook the boy severely, and <char style="add">the boy</char> fell on the ground. He rolled around, and he foamed at the mouth. <verse eid="MRK 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 9:21"/>Jesus asked the boy’s father, “How long has he been like this?” He replied, “<char style="add">This started to happen</char> when he was a child. <verse eid="MRK 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 9:22"/><char style="add">The spirit does not only do this</char>, but he also often throws him into the fire or into the water in order to kill him. But, pity us and help us, if you can!” <verse eid="MRK 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 9:23"/>Jesus exclaimed to him, “<char style="add">Do not say</char> [RHQ] ‘If you can’, for <char style="add">God/I</char> can do anything for people who believe <char style="add">in him/me</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 9:24"/>Immediately the child’s father shouted, “I believe <char style="add">that you can help me, but I do not believe strongly</char>. Help me to believe more strongly!” <verse eid="MRK 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 9:25"/>Because <char style="add">Jesus wanted to heal the boy before</char> the crowd got bigger, he rebuked the evil spirit, saying, “You evil spirit, you who are <char style="add">causing this boy to be</char> deaf and unable to talk! I command you to come out of him and never enter him again!” <verse eid="MRK 9:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 9:26"/>The evil spirit shouted, it shook the boy violently, and then it left the boy. The boy did not move. He seemed like a dead body. So many of the people there said, “He is dead!” <verse eid="MRK 9:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 9:27"/>However, Jesus took him by the hand and helped him get up. Then the boy stood up. <char style="add">He was healed</char>! <verse eid="MRK 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 9:28"/>Later, when Jesus and his disciples were alone in a house, one of them asked him, “Why were we not able to expel <char style="add">the evil spirit</char>?” <verse eid="MRK 9:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 9:29"/>He said to them, “You can expel this kind <char style="add">of evil spirit</char> only by your praying <char style="add">that God will give you the power to do it</char>. There is no other way that you can expel them.”<verse eid="MRK 9:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus was teaching his disciples that he would be handed over to other men, killed, and become alive again; but they did not understand what he was saying.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:30-32">Mark 9:30-32</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 9:30"/>After <char style="add">Jesus and his disciples </char> left that <char style="add">district</char>, they traveled through Galilee <char style="add">district</char>. Jesus did not want anyone <char style="add">else </char> to know <char style="add">that he was in their area</char>; he did not want <verse eid="MRK 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 9:31"/><char style="add">anyone to interrupt him</char> as he taught his disciples. He was telling them, “<char style="add">Some day my enemies</char> [SYN] will seize [MTY] me, the one who came from heaven, and I will be handed over <char style="add">to other</char> men. Those men will kill me. But on the third day after I am killed {after they kill me}, I will become alive again!” <verse eid="MRK 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 9:32"/>But they did not understand what he was telling them. Also, they were afraid to ask him about what he had said.<verse eid="MRK 9:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught his disciples by illustration about what kind of person God considers important.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:33-37">Mark 9:33-37</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 9:33"/>Jesus and his disciples returned to Capernaum <char style="add">town</char>. When they were in the house, he asked them, “What were you discussing <char style="add">while we were traveling</char> on the road?” <verse eid="MRK 9:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 9:34"/>But they did not reply. <char style="add">They were ashamed to reply</char> because, <char style="add">while they were traveling</char>, they had been arguing with each other about which one of them <char style="add">would be</char> the most important <char style="add">when Jesus became king</char>. <verse eid="MRK 9:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 9:35"/>He sat down, he summoned the twelve disciples <char style="add">to come close to him</char>, and then he said to them, “If anyone wants <char style="add">God to consider him</char> to be the most important person of all, he must <char style="add">consider himself</char> to be the least important person of all, and he must serve everyone <char style="add">else</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 9:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 9:36"/>Then he took a child and placed him among them. He took the child in his arms and then he said to them, <verse eid="MRK 9:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 9:37"/>“Those who, <char style="add">because they love</char> me, welcome a child like this one, <char style="add">God considers that</char> they are welcoming me. So <char style="add">it is as though</char> they are also welcoming <char style="add">God</char>, who sent me.”<verse eid="MRK 9:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught his disciples about who is for him and who is against him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:38-41">Mark 9:38-41</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 9:38"/>John said to Jesus, “Teacher, we saw someone who was expelling demons, ◄<char style="add">claiming he had</char> authority from you <char style="add">to do that/while telling people</char> that you <char style="add">have told him to do it</char>►. So we told him to stop doing it because he was not one of us <char style="add">disciples</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 9:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 9:39"/>Jesus said, “Do not tell him <char style="add">not to do that</char>! For no one will speak evilly about me just after he performs a miracle while saying that I <char style="add">have told him to do it</char>. <verse eid="MRK 9:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 9:40"/>Furthermore, those who are not opposing us are trying to <char style="add">achieve the same goals that</char> we are. <verse eid="MRK 9:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 9:41"/>Also think about this: Those <char style="add">who belong to me who help you in any way, even</char> if they <char style="add">just</char> give you a cup of water to drink because you follow <char style="add">me</char>, the Messiah, will certainly be rewarded <char style="add">by God</char>!”<verse eid="MRK 9:41"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught his disciples about sin and its result.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:42-48">Mark 9:42-48</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 9:42"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus also said</char>, “But if you cause someone who believes in me to sin, <char style="add">God will severely punish you</char>, even if that person is <char style="add">socially unimportant like</char> this little child. If someone tied a heavy stone around your neck and you were thrown {and threw you} into the sea, <char style="add">you would consider that was a severe punishment. But God will punish you more severely</char> than that <char style="add">if you cause a person who believes in me to sin</char>. <verse eid="MRK 9:42"/><verse number="43-44" style="v" sid="MRK 9:43-44"/><char style="add">So</char>, if you are <char style="add">wanting to use one of</char> [MTY, PRS] <char style="add">your hands to sin, stop using your hand! Even if you have to</char> cut your hand off and throw it away <char style="add">to avoid sinning, do it</char> [HYP]! It is good that you not sin and that you live eternally, <char style="add">even though you lack one of</char> your hands <char style="add">while you are here on earth</char>. But it is not good that you sin and as a result God throws your whole body into hell. There the fires never go out! <verse eid="MRK 9:43-44"/><verse number="45-46" style="v" sid="MRK 9:45-46"/>If you are <char style="add">wanting to use</char> one of [PRS] your feet to sin, <char style="add">stop using your foot! Even if you have to</char> cut off your foot <char style="add">to avoid sinning, do it</char> [HYP]! It is good that you not sin and live eternally, <char style="add">even though</char> you lack one of your feet <char style="add">while you are here on earth</char>. But it is not good that you sin and go to hell. <verse eid="MRK 9:45-46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 9:47"/>If because of what you see [MTY, PRS] you are tempted to sin, <char style="add">stop looking at those things</char>! Even if you have to gouge out your eye and throw it away [HYP] <char style="add">to avoid sinning, do it! It is good that you not sin and live eternally, even though you lack one of</char> your eyes <char style="add">while you are here on earth</char>. But it is not good that you sin and, as a result, God puts your whole body in hell. <verse eid="MRK 9:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 9:48"/>In that place people suffer forever and the fires are never put out {never go out}.”<verse eid="MRK 9:48"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught that we must endure trials to remain useful to God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 9:49-50">Mark 9:49-50</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 9:49"/>“<char style="add">You must endure difficulties in order that God will be pleased with you. Your difficulties are like</char> a fire <char style="add">that makes things pure</char> [MET]. <char style="add">Your enduring is also like</char> [MET] salt being put <char style="add">on</char> {people putting salt on their} <char style="add">sacrifices to make them pure</char>. <verse eid="MRK 9:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 9:50"/>Salt is useful <char style="add">to put on food</char>, but you cannot [RHQ] make salt to taste salty again if it becomes flavorless [MET]. Similarly, you must remain useful to God, <char style="add">because no one can make you useful to God again if you become useless</char>. You must also live peacefully with each other.”<verse eid="MRK 9:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="MRK 10"/>
  <para style="s1">Some Pharisees asked him if the law permitted a man to divorce his wife. Jesus answered and supported his answer from Scripture.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 10:1-12">Mark 10:1-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 10:1"/>Jesus left ◄that place/Capernaum► <char style="add">with his disciples</char>, and they went through Judea district and on across <char style="add">to the east side of</char> the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>. When crowds gathered around him again, he taught them again, as he customarily did. <verse eid="MRK 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 10:2"/><char style="add">While he was teaching them, some</char> Pharisees approached him and asked him, “Does <char style="add">our Jewish</char> law permit a man to divorce his wife?” They asked that in order to be able to criticize him <char style="add">whether he answered “yes” or “no”</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 10:3"/>He answered them, “What did Moses command your <char style="add">ancestors about a man divorcing his wife</char>?” <verse eid="MRK 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 10:4"/><char style="add">One of</char> them replied, “Moses permitted that a man may write on paper <char style="add">his reason</char> for divorcing <char style="add">his wife</char>, <char style="add">give this paper to her</char>, and then send her away.” <verse eid="MRK 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 10:5"/>Jesus said to them, “It was because your <char style="add">ancestors</char> stubbornly wanted just what they desired that Moses wrote that law for <char style="add">your ancestors</char>, and you <char style="add">are just like them</char>! <verse eid="MRK 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 10:6"/><char style="add">Remember</char> that he <char style="add">also wrote that, when God</char> first created <char style="add">people</char>, he made <char style="add">one</char> man, and <char style="add">one</char> woman <char style="add">to become that man’s wife</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 10:7"/>That explains why <char style="add">God said</char>, ‘When a man <char style="add">and</char> woman marry, they should no longer live with their fathers and mothers <char style="add">after they marry</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 10:8"/>Instead, the two of them shall <char style="add">live together, and they shall</char> become so <char style="add">closely united</char> [MET] <char style="add">that they are like</char> one person.’ Therefore, although the people <char style="add">who marry</char> were two <char style="add">separate persons</char> before, <char style="add">God regards them</char> as one person now, <char style="add">so he wants them to remain married</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 10:9"/>Because that is true, a man must not separate from his <char style="add">wife</char> whom God has joined <char style="add">to him, because God’s plan is for them to remain together</char>!”<verse eid="MRK 10:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 10:10"/>When Jesus and his disciples were alone in a house, they asked him again about this. <verse eid="MRK 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 10:11"/>He said to them, “<char style="add">God considers that a marriage lasts until either the husband or the wife dies, so he considers</char> that any man who divorces his wife and marries another woman is committing adultery, <char style="add">even</char> if he divorces his first wife. <verse eid="MRK 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 10:12"/><char style="add">God also considers</char> a woman who divorces her first husband to be committing adultery if she marries another man.”<verse eid="MRK 10:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus became indignant when he saw his disciples scolding people for bringing children for him to bless them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 10:13-16">Mark 10:13-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 10:13"/>
    <char style="add">One day</char>, some people were bringing children to Jesus in order that he would touch <char style="add">and bless</char> them. But the disciples scolded those people <char style="add">because they thought that Jesus</char> ◄<char style="add">did not want to be bothered spending time with/was not concerned about</char>► <char style="add">children</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 10:14"/>When Jesus saw that, he became angry. He said to the <char style="add">disciples</char>, “Allow the children to come to me! Do not forbid them [DOU]! It is people who <char style="add">are humble and trust as they do</char> who can experience ◄God’s rule <char style="add">in their lives</char>/God taking care of them► [MET]. <verse eid="MRK 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 10:15"/>Note this: Those who do not <char style="add">trustingly</char> allow God to direct <char style="add">their lives</char>, as children <char style="add">do</char>, will not enter the place where God rules.” <verse eid="MRK 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 10:16"/>Then he embraced the children. He also put his hands on them <char style="add">and asked God to</char> bless them.<verse eid="MRK 10:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After a man asked Jesus what he should do in order to live eternally, Jesus told him to sell all his possessions, which astonished the disciples.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 10:17-31">Mark 10:17-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 10:17"/>As Jesus was starting to travel <char style="add">again with his disciples</char>, a <char style="add">young</char> man ran up to him. He knelt before Jesus and then he asked him, “Good teacher, what must I do to have eternal life/in order to live <char style="add">with God</char> eternally?” <verse eid="MRK 10:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 10:18"/>Jesus said to him, “◄You should consider carefully <char style="add">what you are implying</char> (OR, <char style="add">that you are implying that I am God</char>) <char style="add">by</char> calling me good, because only God is good!/Do you realize <char style="add">what you are implying</char> (OR, <char style="add">that you are implying that I am God</char>) <char style="add">by</char> calling me good, because only God is good?► [RHQ] No other person is good <verse eid="MRK 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 10:19"/><char style="add">But to answer your question</char>, you know the commandments <char style="add">of Moses, which will cause you to live eternally if you obey them perfectly</char>. He commanded <char style="add">things such as</char> ‘do not murder anyone, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not ◄testify falsely/lie►, do not cheat anyone, and honor your father and mother’.” <verse eid="MRK 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 10:20"/>The man said to him, “Teacher, I have obeyed all those commandments ever since I was young. <char style="add">So is</char> ◄<char style="add">that enough/there something else that I have not done</char>►?” <verse eid="MRK 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 10:21"/>Jesus looked at him and loved him. He said to him, “There is one thing that you have not <char style="add">yet done</char>. You must go <char style="add">home</char>, sell all that you possess, and then give <char style="add">the money</char> to poor people. <char style="add">As a result</char>, you will be spiritually rich in heaven. After <char style="add">you have done what I have told you</char>, come with me <char style="add">and be my disciple</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 10:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 10:22"/>The man became disappointed when he heard that. He went away sad, because he was very rich <char style="add">and he did not want to give away everything</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 10:23"/>Jesus looked around <char style="add">at the people</char>. Then he exclaimed to his disciples, “It is very difficult for people who are wealthy to <char style="add">decide to</char> let God rule their lives!” <verse eid="MRK 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 10:24"/>The disciples were surprised at what he said. <char style="add">They thought that God favored the rich people, so if God did not save them, he would not save anyone</char>. So Jesus replied again to them, “My dear friends, it is very difficult for anyone <char style="add">to decide</char> to let God rule his life. <verse eid="MRK 10:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 10:25"/>It is impossible for a camel to go through the eye of a needle. It is almost as difficult [HYP] for rich people <char style="add">to decide</char> to let God rule their <char style="add">lives</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 10:26"/>The disciples were very astonished. So they said to each other, “If that is so, ◄it will be unlikely that anyone will be saved {that God will save anyone}!/will <char style="add">God</char> save anyone?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 10:27"/>Jesus looked at them and then he said, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, it is impossible for people <char style="add">to save themselves</char>! But God certainly can <char style="add">save them</char>, because God can do anything!” <verse eid="MRK 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 10:28"/>Peter exclaimed, “<char style="add">You know that</char> we have left behind everything and we have become your disciples. <char style="add">So</char>, ◄<char style="add">what about us/will God &lt;accept us/reward us&gt;</char>►?” <verse eid="MRK 10:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 10:29"/>Jesus replied, “I want you to know this: Those who have left <char style="add">their</char> houses, <char style="add">their</char> brothers, <char style="add">their</char> sisters, <char style="add">their</char> father, <char style="add">their</char> mother, <char style="add">their</char> children, or <char style="add">their</char> plots of ground, to <char style="add">be</char> my <char style="add">disciples</char> and to <char style="add">proclaim</char> the good news, <verse eid="MRK 10:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 10:30"/>will receive in this life 100 times as much <char style="add">as they left behind. That will include houses and people as dear as</char> brothers and sisters and mothers and children, and plots of ground. Furthermore, although people will persecute them <char style="add">here on earth because they believe in me</char>, in the future age <char style="add">they</char> will ◄<char style="add">have</char> eternal life/live <char style="add">with God</char> eternally►. <verse eid="MRK 10:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 10:31"/>But I <char style="add">warn you all</char>: Many of you who <char style="add">now consider yourselves</char> to be very important will be unimportant <char style="add">at that future time</char>, and many of you who <char style="add">now consider yourselves</char> to be unimportant will be very important <char style="add">at that future time</char>!”<verse eid="MRK 10:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">As they were traveling toward Jerusalem, Jesus took the disciples aside and began to tell them again about what was going to happen to him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 10:32-34">Mark 10:32-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 10:32"/>
    <char style="add">Some days later as they continued to travel</char>, Jesus and his disciples were walking on the road that leads up to Jerusalem <char style="add">city</char>. Jesus was walking ahead of them. <char style="add">The disciples/apostles</char> were astonished <char style="add">that he was going to where there were many people who opposed him</char>, and the other people who were with them were afraid <char style="add">about what would happen to him in Jerusalem. Along the way he took the twelve disciples to a place by themselves</char>. Then he began to tell them again about what was going to happen to him, saying, <verse eid="MRK 10:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 10:33"/>“Listen carefully! We are going up to Jerusalem. There the chief priests and the men who teach the Jewish laws will be enabled {someone will help the chief priests and those who teach our <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws} to seize me. Then they will declare that I must die, <char style="add">even though</char> I am the one who came from heaven. Then they will take me to the Roman <char style="add">authorities</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 10:34"/>Those men will ridicule me. They will spit on me. They will ◄scourge me/whip me with a leaded whip.► Then they will kill me. But on the third day after that, I will become alive again!”<verse eid="MRK 10:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After James and John requested to sit on the right and left of Jesus when he rules, Jesus told them what will happen and how they should act.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 10:35-45">Mark 10:35-45</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 10:35"/>
    <char style="add">Along the way</char>, James and John, <char style="add">who were</char> the two sons of Zebedee, approached Jesus and they said to him, “Teacher, please do for us what we will ask you to do!” <verse eid="MRK 10:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 10:36"/>He said to them, “What do you want me to do for you?” <verse eid="MRK 10:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 10:37"/>They said to him, “When you <char style="add">rule</char> gloriously, <char style="add">let us rule with you</char>. Let one of us <char style="add">sit</char> at your right side and one sit at your left side.” <verse eid="MRK 10:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 10:38"/>But Jesus said to them, “You do not understand what you are asking for.” Then he asked them, “Can you endure suffering [MTY] like I am about to suffer? Can you endure being killed [MTY] as I will be killed {people killing you as they will kill me}?” <verse eid="MRK 10:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 10:39"/>They said to him, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, we are able <char style="add">to do that</char>!” Then Jesus said to them, “<char style="add">It is true that</char> you will endure suffering [MTY] like I will suffer, and you will endure being killed as I will be killed {people killing you as they will kill me}. <verse eid="MRK 10:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 10:40"/>But I am not the one who chooses the ones who will sit next to me <char style="add">and rule with me. God will give</char> those places to the ones he appoints.”<verse eid="MRK 10:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 10:41"/>The <char style="add">other</char> ten <char style="add">disciples later</char> heard about what James and John <char style="add">had requested</char>. As a result, they were angry with them <char style="add">because they also wanted to rule with Jesus in the highest positions</char>. <verse eid="MRK 10:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 10:42"/>Then, after Jesus called them all together, he said to them, “You know that those who rule the non-Jews <char style="add">enjoy</char> showing that they are powerful. You also know that officials enjoy commanding others. <verse eid="MRK 10:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 10:43"/>But do not be like them! On the contrary, all those among you who want <char style="add">God to consider them</char> great must become <char style="add">like</char> servants to <char style="add">the rest of</char> you. <verse eid="MRK 10:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 10:44"/>Furthermore, if anyone among you wants <char style="add">God to consider him</char> to be the most important, he must <char style="add">act like</char> a servant for the rest of you. <verse eid="MRK 10:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 10:45"/><char style="add">You should imitate me</char>. Even though I am the one who has come from heaven, I did not come to be served {for others to serve me}. On the contrary, I came in order to serve others and to allow others to kill me, in order that my dying for people would be like a payment to rescue <char style="add">many people from being punished</char> {<char style="add">God punishing them</char>} <char style="add">for their sins</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 10:45"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After a blind man called out and asked Jesus to have mercy on him, Jesus healed him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 10:46-52">Mark 10:46-52</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 10:46"/>
    <char style="add">On the way to Jerusalem, Jesus and the disciples came to Jericho town</char>. Afterwards, while they were leaving Jericho along with a great crowd, a blind man who habitually begged <char style="add">for money</char> was sitting beside the road. His name was Bartimaeus and his father’s name was Timaeus. <verse eid="MRK 10:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 10:47"/>When he heard people say that Jesus from Nazareth <char style="add">was passing by</char>, he shouted, “Jesus! <char style="add">You who are the Messiah</char> descended from <char style="add">King</char> David, ◄be merciful to/help► me!” <verse eid="MRK 10:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 10:48"/>Many people rebuked him and told him that he should be quiet. But he shouted even more, “<char style="add">You who are the Messiah</char> descended from <char style="add">King David</char>, ◄be merciful to/help► me!” <verse eid="MRK 10:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 10:49"/>Jesus stopped and said, “Call him <char style="add">to come over here</char>!” They summoned the blind man, saying, “Jesus is calling you! So cheer up and get up <char style="add">and come</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 10:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 10:50"/>He threw aside his cloak as he jumped up, and he came to Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 10:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 10:51"/>Jesus asked him, “What do you want me to do for you?” The blind man said to him, “Sir, I <char style="add">want to be able</char> to see again!” <verse eid="MRK 10:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 10:52"/>Jesus said to him, “<char style="add">I am</char> healing you <char style="add">because</char> you believed <char style="add">in me</char>. So you may go <char style="add">home</char>!” He could see immediately. And he went with Jesus along the road.<verse eid="MRK 10:52"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="MRK 11"/>
  <para style="s1">They brought a young donkey to Jesus; then Jesus mounted it and rode to Jerusalem with people shouting and praising him as they went along.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 11:1-11">Mark 11:1-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 11:1"/>When they came near to Jerusalem, they came to Bethphage and Bethany <char style="add">villages</char> near Olive <char style="add">Tree</char> Hill. Then Jesus <char style="add">summoned</char> two of his disciples. <verse eid="MRK 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 11:2"/>He said to them, “Go to that village just ahead of you. As soon as you enter it, you will see a donkey that no one has ever ridden, that has been tied {people have tied} up. Untie it, and then bring it <char style="add">to me</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 11:3"/>If anyone says to you, ‘Why are you doing that?’, say, <char style="add">‘Jesus</char>, our Lord, needs <char style="add">to use</char> it. He will send it back here <char style="add">with someone</char> as soon as <char style="add">he no longer needs it</char>.’” <verse eid="MRK 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 11:4"/>So <char style="add">the two disciples</char> went and they found the young donkey. It was tied close to the door <char style="add">of a house</char>, which was beside the street. Then they untied it. <verse eid="MRK 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 11:5"/>Some of the <char style="add">people who were there</char> said to them, “Why are you untying the donkey?” <verse eid="MRK 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 11:6"/>They told them what Jesus had said. So the people permitted them <char style="add">to take the donkey</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 11:7"/>They brought the donkey to Jesus. <char style="add">The disciples</char> put some of their clothes on it <char style="add">in order to make something for him to sit on</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 11:8"/>Many people spread their cloaks on the road <char style="add">to honor him as a king</char>. Others, <char style="add">in order to honor him</char>, spread along the road branches that they cut from <char style="add">palm trees</char> in the fields <char style="add">beside the road</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 11:9"/>The people who were going in front of him and behind him were all shouting <char style="add">things like</char>, “Praise God!” “May God bless this one who comes ◄with his authority/as his representative► [MTY].” <verse eid="MRK 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 11:10"/>“May you be blessed {May <char style="add">God</char> bless you} when you rule <char style="add">like</char> our ancestor <char style="add">King</char> David ruled!” “Praise God who is in the highest heaven!”<verse eid="MRK 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 11:11"/>He entered Jerusalem <char style="add">with them</char>, and then he went into the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>. After he looked around at everything <char style="add">there</char>, he left <char style="add">the city</char> because it was already late <char style="add">in the afternoon</char>. He returned to Bethany with the twelve <char style="add">disciples and slept there</char>.<verse eid="MRK 11:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus cursed a fig tree as a sign of what would happen to the people of Israel.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 11:12-14">Mark 11:12-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 11:12"/>The next day, as Jesus and his disciples were leaving Bethany, Jesus was hungry. <verse eid="MRK 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 11:13"/>He saw from a distance a fig tree with all its leaves, so he went <char style="add">to it</char> to see if he could find any <char style="add">figs</char> on it. But when he came to it, he found only leaves on it. This was because it was not yet time when <char style="add">normal fig trees have ripe</char> figs. <verse eid="MRK 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 11:14"/><char style="add">But to illustrate how God would punish the nation of Israel,</char> he said to the tree, “No one shall ever eat from you again <char style="add">because you will no longer bear figs</char>.” The disciples heard what he said.<verse eid="MRK 11:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus expelled those who were buying and selling goods in the Temple, and taught that the Temple was to be a place of prayer. These actions angered the priests and scribes who, then, looked for a way to kill Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 11:15-19">Mark 11:15-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 11:15"/>Jesus and his disciples went <char style="add">back</char> to Jerusalem. He entered the Temple <char style="add">courtyard. He saw people</char> who were selling and buying <char style="add">animals for sacrifices. They were spoiling the place of worship</char>. He chased those people <char style="add">from the Temple courtyard.</char> He also overturned the tables of those who were giving Temple tax money in exchange for Roman coins. He overturned the seats of the men who were selling doves <char style="add">for sacrifices</char>, <verse eid="MRK 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 11:16"/>and he would not allow anyone who was carrying anything <char style="add">to sell</char> to go through the Temple <char style="add">area</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 11:17"/>Then as he taught those people, he said to them, “It is written {<char style="add">One of the prophets</char> wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures that God said</char>, ‘<char style="add">I want</char> my house to be called {<char style="add">people</char> to call my house} a house where <char style="add">people from</char> all nations may pray’, but you bandits have made it <char style="add">like</char> a cave where you can hide! ◄<char style="add">You know that!/Do you not know that</char>?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 11:18"/>The chief priests and the men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws <char style="add">later</char> heard <char style="add">about what he had done</char>. So they planned how they might kill him, <char style="add">but they knew that it would be difficult</char>, because they realized that the crowd was amazed at what he was teaching and they feared <char style="add">that the people would soon decide that Jesus had more authority over the Temple than they did</char> (OR, <char style="add">feared what the people would do if they tried to arrest Jesus</char>). <verse eid="MRK 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 11:19"/>That evening, <char style="add">Jesus and his disciples</char> left the city <char style="add">and again slept in Bethany</char>.<verse eid="MRK 11:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When Jesus and his disciples passed the fig tree that Jesus had cursed, they saw that it had withered. Jesus used this as an illustration for trusting that God would answer prayer.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 11:20-25">Mark 11:20-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 11:20"/>
    <char style="add">The next</char> morning, while they were going along <char style="add">the road toward Jerusalem, they saw that the fig tree that Jesus had cursed</char> had withered completely. <verse eid="MRK 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 11:21"/>Peter remembered <char style="add">what Jesus had said to the fig tree</char> and he exclaimed to Jesus, “Teacher, look! The fig tree that you cursed has withered!” <verse eid="MRK 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 11:22"/>Jesus replied, “<char style="add">You should not be surprised that God did what I asked</char>! You must trust that God <char style="add">will do whatever you ask him to do</char>! <verse eid="MRK 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 11:23"/><char style="add">Also</char> note this: If anyone says to this hill, ‘Be raised up {Rise up} and then be thrown {throw yourself} into the lake!’ and if he does not doubt <char style="add">that what he asks for will happen</char>, that is, if he believes that what he asks for will happen, <char style="add">God</char> will do it for him. <verse eid="MRK 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 11:24"/>So I tell you, whenever you ask <char style="add">God</char> for something when you pray, believe that you will receive it, and, <char style="add">if you do, God</char> will do it <char style="add">for you</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:24"/><verse number="25-26" style="v" sid="MRK 11:25-26"/>Now, I <char style="add">tell you this also</char>: Whenever you are praying, if you have a grudge against people <char style="add">because they have harmed you</char>, forgive them, in order that your Father in heaven will <char style="add">likewise</char> forgive your sins.”<verse eid="MRK 11:25-26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The chief priests, scribes and elders asked Jesus by what authority he was doing these things. He, then, asked them a question that they would not answer; so he did not answer theirs.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 11:27-33">Mark 11:27-33</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 11:27"/>Jesus and his disciples arrived in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char> in Jerusalem again. While Jesus was walking <char style="add">there, a group consisting of</char> chief priests, <char style="add">some</char> men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws, and elders came to him and they said to him, <verse eid="MRK 11:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 11:28"/>“By what authority are you doing these things? Who authorized you to do things <char style="add">like those you did here yesterday</char>?” <verse eid="MRK 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 11:29"/>Jesus said to them, “I will ask you one question. If you answer me, I will tell you who authorized me to do those things. <verse eid="MRK 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 11:30"/>Did God [MTY] or people <char style="add">authorize</char> John to baptize <char style="add">those who came to him</char>?” <verse eid="MRK 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 11:31"/>They debated among themselves <char style="add">as to what they should answer</char>. They <char style="add">said to each other</char>, “If we say that it was God <char style="add">who authorized</char> him, he will say to us, ‘Therefore, ◄you should have believed what John said!/why did you not believe what John said?► [RHQ]’ <verse eid="MRK 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 11:32"/>On the other hand, if we say that it was people <char style="add">who authorized John, then what will happen to us</char>?” They were afraid <char style="add">to say that about where John got his authority, because they knew that</char> the people <char style="add">would be very angry with them. They knew that</char> all the people truly believed that John was a prophet <char style="add">whom God had sent</char>. <verse eid="MRK 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 11:33"/>So they answered Jesus, “We do not know <char style="add">where John got his authority</char>.” Then Jesus said to them, “<char style="add">Because you did not answer my question, I</char> will not tell you who authorized me to do those things <char style="add">here yesterday</char>.”<verse eid="MRK 11:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="MRK 12"/>
  <para style="s1">After Jesus told the Jewish leaders a parable, they realized that he was accusing them of wanting to kill him, but they feared how the people would react if they arrested Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 12:1-12">Mark 12:1-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 12:1"/>Then Jesus told <char style="add">those Jewish leaders</char> a parable. <char style="add">He wanted to show what God would do to those who rejected the former prophets and himself. He said</char>, “A certain man planted a vineyard. He built a fence around it <char style="add">in order to protect it</char>. He made a stone tank <char style="add">to collect the juice that</char> they would press <char style="add">out of the grapes</char>. He also built a tower <char style="add">for someone to sit in to guard his vineyard</char>. Then he leased the vineyard to some men to care for it and <char style="add">to</char> give him some of the <char style="add">grapes</char> in return. Then he went away to another country. <verse eid="MRK 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 12:2"/>When the time came to harvest the <char style="add">grapes</char>, he sent a servant to the men <char style="add">who were taking care of the vineyard</char> in order to receive from them his share of the grapes that the vineyard had produced. <verse eid="MRK 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 12:3"/>But <char style="add">after the servant arrived</char>, they grabbed him and beat him, and they did not give him any fruit. Then they sent him away. <verse eid="MRK 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 12:4"/>Later the one who owned the vineyard sent another servant to them. But they beat that one on his head, and they insulted him. <verse eid="MRK 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 12:5"/>Later he sent another servant. That man they killed. They mistreated many other servants <char style="add">whom he sent</char>. Some they beat and some they killed. <verse eid="MRK 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 12:6"/>The man still had one other <char style="add">person with him</char>. It was his son. He loved him very much. So, finally he sent his son to them because he thought that they would respect him <char style="add">and give him some of the grapes</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 12:7"/>But <char style="add">when they saw his son coming</char>, those men who were looking after the vineyard said to each other, ‘Look! Here comes the man who will some day inherit the vineyard! So let’s kill him in order that this vineyard will be ours!’ <verse eid="MRK 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 12:8"/>They seized him and killed him. Then they threw his body outside the vineyard. <verse eid="MRK 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 12:9"/>So ◄do you know what the man who owns the vineyard will do?/I will tell you what the man who owns the vineyard will do [RHQ]►. He will come, and he will kill those evil men who were taking care of his vineyard. Then he will arrange for other people to take care of it. <verse eid="MRK 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 12:10"/><char style="add">Now think carefully about these words</char>, which you have read <char style="add">in</char> the Scriptures:</para>
  <para style="p" vid="MRK 12:10">The men who were building the building rejected one stone. But others <char style="add">put that same stone in its proper place, and</char> it has become the most important stone in the building [MET]! <verse eid="MRK 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 12:11"/>The Lord has done this, and we marvel as we look at it.”<verse eid="MRK 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 12:12"/>Then <char style="add">the Jewish leaders</char> realized that he was accusing them when he told this story <char style="add">about what those wicked people did</char>. So they wanted to seize him. But they were afraid of what the crowds <char style="add">would do if they did that</char>. So they left him and went away.<verse eid="MRK 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus foiled the Jewish leaders’ attempt to trap him by their question of whether they should pay taxes to the Roman government.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 12:13-17">Mark 12:13-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 12:13"/>The <char style="add">Jewish leaders</char> sent to <char style="add">Jesus</char> some Pharisees <char style="add">who thought that the Jews should pay only the tax that their own Jewish authorities required people to pay</char>. They also sent some members of the party that supported Herod <char style="add">Antipas and the Roman government</char>. They wanted to make Jesus say something wrong <char style="add">that would make one of those groups very angry with him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 12:14"/>After they arrived, they said to him <char style="add">deceivingly</char>, “Teacher, we know that you <char style="add">teach</char> the truth. We also know that you are not concerned about <char style="add">what</char> people <char style="add">say about you, even if an important person does not like what you say</char>. Instead, you teach truthfully what God wants <char style="add">us to do</char>. So <char style="add">tell us what you think about this matter:</char> Is it right that we pay taxes to the Roman government, or not [MTY]? Should we pay the taxes, or should we not pay them?” <verse eid="MRK 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 12:15"/>Jesus knew that they did not really want to know <char style="add">what God wanted them to do</char>. So he said to them, “◄I <char style="add">know that</char> you are <char style="add">just</char> trying to make me say something wrong for which you can arrest me./Why are you <char style="add">just</char> trying to make me say something wrong for which you can arrest me?► [RHQ] <char style="add">But I will answer your question anyway</char>. Bring me a coin so that I might <char style="add">ask you something after</char> I look at it.” <verse eid="MRK 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 12:16"/>After they brought him a coin, he asked them, “Whose picture is <char style="add">on</char> this <char style="add">coin</char>? And <char style="add">whose</char> name <char style="add">is on it</char>?” They replied, “It is a picture and the name of Caesar, <char style="add">the man who rules the Roman government</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 12:17"/>Then Jesus said to them, “<char style="add">That is correct, so</char> give to the government [MTY] what they <char style="add">require</char>, and give to God what he <char style="add">requires</char>.” They were <char style="add">frustrated at his answer but</char> amazed at what he said, <char style="add">because they were not able to accuse him of anything because of what he said</char>.<verse eid="MRK 12:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus showed from Scripture that the Sadducees were wrong in ridiculing the idea of life after death.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 12:18-27">Mark 12:18-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 12:18"/>
    <char style="add">Men who belong to the</char> Sadducee <char style="add">sect</char> deny that people become alive again after they die. <char style="add">In order to discredit</char> Jesus <char style="add">by ridiculing the idea that people will live again, some of</char> them came to him and asked him, <verse eid="MRK 12:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 12:19"/>“Teacher, Moses wrote for us <char style="add">Jews</char> that if a man who has no children dies, his brother should marry the dead man’s widow. <char style="add">Then if those two bear children, everyone will consider that those children are the</char> children of the man who died, <char style="add">and in that way the dead man will continue to have descendants</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 12:20"/><char style="add">So here is an example</char>. There were seven boys <char style="add">in one family</char>. The oldest one married <char style="add">a woman</char>, but <char style="add">he and his wife</char> did not bear any children. Then he <char style="add">later</char> died. <verse eid="MRK 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 12:21"/>The second <char style="add">brother followed this law and</char> married that woman and he, too, did not bear any children. Then he <char style="add">later</char> died. The third <char style="add">brother did</char> like <char style="add">his other brothers did. But he also did not bear any children, and later died</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 12:22"/>Eventually all seven <char style="add">brothers married that woman, one by one</char>, but they had no children, and one by one they died. Afterwards the woman died, too. <verse eid="MRK 12:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 12:23"/>Therefore, <char style="add">if it were true what some people say, that people will become alive again after they die</char>, whose wife do you think that woman will be when people become alive again? ◄<char style="add">Keep in mind that</char> she was married to all seven <char style="add">brothers</char>!/She was married to all seven <char style="add">brothers, so how can anyone decide</char> [RHQ]?►” <verse eid="MRK 12:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 12:24"/>Jesus replied to them, “You are certainly wrong [RHQ]. You do not know <char style="add">what they have written in</char> the Scriptures <char style="add">about this</char>. You also do not understand God’s power <char style="add">to make people alive again</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 12:25"/><char style="add">That woman will not be the wife of any of them</char>, because when people have become alive again, instead of men having wives and women having husbands, they will be like the angels in heaven, <char style="add">who do not marry</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 12:26"/>But as to people becoming alive again after they die, in the book that Moses <char style="add">wrote, he said something about people who have died</char> that I am sure that you have read [RHQ]. When Moses <char style="add">was looking at</char> the bush <char style="add">that was burning</char>, God said to him, ‘I am the God whom Abraham <char style="add">worships</char> and the God whom Isaac <char style="add">worships</char> and the God whom Jacob <char style="add">worships</char>.’ <verse eid="MRK 12:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 12:27"/>It is not dead people who worship God. It is living people who worship him. <char style="add">Abraham, Isaac and Jacob died long before Moses lived, but God said that they were still worshipping him, so we know their spirits were still alive</char>! So your <char style="add">claim that dead people do not become alive again</char> is very wrong.”<verse eid="MRK 12:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus commended a scribe who accepted Jesus’ assessment of the two greatest commandments, after which they asked Jesus no more questions to trap him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 12:28-34">Mark 12:28-34</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 12:28"/>A man who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws heard their discussion. He knew that Jesus answered the question well. So he stepped forward and asked Jesus, “Which commandment is the most important?” <verse eid="MRK 12:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 12:29"/>Jesus answered, “The most important commandment is this: ‘Listen, <char style="add">you people of</char> Israel! <char style="add">You must worship</char> the Lord, our God, our only Lord. <verse eid="MRK 12:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 12:30"/><char style="add">You must show that you love him in all the ways that you live</char> Show it in all that you want and feel, in all that you think, and in all that you do!’ <verse eid="MRK 12:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 12:31"/>The next <char style="add">most important commandment</char> is: ‘You must love people you come in contact with as much as you love yourself.’ No other commandment is more important than these two!” <verse eid="MRK 12:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 12:32"/>The man said to Jesus, “Teacher, <char style="add">you have answered</char> well. You correctly said that he is the only <char style="add">God</char> and that there is no other God <char style="add">we must worship/obey</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 12:33"/>You have also said correctly that we ◄<char style="add">should/must show that we</char>► love God by all that we are, by all that we think, and by the way that we live. And you have said correctly that we must love ◄people with whom we come in contact/others► as much as we love ourselves. And you have also implied that doing these things <char style="add">pleases God</char> more than offering/giving animals to him or burning <char style="add">other</char> sacrifices.” <verse eid="MRK 12:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 12:34"/>Jesus realized that this man had answered wisely. So he said to him, “<char style="add">I perceive that</char> you will soon <char style="add">decide to let</char> God rule your life.” After that, <char style="add">the Jewish leaders</char> were afraid to ask him any more questions <char style="add">like that to try to trap him</char>.<verse eid="MRK 12:34"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus showed from Scripture that the Messiah must be David’s Lord as well as his descendant.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 12:35-37">Mark 12:35-37</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 12:35"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char>, while he was teaching in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char>, Jesus said <char style="add">to the people</char>, “These men who teach the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws, ◄they must be wrong when they say that the Messiah is <char style="add">merely</char> a descendant of <char style="add">King</char> David!/why do they say that the Messiah is <char style="add">merely</char> a descendant of <char style="add">King</char> David?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 12:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 12:36"/>The Holy Spirit caused David himself to say <char style="add">about the Messiah</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="MRK 12:36">God said to my Lord, ‘Sit here beside me at the place where I will highly honor you! Sit here while I completely defeat your enemies! [MTY]’<verse eid="MRK 12:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 12:37"/>Therefore, <char style="add">because</char> David himself calls <char style="add">the Messiah</char> ‘my Lord,’ ◄the Messiah cannot be <char style="add">just</char> a man who descended <char style="add">from King David!</char>/how can the Messiah be <char style="add">just</char> a man who descended <char style="add">from King David</char>?► [RHQ] <char style="add">He must be much greater than David</char>”! Many people listened to him gladly <char style="add">as he taught those things</char>.<verse eid="MRK 12:37"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus warned them about the scribes’ hypocritical actions.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 12:38-40">Mark 12:38-40</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 12:38"/>While Jesus was teaching <char style="add">the people</char>, he said to them, “Beware that you <char style="add">do not act like</char> the men who teach our <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws. They <char style="add">like people to honor them, so</char> they put on long robes and walk around <char style="add">in order to show people how important they are</char>. They also like people to greet them <char style="add">respectfully</char> in the marketplaces. <verse eid="MRK 12:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 12:39"/><char style="add">They like to sit</char> in the most important seats in our ◄synagogue/Jewish meeting place►. At festivals, <char style="add">they like to sit in</char> the seats where the most honored people sit. <verse eid="MRK 12:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 12:40"/>They ◄swindle/take for themselves► the houses <char style="add">and property</char> of widows by cheating them. <char style="add">Then</char> they pretend <char style="add">that they are good</char> by praying long prayers <char style="add">publicly. God</char> will certainly punish them severely!”<verse eid="MRK 12:40"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus told them that a poor widow’s tiny sacrificial offering was worth more in God’s sight than large amounts of money from rich people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 12:41-44">Mark 12:41-44</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 12:41"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char>, Jesus sat down <char style="add">in the Temple courtyard opposite the boxes in which people put offerings. As he was sitting there</char>, he watched as all the people put money in the box. Many rich people put in large amounts <char style="add">of money</char>. <verse eid="MRK 12:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 12:42"/>Then a poor widow came along and put in two small copper coins, which had a very small value. <verse eid="MRK 12:42"/><verse number="43-44" style="v" sid="MRK 12:43-44"/>He gathered his disciples around him and said to them, “The truth is that these other people have a lot of money, <char style="add">but</char> they gave <char style="add">only a small part of it</char>. But this woman, who is very poor, has put in all the money that she had to pay for the things she needs. <char style="add">So God considers that</char> this poor widow has put more money into the box than all the other people!”<verse eid="MRK 12:43-44"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="MRK 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Jesus prophesied that the Temple would be completely destroyed.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 13:1-2">Mark 13:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 13:1"/>While Jesus was leaving the Temple <char style="add">area</char>, one of his disciples said to him, “Teacher, look at how marvelous <char style="add">these </char> huge stones <char style="add">in the walls are </char> and how wonderful <char style="add">these</char> buildings <char style="add">are</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 13:2"/>Jesus said to him, “<char style="add">Yes</char>, these buildings that you are looking <char style="add">at</char> [RHQ] <char style="add">are wonderful</char>, but I <char style="add">want to tell you something about</char> them. They will <char style="add">soon</char> be destroyed {<char style="add">Foreign invaders</char> will destroy <char style="add">them</char>} <char style="add">completely, with the result that</char> no stone here <char style="add">in this Temple area</char> will be left on top of another stone.”<verse eid="MRK 13:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus taught his disciples about the events that will precede his coming again.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 13:3-37">Mark 13:3-37</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 13:3"/>After they arrived on Olive <char style="add">Tree</char> Hill across <char style="add">the valley</char> from the Temple, Jesus sat down. When Peter, James, John, and Andrew were alone with him, they asked him, <verse eid="MRK 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 13:4"/>“Tell us, when will <char style="add">that</char> happen <char style="add">to the buildings of the Temple? Tell us what will happen that will show us that all these things that God has planned</char> are about to be finished {that <char style="add">God</char> is about to finish all these things <char style="add">that he has planned</char>}.” <verse eid="MRK 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 13:5"/>Jesus replied to them, “<char style="add">I cannot give you a simple answer to your questions. All I will say is</char>, beware that no one deceives you <char style="add">concerning what will happen</char>! <verse eid="MRK 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 13:6"/>Many people will come and say ◄that I sent them/that they have my authority► [MTY]. They will say, ‘I am <char style="add">the Messiah</char>!’ They will deceive many people. <verse eid="MRK 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 13:7"/>Whenever people tell you about wars <char style="add">that are close</char> or wars that are far away, do not be troubled. <char style="add">God has said</char> that those things must happen. <char style="add">But when they do happen, do not think</char> that <char style="add">God</char> will finish all <char style="add">that he has planned</char> at that time! <verse eid="MRK 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 13:8"/><char style="add">Groups who live in various</char> countries will fight each other, and various governments will fight each other. There will also be <char style="add">big</char> earthquakes in various places; and there will be famines. Yet, <char style="add">when these things happen, people will have only just begun to suffer. The first things that they suffer will be like</char> the first pains a woman <char style="add">suffers</char> who is about to bear a child. <char style="add">They will suffer much more after that</char>.<verse eid="MRK 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 13:9"/>Be ready for <char style="add">what people will do to you at that time</char>. Because <char style="add">you believe in</char> me, they will arrest you and put you on trial before the religious councils. ◄In the synagogues/In the Jewish meeting places►, you will be beaten {others will beat you}. You will be put {<char style="add">People will put</char> you} <char style="add">on trial</char> in the presence of high government authorities. As a result, you will be able to tell them <char style="add">about me</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 13:10"/>My good message must be proclaimed {<char style="add">You</char> must proclaim my good message} to <char style="add">people in</char> all people-groups before <char style="add">God finishes all that he has planned</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 13:11"/>And when people arrest you in order to prosecute you <char style="add">because you believe in me</char>, do not worry before that happens about what you will say. Instead, say what <char style="add">God</char> puts into your mind at that time. Then it will not be <char style="add">just</char> you who will be speaking. It will be the Holy Spirit <char style="add">who will be speaking through you</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 13:12"/><char style="add">Other evil things will happen</char>: People <char style="add">who do not believe in me</char> will ◄betray/help others seize► their brothers <char style="add">and sisters</char> in order that <char style="add">the government</char> can execute them. Parents <char style="add">will betray</char> their children, and children will betray their parents so that <char style="add">the government</char> will kill their parents. <verse eid="MRK 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 13:13"/><char style="add">In general</char>, you will be hated by most [HYP] people {most [HYP] people will hate you} because <char style="add">you believe in</char> me. But all you who continue <char style="add">to trust in me strongly</char> until your life is finished will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save all you who continue <char style="add">to trust in me strongly</char> until your life ends}.<verse eid="MRK 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 13:14"/>
    <char style="add">During that time</char> the disgusting <char style="add">thing/person that the prophet Daniel described</char> will enter the Temple. It/He will defile <char style="add">the Temple when he enters it and will cause people to abandon it. When you see it/him standing there</char> where it/he should not be, <char style="add">you should run away quickly</char> (May everyone who is reading this pay attention to <char style="add">this warning from Jesus</char>!) <char style="add">At that time</char> those people who are in Judea <char style="add">district</char> must flee to <char style="add">higher</char> hills. <verse eid="MRK 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 13:15"/>Those people who are outside their houses must not enter their houses in order to get anything <char style="add">before they run away</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 13:16"/>Those who are <char style="add">working</char> in a field must not return <char style="add">to their houses</char> in order to get <char style="add">additional</char> clothes <char style="add">before they flee</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 13:17"/>But I feel very sorry for women who will be pregnant and women who will be nursing their babies in those days, <char style="add">because it will be very difficult for them to run away</char> <verse eid="MRK 13:17"/><verse number="18-19" style="v" sid="MRK 13:18-19"/>In those days people will suffer very severely. People have never suffered like that since the time when God first created the world until now; and people will not <char style="add">suffer that way</char> again. <char style="add">So</char> pray that <char style="add">this painful time</char> will not happen in ◄winter/the rainy season►, <char style="add">when it will be hard to travel</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:18-19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 13:20"/>If the Lord <char style="add">God</char> had not <char style="add">decided that he would</char> shorten that time <char style="add">when people suffer so much</char>, everyone would die. But he has <char style="add">decided to</char> shorten that time because <char style="add">he is concerned about you</char> people whom he has chosen [DOU]. <verse eid="MRK 13:20"/><verse number="21-22" style="v" sid="MRK 13:21-22"/><char style="add">At that time people who will</char> falsely <char style="add">say that they are</char> Messiahs and prophets will appear. Then they will perform many kinds ◄of miracles/of things that ordinary people cannot do► [DOU]. They will even try to deceive <char style="add">you</char> people whom God has chosen, <char style="add">but they will not</char> be able to do that. So at that time if someone says to you, ‘Look, here is the Messiah!’ or <char style="add">if someone says</char>, ‘Look, he is over there!’ do not believe it! <verse eid="MRK 13:21-22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 13:23"/>Be alert! Remember that <char style="add">I</char> have warned you about all this before <char style="add">it happens.</char><verse eid="MRK 13:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 13:24"/>After the time when people suffer like that, the sun will become dark, the moon will not shine, <verse eid="MRK 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 13:25"/>the stars will fall from the sky, and all things in the sky will be shaken {<char style="add">God will cause</char> all things in the sky to shake}. <verse eid="MRK 13:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 13:26"/>Then people will see <char style="add">me</char>, the one who came from heaven, coming through the clouds powerfully and gloriously. <verse eid="MRK 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 13:27"/>Then I will send out my angels in order that they gather together the people whom <char style="add">God</char> has chosen from <char style="add">everywhere, and that includes</char> all the most remote places on earth [IDM, DOU].<verse eid="MRK 13:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 13:28"/>Now I <char style="add">want you to</char> learn something from this parable about <char style="add">the way</char> fig trees <char style="add">grow</char>. <char style="add">In this area</char>, when their buds become tender and their leaves begin to sprout, you know that summer is near. <verse eid="MRK 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 13:29"/>Similarly, when you see <char style="add">what I have just described</char> happening, you yourselves will know that it is very near <char style="add">the time for me to return</char> [MTY]. <char style="add">It will be as though I am</char> already at the door [HEN]. <verse eid="MRK 13:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 13:30"/>Keep this in mind: You have observed the things that I have done and said, but all of those events <char style="add">that I have just told you about</char> will happen before all of you will die. <verse eid="MRK 13:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 13:31"/>You can <char style="add">be certain that</char> these things <char style="add">that I have prophesied</char> will happen. <char style="add">You can be more certain of that than</char> you can <char style="add">be certain that</char> the earth and what is in the sky will stay in place. <verse eid="MRK 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 13:32"/>But no one knows the exact time <char style="add">when I will return</char>. The angels in heaven also do not know. Even <char style="add">I do not know.</char> Only my Father knows. <verse eid="MRK 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 13:33"/>So be ready, <char style="add">like people who are waiting for an important man to come</char>, because you do not know when that time will come <char style="add">when all these events will happen</char>! <verse eid="MRK 13:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 13:34"/>When a man who wants to travel <char style="add">to a distant place</char> is <char style="add">about to</char> leave his house, he tells his servants that they should manage the house. <char style="add">He tells</char> each one what he should do. Then he tells the doorkeeper to be ready <char style="add">for his return</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 13:35"/><char style="add">That man must always be</char> ready, <char style="add">because he does not know whether</char> his master will return in the evening, at midnight, when the rooster crows, or at dawn. <char style="add">Similarly</char>, you also must <char style="add">always</char> be ready, because you do not know <char style="add">when I will return</char>. <verse eid="MRK 13:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 13:36"/><char style="add">May it not happen that</char> when I come suddenly, I will find that you are not ready! <verse eid="MRK 13:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 13:37"/>These words that I am saying to you <char style="add">disciples</char> I am saying to everyone <char style="add">who believes in me: Always</char> be ready!” <char style="add">That is what Jesus warned his disciples</char>.<verse eid="MRK 13:37"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="MRK 14"/>
  <para style="s1">The Jewish leaders planned how they could arrest Jesus without starting a riot.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:1-2">Mark 14:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 14:1"/>It was only two days before the <char style="add">people</char> ◄<char style="add">celebrated/started to celebrate</char>► <char style="add">for one week the</char> festival <char style="add">which they called</char> Passover. During those days they also celebrated the festival of ◄Unleavened Bread/<char style="add">eating</char> bread that had no yeast in it►. The chief priests and the men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws were planning how they could seize Jesus secretly. <char style="add">They wanted to accuse him in front of the Roman authorities</char> so that they would execute him. <verse eid="MRK 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 14:2"/>But they were saying to one another, “We must not <char style="add">do it</char> during the celebration, because, <char style="add">if we do it then</char>, the people will <char style="add">be very angry with us and</char> riot!”<verse eid="MRK 14:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus commended a woman who extravagantly anointed Jesus in anticipation of his death. The chief priests agreed to pay Judas if he would help them seize Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:3-11">Mark 14:3-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 14:3"/>Jesus was at Bethany <char style="add">town</char> in the house of Simon, whom <char style="add">Jesus had healed from</char> leprosy. While they were eating, a woman came <char style="add">to him</char>. <char style="add">She was carrying</char> a stone jar that contained expensive <char style="add">fragrant</char> perfume called nard. She opened the jar and then she poured the perfume on Jesus’ head. <verse eid="MRK 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 14:4"/>One of the people <char style="add">who were present</char> became angry and said to the others, “◄<char style="add">It is terrible that she</char> wasted that perfume!/<char style="add">Why did she</char> waste that perfume?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 14:5"/>It could have been sold {<char style="add">We</char> could have sold it} for ◄a huge amount of money/an amount of money for which a person works for a year►, and then <char style="add">the money</char> could have been given {<char style="add">we</char> could have given <char style="add">the money</char>} to poor people!” So he rebuked her. <verse eid="MRK 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 14:6"/>But Jesus said, “Stop <char style="add">scolding</char> her! She has done to me what I <char style="add">consider to be</char> very appropriate/delightful. So ◄you should not bother her!/why do you bother her?► [RHQ] <verse eid="MRK 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 14:7"/>You will always have poor people among you. So you can help them whenever you want to. But I will not <char style="add">be here among</char> you much longer. <char style="add">So it is good for her to show now that she appreciates me</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 14:8"/><char style="add">It is appropriate that</char> she has done what she was able to do. <char style="add">It is as if she knew that I was going to die soon</char> and has anointed my body for their burying it. <verse eid="MRK 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 14:9"/>I will tell you this: Wherever the good message <char style="add">about me</char> is preached {people preach the good message} throughout the world, what she has done will be told {people will tell others what she has done <char style="add">to me</char>}, and as a result people will remember her.”<verse eid="MRK 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 14:10"/>Then Judas Iscariot (OR, Judas, the man from Kerioth <char style="add">Town</char>) went to the chief priests in order to <char style="add">talk to them about</char> helping them to seize Jesus. He did that <char style="add">even though</char> he was one of the twelve <char style="add">disciples</char> <verse eid="MRK 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 14:11"/>When they heard <char style="add">what he was willing to do for them</char>, they were very happy. They promised that they would give him <char style="add">a large amount of</char> money <char style="add">for doing that. Judas agreed, so they gave him the money</char>. As a result, he <char style="add">began</char> watching for an opportunity ◄to betray Jesus/to enable Jesus’ enemies to seize him►.<verse eid="MRK 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Two disciples followed Jesus’ instructions and prepared the Passover meal.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:12-17">Mark 14:12-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 14:12"/>
    <char style="add">Two days later</char>, when they killed the lambs <char style="add">for the</char> festival at the beginning of the week when <char style="add">people ate</char> bread that had no yeast in it, Jesus’ disciples said to him, “Where do you want us to go and prepare the meal for the Passover <char style="add">celebration</char> in order that you can eat it <char style="add">with us</char>?” <verse eid="MRK 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 14:13"/>So he <char style="add">chose</char> two of his disciples <char style="add">to prepare everything</char>. He said to them, “Go into <char style="add">Jerusalem</char> city. A man will meet you, who will be carrying a large jar full of water. Follow him. <verse eid="MRK 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 14:14"/>When he enters <char style="add">a house</char>, say to the man who owns the house, ‘<char style="add">Our</char> teacher wants us to prepare <char style="add">the meal of</char> the Passover celebration so that he can eat it with us his disciples. ◄Please show us the room that he <char style="add">arranged with you about</char>./Where is the room that he <char style="add">arranged with you about</char>?► [RHQ]’ <verse eid="MRK 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 14:15"/>He will show you a large room that is on the upper floor <char style="add">of the house</char>. It will be furnished and ready <char style="add">for us to eat a meal in it</char>. Then prepare the meal there for us.” <verse eid="MRK 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 14:16"/>So the <char style="add">two</char> disciples left. They went into the city and found <char style="add">everything</char> to be just like he had told them. They prepared the <char style="add">meal for</char> the Passover <char style="add">celebration, and then returned to Jesus and the other disciples</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 14:17"/>When it was evening, Jesus arrived <char style="add">at that house</char> with the twelve <char style="add">disciples</char>.<verse eid="MRK 14:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">During the Passover meal, Jesus prophesied that one disciple would betray him, and he gave them the bread and wine which he said represented his body and blood which would be sacrificed.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:18-26">Mark 14:18-26</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 14:18"/>As they were all sitting there <char style="add">and eating</char>, Jesus said, “Listen carefully to this: One of you will enable my enemies to seize me. Specifically, it is one of you who <char style="add">will do this in spite of the fact that he</char> is eating with me <char style="add">right now</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 14:19"/>The disciples became very sad and they said to him one by one, “Surely ◄it is not I!/I am not the one, am I?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 14:20"/>Then he said to them, “It is one of <char style="add">you</char> twelve <char style="add">disciples</char>, the one who is dipping <char style="add">bread</char> into the <char style="add">sauce in the</char> dish along with me. <verse eid="MRK 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 14:21"/>It is certain that <char style="add">I</char>, the one who came from heaven, will <char style="add">die</char>, because that is what has been {what <char style="add">the prophets</char> have} written about me. But there will be terrible <char style="add">punishment</char> for the man by whom I will be betrayed {who will ◄betray me/help my enemies to seize me►}! In fact, it would be better for that man if he had never been born!”<verse eid="MRK 14:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 14:22"/>While they were eating, he took <char style="add">a flat loaf of</char> bread and thanked God for it. Then he broke it <char style="add">into pieces</char> and gave it to them and said to them, “This <char style="add">bread represents</char> [MET] my body. Take it <char style="add">and eat it</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 14:23"/>Afterwards, he took a cup <char style="add">that contained wine</char> and thanked <char style="add">God for it</char>. Then he gave it to them, and then, as they all drank from it, <verse eid="MRK 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 14:24"/>he said to them, “This <char style="add">wine represents</char> [MET] my blood, which is about to be shed {which is about to flow from my body} <char style="add">when my enemies kill me</char>. With this blood I <char style="add">will sign</char> the agreement <char style="add">that God has made to forgive the sins of</char> many people. <verse eid="MRK 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 14:25"/>I want you to know this: I will not drink any more wine in this way until the time when I drink it with a new <char style="add">meaning</char> when I begin to rule as a king.” <verse eid="MRK 14:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 14:26"/>After they sang a hymn, they went out toward Olive <char style="add">Tree</char> Hill.<verse eid="MRK 14:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus predicted that Peter would deny three times that he knew Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:27-31">Mark 14:27-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 14:27"/>
    <char style="add">While they were on their way</char>, Jesus said to them, “It has been {<char style="add">The prophets</char> have} written <char style="add">in the Scriptures that God said about me</char>, ‘I will kill the shepherd and his sheep will scatter.’ <char style="add">Those words will come true. When they are about to capture me</char>, all of you will leave me and run away. <verse eid="MRK 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 14:28"/>But after I have been made {<char style="add">God</char> has made me} alive again, I will go ahead of you to Galilee <char style="add">district and meet you there</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 14:29"/>Then Peter said to him, “Perhaps all the <char style="add">other disciples</char> will leave you, but not I! I will not <char style="add">leave you</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 14:30"/>Then Jesus said to him, “The truth is that this very night, before the rooster crows a second time, you yourself will deny three times <char style="add">that you know</char> me!” <verse eid="MRK 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 14:31"/>But Peter replied strongly, “Even if they kill me <char style="add">as I defend</char> you, I will never deny <char style="add">that I know</char> you!” And all <char style="add">the other disciples</char> said the same thing.<verse eid="MRK 14:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">While the disciples slept, Jesus prayed that God would spare him from the coming suffering.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:32-42">Mark 14:32-42</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 14:32"/>
    <char style="add">On the way</char>, Jesus and the disciples came to the place that <char style="add">people</char> call Gethsemane. Then he said to <char style="add">some/eight of</char> his disciples, “Stay here while I pray!” <verse eid="MRK 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 14:33"/>Then he took Peter, James, and John with him. He became extremely distressed, and he said to them, <verse eid="MRK 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 14:34"/>“I [SYN] am very sorrowful. <char style="add">It is as if</char> I were about to die. <char style="add">You men</char> remain here and stay awake!” <verse eid="MRK 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 14:35"/>He went a bit further and threw himself on the ground. Then he prayed that if it were possible, he would not <char style="add">have to suffer</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="MRK 14:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 14:36"/>He said, “O my Father, <char style="add">because</char> you are able to do everything, rescue me so that I do not have to suffer <char style="add">now</char> [MTY]! But do not <char style="add">do</char> what I want. Instead, <char style="add">do</char> what you want!” <verse eid="MRK 14:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 14:37"/>Then he returned and found his <char style="add">disciples</char> sleeping. He <char style="add">woke them up and</char> said, “Simon! ◄<char style="add">I am disappointed that</char> you fell asleep and that you were not able to stay awake for just a short time!/<char style="add">Why is it that</char> you fell asleep and that you were not able to stay awake for just one hour?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="MRK 14:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 14:38"/><char style="add">And he said to them</char>, “You want <char style="add">to do what I say</char>, but you are not strong enough [MTY] <char style="add">to actually do it</char>. So keep awake and pray in order that you can resist when <char style="add">something like this</char> tempts you!” <verse eid="MRK 14:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 14:39"/>Then he went away again and prayed again what he prayed before. <verse eid="MRK 14:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 14:40"/>When he returned, he found that they were sleeping again because they were <char style="add">so</char> sleepy that they could not keep their eyes open. <char style="add">Because they were ashamed</char>, they did not know what to say to him <char style="add">when he awakened them</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 14:41"/><char style="add">Then he went and prayed again</char>. He returned a third time; <char style="add">and he found them sleeping again</char>. He <char style="add">woke</char> all of <char style="add">them and</char> said to them, “◄<char style="add">I am disappointed that you are</char> sleeping again!/<char style="add">Why are you</char> sleeping again?► [RHQ] <char style="add">You have slept</char> enough. The time <char style="add">for me to suffer</char> is about to begin. Look! Someone is about to enable sinful men to seize me, the one who came from heaven. <verse eid="MRK 14:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 14:42"/><char style="add">So</char> get up! Let’s go <char style="add">toward him</char> Look! Here comes the one who is enabling them to seize me!”<verse eid="MRK 14:42"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Judas betrayed Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:43-49">Mark 14:43-49</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 14:43"/>While he was still speaking, Judas <char style="add">arrived</char>. <char style="add">Even though he was</char> one of <char style="add">Jesus’</char> twelve <char style="add">disciples</char>, he came <char style="add">to enable Jesus’ enemies to seize him</char>. A crowd who carried swords and clubs was with him. The <char style="add">leaders of</char> the Jewish Council had sent them. <verse eid="MRK 14:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 14:44"/><char style="add">Judas</char>, who was ◄betraying Jesus/helping Jesus’ enemies to seize him►, had <char style="add">previously</char> told this crowd, “The man whom I kiss is the one <char style="add">whom you want. When I kiss him</char>, seize him and lead him away <char style="add">while you guard him</char> carefully.” <verse eid="MRK 14:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 14:45"/>So, when Judas arrived, he immediately went to Jesus and said, “My teacher!” Then he kissed Jesus <char style="add">on his neck/cheek</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 14:46"/>Then <char style="add">the crowd</char> seized Jesus. <verse eid="MRK 14:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 14:47"/>But one of the <char style="add">disciples</char> who was standing nearby drew his short sword. He struck the servant of the high priest with it <char style="add">to kill him, but he only</char> cut off his ear. <verse eid="MRK 14:47"/><verse number="48-49" style="v" sid="MRK 14:48-49"/>Jesus said to them, “◄<char style="add">It is ridiculous that</char> you come <char style="add">here to seize</char> me with swords and clubs, as if I were a bandit!/Have you come <char style="add">here to seize</char> me with swords and clubs, as if I were a bandit [RHQ]?► Day after day I was with you in the Temple <char style="add">courtyard</char> teaching <char style="add">the people</char> Why did you not seize me then? <char style="add">But this is happening</char> in order that <char style="add">what the prophets have written in</char> the Scriptures <char style="add">about me</char> may be fulfilled {may happen}.”<verse eid="MRK 14:48-49"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Mark ran away.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:50-52">Mark 14:50-52</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 14:50"/>All <char style="add">the disciples at once</char> left him and ran away. <verse eid="MRK 14:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 14:51"/>At that time, ◄a young man/I► was following Jesus. He/<char style="add">I was</char> wearing only a linen cloth around his/my body. The crowd seized him/me. <verse eid="MRK 14:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 14:52"/>But, <char style="add">as he/I pulled away from them</char>, he/I left behind the linen cloth <char style="add">in their hands</char>, and then he/I ran away naked.<verse eid="MRK 14:52"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After witnesses accusing Jesus contradicted each other, Jesus said that he was the man who was also God, the Messiah, after which they decided that Jesus must die.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:53-65">Mark 14:53-65</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 14:53"/>The men <char style="add">who had seized</char> Jesus led him away to <char style="add">the house where</char> the supreme priest <char style="add">lived</char>. All of the Jewish Council were gathering <char style="add">there</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 14:54"/>Peter followed Jesus at a distance. He went into the courtyard <char style="add">of the house</char> where the supreme priest <char style="add">lived</char>, and sat there with the men who guarded <char style="add">the house of the supreme priest</char>. He was warming himself beside a fire. <verse eid="MRK 14:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 14:55"/>The chief priests and all the rest of the Jewish council <char style="add">had already</char> tried to find people who would tell lies about Jesus <char style="add">in order that they could convince the Roman authorities</char> to execute him. But they did not succeed, <verse eid="MRK 14:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 14:56"/>because, although many people spoke lies about him, they contradicted each other. <verse eid="MRK 14:56"/><verse number="57" style="v" sid="MRK 14:57"/><char style="add">Finally</char>, some stood up and accused him falsely by saying, <verse eid="MRK 14:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="MRK 14:58"/>“We heard him when he said, ‘I will destroy this Temple that was built by men, and then within three days I will build another temple ◄without help from anyone else/that human hands will not build►.’” <verse eid="MRK 14:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="MRK 14:59"/>But, what <char style="add">some of</char> these men said also did not agree with <char style="add">what others of them said</char>.<verse eid="MRK 14:59"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="60" style="v" sid="MRK 14:60"/>Then the supreme priest <char style="add">himself</char> stood up in front of them and said to Jesus, “Are you not going to reply? What <char style="add">do you say about</char> all the things that they are saying in order to accuse you?” <verse eid="MRK 14:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="MRK 14:61"/>But Jesus was silent and did not reply [DOU]. Then the supreme priest <char style="add">tried again</char>. He asked him, “Are you the Messiah? <char style="add">Do you say that you are</char> ◄the Son of God/the man who is also God►?” <verse eid="MRK 14:61"/><verse number="62" style="v" sid="MRK 14:62"/>Jesus said, “I am. Furthermore, you will see me, the one who came from heaven, <char style="add">ruling</char> beside God, who is completely powerful. <char style="add">You will also see me</char> coming down through the clouds in the sky!” <verse eid="MRK 14:62"/><verse number="63" style="v" sid="MRK 14:63"/><char style="add">In response to Jesus’ words</char>, the supreme priest tore his outer garment. <char style="add">That was their custom to show that he was shocked that Jesus had said that he was equal to God</char>. Then he said, “We certainly do not [RHQ] need any <char style="add">more</char> people who will testify <char style="add">against this man</char>, <verse eid="MRK 14:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="MRK 14:64"/><char style="add">because</char> you have heard what he said against God! <char style="add">He claimed to be equal with God</char> Therefore, what have you decided?” They all said that Jesus was guilty and deserved ◄to be executed/that they should kill him►. <verse eid="MRK 14:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="MRK 14:65"/>Then some of them began spitting on Jesus. They put a blindfold on him, and then they began striking him and saying to him, “<char style="add">If you are</char> a prophet, tell us <char style="add">who hit you</char>!” And those who were guarding Jesus struck him with their hands.<verse eid="MRK 14:65"/></para>
  <para style="s1">As Jesus predicted, Peter denied three times that he knew Jesus.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 14:66-72">Mark 14:66-72</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="66" style="v" sid="MRK 14:66"/>While Peter was outside in the courtyard <char style="add">of the supreme priest’s house</char>, one of the girls who worked for the supreme priest came <char style="add">near him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:66"/><verse number="67" style="v" sid="MRK 14:67"/>When she saw Peter warming himself <char style="add">beside the fire</char>, she looked at him <char style="add">closely</char>. Then she said, “You also were with Jesus, that man from Nazareth <char style="add">town</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 14:67"/><verse number="68" style="v" sid="MRK 14:68"/>But he denied it by saying, “I do not know or understand [DOU] what you are talking about!” Then he went away <char style="add">from there</char> to the gate <char style="add">of the courtyard</char>. <verse eid="MRK 14:68"/><verse number="69" style="v" sid="MRK 14:69"/><char style="add">The </char> servant girl saw him there and said to the people who were standing nearby, “This man is one of <char style="add">those who have been with that man they arrested</char>.” <verse eid="MRK 14:69"/><verse number="70" style="v" sid="MRK 14:70"/>But he denied it again. After a little while, one of those who were standing there said to Peter again, “<char style="add">The way you speak shows that</char> you also are from Galilee <char style="add">district</char>. So it is certain that you are one of those <char style="add">who accompanied Jesus!</char>” <verse eid="MRK 14:70"/><verse number="71" style="v" sid="MRK 14:71"/>But he began to exclaim, “I do not know the man that you are talking about! Because God knows that I am speaking truthfully, may he punish me <char style="add">if I am lying</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 14:71"/><verse number="72" style="v" sid="MRK 14:72"/>Immediately the rooster crowed a second time. Then Peter remembered what Jesus had said to him <char style="add">before</char>, “Before the rooster crows a second time, you will deny three times <char style="add">that you know me.” When he realized that he had denied it three times</char>, he started crying.<verse eid="MRK 14:72"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="MRK 15"/>
  <para style="s1">In the governor Pilate’s presence Jesus refused to answer accusations against him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 15:1-5">Mark 15:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 15:1"/>Very early in the morning the chief priests met together with <char style="add">the rest of</char> the Jewish council, <char style="add">in order to decide how to accuse Jesus before the Roman governor. Their guards</char> tied Jesus’ hands <char style="add">again</char>. They took him to <char style="add">the house of</char> Pilate, <char style="add">the governor, and they started to accuse him, saying</char> “<char style="add">Jesus is claiming that he is a king!</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 15:2"/>Pilate asked Jesus, “Do you <char style="add">claim to be</char> the king of the Jews?” Jesus answered him, “You yourself have said so.” <verse eid="MRK 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 15:3"/>Then the chief priests claimed that Jesus had done many bad things. <verse eid="MRK 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 15:4"/>So Pilate asked him again, “Don’t you have anything to say? Listen to how many bad things they are saying that you <char style="add">have done</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 15:5"/>But <char style="add">even though Jesus was not guilty</char>, he did not say anything more. The result was that Pilate was very much surprised.<verse eid="MRK 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">At the crowd’s insistence, Pilate released a criminal, and gave orders that Jesus should be crucified.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 15:6-15">Mark 15:6-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 15:6"/>It was the governor’s custom <char style="add">each year</char> during the <char style="add">Passover</char> celebration to release <char style="add">one person who was in prison. He customarily released</char> whichever prisoner the people requested. <verse eid="MRK 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 15:7"/><char style="add">At that time</char> there was a man called Barabbas who had been {whom <char style="add">the soldiers had</char>} <char style="add">put in prison with some other men</char>. Those men had murdered <char style="add">some soldiers</char> when they rebelled <char style="add">against the Roman government</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 15:8"/>A crowd approached <char style="add">Pilate</char> and asked him <char style="add">to release someone</char>, just like he customarily did for them <char style="add">during the Passover celebration</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 15:9"/>Pilate answered them, “Would you like me to release for you the <char style="add">man whom you</char> Jewish <char style="add">people say is your</char> king?” <verse eid="MRK 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 15:10"/><char style="add">He asked this</char> because he realized what the chief priests were wanting to do. They were accusing Jesus because they were jealous of him <char style="add">because many people were becoming his disciples</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 15:11"/>But the chief priests urged the crowd <char style="add">to request</char> that Pilate release Barabbas for them instead <char style="add">of Jesus</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 15:12"/>Pilate said to them again, “<char style="add">If I release Barabbas</char>, what do you want me to do with the man whom <char style="add">some of</char> you Jews say is <char style="add">your</char> king?” <verse eid="MRK 15:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 15:13"/>Then they shouted again, “<char style="add">Command that your soldiers</char> crucify him!” <verse eid="MRK 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 15:14"/>Then Pilate said to them, “Why? What crime has he committed?” But they shouted even louder, “<char style="add">Command your soldiers to</char> crucify him!” <verse eid="MRK 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 15:15"/>So, because Pilate wanted to please the crowd, he released Barabbas for them. Then, after <char style="add">his soldiers</char> had whipped Jesus with leather straps into which they had fastened metal pieces, <char style="add">Pilate told the soldiers to take him away</char> in order that he would be crucified {they would crucify him}.<verse eid="MRK 15:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The soldiers ridiculed Jesus as being a king.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 15:16-20">Mark 15:16-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 15:16"/>The soldiers took Jesus into the <char style="add">courtyard of the</char> palace <char style="add">where Pilate lived</char>. That place was the government headquarters. Then they summoned the whole ◄cohort/group of soldiers► <char style="add">who were on duty there</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 15:17"/><char style="add">After the soldiers gathered together</char>, they put a purple robe on Jesus. Then they placed on his head a crown that they made from <char style="add">branches of</char> thornbushes. <char style="add">They did those things in order to ridicule him by pretending that he was a king</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 15:18"/>Then they greeted him <char style="add">like they would greet a king, in order to ridicule him</char>, saying, “Hooray for the King <char style="add">who rules</char> the Jews!” <verse eid="MRK 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 15:19"/>They repeatedly struck his head with a reed and spat on him. By kneeling down, they <char style="add">pretended to honor</char> him. <verse eid="MRK 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 15:20"/>When they had finished ridiculing him, they pulled off the purple robe. They put his own clothes on him, and then they led him outside <char style="add">of the city</char> in order to nail him to a cross.<verse eid="MRK 15:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After they crucified Jesus the soldiers gambled for his clothing.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 15:21-24">Mark 15:21-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 15:21"/>
    <char style="add">After Jesus carried his cross a short distance</char>, a man named Simon from Cyrene <char style="add">city came along</char>. He was the father of Alexander and Rufus. He was passing by while he was returning <char style="add">home</char> from outside <char style="add">the city. The soldiers</char> compelled Simon to carry the cross <char style="add">for Jesus</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 15:22"/>They brought them both to a place that they <char style="add">call</char> Golgotha. That name means, ‘a place <char style="add">like</char> a skull’. <verse eid="MRK 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 15:23"/>Then they tried to give Jesus wine that was {that they} mixed with <char style="add">medicine called</char> myrrh. <char style="add">They wanted him to drink it so that he would not feel so much pain when they crucified him</char>. But he did not drink it. <verse eid="MRK 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 15:24"/><char style="add">Some</char> of the <char style="add">soldiers took his clothes</char>. Then they nailed him to a cross. Afterwards, they divided his clothes among themselves by gambling with <char style="add">something like</char> dice. They did this <char style="add">in order to determine</char> which <char style="add">piece of clothing</char> each one would get.<verse eid="MRK 15:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">People passing by, as well as the Jewish leaders and two criminals crucified with Jesus, insulted him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 15:25-32">Mark 15:25-32</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 15:25"/>It was nine o’clock in the morning when they crucified him. <verse eid="MRK 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 15:26"/>They <char style="add">attached to the cross above Jesus’ head</char> a sign on which it had been written {someone had written} the reason why <char style="add">they were nailing him to the cross</char>. <char style="add">But all</char> that it said was, “The King of the Jews.” <verse eid="MRK 15:26"/><verse number="27-28" style="v" sid="MRK 15:27-28"/>They also nailed to crosses two men who were bandits. They nailed one to a cross at the right side <char style="add">of Jesus</char> and one to a cross at the left side <char style="add">of Jesus</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:27-28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 15:29"/>The people who were passing by insulted him by shaking their heads as <char style="add">if here were an evil man</char>. They said, “Aha! You said that you would destroy the Temple and then you would build it again within three days. <verse eid="MRK 15:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 15:30"/><char style="add">If you could do that, then</char> rescue yourself by coming down from the cross!” <verse eid="MRK 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 15:31"/>The chief priests, along with the men who taught the <char style="add">Jewish</char> laws, also <char style="add">wanted to</char> make fun of Jesus. So they said to each other, “He <char style="add">claims to have</char> saved others <char style="add">from their sicknesses</char> [IRO] but he cannot save himself! <verse eid="MRK 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 15:32"/>He said, ‘I am the Messiah, I am the King who <char style="add">rules the people of</char> Israel.’ <char style="add">If his words are true</char>, he should come down now from the cross! Then we will believe <char style="add">him</char>!” The <char style="add">two</char> men who were crucified beside him also insulted him.<verse eid="MRK 15:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">As several women who had accompanied Jesus watched, he died, after which the Temple curtain split into two parts, and the Roman officer pronounced that Jesus was the Son of God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 15:33-41">Mark 15:33-41</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 15:33"/>At noon the whole land became dark, <char style="add">and it stayed dark</char> until three o’clock in the afternoon. <verse eid="MRK 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 15:34"/>At three o’clock Jesus shouted loudly, “Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani?” That means, “My God, my God, why have you deserted me?” <verse eid="MRK 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 15:35"/>When some of the people who were standing there heard <char style="add">the word ‘Eloi’, misunderstanding it</char>, they said, “Listen! He is calling for <char style="add">the prophet</char> Elijah!” <verse eid="MRK 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 15:36"/>One of them ran and filled a sponge with sour wine. He placed it on <char style="add">the tip of</char> a reed, and then he <char style="add">held it</char> up for <char style="add">Jesus</char> to suck out <char style="add">the wine that was in</char> it. <char style="add">While he was doing that, someone</char> said, “Wait! Let’s see whether Elijah will come to take him down <char style="add">from the cross</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 15:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 15:37"/>And then, after Jesus shouted loudly, he stopped breathing <char style="add">and died</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 15:38"/><char style="add">At that moment</char> the <char style="add">heavy thick</char> curtain that closed off <char style="add">the most holy place in</char> the Temple split into two pieces from top to bottom. <char style="add">That showed that ordinary people could now go into the presence of God</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 15:39"/>The officer who supervised the soldiers <char style="add">who nailed Jesus to the cross</char> was standing in front of Jesus. When he saw how Jesus died, he exclaimed, “Truly, this man was the man who was also God!” <verse eid="MRK 15:39"/><verse number="40-41" style="v" sid="MRK 15:40-41"/>There were also some women there, watching these events from a distance. They had accompanied Jesus when he was in Galilee <char style="add">district</char>, and they had provided what he needed. They had come with him to Jerusalem. Among those women was Mary from Magdala <char style="add">town</char>. There was <char style="add">another</char> Mary, who was the mother of the younger James and of Joses. There was also Salome.<verse eid="MRK 15:40-41"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Several women watched as Joseph and others buried Jesus’ body in a cave after getting permission from Pilate.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 15:42-47">Mark 15:42-47</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42-43" style="v" sid="MRK 15:42-43"/>When evening was near, <char style="add">a man named</char> Joseph from Arimathea <char style="add">town came there</char>. He was a member of the <char style="add">Jewish</char> council, one whom everyone respected. He was also one of those who had been waiting expectantly for the <char style="add">time when</char> God <char style="add">would send</char> his king to begin to rule. <char style="add">He knew that, according to Jewish law, people’s bodies had to be buried</char> {<char style="add">someone had to bury people’s bodies</char>} <char style="add">on the day they died. He also realized that</char> it was the day when <char style="add">people</char> prepared <char style="add">things for</char> ◄<char style="add">the Jewish day of rest/the Sabbath</char>►, <char style="add">and that the Sabbath would start when the sun set</char>. So he became courageous and went to Pilate and asked Pilate <char style="add">to permit him to take</char> the body of Jesus <char style="add">down from the cross and bury it immediately</char>. <verse eid="MRK 15:42-43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 15:44"/>Pilate was surprised <char style="add">when he heard that</char> Jesus was already dead. So he summoned the officer who was in charge of the soldiers <char style="add">who crucified Jesus</char>, and he asked him if <char style="add">Jesus</char> had already died. <verse eid="MRK 15:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 15:45"/>When the officer told <char style="add">Pilate that Jesus was dead</char>, Pilate allowed Joseph <char style="add">to take away</char> the body. <verse eid="MRK 15:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 15:46"/>After Joseph bought a linen cloth, he <char style="add">and others</char> took <char style="add">Jesus’ body down from the cross</char>. They wrapped it in the linen cloth and laid it in a tomb that <char style="add">previously</char> had been dug out of the rock <char style="add">cliff</char>. Then they rolled a <char style="add">huge flat</char> stone in front of the entrance to the tomb. <verse eid="MRK 15:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 15:47"/>Mary <char style="add">from</char> Magdala and Mary the mother of Joses were watching where Jesus’ <char style="add">body</char> was placed {where they placed Jesus’ <char style="add">body</char>}.<verse eid="MRK 15:47"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="MRK 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Two days later several women were astonished to find Jesus’ tomb empty.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 16:1-8">Mark 16:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 16:1"/>
    <char style="add">On Saturday evening</char> when ◄the Sabbath/the Jewish day of rest► had ended, Mary <char style="add">from</char> Magdala, Mary the mother of the <char style="add">younger</char> James, and Salome bought fragrant ointment. <char style="add">The Jews had a custom of</char> anointing bodies <char style="add">before they buried them, and the women wanted to follow this custom</char>. <verse eid="MRK 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 16:2"/>So very early on Sunday, <char style="add">just after</char> the sun rose, they <char style="add">took the fragrant ointment</char> and started toward the tomb. <verse eid="MRK 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 16:3"/><char style="add">While they were going there</char>, they were saying to each other, “Who will roll away for us the stone <char style="add">that blocks</char> the entrance of the tomb?” <verse eid="MRK 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 16:4"/><char style="add">After they arrived</char>, they looked up and saw that the stone had <char style="add">already</char> been rolled away {that someone had <char style="add">already</char> rolled away the stone}. <char style="add">They were surprised because it</char> would have been difficult to move such a huge stone. <verse eid="MRK 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 16:5"/>They entered the tomb and saw <char style="add">an angel who looked like</char> a young man. He was sitting at the right side <char style="add">of the cave</char>. He was wearing a <char style="add">shining</char> white robe. As a result, they were astonished. <verse eid="MRK 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 16:6"/>The young man said to them, “Do not be astonished! I <char style="add">know that</char> you are looking for Jesus, the man from Nazareth, who was nailed to a cross {whom they nailed to a cross}. But he has become alive again! He is not here! Look! <char style="add">Here is</char> the place where they placed his <char style="add">body</char>. <verse eid="MRK 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 16:7"/>But, instead <char style="add">of remaining here</char>, go and tell his disciples. Particularly <char style="add">be sure</char> that you tell Peter. Tell them, ‘<char style="add">Jesus</char> is going ahead of you to Galilee <char style="add">district</char>, and you will see him there, just like he told you <char style="add">previously’</char>!” <verse eid="MRK 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 16:8"/>The women went outside and ran from the tomb. They were trembling <char style="add">because they were afraid</char>, and they were astonished. But they did not say anything to anyone <char style="add">about this</char> while they were going, because they were afraid.<verse eid="MRK 16:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus rebuked the disciples for not believing the reports of his being alive again.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 16:9-14">Mark 16:9-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 16:9"/>[When Jesus became alive <char style="add">again</char> early on Sunday morning, he appeared first to Mary <char style="add">from</char> Magdala <char style="add">town</char>. She was the woman from whom he had <char style="add">previously</char> expelled seven evil spirits. <verse eid="MRK 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 16:10"/>She went to those who had been with <char style="add">Jesus</char>, while they were mourning and crying. She told them <char style="add">what she had seen</char>. <verse eid="MRK 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 16:11"/>But when she told them that Jesus was alive again and that she had seen him, they refused to believe it. <verse eid="MRK 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 16:12"/>Later <char style="add">that day</char>, Jesus appeared to two of <char style="add">his disciples</char> while they were walking <char style="add">from Jerusalem to their homes in</char> the <char style="add">surrounding</char> area. <char style="add">But they did not recognize him quickly because</char> he looked very different. <verse eid="MRK 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 16:13"/><char style="add">After they recognized him</char>, those two went back <char style="add">to Jerusalem. They told his other followers what had happened</char>, but they did not believe it. <verse eid="MRK 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 16:14"/>Later he appeared to the eleven <char style="add">apostles</char> while they were eating. He rebuked them because they had stubbornly refused to believe <char style="add">the reports of</char> those who saw him after he had become alive again.<verse eid="MRK 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Miracles began to happen after Jesus instructed his disciples to preach the gospel everywhere and he told them that miracles would accompany their ministry.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="MRK 16:15-20">Mark 16:15-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 16:15"/>
    <char style="add">Later</char> he said to them, “Go into the whole world and preach the good message to everyone! <verse eid="MRK 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 16:16"/>Everyone who believes <char style="add">your message</char> and who is baptized will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save}. But everyone who does not believe it will be condemned {<char style="add">God</char> will condemn}. <verse eid="MRK 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 16:17"/>Those who believe <char style="add">my good message</char> will perform miracles. Specifically, by my power they will expel evil spirits. They will speak in languages that they have not learned. <verse eid="MRK 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 16:18"/>If they pick up snakes <char style="add">accidentally</char> or if they drink any poisonous <char style="add">liquid accidentally</char>, they will not be hurt. <char style="add">Whenever</char> they put their hands on sick <char style="add">people in order that God will heal them</char>, those sick people will become well.”<verse eid="MRK 16:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 16:19"/>After the Lord Jesus had said this to <char style="add">the disciples, he was taken</char> {<char style="add">God</char> took him} up into heaven. Then he sat down on his throne beside God <char style="add">to rule with him</char>. <verse eid="MRK 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 16:20"/><char style="add">As for the disciples</char>, they went out <char style="add">from Jerusalem, and then they preached everywhere. Wherever they went</char>, the Lord enabled them to perform miracles. <char style="add">By doing that</char>, he showed people that God’s message is true.<verse eid="MRK 16:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="MRK 16"/>
</usx>
