<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="NUM" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">NUMBERS</para>
  <para style="toc1">Numbers</para>
  <para style="toc2">Numbers</para>
  <para style="toc3">Num</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book gives the account of the Israeli people after they escaped from Egypt. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Numbers</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="NUM 1"/>
  <para style="s1">The men of Israel were counted</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 1:1"/>In April of the year after the Israeli people left Egypt, Yahweh spoke to Moses/me while he/I was in the Sacred Tent, in the Sinai Desert. Yahweh said to him/me, <verse eid="NUM 1:1"/><verse number="2-3" style="v" sid="NUM 1:2-3"/>“I want you and Aaron to determine how many Israeli men are able to fight in battles. Write down the names of all the men who are at least 20 years old, and write down the names of their clans and families. <verse eid="NUM 1:2-3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 1:4"/><char style="add">I have chosen</char> one man from each of the tribes to help you to do this. Each one will be a leader of his clan.<verse eid="NUM 1:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5-15" style="v" sid="NUM 1:5-15"/>Their names are:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Elizur, the son of Shedeur, from the tribe of Reuben;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Shelumiel, the son of Zurishaddai, from the tribe of Simeon;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Nahshon, the son of Amminadab, from the tribe of Judah;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Nethanel, the son of Zuar, from the tribe of Issachar;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Eliab, the son of Helon, from the tribe of Zebulun;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Elishama, the son of Ammihud, from the tribe of Joseph’s son Ephraim;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Gamaliel, the son of Pedahzur, from the tribe of Joseph’s son Manasseh;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Abidan, the son of Gideoni, from the tribe of Benjamin;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Ahiezer, the son of Ammishaddai, from the tribe of Dan;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Pagiel, the son of Ocran, from the tribe of Asher;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Eliasaph, the son of Deuel, from the tribe of Gad;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:5-15">Ahira, the son of Enan, from the tribe of Naphtali.”<verse eid="NUM 1:5-15"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 1:16"/>Those were the men whom Yahweh chose from the people. They were leaders of their tribes. They were the chief men of the clans of the Israeli people.<verse eid="NUM 1:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 1:17"/>Aaron and Moses/I summoned all these leaders, <verse eid="NUM 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 1:18"/>and they gathered all of the people together on that same day. They listed/wrote down the names of all the men who were at least 20 years old, and with their names they wrote the names of their clans and their family groups <verse eid="NUM 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 1:19"/>just as Moses/I had commanded. They wrote the names while ◄the Israelis/we► were there in the Sinai Desert.<verse eid="NUM 1:19"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20-43" style="v" sid="NUM 1:20-43"/>This is a list of the number of men who were at least 20 years old and able to fight in battles, and the names of their tribes:</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">There were 46,500 men from the tribe of Reuben (who was Jacob’s oldest son);</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 59,300 men from the tribe of Simeon;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 45,560 men from the tribe of Gad;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 74,600 men from the tribe of Judah;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 54,400 men from the tribe of Issachar;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 57,400 men from the tribe of Zebulun;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 40,500 men from the tribe of Ephraim;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 32,200 men from the tribe of Manasseh;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 35,400 men from the tribe of Benjamin;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 62,700 men from the tribe of Dan;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 41,500 men from the tribe of Asher;</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 1:20-43">there were 53,400 men from the tribe of Naphtali.<verse eid="NUM 1:20-43"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44-45" style="v" sid="NUM 1:44-45"/>That was the number of men from each tribe that Aaron and Moses/I and the twelve leaders of the tribes of Israel listed, along with the names of their clans. <verse eid="NUM 1:44-45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="NUM 1:46"/>The total was 603,550 men.<verse eid="NUM 1:46"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="NUM 1:47"/>But this number did not include the names of the men of the tribe of Levi, <verse eid="NUM 1:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="NUM 1:48"/>because Yahweh had said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 1:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="NUM 1:49"/>“When you ◄count/write the names of► the men of the tribes of Israel, do not count the men in the tribe of Levi. <verse eid="NUM 1:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="NUM 1:50"/>Appoint the male descendants of Levi to take care of the Sacred Tent and the chest inside it that contains <char style="add">the tablets on which are written</char> the Ten Commandments. They must also take care of the other things that are inside the tent. <char style="add">When you travel</char>, they are the ones who must carry the tent and all the things that are inside it, and they must take care of it and set up their tents around it. <verse eid="NUM 1:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="NUM 1:51"/>Whenever it is time for all of you to move <char style="add">to another location</char>, the descendants of Levi are the ones who must dismantle the tent. And when it is time to stop traveling, they are the ones who must set up the Sacred Tent again. Any other person who goes near the Sacred Tent <char style="add">to do this work</char> must be executed. <verse eid="NUM 1:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="NUM 1:52"/>The people of each Israeli tribe must set up their tents in their own area, and they must set up a flag/banner that represents their tribe. <verse eid="NUM 1:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="NUM 1:53"/>But the male descendants of Levi must set up their tents around the Sacred Tent, in order to protect the other Israeli people from being punished [MTY] by Yahweh <char style="add">for coming close to the Sacred Tent</char>. The descendants of Levi are the ones who must stand around the Sacred Tent to guard it.”<verse eid="NUM 1:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="NUM 1:54"/>So the Israeli people did everything just like Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="NUM 1:54"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="NUM 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Instructions for setting up the Israeli camp</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 2:1"/>Then Yahweh said this to Aaron and Moses/me: <verse eid="NUM 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 2:2"/>“When the Israelis set up their tents, they should set them up in areas that surround the Sacred Tent, but not close to it. The people of each tribe must set up their tents in a different area. Each tribe must erect in that area a banner of their own clan and a flag that represents their tribe.<verse eid="NUM 2:2"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3-4" style="v" sid="NUM 2:3-4"/>The people of the tribes of Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun must set up their tents on the east side of the Sacred Tent, close to their tribal flags. These are the names of the leaders of those tribes and the number of soldiers whom they will lead:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 2:3-4">Nahshon, the son of Amminadab, will be the leader of the 74,600 men of the tribe of Judah.<verse eid="NUM 2:3-4"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="5-6" style="v" sid="NUM 2:5-6"/>Nethanel, the son of Zuar, will be the leader of the 54,500 men of the tribe of Issachar.<verse eid="NUM 2:5-6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7-8" style="v" sid="NUM 2:7-8"/>Eliab, the son of Helon, will be the leader of the 57,400 men of the tribe of Zebulun.<verse eid="NUM 2:7-8"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 2:9"/>So there will be 86,400 troops on the east side <char style="add">of the Sacred Tent</char>. Whenever the Israelis move to a new location, those three tribes must go in front of the others.<verse eid="NUM 2:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="10-11" style="v" sid="NUM 2:10-11"/>The tribes of Reuben, Simeon, and Gad must set up their tents on the south side of the Sacred Tent, close to their tribal flags. These are the names of the leaders of those tribes and the number of men whom they will lead:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 2:10-11">Elizur, the son of Shedeur, will be the leader of the 46,500 men of the tribe of Reuben.<verse eid="NUM 2:10-11"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="12-13" style="v" sid="NUM 2:12-13"/>Shelumiel, the son of Zurishaddai, will be the leader of the 59,300 men of the tribe of Simeon.<verse eid="NUM 2:12-13"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="14-15" style="v" sid="NUM 2:14-15"/>Eliasaph, the son of Deuel, will be the leader of the 45,650 men of the tribe of Gad.<verse eid="NUM 2:14-15"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 2:16"/>So there will be 151,450 troops on the south side of the Sacred Tent. Those three tribes will follow the first group <char style="add">when the Israelis travel</char>.<verse eid="NUM 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 2:17"/>Behind that group will walk the descendants of Levi, who will carry the Sacred Tent. The Israelis will march in the same order that they always set up their tents. Each tribe will carry its own flag.<verse eid="NUM 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="18-19" style="v" sid="NUM 2:18-19"/>The tribes of Ephraim, Manasseh, and Benjamin must set up their tents on the west side of the Sacred Tent, close to their tribal flags. These are the names of the leaders of those tribes and number of men whom they will lead:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 2:18-19">Elishama, the son of Ammihud, will be the leader of the 40,500 men of the tribe of Ephraim.<verse eid="NUM 2:18-19"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="20-21" style="v" sid="NUM 2:20-21"/>Gamaliel, the son of Pedahzur, will be the leader of the 32,200 men of the tribe of Manasseh.<verse eid="NUM 2:20-21"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="22-23" style="v" sid="NUM 2:22-23"/>Abidan, the son of Gideoni, will be the leader of the 35,400 men of the tribe of Benjamin.<verse eid="NUM 2:22-23"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 2:24"/>So there will be 108,100 troops on the west side of the Sacred Tent. Those three tribes will follow the second group, <char style="add">behind the descendants of Levi</char>.<verse eid="NUM 2:24"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25-26" style="v" sid="NUM 2:25-26"/>The tribes of Dan, Asher, and Naphtali must set up their tents on the north side of the Sacred Tent, close to their tribal flags. These are the names of the leaders of those tribes and the number of men whom they will lead:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 2:25-26">Ahiezer, the son of Ammishaddai, will be the leader of the 62,700 men of the tribe of Dan.<verse eid="NUM 2:25-26"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="27-28" style="v" sid="NUM 2:27-28"/>Pagiel, the son of Ocran, will be the leader of the 41,500 men of the tribe of Asher.<verse eid="NUM 2:27-28"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="29-30" style="v" sid="NUM 2:29-30"/>Ahira, the son of Enan, will be the leader of the 53,400 men of the tribe of Naphtali.<verse eid="NUM 2:29-30"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 2:31"/>So there will be 157,600 troops on the north side of the Sacred Tent. Those three tribes will be last. They must carry their own flags when the Israelis travel.”<verse eid="NUM 2:31"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 2:32"/>So there were 603,550 Israeli men who were able to fight who were listed according to their families’ ancestors. <verse eid="NUM 2:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 2:33"/>But just as Yahweh had commanded, the names of the descendants of Levi were not included.<verse eid="NUM 2:33"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 2:34"/>The Israelis did everything that Yahweh had told Moses/me. They set up their tents close to their tribal flags, and when they traveled <char style="add">to a new location, they walked</char> with their own clans and family groups.<verse eid="NUM 2:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="NUM 3"/>
  <para style="s1">The sons of Aaron</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 3:1"/>These are some of the things that happened to Aaron and Moses/me when Yahweh spoke to Moses/me on Sinai Mountain.<verse eid="NUM 3:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 3:2"/>Aaron’s four sons were Nadab the oldest, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. <verse eid="NUM 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 3:3"/>They were appointed [MTY] (OR, Moses/I appointed them) to be priests. <verse eid="NUM 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 3:4"/>But, while Yahweh was watching, Nadab and Abihu died in the Sinai Desert because they burned <char style="add">incense</char> in a manner that was different from what Yahweh had commanded. They had no sons, so Eleazar and Ithamar were the <char style="add">only</char> sons of Aaron who <char style="add">were left to be</char> priests, along with their father Aaron.<verse eid="NUM 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 3:5"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 3:6"/>“Bring <char style="add">the men of</char> the tribe of Levi and present them to Aaron, in order that they may assist him. <verse eid="NUM 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 3:7"/>They will serve Aaron and all the other Israeli people, while they do their work inside the Sacred Tent and outside it. <verse eid="NUM 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 3:8"/>They must serve all the Israeli people by taking care of all the things that are inside the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 3:9"/>Appoint them to <char style="add">help</char> Aaron and his two sons. I have chosen them from all the Israeli people to do that. <verse eid="NUM 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 3:10"/>Appoint Aaron and his two sons to do the work that priests do. But anyone else who comes close to the Sacred Tent <char style="add">to do that work</char> must be executed.”<verse eid="NUM 3:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 3:11"/>Yahweh also told Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 3:12"/>“Note that from all the Israelis, I have chosen the men of the tribe of Levi to take the places of all the firstborn sons of the Israeli people. The male descendants of Levi belong to me, <verse eid="NUM 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 3:13"/>because truly all the firstborn <char style="add">males</char> belong to me. That is because on the day that I killed all the firstborn <char style="add">sons</char> of the people of Egypt, I <char style="add">spared</char> all the firstborn <char style="add">sons</char> of the Israelis and set them apart for myself. I also set apart the firstborn <char style="add">males</char> of your domestic animals. They belong to me, Yahweh.”<verse eid="NUM 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 3:14"/>Yahweh spoke to Moses/me again in the Sinai Desert. He said, <verse eid="NUM 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 3:15"/>“Count the male members of the tribe of Levi. Write down their names and the names of their clans and family groups. Count all the males who are at least one month old.” <verse eid="NUM 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 3:16"/>So Moses/I counted them, just as Yahweh commanded.<verse eid="NUM 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 3:17"/>Levi had <char style="add">three</char> sons, whose names were Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.<verse eid="NUM 3:17"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 3:18"/>Gershon had <char style="add">two</char> sons: Libni and Shimei. The clans that were descended from them had the same names as those <char style="add">two</char> sons.<verse eid="NUM 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 3:19"/>Kohath had <char style="add">four</char> sons: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel. The clans that were descended from them had the same names as those <char style="add">four</char> sons.<verse eid="NUM 3:19"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 3:20"/>Merari had <char style="add">two</char> sons: Mahli and Mushi. The clans that were descended from them had the same names as those <char style="add">two</char> sons.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 3:20">Those are the clans that were descended from Levi.<verse eid="NUM 3:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 3:21"/>The two clans descended from Gershon are those that were descended from <char style="add">his sons</char> Libni and Shimei. <verse eid="NUM 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 3:22"/>In those two clans there were 7,500 males who were at least one month old. <verse eid="NUM 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 3:23"/>They were told to set up their tents on the west side of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 3:24"/>The leader of those two clans was Eliasaph, the son of Lael. <verse eid="NUM 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 3:25"/>Their work was to take care of the Sacred Tent, including the coverings of the tent, the curtain at the entrance of the tent, <verse eid="NUM 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 3:26"/>the ◄curtains/large pieces of cloth► that formed the walls around the courtyard that is around the tent and around the altar, the curtains that were at the entrance of the courtyard, and the ropes <char style="add">for fastening the tent</char>. They also did all the work of taking care of the things outside the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 3:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 3:27"/>The clans that were descended from Kohath were those descended from his four sons: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel. <verse eid="NUM 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 3:28"/>In those four clans there were 8,600 males who were at least one month old. The work of the men of the clans was to take care of <char style="add">the things that are inside</char> the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 3:29"/>They set up their tents on the south side of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 3:30"/>The leader of those four clans was Elizaphan, the son of Uzziel. <verse eid="NUM 3:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 3:31"/>The work of the men of those clans was to take care of the sacred chest, the table <char style="add">on which the priest put the sacred bread</char>, the lampstand, the altars, all the items that the priest used in the Sacred Tent, and the curtain that is inside the tent. Their work was also to take care of the things inside the tent.<verse eid="NUM 3:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 3:32"/>Aaron’s son Eleazar was the leader of all the male descendants of Levi. He supervised all the work that was done at the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 3:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 3:33"/>The clans that were descended from Merari were those descended from <char style="add">his sons</char> Mahli and Mushi. <verse eid="NUM 3:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 3:34"/>In those two clans there were 6,200 males who were at least one month old. <verse eid="NUM 3:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 3:35"/>They were told to set up their tents on the north side of the Sacred Tent. The leader of those two clans was Zuriel, the son of Abihail. <verse eid="NUM 3:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 3:36"/>The work of the men of those two clans was to take care of the frames that held up the tent, the crossbars, the pillars, and the bases. They also did all the work that was connected with those items. <verse eid="NUM 3:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 3:37"/>Their work was also to take care of the posts <char style="add">that held up the curtains that formed the walls of</char> the courtyard, and all the bases, tent pegs, and ropes <char style="add">that fastened those curtains</char>.<verse eid="NUM 3:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 3:38"/>Aaron and Moses/I and Aaron’s sons were told to set up their/our tents in the area in front of the Sacred Tent, on the east side. Their/Our work was to supervise the work that would be done in and around the Sacred Tent, for the benefit of the Israeli people. Only the priests were permitted to do that. <char style="add">Yahweh declared that</char> we should execute anyone else who went near the tent <char style="add">to do the work that the priests do</char>.<verse eid="NUM 3:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 3:39"/>When Aaron and Moses/I counted all the males who were at least one month old, who belonged to the clans descended from Levi, the total was 22,000.<verse eid="NUM 3:39"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 3:40"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Now count all the <char style="add">other</char> firstborn males in Israel who are at least one month old, and write down their names. <verse eid="NUM 3:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 3:41"/>Also, set apart for me the descendants of Levi to be substitutes for the firstborn males of the other Israelis. And set apart for me the livestock of the descendants of Levi to be substitutes for the firstborn livestock of the other Israeli people.”<verse eid="NUM 3:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="NUM 3:42"/>So Moses/I did that. He/I counted the firstborn males of all the Israeli people, as Yahweh had commanded. <verse eid="NUM 3:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="NUM 3:43"/>The total of those who were at least one month old was 22,273.<verse eid="NUM 3:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="NUM 3:44"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 3:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="NUM 3:45"/>“Set apart the descendants of Levi to be substitutes for <char style="add">the firstborn males of</char> the other Israeli people. The descendants of Levi belong to me, Yahweh. <verse eid="NUM 3:45"/><verse number="46" style="v" sid="NUM 3:46"/>There are 273 more firstborn males of the other Israeli people than of the descendants of Levi. <verse eid="NUM 3:46"/><verse number="47-48" style="v" sid="NUM 3:47-48"/>To pay for these 273 males, collect five pieces of silver for each of them. Each of those pieces of silver must weigh the same as each of the silver coins that are stored in the Sacred Tent. Give this silver to Aaron and his sons.”<verse eid="NUM 3:47-48"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="49" style="v" sid="NUM 3:49"/>So Moses/I did that. He/I collected the silver from those 273 males. <verse eid="NUM 3:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="NUM 3:50"/>The total was 1,365 pieces of silver. Each silver coin weighed the same as each of the silver coins stored in the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 3:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="NUM 3:51"/>Moses/I gave these silver coins to Aaron and his sons, as Yahweh had commanded.<verse eid="NUM 3:51"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="NUM 4"/>
  <para style="s1">The work of the clans descended from Kohath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 4:1"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 4:2"/>“Write down the names of the men who belong to the clans descended from Levi. <verse eid="NUM 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 4:3"/>Write the names of the men who are between 30 and 50 years old. These will be men who will work at the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 4:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 4:4"/>“The work of these descendants of Kohath will be <char style="add">to take care of</char> the sacred items <char style="add">that are used when the people worship</char> at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 4:5"/>When you Israelis move to another location, Aaron and his sons must enter the tent to take down the curtain that separates the Very Holy Place from the other part of the Sacred Tent. They must cover the sacred chest with that curtain. <verse eid="NUM 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 4:6"/>Then they must cover that with a nice covering made from the skins of goats. Over that they must spread a blue cloth. Then they must insert into the rings on the chest the poles <char style="add">for carrying it</char>.<verse eid="NUM 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 4:7"/>“Then they must put a blue cloth over the table on which the priests put the sacred bread. On top of the cloth they must put the bowls <char style="add">for incense</char>, the pans, the other dishes, the jars for <char style="add">the wine that will be</char> offered as a sacrifice, and the sacred bread. <verse eid="NUM 4:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 4:8"/>Over all of this they must spread a scarlet/red cloth. Finally, they must put on top a nice covering made from the skins of goats. Then they must insert into the <char style="add">rings at the corners of</char> the tables the poles <char style="add">for carrying it</char>.<verse eid="NUM 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 4:9"/>“Then with another blue cloth they must cover the lampstand, the lamps, the lamp snuffers, the trays, and the special jars of <char style="add">olive</char> oil <char style="add">to burn in the lamps</char>. <verse eid="NUM 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 4:10"/>They must cover the lampstand and all the other items with a nice covering made from the skins of goats. They must place all these things on a frame for carrying them.<verse eid="NUM 4:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 4:11"/>“Then they must spread another blue cloth over the gold altar <char style="add">which is used for burning</char> incense. Over this they must spread a nice covering made from the skins of goats. Then they must insert into <char style="add">the rings of</char> that altar the poles for carrying it.<verse eid="NUM 4:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 4:12"/>“They must take all the other items that are inside the Sacred Tent and wrap them in a blue cloth, cover that with a nice covering made from the skins of goats, and place all that on a frame for carrying it.<verse eid="NUM 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 4:13"/>“Then they must remove the ashes from the altar <char style="add">on which they have burned sacrifices</char>. Then they must cover the altar with a purple cloth. <verse eid="NUM 4:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 4:14"/>Then they must spread on top of the cloth all the items used at the altar—the pans <char style="add">for carrying the hot coals</char>, the meat forks, the shovels, the bowls <char style="add">for containing the blood to sprinkle on the people</char>, and all the other containers. Then they must spread over all those things a nice covering made from the skins of goats. Then they must insert into <char style="add">the rings at the sides of</char> the altar the poles <char style="add">for carrying it</char>.<verse eid="NUM 4:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 4:15"/>“Then Aaron and his sons have finished covering all these sacred things, the Israeli people will be ready to move <char style="add">to a new location</char>. The descendants of Kohath must come and carry all the sacred things to <char style="add">the next place</char> where you Israelis will set up your tents. But the descendants of Kohath must not touch any of these sacred items, because they will <char style="add">immediately</char> die <char style="add">if they touch them</char>. They are the ones who will carry these things, <char style="add">but they must not touch them</char>.<verse eid="NUM 4:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 4:16"/>“Aaron’s son Eleazar will have the work of taking care of the <char style="add">olive</char> oil for the lamps, the nice-smelling incense, the grain which will be burned on the altar each day, and the <char style="add">olive</char> oil for anointing <char style="add">the priests</char>. Eleazar is the one who will supervise the work that is done at the Sacred Tent and the men who take care of everything that is in it.”<verse eid="NUM 4:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 4:17"/>“Then Yahweh said to Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 4:17"/><verse number="18-20" style="v" sid="NUM 4:18-20"/>“When the descendants of Kohath approach the sacred items in the Sacred Tent <char style="add">to take them to another location</char>, Aaron and his sons must always go in with them and show each of them what work to do and what things to carry. But the descendants of Kohath must not enter the Sacred Tent <char style="add">at any other time</char> and look at the things that are in it. If they do that, I will get rid of all the descendants of Kohath.”<verse eid="NUM 4:18-20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The work of the men descended from Gershon</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 4:21"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 4:22"/>“Write down the names of all the men who belong to the clans descended from the Gershon <char style="add">division of the descendants of Levi</char>. <verse eid="NUM 4:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 4:23"/>Write the names of the men who are between 30 and 50 years old. They will be men who will also work at the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 4:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 4:24"/>“This is the work that they must do and the things that they must carry <char style="add">when you move to a new location</char>: <verse eid="NUM 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 4:25"/>They must carry the curtains of the Sacred Tent; they must carry the Sacred Tent and all the things that cover it, including the nice outer covering made from skins of goats, and the curtain which is at the entrance of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 4:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 4:26"/>They must also carry the curtains that form the wall that surrounds the courtyard that surrounds the Sacred Tent and the altar, the curtain that is at the entrance to the courtyard, and the ropes <char style="add">that fasten the curtains</char>. They must also do the packing and loading of these things. <verse eid="NUM 4:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 4:27"/>Aaron and his sons will supervise the work of all the descendants of Gershom. That work includes carrying those things and doing other work that is necessary for moving them. They must tell each of the descendants of Gershom what things they must carry. <verse eid="NUM 4:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 4:28"/>Those are the tasks that you must give to the men who belong to the clans descended from Gershom. Aaron’s son Ithamar is the one who will supervise their work.<verse eid="NUM 4:28"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The work of the men descended from Merari</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 4:29"/>Count also the men who belong to the clans descended from Levi’s son Merari. <verse eid="NUM 4:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 4:30"/>Write the names of the men who are between 30 and 50 years old. They will be men who will also work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 4:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 4:31"/>Their work will be to carry the frames that hold up the tent, the crossbars, the posts <char style="add">that hold up the curtains</char>, and the bases. <verse eid="NUM 4:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 4:32"/>They must also carry the posts for <char style="add">the curtains that form the walls of</char> the courtyard and the bases for the posts, the tent pegs, and the ropes <char style="add">to fasten the curtains</char>. Tell each man what things he must carry. <verse eid="NUM 4:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 4:33"/>Those are the tasks that the descendants of Merari must do at the Sacred Tent. Aaron’s son Ithamar is the one who will supervise them.”<verse eid="NUM 4:33"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Summary of the counting of the descendants of Levi</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 4:34"/>So Aaron and Moses/I and the Israeli leaders counted the descendants of Kohath, writing also the names of their clans and family groups. <verse eid="NUM 4:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 4:35"/>They/We counted all the men who were between 30 and 50 years old who were able to work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 4:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 4:36"/>The total was 2,750 men. <verse eid="NUM 4:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 4:37"/>They were the descendants of Kohath who <char style="add">were able to</char> work at the Sacred Tent. Aaron and Moses/I counted them just as Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="NUM 4:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 4:38"/>They/We also counted the descendants of Gershon, writing also the names of their clans and family groups. <verse eid="NUM 4:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 4:39"/>They/We counted all the men who were between 30 and 50 years old who were able to work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 4:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 4:40"/>The total was 2,630 men. <verse eid="NUM 4:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 4:41"/>They were the descendants of Gershon who <char style="add">were able to</char> work at the Sacred Tent. Aaron and Moses/I counted them as Yahweh had commanded.<verse eid="NUM 4:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="NUM 4:42"/>They/We also counted the descendants of Merari, writing also the names of their clans and family groups. <verse eid="NUM 4:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="NUM 4:43"/>They/We counted all the men who were between 30 and 50 years old who were able to work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 4:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="NUM 4:44"/>The total was 3,200 men. <verse eid="NUM 4:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="NUM 4:45"/>They were the descendants of Merari who <char style="add">were able to</char> work. Aaron and Moses/I counted them as Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="NUM 4:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="NUM 4:46"/>So Aaron and Moses/I and the Israeli leaders counted all the descendants of Levi, writing also the names of their clans and family groups. <verse eid="NUM 4:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="NUM 4:47"/>They/We counted all the men who were between 30 and 50 years old. They were ones who <char style="add">were able to</char> work at the Sacred Tent and who carried the tent and everything that was connected with it. <verse eid="NUM 4:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="NUM 4:48"/>The total was 8,580 men. <verse eid="NUM 4:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="NUM 4:49"/>They/We completed the counting <char style="add">of all the descendants of Levi</char>, as Yahweh had commanded Moses/me. And they/we told each man what work he was to do and what things he must carry <char style="add">when they moved to a new location</char>.<verse eid="NUM 4:49"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="NUM 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Expelling those who were ritually impure</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 5:1"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 5:2"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: ‘You must send away from your ◄camp/area where you have your tents► any man or woman who has leprosy and anyone who has a discharge <char style="add">of some fluid from his body</char>, and anyone who has become unacceptable to God because of <char style="add">having touched</char> a corpse. <verse eid="NUM 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 5:3"/>Send them away from there in order that they will not <char style="add">touch people in the camp area</char> where I live among you and cause them to become unacceptable to me.’” <verse eid="NUM 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 5:4"/>So <char style="add">Moses/I told that to the Israeli people, and</char> the Israeli people obeyed what Yahweh commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="NUM 5:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Paying for committing crimes</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 5:5"/>Yahweh also told Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 5:6"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: ‘If someone ◄commits a crime against/does something wrong to► another person, <char style="add">I consider that</char> that person has done wrong to me. <verse eid="NUM 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 5:7"/>That person must confess that he or she is guilty, and he or she must pay to the person to whom wrong was done <char style="add">what others consider to be a suitable/proper payment</char> for what he has done, and he must pay an extra 20 percent. <verse eid="NUM 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 5:8"/>If the person against whom the wrong was done <char style="add">has died and</char> there is no relative to whom the money can be paid, then the money belongs to me, and it must be paid to the priest. In addition, the one who did the wrong must give a male sheep to the priest <char style="add">to sacrifice</char> in order that ◄that person’s sin may be forgiven/I can forgive that person for his sin►. <verse eid="NUM 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 5:9"/>All the sacred offerings that the Israelis bring to the priest belong to the priest. <verse eid="NUM 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 5:10"/>The priest can keep those gifts.’”<verse eid="NUM 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Suspecting a wife of committing adultery</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 5:11"/>Yahweh also said this to Moses/me: <verse eid="NUM 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 5:12"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: ‘Suppose a man thinks that his wife has slept with another man, <verse eid="NUM 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 5:13"/>but neither he nor anyone else knows if it is true or not, because no one saw her doing that. <verse eid="NUM 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 5:14"/>But if the woman’s husband is jealous, and if he suspects that she has committed adultery, and he wants to know whether that is true or not, <verse eid="NUM 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 5:15"/>he should take his wife to the priest. He must take along as an offering two quarts/liters of barley flour. The priest must not pour <char style="add">olive</char> oil or incense on it, because this is an offering that the man has brought because he ◄is jealous/wants his wife to sleep only with him►. It is an offering to find out if she is guilty or not. <char style="add">Neither olive oil nor incense should be used because are associated with joy and this is not a time for joy.</char><verse eid="NUM 5:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 5:16"/>The priest must tell the woman to stand <char style="add">in front of the altar</char> in my presence. <verse eid="NUM 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 5:17"/>He must put some sacred water in a clay jar, and then he must put some dirt from the floor of the Sacred Tent into the water. <verse eid="NUM 5:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 5:18"/>He must untie/unfasten the woman’s hair. Then he must put in her hands the grain that her jealous husband is offering to determine whether she has committed adultery or not. The priest must hold <char style="add">the bowl that contains</char> bitter water that will cause ◄the woman to be cursed/bad things to happen to the woman► <char style="add">if she is guilty</char>. <verse eid="NUM 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 5:19"/>The priest must require her to solemnly declare <char style="add">that she will tell the truth</char>. Then he must say to her, “Has another man had sex [EUP] with you? Have you faithfully <char style="add">slept only with your husband</char> or not? If you have not slept with another man, nothing bad will happen to you if you drink the water. <verse eid="NUM 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 5:20"/>But if you have had sex with another man, <char style="add">Yahweh will curse you</char>. <verse eid="NUM 5:20"/><verse number="21-22" style="v" sid="NUM 5:21-22"/>Your womb will shrivel up and your stomach will swell up. You will never be able to give birth to children, and as a result, everyone will curse you and avoid you. If you have committed adultery, <char style="add">when you drink</char> this water, that is what will happen to you.” Then the woman must answer, “<char style="add">If I am guilty</char>, I will not object if that happens.”<verse eid="NUM 5:21-22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 5:23"/>‘Then the priest must write <char style="add">with ink</char> on a small scroll these ◄curses/bad things that will happen to her if she is guilty► <char style="add">and then wash the ink off into the bitter water</char>. <verse eid="NUM 5:23"/><verse number="24-25" style="v" sid="NUM 5:24-25"/>The priest must take from her the offering of barley flour <char style="add">that she is holding</char>, and lift it up to dedicate it to me. Then he must put it on the altar <verse eid="NUM 5:24-25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 5:26"/>and burn part of it as a sacrifice. Then the woman must drink the bitter water. <verse eid="NUM 5:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 5:27"/>If the woman has committed adultery, the water will cause her to suffer greatly. Her stomach will swell up and her womb will shrink, <char style="add">and she will be unable to give birth to children</char>. And then her ◄relatives/fellow Israelis► will curse her. <verse eid="NUM 5:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 5:28"/>But if she ◄is innocent/has not committed adultery►, her body will not be harmed, and she will still be able to give birth to children.<verse eid="NUM 5:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 5:29"/>‘That is the ritual that must be performed when a woman who is married has been unfaithful to her husband, <verse eid="NUM 5:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 5:30"/>or when a man is jealous and suspects that his wife <char style="add">has had sex with another man</char>. The priest must tell that woman to stand <char style="add">at the altar</char> in my presence and obey these instructions. <verse eid="NUM 5:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 5:31"/>Even if the woman has not done what the husband suspected, he will not be punished [MTY] for doing something wrong <char style="add">by bringing his wife to the priest</char>. But if his wife is guilty, she will suffer as a result.’”<verse eid="NUM 5:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="NUM 6"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules about Nazir-men</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 6:1"/>Yahweh also said this to Moses/me: <verse eid="NUM 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 6:2"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: ‘If any of you <char style="add">wants to</char> make a solemn promise to dedicate himself to belong to me in a special way, <char style="add">after you obey these instructions</char>, you will be called a Nazir-man, <char style="add">which means “dedicated man”</char>. <verse eid="NUM 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 6:3"/>You must not drink any wine or other alcoholic/fermented drink. You must not drink any vinegar made from wine or from any other alcoholic/fermented drink. You must not drink grape juice or eat grapes or raisins. <verse eid="NUM 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 6:4"/>You must not eat anything that comes from grapevines, not even the skins or seeds of grapes, during the time that you are a Nazir-man.<verse eid="NUM 6:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 6:5"/>‘Even your hair will be dedicated to me during the time that you area Nazir-man, so you must never allow anyone to cut your hair. Until the time that your solemn promise to dedicate yourself to me is ended, you must allow your hair to grow long. <verse eid="NUM 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 6:6"/>And you must not go near a corpse during the time that you are a Nazir-man. <verse eid="NUM 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 6:7"/>Even if the person who died is your father or your mother or your brother or your sister, you must not cause yourself to become unacceptable to me <char style="add">by coming close to the corpse</char>. Your long hair [MTY] shows that you belong to me in a special way, so you must not cut your hair. <verse eid="NUM 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 6:8"/>You are required to keep doing this all the time that you are dedicated to me in this special way.<verse eid="NUM 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 6:9"/>‘If anyone dies very suddenly when he is near you, then your hair that you have dedicated to me is no longer sacred. So you must wait seven days and then shave it all off. Then you must perform a special ritual to cause yourself to become acceptable to me again. <verse eid="NUM 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 6:10"/>The next day you must bring two doves or two young pigeons to the priest at the entrance of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 6:11"/>‘The priest must <char style="add">kill the birds and</char> offer them as sacrifices. One of them will be an offering to enable me to forgive you for the sins you have committed, and the other will be an offering that is burned completely to please me. <char style="add">After the priest burns them on the altar</char>, I will forgive you for having come close to a corpse, and <char style="add">when</char> your hair <char style="add">grows again it</char> will be dedicated to me again. <verse eid="NUM 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 6:12"/>The amount of time that you were set apart for me the previous time does not count, because you had become unacceptable to me <char style="add">by coming close to a corpse</char> during the time that you were a Nazir-man. So you must again make a solemn promise to dedicate yourself to me for the entire amount of time that you indicated the previous time. And you must also sacrifice a one-year-old lamb for not doing what you were required to do.<verse eid="NUM 6:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 6:13"/>‘When the time that you promised to dedicate yourself to me is ended, go to the entrance of the Sacred Tent <verse eid="NUM 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 6:14"/>and offer as sacrifices to me three animals that have no defects: Offer a one-year-old ram that will be burned completely, a one-year-old female lamb as a sacrifice to enable me to forgive your sins, and one full-grown ram as a sacrifice to maintain fellowship with me.<verse eid="NUM 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 6:15"/>‘When you bring those animals, you must also bring some wine to offer as a sacrifice. And you must also bring a basket of bread that you have made with very good flour and <char style="add">olive</char> oil. But you must not put any yeast in the bread. Also brush/spread some <char style="add">olive</char> oil on some thin wafers and bring them to the priest.<verse eid="NUM 6:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 6:16"/>‘The priest will put the young lamb and the young ram on the altar and completely burn them, in order that I will be pleased and will forgive you for your sins. <verse eid="NUM 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 6:17"/>Then he will kill the full-grown ram as an offering to restore fellowship with me, and he will also burn on the altar some of the bread and the grain and wine.<verse eid="NUM 6:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 6:18"/>‘After that, you must <char style="add">stand at</char> the entrance of the Sacred Tent and shave off your hair. Then you must put that hair in the fire that is under the <char style="add">animal that has been sacrificed</char> on the altar to maintain fellowship with me.<verse eid="NUM 6:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 6:19"/>‘The meat from the ram’s shoulder must be boiled. After it is cooked, the priest will take it along with one of the loaves of bread and one wafer which has been brushed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil, and he will put them in your hands. <verse eid="NUM 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 6:20"/>Then the priest will <char style="add">take them back and</char> lift them up high to dedicate them to me. They now belong to the priest, and he is permitted to eat some of the meat from the ram’s shoulder and from its ribs and from one of its thighs, because that meat is his share of the sacrifice. After that, you will no longer be a Nazir-man, and you will again be permitted to drink wine.<verse eid="NUM 6:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 6:21"/>‘Those are the regulations about the offerings that Nazir-men solemnly promise to bring to me to end their time of being dedicated to me. They must bring these offerings, but if they want to, they may bring additional offerings. And they must do everything that they solemnly promised to do when they dedicated themselves to me.’”<verse eid="NUM 6:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The blessing for the people</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 6:22"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 6:23"/>“Tell Aaron and his sons that when they <char style="add">ask me to</char> bless the people, they must say,<verse eid="NUM 6:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 6:24"/>‘I desire that Yahweh will bless you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 6:24">and protect you,<verse eid="NUM 6:24"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 6:25"/>and that he will smile at you</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 6:25">and act kindly toward you,<verse eid="NUM 6:25"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 6:26"/>and that he will be good to you [IDM]</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 6:26">and cause things to go well for you.’”<verse eid="NUM 6:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 6:27"/>Then Yahweh said, “If Aaron and his sons ask me to bless the Israeli people, truly I will bless them.”<verse eid="NUM 6:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="NUM 7"/>
  <para style="s1">The offerings brought to the Sacred Tent</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 7:1"/>When Moses/I had finished setting up the Sacred Tent, he/I dedicated [MTY] it to Yahweh. He/I also dedicated the things that are inside the tent, and the altar <char style="add">for burning sacrifices</char>, and all the things that would be used at the altar. <verse eid="NUM 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 7:2"/>Then the leaders of the <char style="add">twelve</char> Israeli tribes, the same men who had <char style="add">helped Aaron and Moses/me to</char> count the men <char style="add">who could fight in battles</char>, <verse eid="NUM 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 7:3"/>came to the tent, bringing gifts to Yahweh. They brought six sturdy/large carts and twelve oxen, one ox from each of the leaders and a cart from each of the two leaders.<verse eid="NUM 7:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 7:4"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 7:5"/>“Accept these gifts, in order that the descendants of Levi can use them for carrying the sacred items that are here at the Sacred Tent.”<verse eid="NUM 7:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 7:6"/>So Moses/I took the carts and oxen and gave them to the descendants of Levi. <verse eid="NUM 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 7:7"/>He/I gave two carts and four oxen to the descendants of Gershon for their work, <verse eid="NUM 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 7:8"/>and he/I gave four carts and eight oxen to the descendants of Merari for their work. Aaron’s son Ithamar was the supervisor of all their work. <verse eid="NUM 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 7:9"/>But he/I did not give any carts or oxen to the descendants of Kohath, because they took care of the sacred items that were to be carried on their shoulders, <char style="add">not on carts</char>.<verse eid="NUM 7:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 7:10"/>On the day that the altar was dedicated [MTY], the <char style="add">twelve</char> leaders brought other gifts to be dedicated and put them in front of the altar. <verse eid="NUM 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 7:11"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Each of the next twelve days one leader should bring his gifts for the dedication of the altar.”<verse eid="NUM 7:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12-83" style="v" sid="NUM 7:12-83"/>These are the gifts that each of the leaders brought:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">—a silver dish that weighed ◄more than three pounds/1.5 kg.►, and a silver bowl that weighed ◄almost two pounds/800 grams►, both of which were full of good flour and mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil to be offerings of grain; they both were weighed using the standard scales;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">—a small gold dish that weighed ◄four ounces/14 grams►, filled with incense;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">—a young bull, a <char style="add">full-grown</char> ram, and a one-year-old ram, to be sacrifices to be completely burned on the altar;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">—a goat to be sacrificed to <char style="add">enable me to forgive the people </char>for the sins they have committed;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">—and two bulls, five full-grown rams, five male goats, and five rams that were one-year-old, to be sacrifices to maintain the people’s fellowship with Yahweh.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 7:12-83">This was the order in which the leaders brought their gifts:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the first day, Nahshon, son of Amminadab from the tribe of Judah brought his gifts;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/second day, Nethanel, son of Zuar, from the tribe of Issachar;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/third day, Eliab, son of Helon, from the tribe of Zebulun;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/fourth day, Elizur, son of Shedeur, from the tribe of Reuben;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/fifth day, Shelumiel, son of Jurishhaddai, from the tribe of Simeon;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/sixth day, Eliasaph, son of Deuel, from the tribe of Gad;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/seventh day, Elishama, son of Ammihud, from the tribe of Ephraim;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/eighth day, Gamaliel, son of Pedahzur, from the tribe of Manasseh;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/ninth day, Abidan, son of Gideoni, from the tribe of Benjamin;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/tenth day, Ahiezer, son of Ammishaddai, from the tribe of Dan;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/eleventh day, Pagiel, son of Acran, from the tribe of Asher;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:12-83">on the next/twelfth day, Ahira, son of Enam, from the tribe of Naphtali.<verse eid="NUM 7:12-83"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="84-88" style="v" sid="NUM 7:84-88"/>When the altar was dedicated to Yahweh, those <char style="add">twelve</char> leaders brought these gifts:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:84-88">—twelve silver plates and twelve silver bowls, weighing a total of about ◄60 pounds/27.6 kg.►, each of them being weighed on the scales kept in the Sacred Tent;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:84-88">—twelve gold dishes filled with incense, weighing a total of about ◄three pounds/1.4 kg.►, each being weighed on those same scales;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:84-88">—twelve bulls, twelve <char style="add">full-grown</char> rams, and twelve one-year-old rams, to be sacrifices that were completely burned, along with the grain offerings;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:84-88">—twelve goats to be sacrificed <char style="add">to forgive the people</char> for the sins <char style="add">they have committed</char>;</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 7:84-88">—and 24 bulls, 60 full-grown rams, 60 goats, and 60 rams that were one-year-old, to be sacrifices to maintain the people’s fellowship with Yahweh.<verse eid="NUM 7:84-88"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="89" style="v" sid="NUM 7:89"/>Whenever Moses/I entered the Sacred Tent to talk with Yahweh, he/I heard Yahweh’s voice speaking between the two <char style="add">images of</char> creatures with wings that were above the lid of the sacred chest.<verse eid="NUM 7:89"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="NUM 8"/>
  <para style="s1">Aaron set up the lampstand</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 8:1"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 8:2"/>“Tell Aaron to put the seven lamps on the lampstand and place them in such a way that they shine toward the front of the lampstand.”<verse eid="NUM 8:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 8:3"/>So <char style="add">Moses/I told him what Yahweh said</char>, and he did that. <verse eid="NUM 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 8:4"/>The lampstand had been made from gold that had been hammered <char style="add">from one large lump of gold</char>, from its base to the decorations at the top <char style="add">that resembled</char> flowers. The lampstand was made exactly like Yahweh had told Moses/me that it should be made.<verse eid="NUM 8:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Instructions for dedicating the descendants of Levi</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 8:5"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 8:6"/>“You must cause the descendants of Levi to be acceptable to me by setting them apart from the other Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 8:7"/>Do that by sprinkling them with water <char style="add">which will symbolize</char> their being freed/cleansed from <char style="add">the guilt of</char> their sins. Then they must shave <char style="add">off all the hair on</char> their bodies and wash their clothes. <verse eid="NUM 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 8:8"/>Then they must bring to the Sacred Tent one bull and some grain mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <char style="add">Those things will be burned</char> as sacrifices. They must also bring another bull <char style="add">that will enable me to forgive them </char> for the sins they have committed. <verse eid="NUM 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 8:9"/>Then you must summon all the Israeli people to come together in front of the Sacred Tent, to <char style="add">gather around</char> the descendants of Levi. <verse eid="NUM 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 8:10"/>Then the Israeli people must lay their hands on the descendants of Levi. <verse eid="NUM 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 8:11"/>Aaron must then present them to me to be a gift from the Israeli people, in order that they can work for me <char style="add">at the Sacred Tent</char>.<verse eid="NUM 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 8:12"/>“After that, the descendants of Levi must place their hands on the heads of the two bulls. Then the bulls will be <char style="add">killed and</char> burned on the altar. One will be an offering to enable me <char style="add">to forgive them for </char>the sins they have committed, and the other will be completely burned <char style="add">to please me</char>. <verse eid="NUM 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 8:13"/>The descendants of Levi must stand <char style="add">at the altar</char> in front of Aaron and his sons, and you must then dedicate to me the descendants of Levi. <verse eid="NUM 8:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 8:14"/>This ritual will show that the descendants of Levi are set apart from the other Israelis and that they belong to me.<verse eid="NUM 8:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 8:15"/>“After the descendants of Levi have been made acceptable to me, and presented to me like a special offering, they may start to work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 8:16"/>They will belong to me. They will work for me as substitutes for the firstborn males of all the Israelis, <char style="add">who also belong to me</char>. <verse eid="NUM 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 8:17"/>All the firstborn males in Israel, both the people and the animals, are mine. When I caused all the firstborn sons of the people of Egypt to die, <char style="add">I ◄spared/did not kill► the firstborn males of the Israelis</char>. I set them apart to belong to me. I said that the firstborn males of all their domestic animals would also belong to me. <verse eid="NUM 8:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 8:18"/>But now I have chosen the descendants of Levi to take the places of the firstborn males of other Israelis. <verse eid="NUM 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 8:19"/>I have appointed the descendants of Levi to help Aaron and his sons at the Sacred Tent, as Aaron and his sons offer the sacrifices so that the Israeli people’s sins will be forgiven, and to prevent the Israelis from coming close to the tent with the result that a plague would cause many of them to become sick and die.”<verse eid="NUM 8:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 8:20"/>Aaron and Moses/I and the other Israelis helped the descendants of Levi to do everything that Yahweh had commanded. <verse eid="NUM 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 8:21"/>The descendants of Levi <char style="add">sprinkled themselves with water to symbolize that</char> they had been freed/cleansed from <char style="add">the guilt of</char> their sins, and they washed their clothes. Then Aaron brought them to <char style="add">the altar to</char> present them to Yahweh, and he offered sacrifices to cleanse them from <char style="add">the guilt of</char> their sins and cause them to become acceptable to Yahweh. <verse eid="NUM 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 8:22"/>After that, the descendants of Levi started to work at the Sacred Tent to assist Aaron and his sons. They did that just as Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="NUM 8:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 8:23"/>Yahweh also said this to Moses/me: <verse eid="NUM 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 8:24"/>“The descendants of Levi who are between 25 and 50 years old will work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 8:25"/>But after they become 50 years old, they must ◄retire/not do that work any more►. <verse eid="NUM 8:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 8:26"/>They may help the other descendants of Levi to do their work at the Sacred Tent, but they must not do the work themselves. That is what you must tell them about the work they will do.”<verse eid="NUM 8:26"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="NUM 9"/>
  <para style="s1">They celebrated Passover again</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 9:1"/>One year after the Israelis left Egypt, during the month of March, while they were in the Sinai Desert, Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 9:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people that they must celebrate the Passover <char style="add">Festival again</char>. <verse eid="NUM 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 9:3"/>They must do it on the fourteenth day of this month, early in the evening, and they must obey all the instructions about it <char style="add">that I gave you previously</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 9:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 9:4"/>So Moses/I told the people what Yahweh had said about celebrating the Passover. <verse eid="NUM 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 9:5"/>The people celebrated it, there in the Sinai Desert, in the evening of the fourteenth day of the month, just as Yahweh had commanded Moses/me.<verse eid="NUM 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 9:6"/>But some of the Israeli people had touched a corpse, and as a result they had become unfit to celebrate the Passover. So they asked Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 9:7"/>“It is true that we have touched a corpse. But why should that prevent us from celebrating the Passover Festival and offering sacrifices to Yahweh like everyone else [RHQ]?”<verse eid="NUM 9:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 9:8"/>Moses/I replied, “Wait here until I go into the Sacred Tent and find out what Yahweh says about it.”<verse eid="NUM 9:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 9:9"/>
    <char style="add">So Moses/I went into the tent and asked Yahweh what he/I should tell the people</char>, and this is what Yahweh said: <verse eid="NUM 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 9:10"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: If any of you or your descendants touch a corpse and as a result become unacceptable to me, or if you are away from home on a long trip <char style="add">at the time to celebrate the Passover</char>, you will still be permitted to celebrate it. <verse eid="NUM 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 9:11"/>But you must celebrate it exactly one month later, early in the evening of the fourteenth day of that month. Eat the meat of the lamb for the Passover Festival with bread that is baked without yeast and eat bitter herbs. <verse eid="NUM 9:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 9:12"/>Do not leave any of it until the next morning. And do not break any of the lamb’s bones. Obey all the regulations about celebrating the Passover. <verse eid="NUM 9:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 9:13"/>But if any of you has not done anything that would make you unfit to celebrate the Passover Festival, and you are not away from home on a long trip, and you do not sacrifice to me at the proper time, you will no longer be allowed to associate with my people. ◄You will be punished/I will punish you►.<verse eid="NUM 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 9:14"/>Foreigners who live among you may also celebrate the Passover Festival, if they obey all my commands concerning it.”<verse eid="NUM 9:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A cloud covered the Sacred Tent</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15-16" style="v" sid="NUM 9:15-16"/>On the day that the Sacred Tent was set up, a cloud covered it. From the time that the sun set until the time that the sun rose <char style="add">the next day</char>, the cloud resembled a <char style="add">huge</char> fire. And that is what happened every day <char style="add">that we/the Israelis were in the desert</char>. <verse eid="NUM 9:15-16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 9:17"/>When the cloud rose up and started to move <char style="add">to a new location</char>, we/they followed it. When the cloud stopped, we/the Israelis stopped there and set up their tents. <verse eid="NUM 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 9:18"/>We/They traveled when Yahweh, <char style="add">by causing the cloud to move or stop</char>, signaled to us/them when to move and when to stop. When the cloud stayed over the Sacred Tent, we/the Israelis stayed at that place. <verse eid="NUM 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 9:19"/>Sometimes the cloud stayed over the tent for a long time, so when that happened, we/they did not travel. <verse eid="NUM 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 9:20"/>Sometimes the cloud remained over the tent for only a few days. We/The people stopped and set up our/their tents as Yahweh commanded us/them, and we/they traveled <char style="add">to a new location</char> when Yahweh commanded us/them to do that. <verse eid="NUM 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 9:21"/>Sometimes the cloud stayed in one place for only one day. When that happened, when the cloud rose up <char style="add">into the sky</char> the next morning, then we/they traveled. Whenever the cloud moved, during the day or during the night, we/they traveled. <verse eid="NUM 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 9:22"/>If the cloud stayed over the Sacred Tent for two days, or for a month, or for a year, during that time we/they stayed where we/they were. But when the cloud rose up <char style="add">into the sky</char>, we/they started to travel. <verse eid="NUM 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 9:23"/>When Yahweh commanded us/them to <char style="add">stop and</char> set up our/their tents, we/they did that. When he told us/them to move, we/they moved. We/They did whatever Yahweh told Moses/me that we/they should do.<verse eid="NUM 9:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="NUM 10"/>
  <para style="s1">The silver trumpets</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 10:1"/>Yahweh also told Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 10:2"/>“<char style="add">Tell someone to</char> make two trumpets by hammering each one from <char style="add">one lump of</char> silver. Blow the trumpets to summon the people to come together and also to signal that they must move their tents <char style="add">to a new location</char>. <verse eid="NUM 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 10:3"/>If both trumpets are blown, it means that everyone must gather together at the entrance of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 10:4"/>If only one trumpet is blown, it means that only the <char style="add">twelve</char> leaders of the tribes must gather together. <verse eid="NUM 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 10:5"/>If the trumpets are blown loudly, the tribes that are to the east <char style="add">of the Sacred Tent</char> should start to travel. <verse eid="NUM 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 10:6"/>When the trumpets are blown loudly the second time, the tribes that are to the south should start to travel. The loud blasts on the trumpet will signal that they should start to travel. <verse eid="NUM 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 10:7"/>When you want only to gather the people together, blow the trumpets, but do not blow them as loudly.<verse eid="NUM 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 10:8"/>“The priests who are descended from Aaron are the ones who should blow the trumpets. That is a regulation that will never be changed. <verse eid="NUM 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 10:9"/>When you fight against enemies who attack you in your own land, tell the priests to blow the trumpets loudly. I, Yahweh, your God, will hear that, and I will rescue you from your enemies. <verse eid="NUM 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 10:10"/>Also tell the priests to blow the trumpets when the people are happy, and at the festivals <char style="add">each year</char>, and at the times when they celebrate the new moon each month. Tell them to blow the trumpets when the people bring offerings that will be completely burned, and when they bring offerings to maintain fellowship with me. If they do that, it will help you to remember that I, Yahweh your God, <char style="add">will help you</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 10:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis traveled</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 10:11"/>On the twentieth day of May in the second year <char style="add">after the/we Israelis left Egypt</char>, the cloud rose up from above the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 10:12"/>So we/the Israelis traveled from the Sinai Desert, and we/they continued traveling <char style="add">north</char> until the cloud stopped in the Paran Desert. <verse eid="NUM 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 10:13"/>That was the first time we/they moved, obeying the instructions that Yahweh had given to Moses/me to tell them.<verse eid="NUM 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 10:14"/>The group that went first, carrying their flag/banner, was the group from the tribe of Judah. Nahshon, the son of Amminadab, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 10:15"/>The group from the tribe of Issachar <char style="add">followed them</char>. Nethanel, the son of Zuar, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 10:16"/>The group from the tribe of Zebulun went next. Eliab, the son of Helon, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 10:17"/>Then they dismantled the Sacred Tent, and the descendants of Gershon and Merari carried it, and they went next.<verse eid="NUM 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 10:18"/>The group from the tribe of Reuben went next, carrying their flag. Elizur, the son of Shedeur, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 10:19"/>The group from the tribe of Simeon was next. Shelumiel, the son of Zurishaddai, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 10:20"/>The group from the tribe of Gad was next. Eliasaph, the son of Deuel, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 10:21"/>The group descended from Kohath was next. They carried the sacred items from the Sacred Tent. The Sacred Tent itself was set up at the new location before they arrived there.<verse eid="NUM 10:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 10:22"/>The group from the tribe of Ephraim was next, carrying their flag. Elishama, the son of Ammihud, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 10:23"/>The group from the tribe of Manasseh went next. Gamaliel, the son of Pedahzur, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 10:24"/>The group from the tribe of Benjamin, went next. Abidan, the son of Gideoni, was their leader.<verse eid="NUM 10:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 10:25"/>The ones who went last were the group from the tribe of Dan, carrying their flag. Ahiezer, the son of Ammishaddai, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 10:26"/>The group from the tribe of Asher went next. Pagiel, the son of Ocran, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 10:27"/>The group from the tribe of Naphtali went last. Ahira, the son of Enan, was their leader. <verse eid="NUM 10:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 10:28"/>That was the order in which the groups of Israeli tribes traveled.<verse eid="NUM 10:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 10:29"/>One day Moses/I said to his/my brother-in-law Hobab, the son of Reuel from the Midian people-group, “We are on the way to the place that Yahweh promised to give to us. Come with us, and we will take good care of you, because Yahweh has promised <char style="add">to do</char> good things for us Israeli people.”<verse eid="NUM 10:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 10:30"/>But Hobab replied, “No, I will not go with you. I want to return to my own land and to my own family.”<verse eid="NUM 10:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 10:31"/>But Moses/I said, “Please do not leave us. You know the places where we can set up our tents in this desert, and you can guide us. <verse eid="NUM 10:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 10:32"/>Come with us. We will share with you all the good things that Yahweh gives to us.”<verse eid="NUM 10:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 10:33"/>
    <char style="add">So Hobab agreed to go with them</char>. The Israelis left Sinai Mountain, <char style="add">which they called</char> Yahweh’s Mountain, and they walked for three days. The <char style="add">men carrying the</char> sacred chest went in front of the other people for those three days, and they kept looking for a place to set up their tents. <verse eid="NUM 10:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 10:34"/>The cloud sent by Yahweh was over them every day.<verse eid="NUM 10:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 10:35"/>Each morning when the men who were carrying the sacred chest started to walk, Moses/I said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 10:35">“Yahweh, arise!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 10:35">Scatter your enemies!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 10:35">Cause those who hate you to run away from you!”<verse eid="NUM 10:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 10:36"/>And each time the men <char style="add">stopped to</char> set down the sacred chest, Moses/I said,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 10:36">“Yahweh, stay close to the thousands of us Israelis!”<verse eid="NUM 10:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="NUM 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh sent fire because the people complained</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 11:1"/>One day the people complained to Yahweh about their troubles. When Yahweh heard what they were saying, he became angry. So he sent a fire which burned among the people at the edge of their camp. <verse eid="NUM 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 11:2"/>Then the people cried out to Moses/me, and he/I prayed to Yahweh. Then the fire stopped burning. <verse eid="NUM 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 11:3"/>So they called that place Taberah, <char style="add">which means ‘burning’</char>, because the fire from Yahweh had burned among them.<verse eid="NUM 11:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Seventy leaders were chosen to help Moses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 11:4"/>Then some troublemakers from other people-groups <char style="add">who were traveling</char> with the Israelis began to want better food. And <char style="add">when they started complaining</char> the Israeli people also started to complain. <verse eid="NUM 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 11:5"/>They said, “We wish we had some meat! <verse eid="NUM 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 11:6"/>We remember the fish that we ate while we were in Egypt, fish that was given to us without ◄cost/asking us to pay for it►. And we had all the cucumbers, melons, leeks, onions, and garlic <char style="add">that we wanted</char>. But now we do not have any desire to eat, because all we have to eat is this manna!”<verse eid="NUM 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 11:7"/>The manna resembled small white seeds. <verse eid="NUM 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 11:8"/><char style="add">Each morning</char> the people would go out and gather some <char style="add">from the surface of the ground</char>. Then they made flour by grinding it or pounding it with stones. Then they <char style="add">added water and</char> boiled it in a pot, or they made flat cakes with it <char style="add">and baked them</char>. The cakes tasted like bread that was baked with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 11:9"/>Each night the manna came down on their ground where their tents were, like dew <char style="add">from the sky</char>.<verse eid="NUM 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 11:10"/>Moses/I heard all the Israeli people complaining as they were standing in the entrances of their tents. Yahweh became very angry, and Moses/I was also very perturbed. <verse eid="NUM 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 11:11"/>He/I <char style="add">went into the Sacred Tent and</char> asked Yahweh, “Why have you caused me, your servant, to experience this trouble [RHQ]? Act mercifully to me! What wrong have I done, with the result that you have appointed me to take care of all of these people [RHQ]? <verse eid="NUM 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 11:12"/>◄I am not their father./Am I their father?► [RHQ] Why have you told me to take care of them like a woman carries around her baby and ◄nurses it/gives it her milk► [MET, RHQ]? How can I take them to the land that you promised to give to our ancestors [RHQ]? <verse eid="NUM 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 11:13"/>Where can I get meat to feed all these people? They keep complaining to me, saying, ‘Give us some meat to eat!’ <verse eid="NUM 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 11:14"/>I cannot carry all these people’s burdens by myself! <char style="add">They are like a heavy load [MET], and</char> I cannot carry this very heavy load any more. <verse eid="NUM 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 11:15"/>If you intend to act like this toward me, kill me now. If you are really concerned about me, be kind to me and <char style="add">kill me to</char> end my misery <char style="add">of trying to take care of them</char>!”<verse eid="NUM 11:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 11:16"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Summon 70 men whom you know are leaders among the Israeli people. Tell them to stand with you in front of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 11:17"/>I will come down and talk with you there. Then I will take some of <char style="add">the power of</char> my Spirit that you have, and I will put <char style="add">that power</char> on them also. They will help you to take care of some of the things that the people are concerned about, in order that you will not need to do it alone.<verse eid="NUM 11:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 11:18"/>“Furthermore, say to the people, ‘Make yourselves acceptable to me, and tomorrow you will have meat to eat. You were complaining, and Yahweh heard you when you were saying, “We want some meat to eat. We had better food in Egypt!” Now Yahweh will give you some meat, and you will eat it. <verse eid="NUM 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 11:19"/>You will eat meat not only for one or two days, nor only for five or ten or 20 days. <verse eid="NUM 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 11:20"/><char style="add">You will eat meat every day</char> for one month, and then you will loathe/despise it, and it will cause you to want to vomit. <char style="add">This will happen</char> because you have rejected Yahweh who is here among you, and you have wailed in his presence, saying <char style="add">“We would have had better food to eat</char> if we had not left Egypt [RHQ].”’”<verse eid="NUM 11:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 11:21"/>But Moses/I replied to Yahweh, “There are 600,000 men <char style="add">plus women and children</char> here with me, so ◄<char style="add">why</char> do you say ‘I will give them plenty of meat every day for a month!’?/it does not seem right for you to say ‘I will give them plenty of meat every day for a month!’► [RHQ] <verse eid="NUM 11:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 11:22"/>Even if we killed all the sheep and cattle, that would not [RHQ] be enough <char style="add">to provide meat for all of them</char> Even if we caught all the fish in the sea <char style="add">and gave it to them</char>, that would not be enough [RHQ]!” <verse eid="NUM 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 11:23"/>But Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Do you think that I [SYN] have no power? You will now see if I can do what I say I will do.”<verse eid="NUM 11:23"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 11:24"/>So Moses/I went out <char style="add">from the Sacred Tent</char> and told the people what Yahweh had said. Then he/I gathered together the 70 leaders and told them to stand around the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 11:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 11:25"/>Then Yahweh came down in the cloud <char style="add">that was above the tent</char> and spoke to Moses/me. He took some of <char style="add">the power of</char> the Spirit that he had given to Moses/me and gave it to the 70 leaders. By means of the power of the Spirit within them, they ◄prophesied/spoke messages that Yahweh gave them►, but they did that only once.<verse eid="NUM 11:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 11:26"/>Two of the leaders whom Moses/I appointed, Eldad and Medad, were not there when the rest of them gathered together. They had not left <char style="add">their tents</char> to go and stand around the Sacred Tent. But Yahweh’s Spirit came on them also, and they started to ◄prophesy/speak messages from Yahweh►. <verse eid="NUM 11:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 11:27"/>So a young man ran and told Moses/me, “Eldad and Medad are prophesying in all their tents!”<verse eid="NUM 11:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 11:28"/>Joshua, who had helped Moses/me since he was a young man, said, “Sir, tell them to stop doing that!”<verse eid="NUM 11:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 11:29"/>But Moses/I replied, “◄Are you worried that they might injure my reputation/Do you think that I want to be the only one who prophesies► [RHQ]? I wish that all Yahweh’s people could ◄prophesy/speak messages from Yahweh►. I wish that Yahweh would give the power of his Spirit to all of them!” <verse eid="NUM 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 11:30"/>Then Moses/I and all the leaders went back to their/our tents.<verse eid="NUM 11:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 11:31"/>Then Yahweh sent a strong wind from the sea. It blew quail into the area all around the camp for miles in every direction, <char style="add">and caused the quail to fall onto the ground</char>. They were piled up on the ground about ◄3 feet/1 meter► high! <verse eid="NUM 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 11:32"/>So the people went out and gathered up the quail all that day, and all that night, and all of the following day. <char style="add">It seemed as though</char> everyone gathered at least 50 bushels! They spread the quail out on the ground all around the camp, <char style="add">so that the quail would dry out</char>. <verse eid="NUM 11:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 11:33"/><char style="add">Then they cooked them and started to eat them</char>. But while they were still eating the meat [MTY], Yahweh <char style="add">showed that he</char> was very angry with them. He struck them with a severe plague/sickness, <char style="add">and many people died</char>. <verse eid="NUM 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 11:34"/>The people who died and were buried were the ones who had said they wanted to eat meat <char style="add">like they had formerly eaten in Egypt</char>. So they called that place Kibroth-Hattaavah, <char style="add">which means ‘graves of those who craved’</char>.<verse eid="NUM 11:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 11:35"/>From there, the Israelis continued walking <char style="add">east</char> until they arrived at Hazeroth <char style="add">town</char>, where they stopped and stayed <char style="add">for a long time</char>.<verse eid="NUM 11:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="NUM 12"/>
  <para style="s1">Miriam and Aaron were jealous of Moses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1-2" style="v" sid="NUM 12:1-2"/>
    <char style="add">Moses’/My older sister</char> Miriam and <char style="add">his/my older brother</char> Aaron were saying this: “Is Moses the only one to whom Yahweh has spoken messages to tell to us [RHQ]? Does Yahweh not speak messages to us two also?” <char style="add">They told people that</char> they were saying that because Moses/I had married a woman who was a descendant of the Cush people-group, <char style="add">but they were really saying that because they ◄were jealous/did not want Moses/me to be the only leader of the Israeli people►</char>. But Yahweh heard what they were saying.<verse eid="NUM 12:1-2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 12:3"/>
    <char style="add">The truth was that</char> Moses/I was very humble. He/I was more humble than anyone else on the earth <char style="add">and Moses/I had not appointed himself/myself to be their leader</char>.<verse eid="NUM 12:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 12:4"/>So immediately Yahweh spoke to Moses/me and to Aaron and Miriam. He said, “All three of you must go and stand at the Sacred Tent.” So they/we did that. <verse eid="NUM 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 12:5"/>Then Yahweh descended to the entrance of the tent in a cloud <char style="add">that resembled a huge white</char> pillar. He told Aaron and Miriam to step forward, so they did. <verse eid="NUM 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 12:6"/>Then he said to them,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 12:6">“Listen to me!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 12:6">When a prophet is among you,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 12:6">I <char style="add">usually</char> reveal myself to him by allowing him to see visions,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 12:6">and I speak to him in dreams.<verse eid="NUM 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 12:7"/>But that is not the way I speak to my servant Moses.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 12:7">I trust that he will lead my people <char style="add">well</char>.<verse eid="NUM 12:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 12:8"/>So I talk to him face-to-face.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 12:8">I speak to him ◄clearly/using words that he will understand easily►, not using parables.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 12:8">He has even seen what I look like.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 12:8">So you should be afraid to criticize my servant Moses!”<verse eid="NUM 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 12:9"/>Yahweh was very angry with Miriam and Aaron, and he left.<verse eid="NUM 12:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 12:10"/>When the cloud rose up from the Sacred Tent, Aaron looked at Miriam, and he saw that her skin was <char style="add">as white</char> as snow, because she now had leprosy. <verse eid="NUM 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 12:11"/>Aaron said to Moses/me, “My master, please do not punish us for this sin that we have foolishly committed. <verse eid="NUM 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 12:12"/>Do not allow Miriam to be like a baby that is already dead when it is born, whose flesh is already half decayed!”<verse eid="NUM 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 12:13"/>So Moses/I cried out to Yahweh, saying, “God, I plead with you to heal her!”<verse eid="NUM 12:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 12:14"/>But Yahweh replied, “If her father had <char style="add">rebuked her for doing something wrong by</char> spitting in her face, she would have been ashamed for seven days. <char style="add">She should be ashamed because of what she has done</char>. So send her outside the camp for seven days. Then <char style="add">she will not have leprosy any more, and</char> she may return to the camp.” <verse eid="NUM 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 12:15"/>So they sent her outside the camp for seven days. ◄The people/We► did not move <char style="add">to another location</char> until she returned.<verse eid="NUM 12:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 12:16"/>But after <char style="add">she returned</char>, they/we left Hazeroth and moved <char style="add">north</char> in the Paran Desert and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 12:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="NUM 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Twelve Israeli men explored Canaan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 13:1"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 13:2"/>“Send some men to Canaan <char style="add">land</char> to explore it. That is the land that I will give to you Israelis. Send men who are leaders in their tribes.”<verse eid="NUM 13:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 13:3"/>So Moses/I did what Yahweh commanded him/me. He/I sent out twelve Israeli men who were all leaders of their tribes. He/I sent them from their/our camp at Paran in the desert. <verse eid="NUM 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 13:4"/>These are the names of the men <char style="add">and the tribes they belonged to:</char></para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 13:4">Shammua, the son of Zaccur, from the tribe of Reuben;<verse eid="NUM 13:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 13:5"/>Shaphat, the son of Hori, from the tribe of Simeon;<verse eid="NUM 13:5"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 13:6"/>Caleb, the son of Jephunneh, from the tribe of Judah;<verse eid="NUM 13:6"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 13:7"/>Igal, the son of Joseph, from the tribe of Issachar;<verse eid="NUM 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 13:8"/>Hoshea, the son of Nun, from the tribe of Ephraim;<verse eid="NUM 13:8"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 13:9"/>Palti, the son of Raphu, from the tribe of Benjamin;<verse eid="NUM 13:9"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 13:10"/>Gaddiel, the son of Sodi, from the tribe of Zebulun;<verse eid="NUM 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 13:11"/>Gaddi, the son of Susi, from the tribe of Manasseh;<verse eid="NUM 13:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 13:12"/>Ammiel, the son of Gemalli, from the tribe of Dan;<verse eid="NUM 13:12"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 13:13"/>Sethur, the son of Michael, from the tribe of Asher;<verse eid="NUM 13:13"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 13:14"/>Nahbi, the son of Vophsi, from the tribe of Naphtali;<verse eid="NUM 13:14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 13:15"/>and Geuel, the son of Maki, from the tribe of Gad.<verse eid="NUM 13:15"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 13:16"/>Those are the names of the men whom Moses/I sent out to explore Canaan. <char style="add">Before they left</char>, Moses/I gave Hoshea a new name, Joshua, <char style="add">which means ‘Yahweh is the one who saves</char>.’<verse eid="NUM 13:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 13:17"/>Before Moses/I sent them to explore Canaan, he/I said to them, “Go through the southern part of Canaan, and then go <char style="add">north</char> into the hilly area. <verse eid="NUM 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 13:18"/>See what the land is like. See if the people who live there are strong or weak. See if there are many people or only a few people. <verse eid="NUM 13:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 13:19"/>Find out what kind of land they live in [RHQ]. Is it good or bad? Find out about the towns in which they live [RHQ]. Do they have walls around them or not? <verse eid="NUM 13:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 13:20"/>Find out about the soil [RHQ]. Is it ◄fertile/good for growing crops► or not? Find out if there are trees there [RHQ]. Try to bring back some of the fruit that grows in that land.” <char style="add">He/I said that because</char> it was the beginning of the time to harvest grapes.<verse eid="NUM 13:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 13:21"/>So those men went to Canaan. They went <char style="add">through the entire land</char>, from the Zin desert <char style="add">in the south</char> all the way to Rehob <char style="add">town</char> near Lebo-Hamath <char style="add">in the north</char>. <verse eid="NUM 13:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 13:22"/>In the south, they went to Hebron, where Ahiman, Sheshai, and Talmai, <char style="add">huge men</char> descended from Anak, lived. Hebron was a city that was built seven years before Zoan <char style="add">city</char> was built in Egypt. <verse eid="NUM 13:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 13:23"/>In one valley, they cut from a grapevine one cluster of grapes. <char style="add">Because it was very large, they needed</char> two men to carry it on a pole. They also picked some pomegranates and some figs <char style="add">to carry back to their camp</char>. <verse eid="NUM 13:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 13:24"/>They called that place Eshcol <char style="add">which means ‘cluster’</char> because they had cut that <char style="add">huge</char> cluster of grapes there. <verse eid="NUM 13:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 13:25"/>After they explored the land for 40 days, they returned to their camp.<verse eid="NUM 13:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The report about Canaan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 13:26"/>They came to Aaron and Moses/me and the rest of the Israeli people in the desert at Paran. They reported to everyone what they had seen. They also showed them the fruit that they had brought back. <verse eid="NUM 13:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 13:27"/>But this is what they reported to Moses/me: “We arrived in the land that you sent us to explore. It is truly a beautiful land, and it is very fertile [IDM]. Here is some of the fruit. <verse eid="NUM 13:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 13:28"/>But the people who live there are very strong. Their cities are large and are surrounded by walls. We even saw some of the <char style="add">huge</char> descendants of Anak there. <verse eid="NUM 13:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 13:29"/>The descendants of Amalek live in the southern part <char style="add">of the land</char>, and the descendants of Heth, Jebus, and Amor live in the hilly area <char style="add">to the north</char>. The descendants of Canaan live along the coast of the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> sea and along the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 13:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 13:30"/>
    <char style="add">When they said that, the people were afraid and started to cry out very loudly</char>. But Caleb told the people who were standing near Moses/me to be quiet. Then he said, “We should go there and take the land, because we are certainly able to conquer it!”<verse eid="NUM 13:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 13:31"/>But the men who had gone with him said, “No, we cannot attack <char style="add">and defeat</char> those people! They are much stronger than we are!” <verse eid="NUM 13:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 13:32"/>So those men gave to the Israeli people a bad report about the land that they had explored. They said, “The land that we explored is very large; we cannot conquer it. And all the people whom we saw are very tall. <verse eid="NUM 13:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 13:33"/>We even saw the descendants of Nephili there. The descendants of Anak <char style="add">whom we saw there</char> are descended from the giant Nephili people. When we saw them, we felt <char style="add">as small</char> as grasshoppers [SIM], and they thought that we looked like grasshoppers too!”<verse eid="NUM 13:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="NUM 14"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israeli people continued to complain</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 14:1"/>That night, all the Israeli people cried loudly. <verse eid="NUM 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 14:2"/>The next day they all complained to Aaron and Moses/me. All the men said, “We wish that we had died in Egypt, or in this desert! <verse eid="NUM 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 14:3"/>Why is Yahweh bringing us to this land, where we men will be killed with swords? And our wives and children will be taken away <char style="add">to be slaves</char>. <char style="add">Instead of going to Canaan</char>. It would be better for us to return to Egypt!” <verse eid="NUM 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 14:4"/>Then <char style="add">some of</char> them said to each other, “We should choose a leader who will take us back to Egypt!”<verse eid="NUM 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 14:5"/>Then Aaron and Moses/I bowed down <char style="add">to pray</char> in front of all the Israeli people who had gathered there. <verse eid="NUM 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 14:6"/>Joshua and Caleb, two of the men who had explored the land, tore their clothes <char style="add">because they were very dismayed</char>. <verse eid="NUM 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 14:7"/>They said to the Israeli people, “The land that we explored is very good. <verse eid="NUM 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 14:8"/>If Yahweh is pleased with us, he will lead us into that very fertile [IDM] land, and he will give it to us. <verse eid="NUM 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 14:9"/>So do not rebel against Yahweh! And do not be afraid of the people in that land! We will ◄gobble them up/completely destroy them► [MET]! They do not have anyone who will protect them, but Yahweh will be with us <char style="add">and help us</char>. So do not be afraid of them!”<verse eid="NUM 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 14:10"/>Then all the Israeli people talked about <char style="add">killing Caleb and Joshua by</char> throwing stones at them. But <char style="add">suddenly</char> Yahweh’s glory appeared to them at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 14:11"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, “How long will these people reject me [RHQ]? I am tired of them not believing in what I <char style="add">can do</char>, in spite of all the miracles I have performed among them [RHQ]! <verse eid="NUM 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 14:12"/>So I will cause a ◄plague/widespread sickness► to strike them and get rid of them. But I will cause your <char style="add">descendants</char> to become a great nation. They will be a nation that is much greater and stronger than these people are.”<verse eid="NUM 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 14:13"/>But Moses/I replied to Yahweh, “<char style="add">Please do not do that, because</char> the people of Egypt will hear about it! You brought these Israeli people from Egypt by your great power, <verse eid="NUM 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 14:14"/>and the people of Egypt will tell that to the <char style="add">descendants of Canaan</char> who live in this land. Yahweh, they have already heard about you. They know that you have ◄been with/helped► these people and that they have seen you face-to-face. They have heard that your cloud is like a huge pillar that stays over them, and by using that cloud you lead them during the day, and the cloud becomes like a fire at night <char style="add">to give them light</char>. <verse eid="NUM 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 14:15"/>If you kill these people all at one time, the people-groups who have heard about your <char style="add">power</char> will say, <verse eid="NUM 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 14:16"/>‘Yahweh was not able to bring them into the land that he promised to give to them, so he killed them in the desert.’<verse eid="NUM 14:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 14:17"/>“So Yahweh, now show that you are very powerful. You said, <verse eid="NUM 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 14:18"/>‘I do not quickly become angry; instead, I love people very much, and I forgive people for having sinned and having disobeyed my laws. But I will always punish [LIT] people who are guilty of doing what is wrong. When parents sin, I will punish them, but I will also punish their children and their grandchildren and their great-grandchildren and their great-great-grandchildren.’ <verse eid="NUM 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 14:19"/>So, because you love people like that, forgive these people for the sins that they have committed, just like you have continued to forgive them ever since they left Egypt.”<verse eid="NUM 14:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 14:20"/>Then Yahweh replied, “I have forgiven them, as you requested me to. <verse eid="NUM 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 14:21"/>But, just as certainly as I live and that people all over the world <char style="add">can see</char> my ◄glory/glorious power►, <char style="add">I solemnly declare this:</char> <verse eid="NUM 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 14:22"/>All these people saw my glory and all the miracles that I performed in Egypt and in the desert, but they disobeyed me, and many times they tested <char style="add">whether they could continue to do evil things without my punishing them</char>. <verse eid="NUM 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 14:23"/>Because of that, not one of them will see the land that I promised their ancestors <char style="add">that I would give to them</char>. No one who rejected me will see that land. <verse eid="NUM 14:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 14:24"/>But Caleb, who serves me <char style="add">well</char>, is different from the others. He obeys me completely. So I will bring him into that land that he has already seen, and his descendants will inherit/possess some of it. <verse eid="NUM 14:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 14:25"/>So, since the descendants of Amalek and Canaan who are living in the valleys <char style="add">in Canaan are very strong</char>, when you leave here tomorrow, <char style="add">instead of traveling toward Canaan</char>, go back along the road through the desert towards the Red Sea.”<verse eid="NUM 14:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Yahweh punished the Israelis</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 14:26"/>Then Yahweh said to Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 14:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 14:27"/>“How long will the wicked people of this nation keep complaining about me [RHQ]? I have heard everything that they have grumbled/complained against me. <verse eid="NUM 14:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 14:28"/>So now tell them this: ‘Just as certainly as I, Yahweh, live, I will do exactly what you said would happen. <verse eid="NUM 14:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 14:29"/><char style="add">I will cause</char> all of you to die here in this desert! Because you grumbled about me, none of you who are more than 20 years old and who were counted when Moses counted everyone <verse eid="NUM 14:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 14:30"/>will enter the land that I solemnly promised to give to you. Only Caleb and Joshua will enter that land. <verse eid="NUM 14:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 14:31"/>You said that your children would be taken from you <char style="add">to become slaves</char>, but I will take them into the land, and they will enjoy living in the land that you ◄rejected/said that you could not conquer►. <verse eid="NUM 14:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 14:32"/>But as for you <char style="add">adults</char>, you will die here in this desert. <verse eid="NUM 14:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 14:33"/>And like shepherds <char style="add">wander around in the desert as they take care of their sheep</char>, your children will wander around in this desert for 40 years. Because you adults were not loyal/faithful to me, your children will suffer until you all die in the desert. <verse eid="NUM 14:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 14:34"/>You will suffer for your sins for 40 years. That will be one year for each of the 40 days that the twelve men explored Canaan land. And I will be like an enemy to you.’ <verse eid="NUM 14:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 14:35"/><char style="add">This will certainly happen because</char> I, Yahweh, have said it! I will do these things to every one in this group who conspired against me. They ◄conspired against/decided together to reject► me here in the desert, and they will all die right here in this desert!”<verse eid="NUM 14:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 14:36"/>Then the ten men <char style="add">who had explored Canaan and</char> who had urged the people to rebel against Yahweh by giving reports that discouraged the people <verse eid="NUM 14:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 14:37"/>were immediately struck with a plague/disease that Yahweh sent, and they died. <verse eid="NUM 14:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 14:38"/>Of the twelve men who had explored Canaan, only Joshua and Caleb remained alive.<verse eid="NUM 14:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 14:39"/>When Moses/I reported to the Israeli people what Yahweh had said, many of them were very sad. <verse eid="NUM 14:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 14:40"/>So the people got up early the next morning and started to go toward the hilly area in Canaan. They said, “<char style="add">We know that</char> we have sinned, but now we <char style="add">are ready to</char> enter the land that Yahweh promised to give to us.”<verse eid="NUM 14:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 14:41"/>But Moses/I said, “Yahweh commanded you <char style="add">to return to the desert, so</char> why are you now disobeying him [RHQ]? It will not ◄succeed/be possible►. <verse eid="NUM 14:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="NUM 14:42"/>Do not try to enter the land now! <char style="add">If you try</char>, your enemies will defeat you, because Yahweh will not ◄be with/help► you. <verse eid="NUM 14:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="NUM 14:43"/>When you begin to fight the descendants of Amalek and Canaan, they will slaughter you! Yahweh will abandon you, because you have abandoned him.”<verse eid="NUM 14:43"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="NUM 14:44"/>But even though Moses/I did not leave the camp, and the sacred chest that contained the Ten Commandments was not taken from the camp, the people began to go towards the hilly area in Canaan. <verse eid="NUM 14:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="NUM 14:45"/>Then the descendants of Amalek and Canaan who lived in that hilly area came down and attacked them and chased them as far <char style="add">south</char> as <char style="add">the town of</char> Hormah.<verse eid="NUM 14:45"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="NUM 15"/>
  <para style="s1">Instructions about offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 15:1"/>Then Yahweh told Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 15:2"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: When you arrive in the land that I am giving to you, <verse eid="NUM 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 15:3"/>you must offer to me special sacrifices which will be pleasing to me <char style="add">when the priest burns them on the altar</char>. Some of them may be offerings that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. Some of them may be to indicate that you have made a solemn promise to me. Some of them may be offerings that you yourselves have decided to make. Some of them may be offerings at one of the festivals that you celebrate each year. These offerings may be taken from your herds <char style="add">of cattle</char> or from your flocks <char style="add">of sheep and goats</char>. <verse eid="NUM 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 15:4"/>When you give these offerings, you must also bring to me a grain offering of two quarts/liters of nice flour mixed with one quart/liter of <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 15:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 15:5"/>When you offer a lamb to be a sacrifice to be completely burned, you must also pour on the altar one quart/liter of wine.<verse eid="NUM 15:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 15:6"/>‘When you offer a ram to be a sacrifice, you must also bring an offering of four quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with ◄a third of a gallon/1.3 liters► of <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 15:7"/>And also pour on the altar ◄a third of a gallon/1.3 liters► of wine. While they are being burned, the smell will be very pleasing to me.<verse eid="NUM 15:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 15:8"/>‘Sometimes you will offer a young bull to be completely burned on the altar. Sometimes you will offer a sacrifice to indicate that you have made a solemn promise to me. Sometimes you will offer a sacrifice to maintain fellowship with me. <verse eid="NUM 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 15:9"/>When you offer these sacrifices, you must also offer a grain offering of six quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with two quarts/liters of <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 15:10"/>Also pour on the altar two quarts/liters of wine to be an offering. While those special gifts are being burned, the smell will be very pleasing to me. <verse eid="NUM 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 15:11"/>Each time someone offers a bull or a ram or a male lamb or a young goat to be a sacrifice, it must be done that way. <verse eid="NUM 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 15:12"/>You must obey these instructions for each animal that you bring to me for an offering.<verse eid="NUM 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 15:13"/>‘All of you people who have been Israelis all of your lives must obey these regulations when you offer sacrifices that will be pleasing to me when they are burned on the altar. <verse eid="NUM 15:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 15:14"/>If any foreigners visit you or live among you, if they also want to bring a sacrifice that will be pleasing to me when it is burned on the altar, they must obey these same instructions. <verse eid="NUM 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 15:15"/>I consider that those who have always been Israelis and those who are foreigners are equal, and so they must all obey the same instructions. All of your descendants must also continue to obey these instructions. <verse eid="NUM 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 15:16"/>You Israelis and the foreigners who live among you must all obey the same instructions.”<verse eid="NUM 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 15:17"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 15:18"/>“Tell these instructions to the Israeli people: <char style="add">Yahweh says this</char>: ‘When you arrive in the land to which I am taking you, <verse eid="NUM 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 15:19"/>and you eat the crops that are growing there, you must set some of them aside to be a sacred offering to me. <verse eid="NUM 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 15:20"/><char style="add">Each year</char> set aside some of the first grain that you gather after you have threshed it. Bake a loaf of bread from the first flour that you grind and bring it to me to be a sacred offering. <verse eid="NUM 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 15:21"/>Every year, you and your descendants must continue to make and bring to me <char style="add">a loaf of bread baked</char> [MTY] <char style="add">with flour</char> from the first part of the grain that you harvest.’”<verse eid="NUM 15:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When people sin unintentionally or deliberately</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 15:22"/>“‘There may be times when you Israelis do not obey all these instructions that I have given to Moses to tell you, but not because you intended to disobey them. <verse eid="NUM 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 15:23"/>There may be times when some of your descendants do not obey all these instructions that I have given to Moses to tell to you. <verse eid="NUM 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 15:24"/>If you or they sin <char style="add">by forgetting to obey these instructions</char> and none of the Israeli people realize that they were doing that, one young bull as an offering for all the people <char style="add">must be brought to the priest</char>. That will be pleasing to me <char style="add">when it is burned on the altar</char>. They must also bring to me a grain offering and an offering of wine, and a male goat, to be sacrificed to enable me to forgive them for the sins they have committed. <verse eid="NUM 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 15:25"/><char style="add">By offering these sacrifices</char>, the priest will make atonement for all of you Israeli people. Then, as a result of their bringing to me an offering to be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, ◄you will be forgiven/I will forgive you►, because you sinned without realizing that you were sinning. <verse eid="NUM 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 15:26"/>You Israeli people and the foreigners who are living among you will all be forgiven.<verse eid="NUM 15:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 15:27"/>If one person commits a sin without realizing that he was sinning, that person must bring to me a female goat to be an offering to enable me to forgive that person for the sins that person has committed. <verse eid="NUM 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 15:28"/>The priest will offer it to be a sacrifice to remove the guilt of that person, and that person will be forgiven. <verse eid="NUM 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 15:29"/>You Israelis and all the foreigners who live among you must obey these same instructions.<verse eid="NUM 15:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 15:30"/>But those who disobey my commands ◄deliberately/because they want to►, both Israelis and the foreigners who live among you, have sinned against me <char style="add">by doing that</char>. So ◄they must be expelled/you must expel them► from your camp. <verse eid="NUM 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 15:31"/>They have despised my commands and deliberately disobeyed them, so they must be punished for their sin by not being allowed to live among you any more.’”<verse eid="NUM 15:31"/></para>
  <para style="s1">A man is punished for working on the Sabbath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 15:32"/>One day, while the Israelis were in the desert, some of them saw a man who was gathering firewood on the Sabbath/rest day. <verse eid="NUM 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 15:33"/>Those who saw him doing that brought him to Aaron and Moses/me and the rest of the Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 15:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 15:34"/>They guarded him carefully, because they did not know what to do <char style="add">to punish</char> him. <verse eid="NUM 15:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 15:35"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, “The man must be executed. All of you must <char style="add">kill him by throwing</char> stones at him outside the camp.” <verse eid="NUM 15:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 15:36"/>So they all took the man outside the camp and killed him by throwing stones at him, as Yahweh had commanded Moses/me that they should do.<verse eid="NUM 15:36"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Putting tassels on clothing</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 15:37"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 15:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 15:38"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: You and all your descendants must <char style="add">twist threads together to</char> make tassels, and then attach them with blue cords to the bottom edges of your clothes. <verse eid="NUM 15:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 15:39"/>When you look at the tassels, you will remember all the instructions that I gave to you, and you will obey them, instead of doing what you desire and as a result causing yourselves to become unacceptable to me. <verse eid="NUM 15:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 15:40"/>Seeing those tassels will help you to remember that you must obey all my commands and that you must be ◄my holy people/dedicated to me►. <verse eid="NUM 15:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 15:41"/>Do not forget that I am Yahweh, your God. I am the one who brought you out of Egypt in order that you might belong to me. I am Yahweh, your God.”<verse eid="NUM 15:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="NUM 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Several men rebelled against Moses</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 16:1"/>One day Korah, who was the son of Izhar and a descendant of Levi’s son Kohath, conspired with Dathan and Abiram, who were the sons of Eliab, and On, who was the son of Peleth. Those three men were from the tribe of Reuben. <verse eid="NUM 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 16:2"/>Korah and those other three men incited 250 other people who were leaders among the Israeli people to join them in rebelling against Moses/me. <verse eid="NUM 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 16:3"/>They came together to criticize Aaron and Moses/me. They said to them/us, “You two are using more <char style="add">authority</char> than you should! Yahweh has set apart all of us Israeli people, and he is with/helping all of us. So why do you act as though you are more important than the rest of us people who belong to Yahweh [RHQ]?”<verse eid="NUM 16:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 16:4"/>When Moses/I heard what they were saying, he/I prostrated himself/myself on the ground. <verse eid="NUM 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 16:5"/>Then he/I said to Korah and those <char style="add">Israeli leaders</char> who were with Korah, “Tomorrow morning Yahweh will show us whom he has chosen to be his <char style="add">priest</char>, and who is holy and allowed to come near to him. Yahweh will permit <char style="add">only</char> those whom he chooses to come into his presence. <verse eid="NUM 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 16:6"/>So Korah, tomorrow you and those who are with you must prepare your pans to burn incense. <verse eid="NUM 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 16:7"/>Then you must light a fire in them and burn the incense in the presence of Yahweh. Then we will see which one of us Yahweh has chosen to be his holy servant. It is you men who are descendants of Levi who are trying to use more <char style="add">authority</char> than you should!”<verse eid="NUM 16:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 16:8"/>Then Moses/I spoke again to Korah. He/I said, “You men who are descendants of Levi, listen to me! <verse eid="NUM 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 16:9"/>The God of us Israelis has chosen all of you to be close to him in order that you can work for him at his Sacred Tent and serve the people. ◄Is that unimportant/Does that mean nothing► to you [RHQ]? <verse eid="NUM 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 16:10"/>Yahweh has brought you, <char style="add">Korah</char>, and your fellow descendants of Levi, near to himself. Now are you demanding to become priests also? <verse eid="NUM 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 16:11"/>It is really Yahweh against whom you and your fellow descendants of Levi are rebelling. Aaron is not the one about whom you are really complaining [RHQ].”<verse eid="NUM 16:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 16:12"/>Then Moses/I summoned Dathan and Abiram, but <char style="add">they refused to come</char>. They <char style="add">sent a message</char> saying, “We will not come to you! <verse eid="NUM 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 16:13"/>You brought us out of Egypt, which was a very fertile [IDM] land, in order to cause us to die here in this desert. That was bad. But now you are also trying to boss us [RHQ], and that is worse. <verse eid="NUM 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 16:14"/>You have not given us a new land to live in, a land that has good fields and vineyards. You are only trying to [RHQ] trick these people. So we will not come to you.”<verse eid="NUM 16:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 16:15"/>Then Moses/I became very angry. He/I said to Yahweh, “Do not accept the grain offerings that they have brought. I have not taken anything from them, not even one donkey, and I have never done anything wrong to them, <char style="add">so they have no reason to complain about me</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 16:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 16:16"/>Then Moses/I said to Korah, “You and all those who are with you must come here tomorrow and stand in front of Yahweh. Aaron will also be here. <verse eid="NUM 16:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 16:17"/>You and all the 250 men who are with you must each take a pan in which to burn incense, and put incense in it, to <char style="add">burn it to be</char> an offering to Yahweh. Aaron will do the same thing.”<verse eid="NUM 16:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 16:18"/>So <char style="add">the next day</char> each of those men got a pan to burn incense. They put in it incense and hot coals to light it, and then they all stood at the entrance of the Sacred Tent with Aaron and Moses/me. <verse eid="NUM 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 16:19"/>Then Korah summoned all the people who supported him and who were against Moses/me, and they also gathered at the entrance of the tent. Then the glory of Yahweh appeared to all of them/us, <verse eid="NUM 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 16:20"/>and Yahweh said to Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 16:21"/>“Get away from all these people, in order that I can get rid of them immediately!”<verse eid="NUM 16:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 16:22"/>But Aaron and Moses/I prostrated themselves/ourselves on the ground. We pleaded with Yahweh, saying, “God, you are the one who caused all these people to live [MTY]. Only one of these men has sinned; so, ◄is it right for you to be angry with all the people?/it is not right for you to be angry with all the people!► [RHQ]”<verse eid="NUM 16:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 16:23"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 16:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 16:24"/>“<char style="add">Okay</char>, but tell all the people to get away from the tents of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram.”<verse eid="NUM 16:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 16:25"/>So Moses/I stood up and went to the tents of Dathan and Abiram. The Israeli leaders followed him/me. <verse eid="NUM 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 16:26"/>He/I told the people, “Get away from the tents of these wicked men, and do not touch anything that belongs to them! If you touch anything, you will die because of their sins!” <verse eid="NUM 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 16:27"/>So all the people moved away from the tents of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram. Dathan and Abiram came out of their tents with their wives and children and babies, and stood at the entrances of their tents.<verse eid="NUM 16:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 16:28"/>Then Moses/I said, “I was not the one who decided to do all these things that I have done. It was Yahweh who <char style="add">chose me and</char> sent me to do them. And now he will prove that to you. <verse eid="NUM 16:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 16:29"/>If these men die in a normal way, then it will be clear that Yahweh did not choose me. <verse eid="NUM 16:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 16:30"/>But if Yahweh does something that has never happened before, if he causes the ground <char style="add">that is under their feet</char> to open up and swallow these men <char style="add">and their families</char> and all their possessions, and they fall into the opening and are buried while they are still alive, then you will know that these men have insulted Yahweh.”<verse eid="NUM 16:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 16:31"/>As soon as Moses/I said this, the ground split open beneath those men. <verse eid="NUM 16:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 16:32"/>It swallowed them and their families and all those who were standing there with Korah and all of their possessions. <verse eid="NUM 16:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 16:33"/>They fell into the opening in the ground while they were still alive, and all their possessions fell into the opening also. They disappeared, and the ground closed back up again. <verse eid="NUM 16:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 16:34"/>They screamed as they fell, and all the people who were standing nearby heard them scream. The people <char style="add">were terrified and</char> cried out as they ran away, saying, “<char style="add">We do not want</char> the ground to swallow us also!”<verse eid="NUM 16:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 16:35"/>And then a fire from Yahweh came down <char style="add">from the sky</char> and burned up the 250 men who were burning the incense!<verse eid="NUM 16:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 16:36"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 16:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 16:37"/>“Tell Aaron’s son Eleazar to take the pans that had incense in them away from the fire and to scatter the burning coals. The pans that those men <char style="add">were carrying</char> are ◄holy/dedicated to me► <char style="add">because they burned incense to me in them</char>. <verse eid="NUM 16:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 16:38"/>Those men have now died because of their sin; so <char style="add">Eleazar must</char> take their pans and hammer the metal to make it become very thin. He must make a covering for the altar with that metal. Those pans were used to offer incense to me, so they are ◄holy/dedicated to me►. <char style="add">What happened to</char> those pans will now warn the Israeli people.”<verse eid="NUM 16:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 16:39"/>So Eleazar the priest collected the 250 pans for burning incense that had been used by the men who died in the fire. He hammered the pans very thin to make a covering for the altar, as Yahweh told Moses/me should be done. <verse eid="NUM 16:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 16:40"/>That warned the Israeli people that only those who were descendants of Aaron were permitted to burn incense for an offering to Yahweh. If anyone else did that, the same thing that happened to Korah and those who were with him would happen to them.<verse eid="NUM 16:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 16:41"/>But the following morning, all the Israeli people started to complain against Aaron and Moses/me, saying “You have killed many people who belonged to Yahweh!”<verse eid="NUM 16:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="NUM 16:42"/>When all the people gathered together to protest about what Aaron and Moses/I had done, they looked at the Sacred Tent and saw that the sacred cloud had covered it, and the glory of Yahweh had appeared. <verse eid="NUM 16:42"/><verse number="43" style="v" sid="NUM 16:43"/>Aaron and Moses/I went and stood in front of the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 16:43"/><verse number="44" style="v" sid="NUM 16:44"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 16:44"/><verse number="45" style="v" sid="NUM 16:45"/>“Get away from these people, in order that I can get rid of them immediately <char style="add">without injuring you two</char>!” But Aaron and Moses/I prostrated themselves/ourselves on the ground <char style="add">and prayed</char>.<verse eid="NUM 16:45"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="NUM 16:46"/>Moses/I said to Aaron, “Quickly take another pan and put in it some burning/hot coals from the altar. Put incense in the pan, and carry it out among the people to atone for the sins of the people. Yahweh is very angry with them, and <char style="add">I know that</char> a ◄severe plague/bad sickness► has already started among them.” <verse eid="NUM 16:46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="NUM 16:47"/>So Aaron did what Moses/I told him. He took the burning incense out among the people. The plague had already started to strike the people, but Aaron continued to burn the incense so that God would forgive them for the sins they had committed. <verse eid="NUM 16:47"/><verse number="48" style="v" sid="NUM 16:48"/>He stood between the people who had already died and those who were still alive, and then the plague stopped. <verse eid="NUM 16:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="NUM 16:49"/>But 14,700 people had already died from that plague/sickness, in addition to the people who died with Korah. <verse eid="NUM 16:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="NUM 16:50"/>Then after the plague had ended, Aaron and Moses/I returned to the entrance of the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 16:50"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="NUM 17"/>
  <para style="s1">Aaron’s walking stick budded</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 17:1"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 17:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people to bring to you twelve walking sticks. They should bring one from each of the leaders of the twelve tribes. You should carve each leader’s name on his stick. <verse eid="NUM 17:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 17:3"/>There must be one stick for the leader of each tribe, so you must carve Aaron’s name on the stick for the tribe of Levi. <verse eid="NUM 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 17:4"/>Put those sticks inside the Sacred Tent, in front of the sacred chest that has in it the tablets on which the Ten Commandments are written. That is the place where I always talk with you. <verse eid="NUM 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 17:5"/>Buds will sprout on the stick of the man whom I have chosen <char style="add">to be the priest</char>. <char style="add">When the people see that</char>, they will stop their constantly complaining about you <char style="add">because they will realize that you are the one whom I have chosen</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 17:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 17:6"/>So Moses/I told the people what Yahweh had said. Then each of the twelve Israeli leaders, including Aaron, brought his walking stick to Moses/me. <verse eid="NUM 17:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 17:7"/>Moses/I placed the sticks inside the Sacred Tent in front of the sacred chest.<verse eid="NUM 17:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 17:8"/>The following morning, when he/I went into the tent, he/I saw that Aaron’s stick, which represented the tribe of Levi, had sprouted, it had produced leaves and blossoms, and it had also produced almonds that were ripe! <verse eid="NUM 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 17:9"/>Moses/I brought all the sticks out of the Sacred Tent and showed them to the people. Each of the twelve leaders took back his own stick.<verse eid="NUM 17:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 17:10"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Put Aaron’s stick in front of the sacred chest, and let it stay there permanently. That will be a warning to people who want to rebel <char style="add">against me</char>. Then no more people will die <char style="add">because of complaining against me</char>.” <verse eid="NUM 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 17:11"/>So Moses/I did what Yahweh had commanded.<verse eid="NUM 17:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 17:12"/>Then the Israeli people said to Moses/me, “We are going to die! All of us are surely going to die! <verse eid="NUM 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 17:13"/>Everyone who comes close to Yahweh’s Sacred Tent dies. Are the rest of us going to die, also?” [RHQ]<verse eid="NUM 17:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="NUM 18"/>
  <para style="s1">The duties of the priests and Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 18:1"/>Yahweh said to Aaron, “You and your sons and the other members of your father’s family are the ones ◄who will be punished/whom I will punish► <char style="add">if anything bad happens to the things</char> inside the Sacred Tent. But only you and your sons will be punished if the priests do something bad. <verse eid="NUM 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 18:2"/>Require that those who belong to your tribe, the tribe of Levi, must assist you and your sons while you perform your work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 18:3"/>But while they do that work, they must not go near the sacred items inside the tent or near the altar. If they do that, they will die, and you will die, too! <verse eid="NUM 18:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 18:4"/>They may assist you in doing all the work to take care of the Sacred Tent, but no one else is permitted to come near the place where you are working.<verse eid="NUM 18:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 18:5"/>“You are the ones who will do the sacred work inside the Sacred Tent and at the altar. If you obey these instructions, I will not become very angry with the Israeli people again. <verse eid="NUM 18:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 18:6"/>I myself have chosen the descendants of Levi from the other Israelis in order that they may be your special helpers. They are like a gift that I have given you to work at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 18:7"/>But it is you and your sons, who are the priests, who must perform all the rituals concerning the altar and with what happens inside the Very Holy Place. I am giving to you this work of serving as priests. So anyone else who tries to do that work must be executed.”<verse eid="NUM 18:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The offerings for the priests and Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 18:8"/>Yahweh also said to Aaron, “I myself have appointed you to take care of all the sacred offerings that the Israeli people bring to me. I have given all these sacred offerings to you and to your sons. You and your descendants will get a share of these offerings permanently. <verse eid="NUM 18:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 18:9"/>The parts of the offerings that are not completely burned on the altar belong to you. Those parts of the sacred offerings, including the offerings of grain, the offerings for sins and for the people to be forgiven for not giving me what they are required to give, are set apart, and are to be given to you and your sons. <verse eid="NUM 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 18:10"/>You must eat those offerings in a sacred place, <char style="add">near the Sacred Tent</char>. You and all of the other males <char style="add">in your clan</char> may eat them, but you must consider those offerings to be holy/dedicated to me.<verse eid="NUM 18:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 18:11"/>“The priests lift up high the sacred offerings while they are standing in front of the altar. All of those offerings that the Israelis offer to me belong to you and your sons and daughters. They will always be your share. All the members of your family who <char style="add">have performed the rituals to cause them to </char> be acceptable to me are permitted to eat from these offerings.<verse eid="NUM 18:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 18:12"/>“ am <char style="add">also</char> giving to you the first food that people harvest each year and bring to me—the best <char style="add">olive</char> oil and new wine and grain. <verse eid="NUM 18:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 18:13"/>All of the first crops that people harvest and bring to me belong to you. Anyone in your family who has <char style="add">performed the ritual to</char> become acceptable to me is permitted to eat that food.<verse eid="NUM 18:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 18:14"/>“Everything in Israel that is set apart to belong to me also belongs to you. <verse eid="NUM 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 18:15"/>The firstborn males, both humans and domestic animals, that are offered to me, will be yours. But people must buy back their firstborn sons and the firstborn animals that may not be used for sacrifices. <verse eid="NUM 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 18:16"/>They must buy them back when they are one month old. The price that they must pay <char style="add">for each one</char> is five pieces of silver. They must weigh the silver on the scales that are in the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 18:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 18:17"/>“But they are not permitted to buy back the firstborn cattle or sheep or goats. They are holy and have been set apart for me. <char style="add">Slaughter them and</char> sprinkle their blood on the altar. Then completely burn the fat of those animals <char style="add">on the altar</char> to be an offering to me. The smell as they burn will be very pleasing to me. <verse eid="NUM 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 18:18"/>The meat from those offerings will be yours, just like the breast and right thigh of animals that are presented to me to maintain fellowship with me as the priest lifts them up high in front of the altar are yours. <verse eid="NUM 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 18:19"/>Anything that the Israeli people present to me as holy/sacred gifts, I am giving to you. They are for you and your sons and daughters <char style="add">to eat</char>. They will always be your share. This is an agreement that I am making with you, an agreement that will ◄last forever/never be changed►. I am also making this agreement with your descendants.”<verse eid="NUM 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 18:20"/>Yahweh also said to Aaron, “You priests will not receive any of the land or the property like the <char style="add">other</char> Israeli people will receive. I am what you will receive.<verse eid="NUM 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 18:21"/>“Then the Israeli people bring to me a tenth of all <char style="add">the crops and of their newborn animals</char>, I will give that to you descendants of Levi. That will be your payment for the work you do at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 18:22"/>The other Israelis must not go near that tent. If they go near it, <char style="add">I will consider that their doing that is a sin, and </char> they will die for committing that sin. <verse eid="NUM 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 18:23"/>Only the descendants of Levi are permitted to work at the Sacred Tent, and they will be punished if anything bad happens to it. That is a law that will never be changed. You descendants of Levi will not receive any land among the other Israeli people, <verse eid="NUM 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 18:24"/>because I will give you one tenth of all the <char style="add">crops and animals</char> that the Israelis bring to be offerings to me. That is why I said that you will not receive any land like the other Israelis will receive.”<verse eid="NUM 18:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 18:25"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 18:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 18:26"/>“Tell this to the descendants of Levi: ‘When you receive one tenth of all <char style="add">the crops and animals</char> from the Israeli people, you must give one tenth of all that to me to be a sacred offering. <verse eid="NUM 18:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 18:27"/>Just like the other Israelis give one tenth of the grain and wine that they produce, <verse eid="NUM 18:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 18:28"/>you must give to me one tenth of all that you receive from them. That will be your sacred offering to me. You must present it to Aaron. <verse eid="NUM 18:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 18:29"/>Select the best parts of the things that are given to you to give them to me.’<verse eid="NUM 18:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 18:30"/>“Also, tell this to the descendants of Levi: ‘When you present those best portions of grain and wine as your offering to me, I will consider that those gifts are as though they came from your own grain fields and vineyards. <verse eid="NUM 18:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 18:31"/>You descendants of Levi and your families are permitted to eat <char style="add">the rest of</char> that food, and you may eat it wherever <char style="add">you want to</char>, because it is your payment for the work that you do at the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 18:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 18:32"/>If you give to the priests the best portions of what you receive, you will not be punished <char style="add">by me</char> for accepting one tenth of the gifts that the people bring to me. But you must consider those gifts to be sacred/holy. If you sin <char style="add">by eating those things in ways that are contrary to these regulations that I have given to you</char>, you will be executed.’ ”<verse eid="NUM 18:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="NUM 19"/>
  <para style="s1">The ritual for removing the guilt of sin</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 19:1"/>Yahweh said to Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 19:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 19:2"/>“I am now giving to you another regulation. Tell the Israeli people to bring to you one reddish-brown cow that has no defects. It must be an animal that ◄has never been/no one has ever► used for plowing ground. <verse eid="NUM 19:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 19:3"/>Give it to Eleazar, the priest. He must take it outside the camp and slaughter it <char style="add">and drain the blood in a basin</char>. <verse eid="NUM 19:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 19:4"/>He must dip one of his fingers in the blood and sprinkle some of it seven times <char style="add">on the ground</char> near the Sacred Tent. <verse eid="NUM 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 19:5"/>Then, while Eleazar watches, the cow must be burned completely—its hide, its meat, <char style="add">the rest of</char> its blood, and even its dung. <verse eid="NUM 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 19:6"/>Eliezer then must take a stick of cedar wood, a stalk of <char style="add">a plant named</char> hyssop, and some scarlet/red yarn, and throw them into the fire where the cow is burning.<verse eid="NUM 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 19:7"/>“Then the priest must wash his clothes and bathe. After doing that, he may return to the camp. But he will be unfit for doing any sacred work until that evening. <verse eid="NUM 19:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 19:8"/>The man who burns the cow must also wash his clothes and bathe, and he will also be unacceptable to me until that evening.<verse eid="NUM 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 19:9"/>“Then someone who has not become unacceptable to me must gather up the ashes of the cow and put them in a ◄sacred place/place that is acceptable to me► outside the camp. The ashes must be kept there for the people of Israel to <char style="add">use when they</char> mix it with water for the ritual to remove the guilt of sin. <verse eid="NUM 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 19:10"/>The man who gathers up the ashes of the cow must <char style="add">also</char> wash his clothes, and he <char style="add">also</char> will be unfit to do any more sacred work until that evening. That is a regulation that will never be changed. It must be obeyed by you Israeli people and by any foreigners who live among you.<verse eid="NUM 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 19:11"/>“All those who touch a corpse will be unacceptable to me for seven days. <verse eid="NUM 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 19:12"/>On the third day and on the seventh day <char style="add">after touching a corpse</char>, in order to become acceptable to me again, <char style="add">they must have sprinkled on them</char> some of that water for removing the guilt of their sin. If they do not do that on both of those days, they will continue to be unacceptable to me. <verse eid="NUM 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 19:13"/>All those who touch a corpse, and do not perform in the correct way the ritual to become acceptable to me again, defile Yahweh’s Sacred Tent. They will no longer be permitted to live among the Israeli people. The water to remove the guilt of sin was not sprinkled on them, so they continue to be unacceptable to me.<verse eid="NUM 19:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 19:14"/>“There is another ritual that must be performed when someone dies inside a tent. All those who were inside that tent when that person died or who enter that tent will be unacceptable to me for seven days. <verse eid="NUM 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 19:15"/>Any jars that are inside that tent that are not covered are not permitted to be used. <verse eid="NUM 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 19:16"/>If someone who is out in a field touches the corpse of someone who was murdered, or who died from natural causes, or if someone touches a bone from some human or touches a grave, that person will be unacceptable to me for seven days.<verse eid="NUM 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 19:17"/>“For someone like that to become acceptable to me again, some of the ashes from <char style="add">the cow</char> that was burned must be taken and put in a jar. Then some fresh water must be poured over the ashes. <verse eid="NUM 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 19:18"/>Then someone who is still acceptable to me must take a stalk of <char style="add">a plant named</char> hyssop and dip it into the water. Then that person must sprinkle some of the water on the tent where that person died, on the things that are in the tent, and on the people who were in the tent. He must also sprinkle some of that water on any person who touched a human bone or who touched a person who died, or who touched a grave. <verse eid="NUM 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 19:19"/>On the third day and on the seventh day after that, the person who is acceptable to me must sprinkle some of that water on those who have become unacceptable to me. On the seventh day, the people who are performing that ritual to become acceptable to me again must wash their clothes and bathe. If they do that, on that evening they will become acceptable to me again.<verse eid="NUM 19:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 19:20"/>“If those who have become unacceptable to me do not become acceptable to me again by doing this, they will no longer be permitted to live among the Israeli people, because they have defiled my Sacred Tent. They did not sprinkle on themselves the water that removes the guilt of their sins, so they remain unacceptable to me. <verse eid="NUM 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 19:21"/>That is a law for the Israeli people that will never be changed. Those who sprinkle that water on themselves must then wash their clothes. And anyone who touches that water which removes guilt for sins will remain unacceptable to God until that evening.<verse eid="NUM 19:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 19:22"/>“If someone touches a thing or a person that has become unacceptable to me, that person will remain unacceptable to me until that evening.”<verse eid="NUM 19:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="NUM 20"/>
  <para style="s1">Water flowed from a rock</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 20:1"/>In March/April <char style="add">of the next year</char>, the Israeli people traveled/walked to the Zin Desert and ◄camped/set up their tents► near Kadesh <char style="add">town</char>. While they/we were there, <char style="add">Moses’/my older sister</char> Miriam died and was buried there.<verse eid="NUM 20:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 20:2"/>There was no water for the people to drink there, so they came to Aaron and Moses/me. <verse eid="NUM 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 20:3"/>They complained and said, “We wish that we had died in front of Yahweh’s Sacred Tent when our fellow Israelis died! <verse eid="NUM 20:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 20:4"/>◄Did you bring us, who are Yahweh’s people, into this desert to die along with our livestock?/You brought us, who are Yahweh’s people, into this desert to die along with our livestock!► [RHQ] <verse eid="NUM 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 20:5"/>Why did you bring us from Egypt to this miserable place [RHQ]? There is no grain, there are no figs, no grapes, and no pomegranates here. And there is no water for us to drink!”<verse eid="NUM 20:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 20:6"/>Aaron and Moses/I turned away from the people and went to the entrance of the Sacred Tent and prostrated themselves/ourselves on the ground. Then Yahweh appeared to them/us with his bright glory, <verse eid="NUM 20:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 20:7"/>and he said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 20:8"/>“You and Aaron must take Aaron’s walking stick with you and gather all the people together. While the people are watching, command that water will flow out of that <char style="add">large</char> rock over there. Water for the people will flow from it; all they and all their livestock will have enough water to drink.”<verse eid="NUM 20:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 20:9"/>So Moses/I did what Yahweh told him/me to do. He/I took Aaron’s walking stick from the place in the Sacred Tent where it was kept. <verse eid="NUM 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 20:10"/>Then Aaron and he/I summoned all the people to gather at the rock. Then Moses/I shouted to them, “All you rebellious people, listen! Is it necessary for us to give you water from this rock?” <verse eid="NUM 20:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 20:11"/>Then Moses/I raised his/my hand and <char style="add">instead of speaking to the rock</char>, he/I struck the rock two times with the walking stick. And water gushed/poured out. So all the people and their livestock drank all the water that they wanted.<verse eid="NUM 20:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 20:12"/>But Yahweh said to Aaron and Moses/me, “You did not believe that I could demonstrate my power to the Israeli people <char style="add">and give them water without your striking the rock</char>. So you will not lead them into the land that I am giving to them!”<verse eid="NUM 20:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 20:13"/>Later this place was called Meribah, <char style="add">which means ‘arguing’</char>, because there the Israeli people argued with Yahweh, and there he showed his power to them <char style="add">by giving them water</char>.<verse eid="NUM 20:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The king of Edom refused to allow the Israelis to travel through his country</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 20:14"/>
    <char style="add">While the people were</char> at Kadesh <char style="add">town</char>, Moses/I sent messengers to the king of Edom to tell him this:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 20:14">“Your relatives, the Israeli people, are sending you this message. You know the many troubles/hardships that have happened to us. <verse eid="NUM 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 20:15"/>You know that our ancestors went down to Egypt. You know that they stayed there for many years. They suffered because the <char style="add">rulers of</char> Egypt caused them to become their slaves <char style="add">and to work very hard</char>.<verse eid="NUM 20:15"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 20:16"/>“But when they called out to Yahweh, he heard them and sent an angel who brought them out of Egypt. Now we have set up our tents here at Kadesh, a town at the border of your land. <verse eid="NUM 20:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 20:17"/>Please allow us to travel through your country. We will <char style="add">be careful to</char> not walk through your fields and your vineyards. We will not even drink water from your wells. As we travel, we will stay on the king’s highway, <char style="add">the main road that goes from the south to the north</char>, and we will not leave that road until we have crossed the border <char style="add">of your country in the north</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 20:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 20:18"/>But the king of Edom refused. He replied, “Stay out of my country! If you try <char style="add">to enter it</char>, I will <char style="add">send my army to</char> attack you!”<verse eid="NUM 20:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 20:19"/>The Israeli messengers replied, “<char style="add">If we travel through your country</char>, we will stay on the main road. If we and any of our livestock drink any of your water, we will pay for it. We want only to travel through your country. We do not want anything else.”<verse eid="NUM 20:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 20:20"/>But the king replied, “No! Stay out of our country! We will not <char style="add">allow you</char> to travel through our land!” Then he sent the strongest soldiers in his army to prevent the Israelis <char style="add">from entering his country</char>.<verse eid="NUM 20:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 20:21"/>So, because <char style="add">the king of</char> Edom refused to allow the Israelis to travel through his country, the Israelis turned <char style="add">and traveled a different way</char>.<verse eid="NUM 20:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Aaron died</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 20:22"/>The Israeli people left Kadesh. They went to Hor Mountain, <verse eid="NUM 20:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 20:23"/><char style="add">which is at the border of Edom</char>. While they were there, Yahweh said to Aaron and Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 20:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 20:24"/>“It is time for Aaron to die [EUP]. He will not enter the land that I am giving to you Israelis, because the two of you disobeyed me <char style="add">when I told you to speak to the rock to cause</char> the water <char style="add">to flow</char> at Meribah. <verse eid="NUM 20:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 20:25"/>Now you, Moses, take Aaron and his son Eleazar up on Hor Mountain. <verse eid="NUM 20:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 20:26"/>There you must remove Aaron’s robes <char style="add">that he wears when he does the work of a priest</char>, and put them on his son, Eleazar. Aaron will die up there.”<verse eid="NUM 20:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 20:27"/>So Moses/I did what Yahweh commanded. The three of them/us climbed up Hor Mountain, while all the Israeli people watched. <verse eid="NUM 20:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 20:28"/>At the top of the mountain, Moses/I took off the robes that Aaron wore <char style="add">while he did the work of a priest</char> and put them on Eleazar. Then Aaron died there on the top of the mountain, and Eleazar and Moses/I went back down. <verse eid="NUM 20:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 20:29"/>When the Israeli people realized that Aaron had died, they all mourned for him for 30 days.<verse eid="NUM 20:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="NUM 21"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis defeated the Canaan people</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 21:1"/>The king of Arad <char style="add">city</char> lived in the area where the Canaan people-group lived, in the desert in the southern part of the land. He heard a report that the Israelis were approaching on the road to Atharim <char style="add">village</char>. So his army attacked the Israelis and captured some of them. <verse eid="NUM 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 21:2"/>Then the Israelis solemnly vowed: “Yahweh, if you will help us to defeat these people, we will completely destroy all their towns.” <verse eid="NUM 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 21:3"/>Yahweh heard what they requested, and he enabled them to defeat the army of the Canaan people-group. The Israeli soldiers killed all the people and destroyed their towns. <char style="add">Ever since that time</char>, that place has been called Hormah <char style="add">which means ‘destruction’</char>.<verse eid="NUM 21:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The bronze snake</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 21:4"/>Then the Israelis left Hor Mountain and traveled on the road towards the Red Sea, in order to go around <char style="add">the land of</char> Edom. But the people became impatient along the way, <verse eid="NUM 21:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 21:5"/>and they began to grumble/complain against God and against Moses/me. They said, “Why have you brought us out of Egypt to die here in this desert [RHQ]? There is nothing to eat here, and nothing to drink. And we detest this lousy <char style="add">manna</char> food!”<verse eid="NUM 21:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 21:6"/>So Yahweh sent poisonous snakes among them. Many of the people were bitten by the snakes and died. <verse eid="NUM 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 21:7"/>Then the people came to Moses/me and cried out, saying, “We <char style="add">now know that we</char> have sinned against Yahweh and against you. Pray to Yahweh, asking that he will take away the snakes!” So Moses/I prayed for the people.<verse eid="NUM 21:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 21:8"/>Then Yahweh told him/me, “Make a model/image of a poisonous snake, and attach it to the top of a pole. If those who are bitten by the snakes look at that model, they will ◄recover/get well►.” <verse eid="NUM 21:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 21:9"/>So Moses/I made a snake from bronze and attached it to the top of a pole. Then, when those who had been bitten by a snake looked at the bronze snake, they recovered!<verse eid="NUM 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis traveled to Moab</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 21:10"/>Then the Israelis traveled to Oboth and ◄camped/set up their tents► there. <verse eid="NUM 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 21:11"/>Then they left there, and went to Iye-Abarim, in the desert on the eastern border of Moab. <verse eid="NUM 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 21:12"/>From there they traveled to the valley where the Zered riverbed is, and camped there. <verse eid="NUM 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 21:13"/>Then they traveled to the north side of the Arnon <char style="add">River</char>. That area is in the desert next to the land where the Amor people-group lived. The Arnon <char style="add">River</char> is the boundary between Moab and where the Amor people-group lived. <verse eid="NUM 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 21:14"/>That is why in the book called ‘The Book of the Wars of Yahweh’ it tells about</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 21:14">“Waheb <char style="add">town</char> in the Suphah area, and the ravines there;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:14">and the Arnon <char style="add">River</char><verse eid="NUM 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 21:15"/>and the ravines there,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:15">which extend as far as Ar <char style="add">village</char> on the border of Moab.”<verse eid="NUM 21:15"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 21:16"/>From there, the Israelis traveled to Beer. There was a well there, where Yahweh previously had said to Moses/me, “Gather the people together, and I will give them water.” <verse eid="NUM 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 21:17"/>There the Israelis sang this song:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 21:17">“O well, give us water!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 21:17">Sing about this well!<verse eid="NUM 21:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 21:18"/>Sing about this well</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:18">which our leaders dug;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:18">they dug out <char style="add">the dirt</char> with their royal scepters and their walking sticks.”</para>
  <para style="m" vid="NUM 21:18">Then the Israelis left that desert and went through Mattanah, <verse eid="NUM 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 21:19"/>Nahaliel, and Bamoth <char style="add">villages</char>. <verse eid="NUM 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 21:20"/>Then they went to the valley in Moab where Pisgah <char style="add">Mountain</char> rises above the desert.<verse eid="NUM 21:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis defeated kings Sihon and Og</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 21:21"/>Then the Israelis sent messengers to Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group. This was the message <char style="add">that they/we gave him</char>:<verse eid="NUM 21:21"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 21:22"/>“Allow us to travel through your country. We will stay on the king’s highway, <char style="add">the main road that goes from the south to the north</char>, until we have finished traveling through your land. We will not walk through any field or vineyard, or drink water from your wells.”<verse eid="NUM 21:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 21:23"/>But King Sihon refused. He would not allow them to walk through his land. Instead, he sent his whole army to attack the Israelis in the desert. They attacked the Israelis at Jahaz <char style="add">village</char>. <verse eid="NUM 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 21:24"/>But the Israelis completely defeated them and occupied their land, from the Arnon <char style="add">River in the south</char> to the Jabbok <char style="add">River in the north</char>. They stopped at the border of the land where the Ammon people-group lived, because <char style="add">the Ammon army was defending</char> the border strongly. <verse eid="NUM 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 21:25"/>So the Israelis occupied all the cities and towns where the Amor people-group lived, and some of the Israelis began to live in them. They occupied Heshbon <char style="add">city</char> and the nearby villages. <verse eid="NUM 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 21:26"/>Heshbon was the capital of the country. It was the city where King Sihon ruled. His army had previously defeated the army of the king of Moab, and then his people had begun to live in all of the land of Moab as far as the Arnon <char style="add">River in the south</char>.<verse eid="NUM 21:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 21:27"/>For that reason, one of the poets wrote long ago,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 21:27">“Come to Heshbon, the city where King Sihon <char style="add">ruled</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:27">We want the city to be restored/rebuilt.<verse eid="NUM 21:27"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 21:28"/>A fire blazed from Heshbon;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:28">it burned down Ar <char style="add">city</char> in Moab,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 21:28">it destroyed <char style="add">everything on</char> the hills along the Arnon <char style="add">River</char>.<verse eid="NUM 21:28"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 21:29"/>You people of Moab, terrible things have happened to you!</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:29">You people who <char style="add">worship your god</char> Chemosh have been ◄annihilated/wiped out►!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 21:29">The men who <char style="add">worshiped</char> [MET] Chemosh have run away and are now refugees,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:29">and the women <char style="add">who worshiped him</char> have been captured by <char style="add">the army of</char> Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group.<verse eid="NUM 21:29"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 21:30"/>But we have defeated <char style="add">Sihon and</char> those descendants of Amor,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 21:30">all the way from Heshbon <char style="add">in the north</char> to Dibon <char style="add">city in the south</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 21:30">We have completely obliterated/destroyed them as far as Nophah and Medeba <char style="add">towns</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 21:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 21:31"/>So the Israeli people began to live in the land where the Amor people-group lived.<verse eid="NUM 21:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 21:32"/>After Moses/I sent some men to explore the area near Jazer <char style="add">city</char>, Israeli people began to live in all the towns in that region and expelled the Amor people-group who lived there. <verse eid="NUM 21:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 21:33"/>Then they turned <char style="add">north</char> toward the Bashan region, but King Og of Bashan and all his army attacked them at Edrei <char style="add">town</char>.<verse eid="NUM 21:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 21:34"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Do not be afraid of Og, because I am going to enable your men to defeat him and his army, and to take possession of all his land. You will do to him what you did to Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group, who ruled in Heshbon.”<verse eid="NUM 21:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 21:35"/>And that is what happened. We Israelis defeated Og’s army, and killed King Og and his sons and all his people. Not a person survived! And then we Israelis began to live in their land.<verse eid="NUM 21:35"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="NUM 22"/>
  <para style="s1">King Balak summoned Balaam</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 22:1"/>Then the Israelis traveled west to the area of Moab that was in the valley of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, across the river from Jericho <char style="add">city</char>.<verse eid="NUM 22:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 22:2"/>But King Balak, the son of Zippor, who ruled Moab, found out what the Israelis had done to the Amor people-group. <verse eid="NUM 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 22:3"/><char style="add">When he saw that</char> the Israelis were very numerous, he and his people became terrified.<verse eid="NUM 22:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 22:4"/>So the king of Moab <char style="add">went to</char> the leaders of the Midian people-group and said to them, “This huge group <char style="add">of Israelis</char> will ◄wipe out/destroy► everything around them, like an ox devours grass!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 22:4">Balak was the king of Moab. <verse eid="NUM 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 22:5"/>He sent messengers to <char style="add">a prophet named</char> Balaam, who was living in his own area, in Pethor <char style="add">town</char>, near the <char style="add">Euphrates</char> River. He sent this message to request that Balaam would come <char style="add">to help him</char>:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 22:5">“A huge group of people has arrived here from Egypt. <char style="add">It looks like</char> they are covering the entire land! And they have begun to live close to us. <verse eid="NUM 22:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 22:6"/>Because they are very powerful/numerous, <char style="add">we are afraid of them. So</char> please come and curse them for me. Then my army may be able to defeat them and expel them from the land <char style="add">where they are now living</char>. I know that good things will happen to the people whom you bless, and disasters will happen to the people whom you curse.”<verse eid="NUM 22:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 22:7"/>
    <char style="add">Balak’s messengers, who were</char> leaders of both the Moab and Midian people-groups, took money with them to pay Balaam in order that he would <char style="add">come and</char> curse the Israelis. They went to Balaam and told him what Balak had said.<verse eid="NUM 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 22:8"/>Balaam said, “Stay here tonight. <char style="add">Tomorrow morning</char> I will tell you whatever Yahweh tells me that I should say to you.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 22:8">So the leaders from Moab stayed there that night. <verse eid="NUM 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 22:9"/>During the night, God appeared to Balaam and asked him, “◄Who are/Tell me about► these men who are staying with you.”<verse eid="NUM 22:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 22:10"/>Balaam replied, “Balak, the king of Moab, sent these men to tell me this: <verse eid="NUM 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 22:11"/>‘A huge group of people has come from Egypt, and they have spread all over this area. Please come immediately to curse them. Then I may be able to defeat them and expel them <char style="add">from this area</char>.’”<verse eid="NUM 22:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 22:12"/>God replied to Balaam, “Do not go with them! I have blessed those people, so you must not curse them!”<verse eid="NUM 22:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 22:13"/>The next morning, Balaam got up and told Balak’s men, “Go back home. <char style="add">But go by yourselves, because</char> Yahweh is not allowing me to go with you.”<verse eid="NUM 22:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 22:14"/>So the men from Moab returned to King Balak and they reported to him, “Balaam refused to come with us.”<verse eid="NUM 22:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 22:15"/>But Balak sent another <char style="add">group of</char> leaders to Balaam. It was a group that was larger and they were more important <char style="add">than the men in the first group</char>. <verse eid="NUM 22:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 22:16"/>They went to Balaam and told him this:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="NUM 22:16">“This is what King Balak says: ‘Please do not allow anything to hinder you from coming here. <verse eid="NUM 22:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 22:17"/>I will pay you ◄a lot of money/very well► <char style="add">if you come</char>, and I will do anything that you ask me to do. Just come and curse these <char style="add">Israeli</char> people for me!’”<verse eid="NUM 22:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 22:18"/>But Balaam answered them, “Even if Balak would give me a palace filled with silver and gold, I would not do anything to disobey Yahweh, ◄my God/the God whom I <char style="add">worship</char>►. <verse eid="NUM 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 22:19"/>But stay here one more night, like the other messengers did, and I will find out if Yahweh has anything more to say to me.”<verse eid="NUM 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 22:20"/>That night God appeared to Balaam again and said to him, “These men have come to request that you go back with them, so you may go with them, but do only what I tell you <char style="add">to do</char>!”<verse eid="NUM 22:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Balaam’s donkey spoke to warn him</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 22:21"/>So the next morning, Balaam put a saddle on his donkey and he departed <char style="add">with two of his servants</char> along with the men from Moab. <verse eid="NUM 22:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 22:22"/><char style="add">Even though God had given Balaam permission to go, he was still angry</char>. So he sent one of his angels to Balaam. This angel stood in the road to block Balaam’s path. As Balaam and the two servants were riding on their donkeys, <verse eid="NUM 22:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 22:23"/>Balaam’s donkey saw the angel. The angel was standing in the road and was holding a sword in his hand, <char style="add">but Balaam did not see him</char>.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 22:23">Balaam’s donkey turned off the road into a field. So Balaam struck the donkey and forced it to go back onto the road. <verse eid="NUM 22:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 22:24"/>Then the angel stood in a place where the road was very narrow, between two vineyards, with walls on each side of the road. <verse eid="NUM 22:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 22:25"/>When the donkey saw the angel standing there, it walked very close to the wall <char style="add">to try to get past the angel</char>. As a result, it bashed Balaam’s foot against the wall. So Balaam struck the donkey again.<verse eid="NUM 22:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 22:26"/>Then the angel went further along the road and stood at a place that was extremely narrow, with the result that the donkey could not get past at all. <verse eid="NUM 22:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 22:27"/>This time, when the donkey saw the angel, it lay down <char style="add">on the ground</char> with Balaam sitting on top of it. Balaam became extremely angry, and he struck the donkey again with his walking stick. <verse eid="NUM 22:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 22:28"/>Then Yahweh enabled the donkey to speak! It said to Balaam, “What bad thing have I done to you that caused you to strike me three times?”<verse eid="NUM 22:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 22:29"/>Balaam shouted, “I struck you because you have caused me to appear to be foolish! If I had a sword with me, I would kill you!”<verse eid="NUM 22:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 22:30"/>But the donkey answered, “I am your own donkey [RHQ], the one that you have always ridden! Have I ever done anything like this previously?”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 22:30">Balaam said, “No.”<verse eid="NUM 22:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 22:31"/>Then Yahweh enabled Balaam to see the angel standing on the road, holding a sword in his hand. Balaam <char style="add">realized that it was an angel and</char> prostrated himself on the ground in front of the angel.<verse eid="NUM 22:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 22:32"/>The angel asked him, ‘◄Why did you strike your donkey three times?/ You should certainly not have struck the donkey three times! [RHQ] I have come to block your path because what you are planning to do is wrong. <verse eid="NUM 22:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 22:33"/>Three times your donkey saw me and turned away from me. If it had not done that, I would certainly have killed you already, but I would have allowed the donkey to live.”<verse eid="NUM 22:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 22:34"/>Then Balaam said to the angel, “I have sinned. But I did not realize that you were standing there, trying to block my path. So if you do not want me to continue going, I will return home.”<verse eid="NUM 22:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 22:35"/>But the angel replied, “I will allow you to go with these men, but you must say only what I tell you to say!”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 22:35">So Balaam went on with the leaders whom Balak <char style="add">had sent</char>.<verse eid="NUM 22:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 22:36"/>When King Balak heard that Balaam was coming, he went to meet him at a Moab town alongside the Arnon <char style="add">River</char> that was at the border of his own land. <verse eid="NUM 22:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 22:37"/><char style="add">When he arrived where</char> Balaam was, he said to him, “I sent you [RHQ] a message saying that you should come immediately [RHQ]! Why did you not come immediately? <char style="add">Did you think that</char> I was not able to pay you a lot of money for coming?”<verse eid="NUM 22:37"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 22:38"/>Balaam replied, “I have come here now, but I am not able to say anything <char style="add">that I want to</char>. I will say only the words that God tells me to say [MTY].”<verse eid="NUM 22:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 22:39"/>Then Balaam went with Balak to Kiriath-Huzoth <char style="add">town</char>. <verse eid="NUM 22:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 22:40"/>There Balak killed some cattle and sheep as sacrifices, and offered <char style="add">parts of the meat</char> to Balaam and the leaders who were with him. <verse eid="NUM 22:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 22:41"/><char style="add">They slept there</char>, and the next morning Balak took Balaam part way up <char style="add">the mountain</char> to Bamoth-Baal <char style="add">village</char>. From there, they could see some of the Israeli people who were down below.<verse eid="NUM 22:41"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 22"/>
  <chapter number="23" style="c" sid="NUM 23"/>
  <para style="s1">Balaam blessed the Israeli people</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 23:1"/>Balaam said to King Balak, “Build seven altars for me here. Then kill seven young bulls and seven rams <char style="add">for a sacrifice</char>.” <verse eid="NUM 23:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 23:2"/>So Balak did that. And then he and Balaam each burned a young bull and a ram <char style="add">as a sacrifice</char> on each altar.<verse eid="NUM 23:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 23:3"/>Then Balaam said to Balak, “You stand here close to your burned offerings, and I will go and ask Yahweh if he has something else to tell me. Then I will tell you what he says to me.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 23:3">Then Balaam went by himself to the top of a hill, <verse eid="NUM 23:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 23:4"/>and God appeared to him there. Balaam said to him, “We have built seven altars, and I have killed and burned a young bull and a ram <char style="add">as a sacrifice to you</char> on each altar.”<verse eid="NUM 23:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 23:5"/>Then Yahweh gave Balaam a message to give to King Balak. Then he said, “Go back and tell him what I told you.”<verse eid="NUM 23:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 23:6"/>When Balaam returned to Balak, Balak was standing with the leaders from Moab beside the offerings he had burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="NUM 23:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 23:7"/>This is the message that Balaam told them:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:7">“Balak, the King of Moab, summoned me to come here from Syria;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:7">he brought me here from the hills at the eastern side of Syria.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:7">He said, ‘Come and curse the descendants of Jacob for me,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:7">saying that bad things will happen to these Israeli people!’<verse eid="NUM 23:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 23:8"/>But ◄how can I curse people whom God has not cursed?/I certainly cannot curse people whom God has not cursed!► [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:8">◄How can I condemn people whom Yahweh has not condemned?/I cannot condemn people whom Yahweh has not condemned!► [RHQ]<verse eid="NUM 23:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 23:9"/>I have seen them from the tops of the rocky peaks.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:9">I see that they are a group of people who live by themselves;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:9">they have separated themselves from other nations.<verse eid="NUM 23:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 23:10"/>◄Who can count the descendants of Jacob; they are as numerous as particles of &lt;dust/dirt&gt;?/No one can count the descendants of Jacob; they are as numerous as particles of &lt;dust/dirt&gt;!► [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:10">◄Who can count even a quarter of the Israeli people?/No one can count even a quarter of the Israeli people!► [RHQ]</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:10">I wish/hope that I will die like righteous people die;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:10">I hope that I will die <char style="add">peacefully</char> like they will die.”<verse eid="NUM 23:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 23:11"/>Then Balak said, “What have you done to me [RHQ]? I brought you here to curse my enemies, but instead you have ◄blessed them/asked Yahweh to bless them►!”<verse eid="NUM 23:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 23:12"/>But Balaam replied, “I can [RHQ] say only what Yahweh tells me to say. I cannot say anything else.”<verse eid="NUM 23:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Balaam prophesied about the Israelis again</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 23:13"/>Then King Balak told Balaam, “Come with me to another place. There you will see only part of the Israeli people, and you will be able to curse those people for me.” <verse eid="NUM 23:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 23:14"/>So Balak took Balaam to a field on the top of Pisgah <char style="add">Mountain</char>. There, again he built seven altars and offered a young bull and a ram <char style="add">as a sacrifice</char> on each altar.<verse eid="NUM 23:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 23:15"/>Then Balaam said to the king, “Stand here close to your burned offerings, while I go and talk with Yahweh.”<verse eid="NUM 23:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 23:16"/>So Balaam did that, and Yahweh appeared to Balaam again and gave him another message. Then he said, “Go back to Balak and tell him that message.”<verse eid="NUM 23:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 23:17"/>So Balaam returned to where the king and the leaders from Moab were standing, next to the altar where Balak had burned the sacrifices. Balak asked him, “What did Yahweh say?”<verse eid="NUM 23:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 23:18"/>Then Balaam told him this message:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:18">“Balak, listen carefully;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:18">hear what I have to say, you son of Zippor [DOU]!<verse eid="NUM 23:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 23:19"/>God is not a human being.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:19">Humans lie, but God never lies.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:19">He never changes his mind/thoughts, as humans do.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:19">Whatever he has said that he will do, he does.<verse eid="NUM 23:19"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 23:20"/>He commanded me <char style="add">to request him</char> to bless <char style="add">the Israelis</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:20">So he has blessed them, and I cannot change that.<verse eid="NUM 23:20"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 23:21"/>Yahweh their God is with/helping them;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:21">they have declared that he is their true king.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:21">So the descendants of Jacob will not be harmed;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:21">they will not have any troubles [DOU].<verse eid="NUM 23:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 23:22"/>God brought them out of Egypt <char style="add">where they were slaves</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:22">he is as strong as a wild ox.<verse eid="NUM 23:22"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 23:23"/>When people curse [PRS] the descendants of Jacob, they will not be harmed;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:23">when people work sorcery on them, it will have no power.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:23">So now people will say about the descendants of Jacob,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:23">‘God has done wonderful things for the Israelis!’<verse eid="NUM 23:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 23:24"/>They are very strong, like lionesses that are ready to attack <char style="add">other animals</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:24">they stand firm like lions.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 23:24">The lions refuse to rest until they have <char style="add">killed and</char> eaten their prey,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 23:24">and drunk the blood of the animals they slaughtered.”<verse eid="NUM 23:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 23:25"/>Then Balak said to Balaam, “If you will not curse them, then <char style="add">I certainly</char> do not <char style="add">want you to</char> bless them!”<verse eid="NUM 23:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 23:26"/>But Balaam replied, “I told you that I must do only what Yahweh tells me to do!”<verse eid="NUM 23:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Balaam prophesied about the Israelis a third time</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 23:27"/>Then King Balak said to Balaam, “Come with me; I will take you to another place. Perhaps it will please God to allow you to curse them from that place.” <verse eid="NUM 23:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 23:28"/>So Balak took Balaam to the top of Peor <char style="add">Mountain</char> where they could look down <char style="add">and see the Israelis in</char> the desert.<verse eid="NUM 23:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 23:29"/>Balaam again told Balak, “Build me seven altars again and kill seven young bulls and seven rams <char style="add">for a sacrifice</char>.” <verse eid="NUM 23:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 23:30"/>So Balak did what Balaam told him to do. He burned a young bull and a ram on each altar as sacrifices.<verse eid="NUM 23:30"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 23"/>
  <chapter number="24" style="c" sid="NUM 24"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 24:1"/>Balaam now realized that Yahweh wanted to bless the Israeli people, <char style="add">not curse them</char>. So he did not use magic/divination <char style="add">like a shaman would do</char> to find out what Yahweh wanted, as he often did. Instead, he turned toward the desert. <verse eid="NUM 24:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 24:2"/>He saw the Israeli people camped there <char style="add">in their tents</char>, with each tribe gathered in its own group. Then the Spirit of God took control of him, <verse eid="NUM 24:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 24:3"/>and enabled him to give this prophetic message to Balak:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:3">“I, Balaam, the son of Beor, am giving this prophecy;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:3">I am speaking as a man who sees <char style="add">what will happen in the future</char> clearly speaks.<verse eid="NUM 24:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 24:4"/>I hear this message from God;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:4">I see a vision from him who is all-powerful.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:4">My eyes are open as I prostrate myself in front of him.<verse eid="NUM 24:4"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 24:5"/>You descendants of Jacob, your tents are very beautiful;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:5">they are truly lovely!<verse eid="NUM 24:5"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 24:6"/>Your tents are spread out <char style="add">in front of me like groves of palm trees in</char> valleys,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:6">like gardens alongside a river.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:6">They are like strong aloe trees/plants that Yahweh has planted,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:6">like <char style="add">strong</char> cedar trees <char style="add">that grow</char> along the rivers.<verse eid="NUM 24:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 24:7"/>Your water buckets will always be full;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:7">the seeds <char style="add">that you plant</char> will always have plenty of water <char style="add">to make them grow</char>.</para>
  <para style="b" vid="NUM 24:7"/>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:7">The Israelis’ king will be greater than <char style="add">King</char> Agag;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:7">the kingdom that he rules will be honored.<verse eid="NUM 24:7"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 24:8"/>God brought the Israelis out of Egypt,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:8">
    <char style="add">leading them along</char> with his great power [MTY] like a wild ox has.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:8">He devastates all the nations that oppose him;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:8">he breaks all those people’s bones into pieces,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:8">and shoots them with his arrows.<verse eid="NUM 24:8"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 24:9"/>The Israelis are like lions that crouch and lie down, <char style="add">ready to pounce on their prey</char> [SIM].</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:9">They are like lionesses <char style="add">that are resting, but ready to attack</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:9">no one [RHQ] would dare to arouse them!</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 24:9">
    <char style="add">God</char> will bless everyone who blesses you Israelis,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:9">and he will curse everyone who curses you.”<verse eid="NUM 24:9"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 24:10"/>Then King Balak was extremely angry with Balaam. He showed with his hands that he was very angry, and he <char style="add">shouted at Balaam</char>, “I summoned you here to curse my enemies! Instead, you have ◄blessed/asked God to bless► them three times! <verse eid="NUM 24:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 24:11"/>So now, get out of here! Go back home! I said that I would pay you a lot of money <char style="add">if you cursed them</char>, but Yahweh has prevented you from getting any pay!”<verse eid="NUM 24:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 24:12"/>Balaam said to Balak, “<char style="add">Do you not remember what</char> [RHQ] I told the messengers that you sent to me? I said, <verse eid="NUM 24:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 24:13"/>‘Even if Balak would give me a palace filled with silver and gold, I would not disobey Yahweh. I cannot do anything bad or anything that is good <char style="add">that he does not approve of</char>.’ And I told you that I could say only what Yahweh says to me. <verse eid="NUM 24:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 24:14"/>So yes, I will return to my people, but first, allow me to tell you what will happen to you Moab people in the future.”<verse eid="NUM 24:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Balaam prophesied a fourth time</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 24:15"/>So Balaam said this <char style="add">to Balak</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:15">“I, Balaam, son of Beor, am again giving a prophecy,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:15">speaking as a man who sees <char style="add">what will happen in the future</char> clearly speaks.<verse eid="NUM 24:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 24:16"/>I hear a message from God;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:16">I know things that God, who lives in heaven, has <char style="add">revealed to me</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:16">I see a vision from him who is all-powerful.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:16">My eyes are open as I prostrate myself in front of him.<verse eid="NUM 24:16"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 24:17"/>The things that I see <char style="add">in the vision</char> are not <char style="add">going to happen</char> <char style="bd">now</char>;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:17">I see things <char style="add">that God will cause to happen</char> in the future.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:17">A man who is <char style="add">a descendant of</char> Jacob will appear like a star [MET];</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:17">a king who holds a scepter will be one of the Israeli people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:17">He will crush the heads of you people of Moab;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:17">he will wipe out the descendants of Seth.<verse eid="NUM 24:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 24:18"/>The Israelis will occupy Edom,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:18">and they will conquer their enemies <char style="add">who live near</char> Seir <char style="add">Mountain</char>.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:18">The Israeli people will be victorious/strong.<verse eid="NUM 24:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 24:19"/>A ruler who is a descendant of Jacob will come;</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:19">he will get rid of the people who still live in the city <char style="add">where Balaam first met Balak</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 24:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Balaam’s final prophecies</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 24:20"/>Then Balaam looked out over where the Amalek people-group <char style="add">lived</char>, and he prophesied this:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:20">“The Amalek people-group were the greatest nation,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:20">but they will be wiped out.”<verse eid="NUM 24:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 24:21"/>Then he looked out over the area where the Ken people-group <char style="add">lived</char>, and he prophesied this:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:21">“You <char style="add">think that</char> the place where you live is secure/safe</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:21">like a nest that is made in the cliffs [MET],<verse eid="NUM 24:21"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 24:22"/>but you will be wiped out</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:22">when the army of Assyria conquers you.”<verse eid="NUM 24:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 24:23"/>Balaam ended his prophecies by saying,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="NUM 24:23">“Also, ◄who can &lt;survive/escape&gt; when God does all these things?/no one will be able to &lt;survive/escape&gt; when God does all these things!► [RHQ]<verse eid="NUM 24:23"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 24:24"/>Ships will come from Cyprus <char style="add">Island</char>,</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:24">and <char style="add">the men in those ships</char> will defeat <char style="add">the armies of</char> Assyria and Eber.</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="NUM 24:24">But God will get rid of those men, too.”<verse eid="NUM 24:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 24:25"/>Then Balaam and Balak returned to their homes.<verse eid="NUM 24:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 24"/>
  <chapter number="25" style="c" sid="NUM 25"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis worshiped Baal</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 25:1"/>While the Israelis were camped at a place called Acacia <char style="add">Grove</char>, some of the men caused themselves to become unacceptable to God by having sex with some of the women of the Moab <char style="add">people-group who lived in that area</char>. <verse eid="NUM 25:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 25:2"/>Then those women invited the men to come when the sacrifices were being offered to their gods. The Israeli men <char style="add">accepted</char>. They went to the feasts with the women and worshiped the gods of the Moab people-group. <verse eid="NUM 25:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 25:3"/>By doing that, those Israeli people joined the women in worshiping the god Baal <char style="add">add </char>who the Moab people-group thought lived on Peor Mountain. That caused Yahweh to become very angry with his people.<verse eid="NUM 25:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 25:4"/>Yahweh said this to Moses/me: “Seize all the leaders of those men who are doing this and execute them while I am watching. Do that in the daytime. After you do that, I will no longer be angry with the Israeli people.”<verse eid="NUM 25:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 25:5"/>So Moses/I said to the other Israeli leaders, “Each of you must execute your men who have joined <char style="add">others</char> in worshiping Baal.”<verse eid="NUM 25:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 25:6"/>
    <char style="add">But later</char>, while Moses/I and many [HYP] other people were crying at the entrance of the Sacred Tent, while they/we were watching, one of the Israeli men brought a woman from the Midian people-group into his tent <char style="add">and started to have sex with her</char>. <verse eid="NUM 25:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 25:7"/>When Phinehas, who was the grandson of Aaron, saw that, he grabbed a spear <verse eid="NUM 25:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 25:8"/>and rushed into the man’s tent. He thrust the spear completely through the man’s body and into the woman’s belly <char style="add">and killed both of them</char>. When he did that, the ◄plague/serious illness► <char style="add">that had started to strike the Israelis</char> stopped. <verse eid="NUM 25:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 25:9"/>But 24,000 people had already died <char style="add">from that plague</char>.<verse eid="NUM 25:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 25:10"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 25:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 25:11"/>“Phinehas has caused me to stop being angry with the Israeli people, by being as eager as I am <char style="add">to stop this sinful behavior</char>. I was ready to get rid of all the Israeli people because I was extremely angry, but Phinehas has prevented me from doing that. <verse eid="NUM 25:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 25:12"/>Now tell him that I am making a special peace agreement with him. <verse eid="NUM 25:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 25:13"/>In this agreement, I am promising to give to him and to his descendants the right/authority to be priests. I am doing this because <char style="add">he showed that</char> he was very eager to honor me, his God, by stopping this sinful behavior. He has caused the Israeli people to become acceptable to me again by causing them to be forgiven for their sin.”<verse eid="NUM 25:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 25:14"/>The Israeli man who was killed with the woman of the Moab people-group was named Zimri. He was the son of Salu, who was the leader of a family from the tribe of Simeon. <verse eid="NUM 25:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 25:15"/>The woman’s name was Cozbi. She was the daughter of Zur, who was the leader of one of the clans of the Midian people-group.<verse eid="NUM 25:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 25:16"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 25:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 25:17"/>“<char style="add">Take your men and</char> attack the Midian people-group and kill them. <verse eid="NUM 25:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 25:18"/>They have become your enemies, because they tricked you Israeli people and induced/persuaded many of you to worship Baal, and because <char style="add">one of your men had sex with</char> Cozbi, who was the daughter of a leader of the Midian people-group. She was killed at the time the plague <char style="add">started because the people sinned</char> at Peor <char style="add">Mountain</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 25:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 25"/>
  <chapter number="26" style="c" sid="NUM 26"/>
  <para style="s1">The people were counted again</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 26:1"/>After the plague <char style="add">ended</char>, Yahweh said to Eleazar and Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 26:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 26:2"/>“Count all the people of Israel <char style="add">again</char>. Write down the names of all the men who are at least 20 years old who are able to fight <char style="add">in battles</char>, along with their family names.” <verse eid="NUM 26:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 26:3"/>So while the Israelis were on the plains where the Moab people-group lived, Eleazar and Moses/I told this to the Israeli leaders: <verse eid="NUM 26:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 26:4"/>“Write down the names of all the Israeli men who are at least 20 years old, as Yahweh has commanded us.”</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 26:4">
    <char style="add">So they did that</char>, and this is a record of all the descendants of Jacob who came out of Egypt <char style="add">who were still alive</char>.<verse eid="NUM 26:4"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="5-7" style="v" sid="NUM 26:5-7"/>
    <char style="add">They counted</char> 43,730 men from the tribe of Reuben, Jacob’s oldest son. They were in clans descended from Hanoch, Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi. <verse eid="NUM 26:5-7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 26:8"/>Pallu’s son was Eliab <verse eid="NUM 26:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 26:9"/>and his grandsons were Nemuel, Dathan and Abiram. Dathan and Abiram were the leaders who joined with Korah to conspire against Aaron and Moses/me and rebelled against Yahweh.<verse eid="NUM 26:9"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 26:10"/>But the earth opened up and swallowed them and Korah. Yahweh also sent a fire that burned up 250 men who supported those three men. That was a warning <char style="add">to all the Israeli people</char> that they should respect and obey the leaders whom Yahweh had appointed. <verse eid="NUM 26:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 26:11"/>But the descendants of Korah did not die <char style="add">on that day</char>.<verse eid="NUM 26:11"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="12-14" style="v" sid="NUM 26:12-14"/>The Israeli leaders counted 22,200 men from the tribe of Simeon. They were in clans descended from Nemuel, Jamin, Jakin, Zerah, and Shaul.<verse eid="NUM 26:12-14"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="15-18" style="v" sid="NUM 26:15-18"/>They counted 40,500 men from the tribe of Gad. They were in clans descended from Zephon, Haggi, Shuni, Ozni, Eri, Arod, and Areli.<verse eid="NUM 26:15-18"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="19-22" style="v" sid="NUM 26:19-22"/>They counted 76,500 men from the tribe of Judah. They were in clans descended from Shelah, Perez, Zerah, Hezron, and Hamul. Judah’s other two sons, Er and Onan, died in Canaan <char style="add">without having had any children</char>.<verse eid="NUM 26:19-22"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="23-25" style="v" sid="NUM 26:23-25"/>They counted 64,300 men from the tribe of Issachar. They were in clans descended from Tola, Puvah, Jashub, and Shimron.<verse eid="NUM 26:23-25"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="26-27" style="v" sid="NUM 26:26-27"/>They counted 60,500 men from the tribe of Zebulun. They were in clans descended from Sered, Elon, and Jahleel.<verse eid="NUM 26:26-27"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="28-34" style="v" sid="NUM 26:28-34"/>They counted 52,700 men from the tribe of Manasseh, who was one of the sons of Joseph. They were in clans descended from Machir, from his son Gilead, and from his six grandsons—Jezer, Helek, Asriel, Shechem, Shemida, and Hepher. Hepher’s son Zelophehad did not have any sons, but he had five daughters—Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah.<verse eid="NUM 26:28-34"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="35-37" style="v" sid="NUM 26:35-37"/>They counted 32,500 men from the tribe of Ephraim, who was Joseph’s other son. They were in clans descended from Shuthelah, Becher, Tahan, and Shuthelah’s son Eran.<verse eid="NUM 26:35-37"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="38-41" style="v" sid="NUM 26:38-41"/>They counted 45,600 men from the tribe of Benjamin. They were in clans descended from Bela, Ashbel, Ahiram, Shephupham, and Hupham, and from Bela’s two sons—Ard and Naaman.<verse eid="NUM 26:38-41"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="42-43" style="v" sid="NUM 26:42-43"/>They counted 64,400 men from the tribe of Dan. They were in one clan descended from Shuham.<verse eid="NUM 26:42-43"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="44-47" style="v" sid="NUM 26:44-47"/>They counted 53,400 men from the tribe of Asher. They were in clans descended from Imnah, Ishvi, and Beriah, and from Beriah’s two sons—Heber and Malkiel. Asher also had a daughter named Serah.<verse eid="NUM 26:44-47"/></para>
  <para style="li1">
    <verse number="48-50" style="v" sid="NUM 26:48-50"/>They counted 45,400 men from the tribe of Naphtali. They were in clans descended from Jahzeel, Guni, Jezer, and Shillem.<verse eid="NUM 26:48-50"/></para>
  <para style="m">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="NUM 26:51"/>The total of the Israeli men whom the leaders counted was 601,730.<verse eid="NUM 26:51"/></para>
  <para style="b"/>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="52" style="v" sid="NUM 26:52"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 26:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="NUM 26:53"/>“Divide Canaan land among the tribes. Distribute the land according the number of people in each tribe that are on your lists. <verse eid="NUM 26:53"/><verse number="54-56" style="v" sid="NUM 26:54-56"/>Decide by ◄casting lots/throwing stones which are marked► to determine which group will get which area, but give the largest areas to the groups with the most people.”<verse eid="NUM 26:54-56"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="57" style="v" sid="NUM 26:57"/>The leaders also counted the male descendants of Levi. They were in clans descended from Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. <verse eid="NUM 26:57"/><verse number="58" style="v" sid="NUM 26:58"/>These also included people from the clans of Libni, Hebron, Mahli, Mushi, and Korah. All of them were descendants of Levi. Kohath was the ancestor of Amram, <verse eid="NUM 26:58"/><verse number="59" style="v" sid="NUM 26:59"/>whose wife was Jochebed. She also was a descendant of Levi, but she was born in Egypt. She and Amram had two sons, Aaron and Moses/me, and their/our <char style="add">older</char> sister Miriam. <verse eid="NUM 26:59"/><verse number="60" style="v" sid="NUM 26:60"/>Aaron’s sons were Nadab, Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. <verse eid="NUM 26:60"/><verse number="61" style="v" sid="NUM 26:61"/>But Nadab and Abihu died when they burned <char style="add">incense for a sacrifice</char> to Yahweh in a way that disobeyed what Yahweh had commanded.<verse eid="NUM 26:61"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="62" style="v" sid="NUM 26:62"/>The leaders counted 23,000 men from the descendants of Levi who were at least one month old. But these men were not counted when the rest of the Israeli people <char style="add">were counted</char>, because they were not given any land.<verse eid="NUM 26:62"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="63" style="v" sid="NUM 26:63"/>Those were the men whom Eleazar and Moses/I said should be counted. They counted the Israeli people on the plains where the Moab people-group lived, on the <char style="add">east</char> side of the Jordan River, across from Jericho <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="NUM 26:63"/><verse number="64" style="v" sid="NUM 26:64"/>None of the men whom they counted were on the lists that were made by Aaron and Moses/me when the Israelis were in the Sinai Desert, <verse eid="NUM 26:64"/><verse number="65" style="v" sid="NUM 26:65"/>because Yahweh had said about them, “They will all die in this desert,” <char style="add">and that is what happened</char>. The only ones who were still alive were Jephunneh’s son Caleb and Nun’s son Joshua.<verse eid="NUM 26:65"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 26"/>
  <chapter number="27" style="c" sid="NUM 27"/>
  <para style="s1">The request of the daughters of Zelophehad</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 27:1"/>One day the five daughters of Zelophehad came <char style="add">to Moses/me</char>. They were Mahlah, Noah, Hoglah, Milcah, and Tirzah. <verse eid="NUM 27:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 27:2"/>They came to the entrance of the Sacred Tent and stood in front of Eleazar, Moses/me, the tribal leaders, and many [EUP] other Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 27:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 27:3"/>They said, “Our father died <char style="add">during the time that we were</char> in the desert, and he did not have any sons. But he was not among those who supported Korah, who rebelled against Yahweh. He died just because he was a sinner <char style="add">like everyone else</char>. <verse eid="NUM 27:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 27:4"/>◄Why should the name of his clan disappear <char style="add">with the result that we do not receive any land</char> only because our father had no sons?/It is not right that the name of his clan disappear <char style="add">with the result that we do not receive any land</char> only because our father had no sons.► [RHQ] So give us some land like our relatives will be getting!”<verse eid="NUM 27:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 27:5"/>So Moses/I asked Yahweh <char style="add">what to do about</char> their request. <verse eid="NUM 27:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 27:6"/>And Yahweh replied, <verse eid="NUM 27:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 27:7"/>“What the daughters of Zelophehad are requesting is right. You must give them some land, just as you are giving to their father’s relatives. Give to each of them some of the land that would have been given to their brothers <char style="add">if they had any</char>.<verse eid="NUM 27:7"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 27:8"/>“Also tell this to the Israeli people: ‘If a man who has no sons dies, give the things that his sons would have inherited to his daughters. <verse eid="NUM 27:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 27:9"/>If the man has no sons or daughters, give to his brothers the things that his sons and daughters would have inherited. <verse eid="NUM 27:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 27:10"/>If the man had no brothers, give to his father’s brothers the things that his sons or daughters or brothers would have inherited. <verse eid="NUM 27:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 27:11"/>If the man’s father has no brothers, give to his closest relative the things that the others would have inherited.’ That will be a rule for the Israeli people, because I am giving this as a command to you, Moses, <char style="add">to tell them</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 27:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Joshua was chosen to be the Israelis’ new leader</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 27:12"/>One day, Yahweh said to Moses/me, “Climb to the top of the Abarim Mountains <char style="add">east of the Jordan River</char>. Then look out over the land that I am giving to the Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 27:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 27:13"/>After you have seen it, you will die [EUP] just like your <char style="add">older</char> brother Aaron did. <verse eid="NUM 27:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 27:14"/>The reason <char style="add">that you will die and not enter that land</char> is that you both disobeyed my instructions/commands in the Zin Desert. When the Israeli people rebelled against me there at Meribah, near Kadesh, <char style="add">I told you to speak to the rock to cause</char> water to flow out of it. <char style="add">But because you struck the rock instead of speaking to it</char>, you did not show the people my holy power.”<verse eid="NUM 27:14"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 27:15"/>Then Moses/I said this to Yahweh: <verse eid="NUM 27:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 27:16"/>“Yahweh, you are the God who directs the spirits of all people. So please appoint a new leader for the Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 27:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 27:17"/>Appoint someone who will lead your people when they go to fight a battle, so that they will not <char style="add">just wander around</char> like sheep that do not have a shepherd.” [SIM]<verse eid="NUM 27:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 27:18"/>Yahweh replied, “Get Joshua, the son of Nun, who has my Spirit within him. Lay your hands on him <char style="add">to appoint him</char>. <verse eid="NUM 27:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 27:19"/>Cause him to stand in front of Eleazar the priest, as all the people are watching, and commission/appoint him to be the new leader of the Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 27:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 27:20"/>Give to him some of the authority that you now have, in order that all the Israeli people will <char style="add">know that they must</char> obey him. <verse eid="NUM 27:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 27:21"/>When you all need me to guide you, Joshua will stand in front of Eleazar. Then by ◄casting lots/throwing marked stones on the ground► Eleazar will find out what they should do.”<verse eid="NUM 27:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 27:22"/>So Moses/I did what Yahweh commanded. He/I presented Joshua to Eleazar and to all the Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 27:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 27:23"/>Moses/I laid his/my hands on him and commissioned/appointed him to do the work that Yahweh told Moses/me to tell him to do.<verse eid="NUM 27:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 27"/>
  <chapter number="28" style="c" sid="NUM 28"/>
  <para style="s1">The daily offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 28:1"/>Yahweh said this to Moses/me: <verse eid="NUM 28:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 28:2"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: Bring to me the offerings that will be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. When they are burned, the smell will be very pleasing to me. And tell them that they must bring them at the proper/right time. <verse eid="NUM 28:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 28:3"/>Tell them that what they must bring to me each day are two male lambs that are one-year-old. They must have no defects. They must be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="NUM 28:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 28:4"/>They should bring one in the morning and the other early in the evening. <verse eid="NUM 28:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 28:5"/>They must also bring an offering of grain, consisting of two quarts/liters of finely-ground flour, mixed with a quart of <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 28:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 28:6"/>That is the offering that they must bring every day. They started to bring those offerings <char style="add">while you were</char> at Sinai Mountain. When those offerings are burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, the smell will be very pleasing to me. <verse eid="NUM 28:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 28:7"/>When they burn each lamb, they must also pour on the sacred altar one quart/liter of wine. <verse eid="NUM 28:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 28:8"/>In the evening, when they offer the second lamb, they must also bring the same offerings of grain and wine <char style="add">as they burned in the morning</char>. When they are burned, the smell will also be very pleasing to me.”<verse eid="NUM 28:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The offerings on the Sabbath</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 28:9"/>“On each ◄Sabbath/rest day►, <char style="add">you must bring</char> two male lambs that have no defects. Also bring a grain offering of four quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil and a wine offering of four quarts/liters of wine. <verse eid="NUM 28:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 28:10"/>Those are the offerings that are to be burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> each ◄Sabbath/rest day►. Those are in addition to the offerings of two lambs and wine that you must bring each day.”<verse eid="NUM 28:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The monthly offerings</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 28:11"/>“On the first day of each month, you must bring to me an offering of two young bulls, one male sheep, and seven male lambs that are one-year-old. All of these must be without defects. They must all be burned <char style="add">completely on the altar</char>. <verse eid="NUM 28:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 28:12"/>Also bring with each bull an offering of six quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. With each male sheep make an offering of four quarts of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 28:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 28:13"/>Also bring an offering of two quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil with each lamb. When all of these are burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, the smell will be very pleasing to me. <verse eid="NUM 28:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 28:14"/>With each bull, also bring two quarts/liters of wine. With each male sheep, bring ◄1-1/3 quarts/1.2 liters► of wine. With each lamb, bring one quart/liter of wine. These offerings must be brought on the first day of each month and burned completely <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="NUM 28:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 28:15"/>In addition to these offerings that you burn, you must bring to me one goat for an offering <char style="add">to enable me to forgive you for the sins you have committed</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 28:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The sacrifices during the Festivals of Passover and Unleavened Bread</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 28:16"/>“The Passover Festival must be celebrated to <char style="add">honor</char> me <char style="add">each year</char> on the fourteenth day of the first month <char style="add">of each year</char>. <verse eid="NUM 28:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 28:17"/>The Festival of Unleavened Bread will start on the next day. For the following seven days, the bread that you eat must be made without yeast. <verse eid="NUM 28:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 28:18"/>On the first day of that festival, you must gather together to worship me, and you must not do any work. <verse eid="NUM 28:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 28:19"/>On that day, you must bring to me for an offering that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> two young bulls, one male sheep, and seven male lambs that are one-year-old. They must all have no defects. <verse eid="NUM 28:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 28:20"/>With each of these bulls, bring a grain offering of grain, consisting of six quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. With the male sheep, bring an offering of grain consisting of four quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 28:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 28:21"/>With each of the seven lambs, bring an offering of two quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. <verse eid="NUM 28:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 28:22"/>Also bring one goat for a sacrifice to cause you to be forgiven for your sin. <verse eid="NUM 28:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 28:23"/>Bring these offerings in addition to the offerings that you bring each morning. <verse eid="NUM 28:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 28:24"/>The smell of the grain that is burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> each day for seven days will be very pleasing to me. Bring the grain in addition to the animals and the wine that you burn <char style="add">on the altar</char>. <verse eid="NUM 28:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 28:25"/>On the seventh day of that festival, you must <char style="add">again</char> gather together to worship me, and you must not do any work.”<verse eid="NUM 28:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The sacrifices during the Harvest Festival</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 28:26"/>“On the day of the Harvest Festival, when you bring to me the first grain that you have harvested, you must gather together to worship me. Do not do any work on that day. <verse eid="NUM 28:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 28:27"/>Bring to me two young bulls, one male sheep, and seven male lambs that are one-year-old. When they are completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, the smell will be very pleasing to me. <verse eid="NUM 28:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 28:28"/>Also bring a grain offering of nice flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. For each bull, bring six quarts/liters, and with each male sheep, bring four quarts/liters, <verse eid="NUM 28:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 28:29"/>and with each of the lambs bring two quarts/liters. <verse eid="NUM 28:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 28:30"/>Also sacrifice one male goat to cause you to be forgiven for your sins. <verse eid="NUM 28:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 28:31"/>Bring these offerings and the offering of wine in addition to the animals and grain that you burn <char style="add">on the altar</char> each day. <char style="add">And remember that</char> the animals that you sacrifice must have no defects.”<verse eid="NUM 28:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 28"/>
  <chapter number="29" style="c" sid="NUM 29"/>
  <para style="s1">The sacrifices for the Festival of Trumpets</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 29:1"/>“<char style="add">Each year</char>, gather together to worship me on the first day of the seventh month, and do not do any work on that day. On that day <char style="add">the priests</char> must blow their trumpets.<verse eid="NUM 29:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 29:2"/>When the offerings <char style="add">on the altar on that day</char> are being completely burned, the smell will be very pleasing to me. The animals that you must bring are one young bull, one male sheep, and seven male lambs that are one-year-old. They must have no defects. <verse eid="NUM 29:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 29:3"/>With these animals bring an offering of grain consisting of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. With the bull, bring six quarts/liters. With the male sheep, bring four quarts/liters, <verse eid="NUM 29:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 29:4"/>and with each of the seven lambs bring two quarts/liters. <verse eid="NUM 29:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 29:5"/>Also offer one male goat in order that you will be forgiven for your sins. <verse eid="NUM 29:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 29:6"/>All of those animals are in addition to the animals that are completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> each morning and on the first day of each month. The offerings of grain and wine must be made exactly as I have told you to do. When these offerings are burned, the smell will be very pleasing to me.”<verse eid="NUM 29:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The day of Atonement</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 29:7"/>“<char style="add">Each year</char>, on the tenth day of the seventh month, you must gather together to worship me. Do not eat any food or do any work on that day. <verse eid="NUM 29:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 29:8"/>When you burn offerings <char style="add">on the altar</char> on that day, the smell will be very pleasing to me. The animals that you must bring are one young bull, one male sheep, and seven male lambs that are one-year-old. They must have no defects. <verse eid="NUM 29:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 29:9"/>With the bull, bring an offering of grain consisting of six quarts/liters of nice flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. With the male sheep, bring four quarts/liters. <verse eid="NUM 29:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 29:10"/>With each of the lambs, bring two quarts/liters. <verse eid="NUM 29:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 29:11"/>Also bring one male goat to <char style="add">enable me to forgive</char> you for the sins you have committed, and the animals and grain and wine that you burn <char style="add">on the altar</char> each day to enable me to forgive you for the sins you have committed. Those offerings will be in addition to the animals and grain and wine that are completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> each day.”<verse eid="NUM 29:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Festival of Shelters</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 29:12"/>“On the fifteenth day of the seventh month <char style="add">of each year</char>, you must all gather together to worship me. You must not do any work on that day. You must continue to celebrate for seven days. <verse eid="NUM 29:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 29:13"/>When the offerings are burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, the smell will be very pleasing to me. The animals that you must bring are 13 young bulls, two male sheep, and 14 male lambs that are one-year-old. These animals must have no defects. <verse eid="NUM 29:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 29:14"/>With each of the 13 bulls, bring a grain offering of six quarts/liters of finely-ground flour mixed with <char style="add">olive</char> oil. With each of the male sheep, bring four quarts/liters. <verse eid="NUM 29:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 29:15"/>With each of the 14 lambs, bring two quarts/liters. <verse eid="NUM 29:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 29:16"/>Also bring one male goat to be sacrificed <char style="add">to enable me to forgive you</char> for your sins, in addition to the offerings of animals and grain and wine that are completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> each day.<verse eid="NUM 29:16"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17-34" style="v" sid="NUM 29:17-34"/>“For the next six days of the festival, you must also bring animals to sacrifice. On the second day, bring twelve bulls. On the third/next day, bring eleven bulls. One the fourth/next day, bring ten bulls. On the fifth/next day, bring nine bulls. On the sixth/next day, bring eight bulls. On the seventh/last day, bring seven bulls. But on each of those days, all the other sacrifices and offerings that you bring will remain the same.<verse eid="NUM 29:17-34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 29:35"/>“On the eighth day of the festival, you must <char style="add">again</char> gather together to worship me, and do not do any work on that day. <verse eid="NUM 29:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 29:36"/>On that day, you must bring to the altar one bull, one full-grown ram, and seven lambs that are one-year-old. These animals must have no defects. They must all be burned on the altar, and their smell will please me. <verse eid="NUM 29:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 29:37"/>Bring also with the bull and the male sheep and each of the lambs the offerings of grain and wine that ◄are required/I told you to bring►. <verse eid="NUM 29:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 29:38"/>Also offer one male goat to be sacrificed <char style="add">to enable me to forgive you</char> for your sins. These animals will be in addition to the offerings of animals and grain and wine that are completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char> each day.<verse eid="NUM 29:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 29:39"/>“At your festivals, these are the offerings that you must bring to me: The offerings that will be completely burned <char style="add">on the altar</char>, the offerings of grain and wine, and the offerings to maintain fellowship with me. Those are in addition to the offerings that you give to me because you promised to do something, and other special offerings that you want to give to me.”<verse eid="NUM 29:39"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 29:40"/>Then Moses/I told to the Israeli people all the things that Yahweh had commanded him/me.<verse eid="NUM 29:40"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 29"/>
  <chapter number="30" style="c" sid="NUM 30"/>
  <para style="s1">Rules about special promises to Yahweh</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 30:1"/>Moses/I spoke with the leaders of the Israeli tribes. He/I told them these commands that Yahweh had given to him/me:<verse eid="NUM 30:1"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 30:2"/>“If a man solemnly promises Yahweh that he will do something, he must do what he promised.<verse eid="NUM 30:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 30:3"/>“If a young woman who is still living with her parents solemnly promises to Yahweh to do something, <verse eid="NUM 30:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 30:4"/>and if her father hears about what she promised, and if he does not object, she must do what she promised [DOU]. <verse eid="NUM 30:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 30:5"/>But if her father hears about what she promised and does not allow her to do that, then she does not need to do what she promised. Yahweh will forgive her for not doing what she promised.<verse eid="NUM 30:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 30:6"/>“If a woman promises Yahweh that she will do something, but then she gets married, <verse eid="NUM 30:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 30:7"/>if her husband hears about what she promised to do, and he does not object, she must do what she promised [DOU]. <verse eid="NUM 30:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 30:8"/>But if her husband hears about it and does not allow her to do that, she does not need to do what she promised, and Yahweh will forgive her for not doing what she promised.<verse eid="NUM 30:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 30:9"/>“If a widow or a woman who has been divorced makes a promise, she must do what she promised.<verse eid="NUM 30:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 30:10"/>“If a woman who is married promises [DOU] to do something, <verse eid="NUM 30:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 30:11"/>and if her husband hears about it but does not object, she must do what she promised. <verse eid="NUM 30:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 30:12"/>But if he hears about it and does not allow her to do that, she does not need to do what she promised, and Yahweh will forgive her for not doing it. <verse eid="NUM 30:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 30:13"/>A woman’s husband may require her to do what she has promised, or he may not allow her to do what she has promised. <verse eid="NUM 30:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 30:14"/>If he does not object for several days <char style="add">after he hears about it</char>, she must do what she promised. <verse eid="NUM 30:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 30:15"/>But if he waits a long time after she has promised to do something and then he tells her that he will not permit her to do it, if she does not do what she promised, <char style="add">she will not be punished</char>; her husband is the one whom <char style="add">Yahweh</char> will punish.”<verse eid="NUM 30:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 30:16"/>Those are the rules that Yahweh gave to Moses/me for husbands and wives, and for young women who are still living with their parents.<verse eid="NUM 30:16"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 30"/>
  <chapter number="31" style="c" sid="NUM 31"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis attacked the Midian people-group</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 31:1"/>Yahweh spoke to Moses/me and said, <verse eid="NUM 31:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 31:2"/>“Before you die, <char style="add">tell the</char> Israeli people that they should ◄pay back/get revenge on► the Midian people-group for what they did to you.”<verse eid="NUM 31:2"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 31:3"/>So Moses/I said to the people, “Get some men prepared for battle. Yahweh will enable them to ◄pay back/get revenge on► the Midian people-group <char style="add">for what they did to us</char>. <verse eid="NUM 31:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 31:4"/>Select 1,000 men from each tribe to fight.” <verse eid="NUM 31:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 31:5"/>So 12,000 men prepared for fighting in the battle, 1,000 from each tribe. <verse eid="NUM 31:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 31:6"/>When Moses/I sent them to the battle, Phinehas, the son of Eleazar the priest, went with them. He took with him some of the things from the Sacred Tent and the trumpets that would be blown to give the signal <char style="add">to start the battle</char>.<verse eid="NUM 31:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 31:7"/>The Israeli men fought the soldiers from the Midian people-group, as Yahweh had told Moses/me to tell them to do, and they killed every man from the Midian people-group. <verse eid="NUM 31:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 31:8"/>Among those whom they killed were the five kings of the Midian people-group—Evi, Rekem, Zur, Hur, and Reba. They also killed with a sword Balaam, the son of Beor. <verse eid="NUM 31:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 31:9"/>They captured all the women and children of the Midian people-group and took away their cattle, their flocks of sheep, and herds of goats, and all their other possessions. <verse eid="NUM 31:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 31:10"/>Then they burned down all the houses in the towns and villages where the people of the Midian people-group lived, <verse eid="NUM 31:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 31:11"/>but they took home with them all the women and children and animals and possessions. <verse eid="NUM 31:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 31:12"/>They brought all these to Eliezer and Moses/me, and to the rest of the Israeli people who were at their/our camp on the plains where the Moab people-group lived, near the Jordan River, across from Jericho. <verse eid="NUM 31:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 31:13"/>Eleazar and all the leaders of the people and Moses/I went outside the camp to greet/meet with them.<verse eid="NUM 31:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 31:14"/>But Moses/I was angry with some of the men who had returned from the battle. He/I was angry with the army officers and the men who were commanders of 1,000 men and those who were commanders of 100 men. <verse eid="NUM 31:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 31:15"/>He/I asked them, “Why did you allow the women to live [RHQ]? <verse eid="NUM 31:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 31:16"/>They are the ones who did what Balaam suggested and urged/persuaded our people to worship Baal <char style="add">instead of Yahweh</char>. As a result, Yahweh caused a plague to strike his people while they were at Peor. <verse eid="NUM 31:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 31:17"/>So, now you must kill all the boys of the Midian people-group, and also kill all the women who have had sex [EUP] with any man. <verse eid="NUM 31:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 31:18"/>Spare only the girls who are virgins [EUP]. You can keep them to be your <char style="add">wives or your slaves</char>.<verse eid="NUM 31:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 31:19"/>All of you who have killed someone or touched the corpse of someone who was killed <char style="add">in the battle</char> must stay outside the camp for seven days. On the third day and on the seventh day, you must <char style="add">perform the ritual to</char> cause you and those whom you have captured to become acceptable to God again. <verse eid="NUM 31:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 31:20"/>You must also wash your clothes and anything <char style="add">that you took to the battle</char> that is made of leather or goat’s hair or wood.”<verse eid="NUM 31:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 31:21"/>Then Eleazar said to the soldiers who had returned from the battle, “This is what Yahweh has instructed Moses: <verse eid="NUM 31:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 31:22"/>You must put into a fire any gold or silver or bronze or iron or tin or lead things <char style="add">that you brought back from the battle</char>. <verse eid="NUM 31:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 31:23"/>Put everything that will not burn into the fire, and then they will be acceptable for you to use. But also sprinkle those things with the water that causes things and people to become acceptable to God. The things that would burn <char style="add">if you put them</char> in a fire, sprinkle them with that water. <verse eid="NUM 31:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 31:24"/>On the seventh day, wash your clothes, and then you will become acceptable to God again. After you do that, you may return to the camp.”<verse eid="NUM 31:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Dividing the captured goods</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 31:25"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 31:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 31:26"/>“Tell Eleazar and the leaders of the family groups that they must write down a list of all the goods, the women, and the animals that were captured <char style="add">in the battle</char>. <verse eid="NUM 31:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 31:27"/>Then they must divide all those things, half given to the men who fought in the battle and the other half given to the rest of the people. <verse eid="NUM 31:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 31:28"/>From the men who fought in the battle, take one from every 500 people and from every 500 cattle and donkeys and sheep, to be a tax for me. <verse eid="NUM 31:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 31:29"/>Take these things to Eleazar to ◄be my share/belong to me►. <verse eid="NUM 31:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 31:30"/>And from the half that belongs to the ordinary people, take one item from every 50. That includes people, cattle, donkeys, sheep, goats, and other animals. Give those things to the descendants of Levi who take care of my Sacred Tent.” <verse eid="NUM 31:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 31:31"/>So Eleazar and Moses/I did what Yahweh commanded.<verse eid="NUM 31:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32-35" style="v" sid="NUM 31:32-35"/>There were 675,000 sheep, 72,000 cattle, 61,000 donkeys, and 32,000 virgins that they had captured from the Midian people-group.<verse eid="NUM 31:32-35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 31:36"/>The men who fought in the battle took 337,000 sheep <char style="add">from the battle</char>, <verse eid="NUM 31:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 31:37"/>and they gave 675 of them to Yahweh. <verse eid="NUM 31:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 31:38"/>They took 36,000 cattle and gave 72 of them to Yahweh. <verse eid="NUM 31:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 31:39"/>They took 30,500 donkeys, and they gave 61 of them to Yahweh. <verse eid="NUM 31:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 31:40"/>They took 16,000 virgins, and they dedicated 32 of them to Yahweh.<verse eid="NUM 31:40"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 31:41"/>Moses/I gave to Eleazar all <char style="add">the animals</char> that had been given to Yahweh, as Yahweh had commanded.<verse eid="NUM 31:41"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="42-46" style="v" sid="NUM 31:42-46"/>Moses/I separated what those who had fought in the battle received from what the other people received. The people had taken 337,500 sheep, 36,000 cattle, 30,500 donkeys, and 16,000 virgins, <verse eid="NUM 31:42-46"/><verse number="47" style="v" sid="NUM 31:47"/>From what the people received, Moses/I took one from every 50 items and dedicated them to Yahweh. That included animals and people. As Yahweh commanded, he/I gave them all to the descendants of Levi who took care of the Sacred Tent.<verse eid="NUM 31:47"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="NUM 31:48"/>Then the army officers and those who commanded 1,000 men and those who commanded 100 men came to Moses/me. <verse eid="NUM 31:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="NUM 31:49"/>They said, “We, who are your servants, have counted the soldiers whom we command, and <char style="add">we found that</char> none of them ◄is missing/has been killed►. <verse eid="NUM 31:49"/><verse number="50" style="v" sid="NUM 31:50"/>So <char style="add">to thank Yahweh for that</char>, we have brought to him a gift of the gold items that we found <char style="add">after the battle</char>: Gold arm bands and bracelets and rings and earrings and necklaces. This will enable us to be forgiven for our sins.”<verse eid="NUM 31:50"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="51" style="v" sid="NUM 31:51"/>So Eleazar and Moses/I accepted the gold items that they brought. <verse eid="NUM 31:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="NUM 31:52"/>The total of it weighed about ◄420 pounds/190 kg.►. <verse eid="NUM 31:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="NUM 31:53"/>Each soldier had taken these things for himself. <verse eid="NUM 31:53"/><verse number="54" style="v" sid="NUM 31:54"/>Eleazar and Moses/I accepted these gold items from these commanders and put them in the Sacred Tent to remind the Israeli people about how Yahweh <char style="add">had helped them defeat the Midian people-group</char>.<verse eid="NUM 31:54"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 31"/>
  <chapter number="32" style="c" sid="NUM 32"/>
  <para style="s1">The land east of the Jordan River</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 32:1"/>The people of the tribes of Reuben and Gad had much livestock. They saw that the land near Jazer <char style="add">city</char> and the Gilead <char style="add">region east of the Jordan River</char> had good <char style="add">grass</char> for the animals <char style="add">to graze on</char>. <verse eid="NUM 32:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 32:2"/>So their leaders came to Eleazar and the other leaders of the people and Moses/me. They said, <verse eid="NUM 32:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 32:3"/>“We have a great amount of livestock. <verse eid="NUM 32:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 32:4"/>Yahweh has enabled us Israelis to capture some land that is very good for animals <char style="add">to graze on</char>—the land near Ataroth, Dibon, Jazer, Nimrah, Heshbon, Elealeh, Sebam, Nebo, and Beon <char style="add">towns</char>. <verse eid="NUM 32:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 32:5"/>If it pleases you, we would like this land to be ours, instead of land on the other side of the Jordan River.”<verse eid="NUM 32:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 32:6"/>Moses/I replied to the leaders of the tribes of Gad and Reuben, “It is not right for [RHQ] your fellow Israelis to go to fight in wars and you stay here! <verse eid="NUM 32:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 32:7"/><char style="add">If you do that</char>, you will cause the other Israelis to be discouraged, with the result that they will not cross <char style="add">the Jordan River</char> to the land that Yahweh is giving to them [RHQ]. <verse eid="NUM 32:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 32:8"/>Your ancestors did the same kind of thing. I sent them from Kadesh-Barnea to see what the land <char style="add">of Canaan</char> was like. <verse eid="NUM 32:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 32:9"/>They went as far as Eshcol Valley, but when they saw <char style="add">the huge people in</char> the land, <char style="add">they returned and</char> caused the Israeli people to be discouraged, saying ‘We should not try to enter the land that Yahweh said that he is giving to us.’ <verse eid="NUM 32:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 32:10"/>So Yahweh became very angry with them, and he solemnly declared this: <verse eid="NUM 32:10"/><verse number="11-12" style="v" sid="NUM 32:11-12"/>‘From all the people who came out of Egypt, the only ones who are at least 20 years old who will see the land that I promised to give to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, are Jephunneh’s son Caleb and Nun’s son Joshua, because they trusted me completely. None of the other people who came out of Egypt will even see that land, because they have not completely believed in my <char style="add">power</char>.’ <verse eid="NUM 32:11-12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 32:13"/>So Yahweh was angry with the Israeli people, and <char style="add">as a result</char> he has caused us to wander in this desert for 40 years. Finally, all the people who had sinned against Yahweh <char style="add">by refusing to trust him</char> died, <char style="add">one by one</char>. <verse eid="NUM 32:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 32:14"/>And you are acting like your ancestors did! You sinful Israeli people are going to cause Yahweh to be more angry with you <char style="add">than he was with our ancestors</char> <verse eid="NUM 32:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 32:15"/>If you stop trusting him, he will cause you and all your fellow Israelis to stay longer in the desert, and he will get rid of all of you!”<verse eid="NUM 32:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 32:16"/>Then the <char style="add">leaders of the tribes of Reuben and Gad</char> said to Moses/me, “First we will build pens for our animals and build cities for our families here. <verse eid="NUM 32:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 32:17"/>Then our families will live in strong cities with walls around them, and they will be safe from the people who live in this land. Then we will get ready to fight battles. We will help the other Israelis to get land <char style="add">on the other side of the river</char>. <verse eid="NUM 32:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 32:18"/>We will not return to our homes until every Israeli has received some land. <verse eid="NUM 32:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 32:19"/>We will not take any land on the west side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>; our land will be here on the east side.”<verse eid="NUM 32:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 32:20"/>So Moses/I told them, “<char style="add">Okay, I will tell you</char> what you all must do. You must get ready to fight battles for Yahweh. <verse eid="NUM 32:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 32:21"/>You all must cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> carrying your weapons. <verse eid="NUM 32:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 32:22"/>After Yahweh helps us to take that land <char style="add">from the people who live there</char>, you will be permitted to return to your homes. You will have done what you have promised Yahweh and the Israeli people that you would do, and you may keep this land to be your own, given to you by Yahweh.<verse eid="NUM 32:22"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 32:23"/>“But if you do not do these things, you will be sinning against Yahweh, and he will punish you for <char style="add">that</char> sin. <verse eid="NUM 32:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 32:24"/>Now you can build cities for your families and pens for your animals, but after doing that, you must do what you have promised.”<verse eid="NUM 32:24"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 32:25"/>The leaders of the tribes of Gad and Reuben replied, “We will do what you have asked us to do [MTY], because you are our leader. <verse eid="NUM 32:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 32:26"/>Our wives and children and our cattle and sheep and goats will stay here in the cities in the Gilead area, <verse eid="NUM 32:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 32:27"/>but we will prepare to go to battle. We will take our weapons and go across <char style="add">the Jordan River</char> and fight for Yahweh, just as you, our leader, have said.”<verse eid="NUM 32:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 32:28"/>So Moses/I gave instructions about them to Eleazar, Joshua, and the leaders of the Israeli tribes. <verse eid="NUM 32:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 32:29"/>Moses/I said to them, “If the men from the tribes of Gad and Reuben prepare for battle and cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> with you, in order to do what Yahweh desires and help you to take that land, give them the Gilead area to belong to them. <verse eid="NUM 32:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 32:30"/>But if they do not take their weapons and go with you prepared to fight, they will not receive this land. They will need to accept some land in Canaan, like the rest of you will do.”<verse eid="NUM 32:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 32:31"/>The <char style="add">leaders of the tribes of Gad and Reuben</char> replied, “We will do what you have said and what Yahweh has said. <verse eid="NUM 32:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 32:32"/>We will cross the river into Canaan land, and we will do what Yahweh desires and be prepared for battle. But our land will be <char style="add">here</char> on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 32:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 32:33"/>So Moses/I agreed to give that land to the tribes of Gad and Reuben and to half of the tribe of Joseph’s son Manasseh. That land was previously the land where Sihon, the king of the Amor people-group, ruled, and the land where Og, the king of Bashan <char style="add">region</char>, ruled, including its cities and surrounding land.<verse eid="NUM 32:33"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 32:34"/>The people of the tribe of Gad rebuilt Dibon, Ataroth, Aroer, <verse eid="NUM 32:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 32:35"/>Atroth-Shophan, Jazer, Jogbehah, <verse eid="NUM 32:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 32:36"/>Beth-Nimrah, and Beth-Haran cities. Those were cities with strong walls around them. And they also built pens for their sheep.<verse eid="NUM 32:36"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 32:37"/>The people of the tribe of Reuben rebuilt Heshbon, Elealeh, Kiriathaim, <verse eid="NUM 32:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 32:38"/>Nebo, Baal-Meon, and Sibmah cities. When they rebuilt Nebo and Baal-Meon, they gave new names to those cities.<verse eid="NUM 32:38"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 32:39"/>The descendants of Manasseh’s son Makir went to the Gilead <char style="add">region</char> and compelled the people of the Amor people-group to leave that area. <verse eid="NUM 32:39"/><verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 32:40"/>So Moses/I gave Gilead to the family of Makir, and they started to live there. <verse eid="NUM 32:40"/><verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 32:41"/>Jair, who was also a descendant of Manasseh, went and captured the small towns in that region, and he named them the Towns of Jair. <verse eid="NUM 32:41"/><verse number="42" style="v" sid="NUM 32:42"/>A man named Nobah went and captured Kenath <char style="add">city</char> and the nearby towns, and then he put his own name to be the new name of that area.<verse eid="NUM 32:42"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 32"/>
  <chapter number="33" style="c" sid="NUM 33"/>
  <para style="s1">The Israelis’ journey from Egypt to Moab</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 33:1"/>Here is a list of the places where the/we Israelis went as Aaron and Moses/I led them/us after they/we left Egypt. <verse eid="NUM 33:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 33:2"/>Yahweh commanded Moses/me to write down the names of the places where they/we went.<verse eid="NUM 33:2"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 33:3"/>On the fifteenth day of the first month <char style="add">of the year</char>, the day after we celebrated the ◄Passover/the time when Yahweh killed all the firstborn sons of the people of Egypt►, they/we left Rameses <char style="add">city in Egypt</char> and marched boldly while the Egyptian army was coming behind them/us. <verse eid="NUM 33:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 33:4"/>As they/we left, the people of Egypt were still burying the bodies of their firstborn sons. <char style="add">By killing them</char>, Yahweh showed that the gods that the people of Egypt worshiped were false gods.<verse eid="NUM 33:4"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 33:5"/>After leaving Rameses, they/we first went to Succoth and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:5"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 33:6"/>Then they/we left Succoth and went to Etham, at the edge of the desert, and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 33:7"/>Then they/we left Etham and returned to Pi-Hahiroth, to the east of Baal-Zephon, and set up their/our tents near Migdol.<verse eid="NUM 33:7"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 33:8"/>Then they/we left Pi-Hahiroth and walked through the <char style="add">Red</char> Sea into the Etham Desert, and set their/our tents at Marah.<verse eid="NUM 33:8"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 33:9"/>Then they/we left Marah and went to Elim. There were twelve springs and 70 palm trees there. They/We set up our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:9"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 33:10"/>Then they/we left Elim and went to the area near the Red Sea and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:10"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 33:11"/>Then they/we left the Red Sea area and went to the area near the Sin Desert and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:11"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 33:12"/>Then they/we left the Sin Desert and went to Dophkah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:12"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 33:13"/>Then they/we left Dophkah and went to Alush and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:13"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 33:14"/>Then they/we left Alush and went and set up their/our tents at Rephidim, where they/we had no water to drink.<verse eid="NUM 33:14"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 33:15"/>Then they/we left Rephidim and went to the Sinai Desert and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:15"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 33:16"/>Then they/we left the Sinai Desert and went to Kibroth-Hattaavah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:16"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 33:17"/>Then they/we left Kibroth-Hattaavah and went to Hazeroth and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:17"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 33:18"/>Then they/we left Hazeroth and went to Rithmah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:18"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 33:19"/>Then they/we left Rithmah and went to Rimmon-Perez and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:19"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 33:20"/>Then they/we left Rimmon-Perez and went to Libnah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:20"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 33:21"/>Then they/we left Libnah and went to Rissah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:21"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 33:22"/>Then they/we left Rissah and set up their/our tents at Kehelathah.<verse eid="NUM 33:22"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 33:23"/>Then they/we left Kehelathah and went to Shepher Mountain and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:23"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 33:24"/>Then they/we left Shepher and went to Haradah <char style="add">Mountain</char> and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:24"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 33:25"/>Then they/we left Haradah and went to Makheloth and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:25"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 33:26"/>Then they/we left Makheloth and went to Tahath and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:26"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 33:27"/>Then they/we left Tahath and went to Terah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:27"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 33:28"/>Then they/we left Terah and went to Mithcah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:28"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 33:29"/>Then they/we left Mithcah and went to Hashmonah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:29"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 33:30"/>Then they/we left Hashmonah and went to Moseroth and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:30"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 33:31"/>Then they/we left Moseroth and went to Bene-Jaakan and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:31"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 33:32"/>Then they/we left Bene-Jaakan and went to Hor-Haggidgad and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:32"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 33:33"/>Then they/we left Hor-Haggidgad and went to Jotbathah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:33"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 33:34"/>Then they/we left Jotbathah and went to Abronah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:34"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="NUM 33:35"/>Then they/we left Abronah and went to Ezion-Geber and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:35"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="NUM 33:36"/>Then they/we left Ezion-Geber and went to Zin Desert and set up their/our tents at Kadesh there.<verse eid="NUM 33:36"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="37" style="v" sid="NUM 33:37"/>Then they/we left Kadesh and went to Hor Mountain, at the border of Edom land and set up their/our tents there. <verse eid="NUM 33:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="NUM 33:38"/>Aaron, the priest, obeyed Yahweh and climbed up the mountain. There he died, on the first day of their/our fifth month, 40 years after the/we Israelis left Egypt. <verse eid="NUM 33:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="NUM 33:39"/>Aaron was 123 years old when he died.<verse eid="NUM 33:39"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="40" style="v" sid="NUM 33:40"/>(That was when the king of Arad <char style="add">city</char> heard that the/we Israelis were coming. Arad was in the southern part of Canaan, where the Canaan people-group lived.)<verse eid="NUM 33:40"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="41" style="v" sid="NUM 33:41"/>The Israelis left Hor Mountain and went to Zalmonah and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:41"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="42" style="v" sid="NUM 33:42"/>Then they/we left Zalmonah and went to Punon and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:42"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="43" style="v" sid="NUM 33:43"/>Then they/we left Punon and went to Oboth and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:43"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="44" style="v" sid="NUM 33:44"/>Then they/we left Oboth and went to Iye-Abarim, which was on the border of the Moab region, and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:44"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="45" style="v" sid="NUM 33:45"/>Then they/we left Iye-Abarim and went to Dibon-Gad and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:45"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="46" style="v" sid="NUM 33:46"/>Then they/we left Dibon-Gad and set up their/our tents at Almon-Diblathaim.<verse eid="NUM 33:46"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="47" style="v" sid="NUM 33:47"/>Then they/we left Almon-Diblathaim and went to the Abarim Mountains, near Nebo and set up their/our tents there.<verse eid="NUM 33:47"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="48" style="v" sid="NUM 33:48"/>Then they/we left the Abarim Mountains and went to the plains of the Moab region, near the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, across from Jericho. <verse eid="NUM 33:48"/><verse number="49" style="v" sid="NUM 33:49"/>They/We set up our tents there; their/our tents stretched <char style="add">for several miles/km.</char> from Beth-Jeshimoth to Acacia.<verse eid="NUM 33:49"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="50" style="v" sid="NUM 33:50"/>While we were there on the plains of the Moab <char style="add">region</char> near the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, across from Jericho, Yahweh spoke to Moses/me. He said, <verse eid="NUM 33:50"/><verse number="51" style="v" sid="NUM 33:51"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: When you cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and enter the Canaan <char style="add">region</char>, <verse eid="NUM 33:51"/><verse number="52" style="v" sid="NUM 33:52"/>you must force all the people who live there to leave. Destroy all their carved statues and all their idols made of metal. Wreck all the places where they worship <char style="add">their idols</char>. <verse eid="NUM 33:52"/><verse number="53" style="v" sid="NUM 33:53"/>Take their land from them and start to live there, because I have given their land to you for you to own.<verse eid="NUM 33:53"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="54" style="v" sid="NUM 33:54"/>“Divide up the land by throwing ◄lots/small stones which have been marked► <char style="add">to decide which group will get which area</char>. Give the larger areas to the groups that have more people, and give the smaller areas to the groups that have fewer people. Each tribe will receive its own land. <verse eid="NUM 33:54"/><verse number="55" style="v" sid="NUM 33:55"/>If you do not force the people who live there to leave, they will cause you to have much trouble. They will be like sharp hooks in your eyes, and like thorns in your sides. And they will bring trouble to you, in that land where you will be living. <verse eid="NUM 33:55"/><verse number="56" style="v" sid="NUM 33:56"/>And then I will punish you, as I had planned to punish them.”<verse eid="NUM 33:56"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 33"/>
  <chapter number="34" style="c" sid="NUM 34"/>
  <para style="s1">The boundaries of the land of Canaan</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 34:1"/>Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 34:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 34:2"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: You will soon enter Canaan land, and it will become yours. These will be the borders of the land: <verse eid="NUM 34:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 34:3"/>On the south you will receive part of the Zin Desert, near the border of the Edom <char style="add">region</char>. On the east side, the border will start at the south end of the Dead Sea.<verse eid="NUM 34:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 34:4"/>It will extend to a little south of the Scorpion Pass, and extend <char style="add">west</char> through <char style="add">the</char> Zin <char style="add">Desert</char> and south of Kadesh-Barnea. From there it will extend to Hazar Addar and from there to Azmon. <verse eid="NUM 34:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 34:5"/>From Azmon it will extend <char style="add">west</char> to the dry riverbed <char style="add">at the border</char> of Egypt and then to the <char style="add">Mediterranean</char> Sea.<verse eid="NUM 34:5"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 34:6"/>The border on the west will be the Mediterranean Sea.<verse eid="NUM 34:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 34:7"/>The border on the north will start from the Mediterranean Sea and extend <char style="add">east</char> to Hor Mountain. <verse eid="NUM 34:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 34:8"/>From there it will extend to Lebo-Hamath and then to Zedad. <verse eid="NUM 34:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 34:9"/>From there the border will extend to Ziphron, and it will end at Hazar-Enan.<verse eid="NUM 34:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 34:10"/>The border on the east will start at Hazar-Enan and extend <char style="add">south</char> to Shepham. <verse eid="NUM 34:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 34:11"/>From there it will extend east of Ain to Riblah and then along the hills that are east of Galilee Lake. <verse eid="NUM 34:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 34:12"/>Then the border will extend south along the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and end at the Dead Sea.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="NUM 34:12">Those will be the borders around your country.”<verse eid="NUM 34:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 34:13"/>So Moses/I <char style="add">told all that</char> to the Israeli people. Then he/I said to them, “That is the land that you will receive. You must throw ◄lots/stones that have been marked► to decide which area will go to each of the nine and a half tribes, because Yahweh has commanded that it should be divided among them. <verse eid="NUM 34:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 34:14"/>The tribes of Reuben, Gad, and half of the tribe of Manasseh have already received the land in which they will live. <verse eid="NUM 34:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 34:15"/>They have received land on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, across from Jericho.”<verse eid="NUM 34:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="NUM 34:16"/>Then Yahweh said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 34:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="NUM 34:17"/>“These are the men who will divide the land: First, Eleazar and Joshua. <verse eid="NUM 34:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="NUM 34:18"/>But one leader <char style="add">from each of the twelve tribes will help them divide the land</char>.<verse eid="NUM 34:18"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="19-28" style="v" sid="NUM 34:19-28"/>“From the tribe of Judah, appoint Jephunneh’s son Caleb.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Simeon appoint Ammihud’s son Shemuel.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Benjamin appoint Kislon’s son Elidad.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Dan appoint Jogli’s son Bukki.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Manasseh appoint Ephod’s son Hanniel.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Ephraim appoint Shiphtan’s son Kemuel.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Zebulun appoint Parnach’s son Elizaphan.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Issachar appoint Azzan’s son Paltiel.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Asher appoint Shelomi’s son Ahihud.</para>
  <para style="li1" vid="NUM 34:19-28">From the tribe of Naphtali appoint Ammihud’s son Pedahel.”<verse eid="NUM 34:19-28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 34:29"/>Yahweh commanded that all those were the men who should divide the Canaan region among the Israeli people.<verse eid="NUM 34:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 34"/>
  <chapter number="35" style="c" sid="NUM 35"/>
  <para style="s1">The towns given to the Levites</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 35:1"/>Yahweh told this to Moses/me <char style="add">while the Israeli people were</char> on the plain in the Moab region near the Jordan <char style="add">River</char>, across from Jericho: <verse eid="NUM 35:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 35:2"/>“Tell the Israeli people that from the land that they will receive, they must give to the descendants of Levi some cities in which they can live. They must also give them some land around these cities. <verse eid="NUM 35:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 35:3"/>Those will be for the descendants of Levi to live in, and around the cities will be land for their cattle and flocks of sheep and goats and other animals.<verse eid="NUM 35:3"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 35:4"/>“The land that you give them for their animals must extend out for ◄1,500 feet/450 meters► from the walls of the cities. <verse eid="NUM 35:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 35:5"/>Also measure ◄3,000 feet/900 meters► in each direction out from the walls of each city. That additional land will be land for their animals outside the walls of the cities.”<verse eid="NUM 35:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The cities of safety</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 35:6"/>“Six of the cities that you give to the descendants of Levi will be cities to which people <char style="add">can run</char> to be safe. If someone <char style="add">accidentally</char> kills someone else, the one who killed that person may run to one of those cities to be safe. <verse eid="NUM 35:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 35:7"/>You must also give to the descendants of Levi 42 other cities and the land around those cities, for their animals,. <verse eid="NUM 35:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 35:8"/>The Israeli tribes that have the most people must give them more cities than the tribes that have fewer people give. Each tribe must give some of its cities to the descendants of Levi, but the tribes that have more land must give more cities, and the tribes that have less land will give fewer cities.”<verse eid="NUM 35:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 35:9"/>Yahweh also said to Moses/me, <verse eid="NUM 35:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 35:10"/>“Tell this to the Israeli people: When you cross the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and enter the Canaan <char style="add">region</char>, <verse eid="NUM 35:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 35:11"/>you must choose some cities to which people can run to be safe/protected. If someone kills another person ◄accidentally/without planning to do that►, the one who killed that person may run to one of those cities and be safe. <verse eid="NUM 35:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 35:12"/>One of the relatives of the person who was killed may think he must avenge his relative’s death <char style="add">by killing the murderer</char>. But in that city, the killer will be safe <char style="add">because the people in that city would kill those relatives if they tried to get revenge there</char>. The man who killed someone accidentally <char style="add">must</char> be put on trial in a court. <verse eid="NUM 35:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 35:13"/>You must set apart six cities to be cities to which someone who killed another person accidentally may run and be safe. <verse eid="NUM 35:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="NUM 35:14"/>There must be three of those cities on the east side of the Jordan <char style="add">River</char> and three that will be <char style="add">on the west side</char>, in the Canaan region. <verse eid="NUM 35:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="NUM 35:15"/>Those six cities will be cities where Israeli people may run to and be safe, and where foreigners and other people who are living among you can also run to and be safe. Any of those people who accidentally kills someone may run to one of those cities <char style="add">and be safe/protected there</char>.<verse eid="NUM 35:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16-18" style="v" sid="NUM 35:16-18"/>“But <char style="add">you must consider that</char> anyone who kills another person with an iron weapon or with a big rock or with a piece of wood, is a murderer, and the one who killed the other person must be executed. <verse eid="NUM 35:16-18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="NUM 35:19"/>A relative of the person who was murdered must be the one who executes the murderer as soon as he finds him. <verse eid="NUM 35:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="NUM 35:20"/>If someone shoves another person <char style="add">over a cliff</char> or throws something at another person <verse eid="NUM 35:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="NUM 35:21"/>or hits that person with his hand/fist and causes that person to die, if he did it because he hated that person, then you must consider that he is a murderer, and must be executed. A relative of the person who was killed must be the one who executes the murderer as soon as he finds him.<verse eid="NUM 35:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="NUM 35:22"/>“But someone might accidentally shove someone else, or accidentally throw something at another person and hit him, not because he hates that person. <verse eid="NUM 35:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="NUM 35:23"/>Or he might drop a rock on someone that he did not see. If the one who does that does not plan to hurt anyone and does not hate the person that was killed, <verse eid="NUM 35:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="NUM 35:24"/>the people of that city must decide whether the relative of the dead person <char style="add">has the right to get revenge</char>, or whether the one who killed the other person <char style="add">truly did it ◄accidentally/without planning to do it►</char>. <verse eid="NUM 35:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="NUM 35:25"/><char style="add">If they decide that the killer planned to kill the other person, they must not allow him to stay in their city. But if they decide that it was done accidentally</char>, they must protect the killer from being killed by the dead person’s relative. They must send the killer to one of the cities where he will be safe/protected, and allow him to stay there until the Supreme Priest dies. <char style="add">After that, the killer may go back to his home, because the dead person’s relative no longer has the right to get revenge</char>.<verse eid="NUM 35:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="NUM 35:26"/>“But <char style="add">while the Supreme Priest is still living</char>, the person who is in that safe city must not leave that city. <verse eid="NUM 35:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="NUM 35:27"/>If he goes outside the city, and if a relative of the dead person finds him, that relative is permitted to kill that person, <char style="add">and people will not consider that the relative is guilty of murder.</char> <verse eid="NUM 35:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="NUM 35:28"/>The killer must stay in that city where he will be safe/protected until the Supreme Priest dies. <char style="add">He will be safe from revenge after that, because the death of the Supreme Priest will be considered to be a sacrifice to atone for that murder</char>. After that, the killer may return to his home.<verse eid="NUM 35:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="NUM 35:29"/>“You must always obey those regulations, wherever you live.<verse eid="NUM 35:29"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="NUM 35:30"/>“If someone <char style="add">is accused of</char> killing another person, the one who is accused may be executed only if there are people who saw him do it. There must be more than one witness; no one is permitted to be executed if there was only one ◄witness/person who saw him do it►.<verse eid="NUM 35:30"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="NUM 35:31"/>“If there is a murderer who truly should be executed, do not <char style="add">spare his life by</char> accepting ◄a ransom/money for him not to be killed►. He must be executed.<verse eid="NUM 35:31"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="32" style="v" sid="NUM 35:32"/>“If someone has run to a city where he will be safe/protected, do not allow him to give you money in order that you will permit him to return to his home before the Supreme Priest dies.<verse eid="NUM 35:32"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="NUM 35:33"/>“You must execute people who truly murder others. If you did not do that, you would be causing the people who live in the land to become unacceptable to me. Anyone who deliberately kills an innocent person must be executed. <verse eid="NUM 35:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="NUM 35:34"/>I am Yahweh, and I live among you Israelis, so do not spoil/pollute the land by allowing people to murder others without being punished.”<verse eid="NUM 35:34"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 35"/>
  <chapter number="36" style="c" sid="NUM 36"/>
  <para style="s1">Land for Zelophehad’s daughters</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="NUM 36:1"/>The family leaders of the clan of Gilead of the tribe of Manasseh went to Moses/me and the other family leaders of the Israeli people. <verse eid="NUM 36:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="NUM 36:2"/>They said to Moses/me, “Yahweh commanded you, our leader, to apportion the land to the Israeli tribes by throwing ◄lots/stones that have been marked► to decide <char style="add">which group would get which area</char>. Yahweh also commanded you to give the land that belonged to our fellow Israeli Zelophehad to his daughters. <verse eid="NUM 36:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="NUM 36:3"/>But if his daughters marry men from the other Israeli tribes, that land will no longer belong to our tribe. People of other tribes will get it. So some of our land will no longer belong to us. <verse eid="NUM 36:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="NUM 36:4"/>When the Year of Celebration comes, <char style="add">when all the land that has been bought by someone is returned to its original owners</char>, the land that belonged to Zelophehad will belong to the tribes of the men that his daughters marry. So some of our land, the land that we received from our fathers, will be taken from us, <char style="add">and we will never own it again</char>.”<verse eid="NUM 36:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="NUM 36:5"/>Yahweh told Moses/me what to reply to them, so Moses/I said this to them: “These men from the tribe of Manasseh are right. <verse eid="NUM 36:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="NUM 36:6"/>This is what Yahweh is saying to the daughters of Zelophehad: ‘Each of you may marry anyone you want to, but you must marry only someone from your own tribe.’ <verse eid="NUM 36:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="NUM 36:7"/>In that way, the land that belongs to Israelis will not be passed from one tribe to another tribe. Each Israeli will keep the land in the tribe that belonged to his ancestors. <verse eid="NUM 36:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="NUM 36:8"/>A woman who inherits her father’s land may get married, but she must marry someone from her own tribe. In that way, every Israeli will keep the land that belonged to his ancestors. <verse eid="NUM 36:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="NUM 36:9"/>The land must not be passed from one tribe to another tribe. Each Israeli tribe must keep the land that it received from its ancestors.”<verse eid="NUM 36:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="NUM 36:10"/>Zelophehad’s daughters obeyed what Yahweh told Moses/me. <verse eid="NUM 36:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="NUM 36:11"/>The five daughters—Mahlah, Tirzah, Hoglah, Milcah and Noah—married their cousins, their father’s relatives. <verse eid="NUM 36:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="NUM 36:12"/>The men whom they married were from the tribe of Manasseh, so their land continued to belong to their father’s family and tribe.<verse eid="NUM 36:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="NUM 36:13"/>Those were the commands [DOU] that Yahweh gave to Moses/me to tell to the Israelis, while they/we were on the plains of the Moab region, close to the Jordan River, across from Jericho.<verse eid="NUM 36:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="NUM 36"/>
</usx>
