<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="REV" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">REVELATION</para>
  <para style="toc1">Revelation</para>
  <para style="toc2">Revelation</para>
  <para style="toc3">Rev</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book contains the account of Jesus giving the Apostle John some visions. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Revelation</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="REV 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Revelation 1:1-3</para>
  <para style="s1">John urged people to read this book, listen carefully to it, and obey it.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 1:1"/>
    <char style="add">This book tells the message</char> that God revealed to Jesus Christ. God revealed it to him in order that he might reveal to his servants the <char style="add">things/events</char> that must happen soon. Jesus communicated <char style="add">this message</char> to <char style="add">me</char>, his servant John, by sending his angel to me. <verse eid="REV 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 1:2"/><char style="add">As I write it, I</char>, John, am truthfully reporting everything that I saw <char style="add">and heard</char>, the message from God that Jesus Christ <char style="add">truthfully reported to me</char>. <verse eid="REV 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 1:3"/><char style="add">God is</char> pleased with those who read <char style="add">this book to the congregations</char>, and he will be pleased with those who listen carefully to it and obey what <char style="add">he has commanded in this prophetic message that I</char> am writing. <char style="add">So read this message to the congregations, listen carefully to it, and obey it</char>, because <char style="add">these things that Jesus has revealed</char> will happen soon.<verse eid="REV 1:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John said that he was writing to believers in the seven congregations in Asia. He prayed that God would bless them. He said that Christ is coming to judge rebellious people and to start to rule as king.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 1:4-8">Revelation 1:4-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 1:4"/>
    <char style="add">I</char>, John, am <char style="add">writing this</char> to <char style="add">you believers in</char> the seven congregations <char style="add">that are located</char> in Asia <char style="add">province</char>. <char style="add">I pray that God the Father, God’s Spirit, and Jesus Christ</char> be kind to (OR, bless) you and cause you to have <char style="add">inner</char> peace. <char style="add">God the Father is</char> the one who exists, who has always existed, and who will always exist. The Spirit <char style="add">of God, who</char> is in front of God’s throne, has <char style="add">all kinds of power</char> (OR, The Spirit of God <char style="add">is symbolized</char> by seven spirits who are in front of God’s throne). <verse eid="REV 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 1:5"/>Jesus Christ is the one who has faithfully told <char style="add">people about God</char>. He is the first one ◄whom God has raised from the dead/who became alive again after being dead►, in order <char style="add">to show that God will raise us who trust in Jesus</char>. Jesus is the one who rules the kings of the earth. He is the one who loves us. He is the one who has erased the record our sins. He did that by shedding his blood <char style="add">when he died on the cross</char>. <verse eid="REV 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 1:6"/>He is <char style="add">the one who</char> has caused us to become people whose lives God rules, and he has made us to be priests <char style="add">who serve </char> God his Father. <char style="add">As a result of this, we acknowledge that</char> Jesus Christ is eternally divine and eternally powerful. ◄Amen!/That is true!►<verse eid="REV 1:6"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 1:7"/>Listen carefully! Christ will surely come in the midst of the clouds <char style="add">in order that he may judge the rebellious people of earth</char>, and everyone [SYN] will see him <char style="add">come</char>. Even those who <char style="add">are responsible for</char> piercing <char style="add">and killing</char> him [MTY] <char style="add">will see him come. People from</char> all people-groups on earth will mourn because he <char style="add">will punish them</char>. ◄Amen!/May it be so.► <verse eid="REV 1:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 1:8"/>The Lord God declares, “I am the one who created <char style="add">everything</char>, and I am the <char style="add">one who will cause everything to</char> end [MET].” He is the one who exists, who has always existed, and who will always exist. He is the Almighty One.<verse eid="REV 1:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ appeared to John and commissioned him to write down the vision that he was about to give him and to send it to the seven congregations in Asia.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 1:9-20">Revelation 1:9-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 1:9"/>I, John, your fellow believer, am suffering as you <char style="add">are</char> because of our letting Jesus rule <char style="add">our lives</char>. We are steadfastly enduring <char style="add">trials</char> because of our relationship with him. I was punished by being sent/exiled to Patmos island because <char style="add">of my proclaiming</char> God’s message and telling <char style="add">people about</char> Jesus. <verse eid="REV 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 1:10"/><char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit took control of me on one of the days <char style="add">that we believers met to worship</char> the Lord. <verse eid="REV 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 1:11"/><char style="add">At that time</char>, I heard behind me someone <char style="add">speaking to me as loudly and as clearly</char> [SIM] as a trumpet. He was saying <char style="add">to me</char>, “Write on a scroll what you see, and send it to seven congregations. Send it to <char style="add">the congregations</char> in Ephesus <char style="add">city</char>, in Smyrna <char style="add">city</char>, in Pergamum <char style="add">city</char>, in Thyatira <char style="add">city</char>, in Sardis <char style="add">city</char>, in Philadelphia <char style="add">city</char>, and in Laodicea <char style="add">city</char>.” <verse eid="REV 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 1:12"/><char style="add">In this vision</char> I turned in order that I might see who had spoken to me [SYN]. When I turned, <verse eid="REV 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 1:13"/>I saw seven golden lampstands. In the midst of the lampstands there was <char style="add">someone</char> who looked like he came from heaven. He wore a robe that reached to his feet, and he wore a gold band around his chest. <verse eid="REV 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 1:14"/>The hair on his head was white like white wool <char style="add">or</char> like snow. His eyes were <char style="add">shining brightly</char> [SIM], like a flame of fire. <verse eid="REV 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 1:15"/>His feet <char style="add">looked</char> like brass that glows <char style="add">as it is being</char> purified {as <char style="add">people</char> purify it} in a furnace. <char style="add">When he spoke</char>, his voice <char style="add">sounded</char> like the sound <char style="add">made by</char> a huge waterfall (OR, a great/wide river of rushing water). <verse eid="REV 1:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 1:16"/>In his right hand he held seven stars. A sword that had two sharp edges extended from his mouth. His face <char style="add">shone as bright</char> as the sun shines <char style="add">at midday</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="REV 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 1:17"/>When I saw him, I fell down at his feet <char style="add">and was unable to move or speak</char> [SIM], as though <char style="add">I were</char> dead. But he put his right hand on me and said to me, “Don’t be afraid! I am the one who created <char style="add">all things</char> and the <char style="add">one who will cause all things to</char> end. <verse eid="REV 1:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 1:18"/>I am the living one. Although I died, I am alive again and will live forever! I have <char style="add">the power to cause people</char> to die, and I have authority over the place where all the dead people <char style="add">are</char>. <verse eid="REV 1:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 1:19"/>So write the <char style="add">vision</char> that you are seeing. Write about the <char style="add">conditions</char> that exist now, and the <char style="add">events</char> that are about to happen next. <verse eid="REV 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 1:20"/>The meaning of the seven stars that you saw in my right hand and the seven golden lampstands <char style="add">that you saw is this</char>: The seven stars <char style="add">in my hand represent the leaders, who are like</char> angels, <char style="add">who watch over</char> the seven congregations, and the <char style="add">seven</char> lampstands <char style="add">represent</char> the seven congregations.”<verse eid="REV 1:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="REV 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Christ exhorts the congregation at Ephesus to repent and to begin again to love him and each other.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 2:1-7">Revelation 2:1-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 2:1"/>
    <char style="add">He also said to me</char>, “Write <char style="add">this message</char> to the leader [MET] of the congregation in Ephesus <char style="add">city: ‘I</char> am saying these things <char style="add">to you: I am</char> the one who firmly holds the seven stars in my right hand. <char style="add">I am</char> the one who walks among the seven golden lampstands. <verse eid="REV 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 2:2"/>I know what you do: You labor <char style="add">for me</char> intensely, and you continue <char style="add">to serve me</char> steadfastly. <char style="add">I know</char> that you cannot tolerate people <char style="add">who teach what is</char> evil [MTY], and that you investigated people who falsely claimed that they are apostles, and you found that they were lying. <verse eid="REV 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 2:3"/><char style="add">I know</char> also that you continue <char style="add">to serve me</char> steadfastly. <char style="add">Even when people</char> ◄<char style="add">caused you to suffer/persecuted you</char>►, you continued to serve <char style="add">me</char> because <char style="add">you believe</char> in me, and you have not become too tired <char style="add">to keep on serving me</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 2:4"/>Nevertheless, I have <char style="add">this complaint</char> against you: You no longer love <char style="add">each other and me</char> as you did when you first [MTY] <char style="add">trusted in me</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 2:5"/><char style="add">So, I tell you to</char> remember how you used to love <char style="add">me and each other, and</char> to <char style="add">realize</char> that you no longer love as you did. <char style="add">I tell</char> you to turn away from your sin <char style="add">of not loving me and each other</char>, and start loving <char style="add">each other and me again</char> as you did at first. If you do not turn away from your sinful behavior, I will come <char style="add">to judge</char> you and cause your group to cease to be a Christian congregation [MET]. <verse eid="REV 2:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 2:6"/>But you have the following good quality: Those Nicolaitans <char style="add">teach you believers that you can worship idols and that you may act immorally</char>. However, you hate such teaching, just like I also hate it. <verse eid="REV 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 2:7"/>Everyone who wants to understand my message [MTY] must listen carefully to the message that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit speaks to the congregations. To everyone who overcomes <char style="add">Satan</char>, I will give the right to eat <char style="add">fruit</char> [MTY] from the tree <char style="add">that gives</char> eternal life, the tree that is in God’s garden.’”<verse eid="REV 2:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ exhorts the congregation at Smyrna not to fear what they will suffer, but to trust in him, even if they must die because they trust in him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 2:8-11">Revelation 2:8-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 2:8"/>“Write <char style="add">this message</char> to the leader [MET] of the congregation in Smyrna <char style="add">city: ‘I am</char> saying these things <char style="add">to you. I am</char> the one who caused <char style="add">everything to have a beginning</char> and <char style="add">who will cause all things to</char> end. I am the one who died and became alive <char style="add">again</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 2:9"/>I know that you suffer <char style="add">because of what unbelievers do to you</char>, and that you lack <char style="add">material possessions</char>. But <char style="add">I also know that</char> you are <char style="add">spiritually</char> [MET] rich. <char style="add">I know</char> that people ◄slander/say evil things about► you. They say that they are Jews, but I do not <char style="add">consider that they are Jews. I consider that</char> they <char style="add">belong to</char> the group that Satan <char style="add">controls</char>! <verse eid="REV 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 2:10"/>Do not be afraid of any of the things that you are about to suffer. The truth is that the devil is about to <char style="add">put</char> some of you in prison, to tempt you <char style="add">to deny that you believe in me</char>. For a short period of time you will suffer <char style="add">because of what people will do to you</char> [MTY]. Continue to trust in me, <char style="add">even if</char> they kill you <char style="add">because you trust in me</char>. As a result, I will <char style="add">reward you with</char> eternal life, <char style="add">just like</char> [MET] <char style="add">people reward a victorious athlete by putting</char> a wreath <char style="add">on his head</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 2:11"/>Everyone who wants to understand [MTY] must listen carefully to the message that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit speaks to the congregations. <char style="add">After</char> those who conquer <char style="add">Satan die</char>, they will live with God. They will never suffer again, even though many others will suffer as though they died a second time.’ ”<verse eid="REV 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ exhorts the congregation at Pergamum to stop listening to what the Nicolaitans teach.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 2:12-17">Revelation 2:12-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 2:12"/>“Write <char style="add">this message</char> to the leader [MET] of the congregation in Pergamum <char style="add">city: ‘I am</char> saying these things <char style="add">to you. I am</char> the one who has the sharp two-edged sword. <verse eid="REV 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 2:13"/>I know where you live: It is where Satan controls [MTY] <char style="add">people</char>. <char style="add">I know</char> that you firmly believe in me [MTY]. You did not deny that you believe/trust in me, not even in the time when Antipas, ◄my faithful witness/who faithfully told people about me►, <char style="add">was alive</char>. He was killed {People killed him} in your city, a city where <char style="add">people</char> habitually obey Satan. <verse eid="REV 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 2:14"/>Nevertheless, I have this <char style="add">complaint</char> against you: You permit some of your <char style="add">members</char> to teach things like Balaam <char style="add">taught long ago. He</char> taught Balak to persuade the Israeli people to sin. <char style="add">Specifically</char>, he taught them to eat food that had been offered to idols, and to practice sexual immorality. <verse eid="REV 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 2:15"/>In that way, you are also permitting some of <char style="add">your members</char> to practice what the Nicolaitans teach, <char style="add">which is like what Balaam taught</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 2:16"/>So you must stop doing <char style="add">this</char>. If <char style="add">you do</char> not stop doing <char style="add">it</char>, I will come to you suddenly. Using the words that I will say I will fight against those <char style="add">who believe this false teaching</char> [MTY], and I will ◄<char style="add">condemn them/say that they must be punished</char>►. <verse eid="REV 2:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 2:17"/>Everyone who wants to understand [MTY] must listen carefully to the message that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit speaks to the congregations. To everyone who conquers <char style="add">Satan</char>, I will give <char style="add">blessings that will be like</char> the <char style="add">food called</char> manna <char style="add">that is in a jar</char> that is {that someone has} hidden. I will also give them a white stone on which <char style="add">I will</char> engrave a new name, a name that no one but the ones who receive it will know.’”<verse eid="REV 2:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ rebukes the congregation at Thyatira for tolerating a teacher who encourages sexual immorality and eating food offered to idols. He warns those who participate in these things that he will punish them unless they repent, and he exhorts the rest of the members to remain loyal to him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 2:18-29">Revelation 2:18-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 2:18"/>“Write <char style="add">this message</char> to the leader [MET] of the congregation in Thyatira <char style="add">city: ‘I</char>, ◄the Son of God/the one who is also God►, am saying these things <char style="add">to you: I am</char> the one whose eyes <char style="add">shine</char> [SIM] like a flame of fire, and whose feet <char style="add">shine</char> [MET] like fine brass. <verse eid="REV 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 2:19"/>I know that you love <char style="add">me and each other</char>, and that you trust <char style="add">in me</char>. I know that you serve <char style="add">others</char> and that you steadfastly endure <char style="add">a lot of difficulties/trials. I know</char> that you are doing these things more now than <char style="add">you have done them</char> in the past. <verse eid="REV 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 2:20"/>Nevertheless, I have this <char style="add">complaint</char> about you: You tolerate that woman <char style="add">among your members who is like</char> [MET] <char style="add">that wicked queen</char> Jezebel <char style="add">who lived long ago</char>. She says that she ◄is a prophetess/proclaims messages that come directly from God►, but through what she teaches she is deceiving my servants. She is urging them to commit sexual immorality and to eat food that they have offered to idols. <verse eid="REV 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 2:21"/>Although I gave her time to stop <char style="add">her sexual immorality and pagan practices</char>, she did not want to stop <char style="add">doing them</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 2:22"/><char style="add">As a result</char>, I will cause her to become very ill [MTY]. I will also cause those <char style="add">who act immorally as she does</char> [MET] to suffer greatly, if they do not stop <char style="add">doing</char> what she does. <verse eid="REV 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="REV 2:23"/>Some <char style="add">have become like</char> her children by doing <char style="add">what she teaches</char> [MET]; I will certainly get rid of them. As a result, all the congregations will recognize that I am the one who finds out what everyone thinks and desires [MTY]. I will reward each of you according to what you have done. <verse eid="REV 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="REV 2:24"/>But I have something good to say about the rest <char style="add">of you believers</char> in Thyatira. <char style="add">It is good</char> that you do not accept that <char style="add">false</char> teaching. <char style="add">It is good that you reject</char> what those <char style="add">teachers</char> call their ‘secret <char style="add">practices’, practices that</char> Satan <char style="add">inspired</char> (OR, what those teachers <char style="add">facetiously</char> call the secret, profound <char style="add">practices that</char> Satan <char style="add">inspires</char>). I will not burden you with any commands <char style="add">other than that which you already have been told</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="REV 2:25"/>Just keep <char style="add">believing firmly in me, and obey me</char> until I return. <verse eid="REV 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="REV 2:26"/>As for those who conquer <char style="add">Satan</char> and who (OR, <char style="add">because</char> they) keep on doing what I command until they die, I will give them authority, just like I myself received it from my Father. <char style="add">They will exercise that authority</char> over the nations <char style="add">that rebel against God</char>. <verse eid="REV 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="REV 2:27"/>They will rule them <char style="add">severely as if they were striking them</char> [HYP] with an iron rod. They <char style="add">will destroy those who do evil things</char> just like <char style="add">people</char> shatter clay pots [MET]. <verse eid="REV 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="REV 2:28"/>I will also enable <char style="add">everyone who conquers Satan to shine gloriously like</char> the morning star <char style="add">does</char> [MTY, MET]. <verse eid="REV 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="REV 2:29"/>Everyone who wants to understand [MTY] must listen carefully to the message that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit speaks to the congregations.’ ”<verse eid="REV 2:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="REV 3"/>
  <para style="s1">Christ exhorts the congregation at Sardis to wake up and repent. But the members who are worthy will live with him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 3:1-6">Revelation 3:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 3:1"/>“Write <char style="add">this message</char> to the leader [MET] of the congregation in Sardis <char style="add">city</char>: ‘I am saying these things <char style="add">to you. I am</char> the one who can give <char style="add">to people</char> all the power of God’s Spirit (OR, in whom is the Spirit of God who has all kinds of power; OR, <char style="add">who has God’s Spirit, who is symbolized as</char> seven spirits), and <char style="add">I am the one</char> who has the seven stars. I know everything that you have done. You <char style="add">(pl)</char> appear to be alive <char style="add">spiritually</char>, but <char style="add">you are so weak spiritually it is as though</char> you are dead [MET]. <verse eid="REV 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 3:2"/><char style="add">Become aware of your spiritual need as though you were</char> awaking <char style="add">from sleep</char> [MET], and strengthen <char style="add">yourself spiritually, because you are so useless that you are like someone who is</char> about to die [MET]. <char style="add">You must do this</char> because I know that my God considers that nothing that you do is satisfactory. <verse eid="REV 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 3:3"/>So then, keep remembering <char style="add">God’s message, what</char> you accepted when you heard it. Obey it continually, and turn away from your sinful behavior. If <char style="add">you do not become aware of your spiritual need and turn away from your</char> [MET] <char style="add">sinful behavior</char>, I will come to you <char style="add">when you are not expecting me</char>, as a thief <char style="add">comes</char> [SIM]. You will never know at what time I will come to <char style="add">judge</char> you. <verse eid="REV 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 3:4"/>Nevertheless, <char style="add">there</char> in Sardis you have a few members who <char style="add">have not been doing what is wrong. It is as though they</char> have not soiled their garments [MET]. As a result, because they are worthy <char style="add">to live with me</char>, they will live with me <char style="add">and will be pure in every way</char> [MET], <char style="add">like people who are dressed</char> in <char style="add">pure</char> white <char style="add">clothing</char>. <verse eid="REV 3:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 3:5"/>Everyone who conquers <char style="add">Satan</char> I will dress in these same white garments [MET] (OR, will be <char style="add">pure in every way as though they are</char> dressed in these white garments), and I will never erase their names from the book <char style="add">that contains the names of the people who have eternal</char> life. Instead, as my Father and his angels are listening, I will acknowledge that they [MTY] <char style="add">belong to me</char>. <verse eid="REV 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 3:6"/>Everyone who wants to understand [MTY] must listen carefully to the message that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit speaks to the congregations.’”<verse eid="REV 3:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ exhorts the congregation at Philadelphia to continue to obey his word and to be faithful; he promises that some Jews will acknowledge that he loves the congregation, and he also promises that he will keep the congregation from spiritual harm during the period of testing.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 3:7-13">Revelation 3:7-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 3:7"/>“Write <char style="add">this message</char> to the leader [MET] of the congregation in Philadelphia <char style="add">city</char>: ‘I am saying these things <char style="add">to you. I am</char> God’s Holy One, the True One. <char style="add">Just like King</char> David had authority [MTY] <char style="add">to allow people to enter the ancient city of Jerusalem, so I have the authority to allow people to enter</char> my kingdom. <char style="add">I am</char> the one who opens <char style="add">doors</char> so that no one can close them, and who closes doors so that no one can open them. <verse eid="REV 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 3:8"/>I know everything you have done. Be aware that I have opened a door before you, a door that no one can close. <char style="add">I know that although</char> there are not <char style="add">many believers</char> (OR, much <char style="add">spiritual</char> strength) [MTY] <char style="add">in your congregation</char>, you have obeyed what I say, and you have not denied <char style="add">that you believe in</char> me [MTY]. <verse eid="REV 3:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 3:9"/><char style="add">I am aware that</char> some of your people meet together with those who <char style="add">follow/worship</char> Satan. They claim to be Jews, but I know that they are not true Jews. They are lying. I will cause them to come to you and to bow down <char style="add">humbly</char> at your feet and to acknowledge that I love you.<verse eid="REV 3:9"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 3:10"/>Because you have paid attention to the message to endure patiently <char style="add">when you suffered</char>, I will keep you <char style="add">safe from those who will try to harm you spiritually</char> during the period/time that is about to come. At that time <char style="add">God will cause rebellious people</char> on the earth to suffer, in order that I can determine <char style="add">whether they will turn away from their sins or not</char>. <verse eid="REV 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 3:11"/>I am coming soon. <char style="add">So</char> continue believe firmly the <char style="add">message</char> that you have received, in order that no one may cause you to lose the reward <char style="add">that God has reserved for</char> you. <verse eid="REV 3:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 3:12"/>I will make everyone who conquers <char style="add">Satan secure</char>. They will stand in the temple of my God, <char style="add">they will stand firm like</char> [MET] pillars, and they will remain there forever. I will mark them with the name of my God, <char style="add">showing that they belong to him. I will also mark them</char> with the name of the city of my God, <char style="add">showing that they will live there. That city is</char> the New Jerusalem, the city that my God will cause to descend down from heaven. <char style="add">I will also mark them</char> with my new name, <char style="add">showing that they belong to me</char>. <verse eid="REV 3:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 3:13"/>Everyone who wants to understand [MTY] must listen carefully to the message that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit speaks to the congregations.’”<verse eid="REV 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Christ exhorts the congregation at Laodicea to repent of their neglect of fellowship with him and of their failure to accept his provision for their spiritual needs. He waits to restore fellowship with any member of the congregation who will respond to his call.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 3:14-22">Revelation 3:14-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 3:14"/>“Write <char style="add">this message</char> to the leader [MET] of the congregation in Laodicea <char style="add">city: ‘I</char> am saying these things <char style="add">to you. I am</char> the one who ◄guarantees <char style="add">everything that God’s promises/</char>confirms that <char style="add">he</char> will do <char style="add">all that he has promised</char>► [MET]. I am the one who testifies <char style="add">about God</char> reliably and accurately. I am the one who God used to create <char style="add">everything</char>. <verse eid="REV 3:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 3:15"/>I know everything that you have done: You <char style="add">neither deny that you trust in me nor love/obey me zealously/wholeheartedly. You are like water that is</char> neither cold nor hot. I wish that you were either cold or hot! <verse eid="REV 3:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 3:16"/>Because you are neither enthusiastic about me nor concerned about your lack of spiritual growth [MET], I am about to <char style="add">reject</char> you [MET], <char style="add">as if</char> I were spitting <char style="add">lukewarm water</char> out of my mouth. <verse eid="REV 3:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 3:17"/>You are saying, “<char style="add">Because we have all that we need spiritually</char>, we are <char style="add">like</char> rich <char style="add">people who</char> have acquired a lot of wealth. We lack nothing!” But you do not realize that you are <char style="add">lacking in so many ways spiritually that you are like</char> [MET] people who are very wretched and pitiful, poor, blind, and naked. <verse eid="REV 3:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 3:18"/>I advise you <char style="add">to obtain from me all that you need spiritually, as though you were</char> buying from me gold that has been refined by fire {that fire has refined}, in order that you may be <char style="add">truly</char> rich [MET] <char style="add">spiritually. Let me make you righteous, as though you were</char> [MET] buying from me white garments in order that you might wear clothes instead of being naked and ashamed. <char style="add">Let me help you to perceive spiritual things, as though</char> [MET] you were buying from me eye salve to put in your eyes in order that you might see. <verse eid="REV 3:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 3:19"/><char style="add">Since</char> I rebuke and correct all those whom I affectionately love, earnestly stop your sinful behavior. <verse eid="REV 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 3:20"/>Be aware that <char style="add">I invite each one of you to respond to me</char> as though [MET] I <char style="add">was</char> standing <char style="add">waiting</char> at <char style="add">your</char> door and knocking. I will come to all those who hear my voice and respond to me, and I <char style="add">will fellowship</char> with them <char style="add">as friends do when they</char> eat together [MET]. <verse eid="REV 3:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 3:21"/>I will permit everyone who conquers <char style="add">Satan</char> to sit <char style="add">and rule</char> with me on my throne, just like I conquered <char style="add">Satan</char> and now sit <char style="add">and rule</char> beside my Father on his throne. <verse eid="REV 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 3:22"/>Everyone who wants to understand [MTY] must listen carefully to the message that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit speaks to the congregations.’ ”<verse eid="REV 3:22"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="REV 4"/>
  <para style="s1">A throne was in heaven with someone sitting on it. He was in the midst of every creature and object in heaven. The elders and the living creatures worshipped him as God, the mighty Creator.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 4:1-11">Revelation 4:1-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 4:1"/>After these things I, <char style="add">John</char>, saw <char style="add">in the vision that</char> there was a door open in heaven. The one whose voice was like [SIM] a <char style="add">loud</char> trumpet, the one <char style="add">who had spoken to me</char> previously, said <char style="add">to me</char>, “Come up here! I will show you events that must happen later.” <verse eid="REV 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 4:2"/>Immediately I experienced that <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">was specially controlling me</char>. There was a throne there in heaven, and on the throne someone was sitting <char style="add">and ruling</char>. <verse eid="REV 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 4:3"/>He <char style="add">shone</char> like [SIM] a <char style="add">brilliant crystalline</char> jasper <char style="add">jewel</char> and like a <char style="add">brilliant red</char> carnelian <char style="add">jewel</char>. Around the throne was a rainbow that <char style="add">shone like a brilliant green</char> emerald <char style="add">jewel</char>. <verse eid="REV 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 4:4"/>Around the throne there were 24 other thrones. On these thrones 24 elders were <char style="add">sitting</char>. They were wearing <char style="add">pure</char> white garments and had golden crowns on their heads. <verse eid="REV 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 4:5"/>From the throne there came lightning and rumblings and thundering. Seven torches of fire were burning in front of the throne. Those <char style="add">represent</char> the Spirit of God, who has all kinds of <char style="add">power</char> (OR, who is <char style="add">also</char> symbolized as seven spirits). <verse eid="REV 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 4:6"/>In front of the throne <char style="add">there was what looked</char> like an ocean <char style="add">made of</char> glass. It was <char style="add">clear</char>, like crystal. On each of the four sides of the throne there was a living <char style="add">creature</char>. Each one was covered with eyes in front and behind. <verse eid="REV 4:6"/><verse number="7-8" style="v" sid="REV 4:7-8"/>The first living <char style="add">creature</char> was like a lion. The second living <char style="add">creature</char> was like an ox. The third living <char style="add">creature</char> had a face like a man’s face. The fourth living creature was like an eagle that was flying. Each of the four living <char style="add">creatures</char> had six wings. They were covered with eyes, all around <char style="add">their bodies</char> and under <char style="add">their wings</char>. Day and night they continually [LIT] sing:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:7-8">Holy, holy, holy is the Lord God, the Almighty One.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:7-8">He is the one who has always existed,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:7-8">who exists now, and who will always exist.<verse eid="REV 4:7-8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9-10" style="v" sid="REV 4:9-10"/>The living <char style="add">creatures praise</char>, honor [DOU], and thank the one who sits on the throne, the one who lives forever. Whenever they do that, the 24 elders ◄prostrate themselves/kneel down► before the one who sits on the throne, and they worship him, the one who lives forever. They lay their crowns in front of the throne and sing:<verse eid="REV 4:9-10"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 4:11"/>Our(exc) Lord and God,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:11">you are worthy that all beings praise you,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:11">you are worthy that all beings honor you, and</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:11">you are worthy that all beings acknowledge</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:11">that you are the powerful one,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:11">because you alone created all things.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:11">Moreover, because you planned that they should exist,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 4:11">you created them, and so they exist.<verse eid="REV 4:11"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="REV 5"/>
  <para style="s1">When the Lamb took the scroll from the one on the throne, the whole created universe worshipped him who is the worthy Redeemer. The 24 elders and the four living creatures acknowledged that he alone was worthy to open the seals on the scroll.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 5:1-14">Revelation 5:1-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 5:1"/>I saw that there was a scroll in the right hand of the one who was sitting on the throne. The scroll was written on its outside as well as on its inside, and it was sealed {Someone had written on the outside as well as on the inside of the scroll and sealed it} with seven seals. <verse eid="REV 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 5:2"/>I saw a strong angel who was announcing in a loud voice, “◄The person who is worthy to break the seals of the scroll and then to open it should come to do it!/Who is worthy to break the seals of the scroll and then to open it?►” [RHQ] <verse eid="REV 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 5:3"/>But no created being in heaven nor any created being on the earth nor any created being under the earth was able to open the scroll and see what was written on it. <verse eid="REV 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 5:4"/>I cried loudly because there was no one worthy to do that. <verse eid="REV 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 5:5"/>But one of the elders said to me, “Do not cry any longer! Look, the one who is called the Lion from the tribe of Judah, the Messiah who is the descendant of King David, has overcome Satan! As a result, he is worthy to break the seven seals on the scroll and open it!” <verse eid="REV 5:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 5:6"/>Then I saw Jesus, the one who is like a [MET] sacrificial lamb, standing there. He stood near the throne, in the midst of the four living creatures and the elders. It appeared that he had been killed {that people had killed him}, but he was alive again. He had seven horns <char style="add">on his head</char>, and he had seven eyes that symbolize the Spirit of God who has all kinds of power (OR, who is also symbolized as seven spirits). <char style="add">He</char> sends <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit out into all the earth. <verse eid="REV 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 5:7"/>He came and took the scroll from the right hand of the one who sits on the throne. <verse eid="REV 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 5:8"/>When he took the scroll, the four living <char style="add">creatures</char> and the 24 elders ◄prostrated themselves/knelt down► before <char style="add">Jesus</char>, the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb, <char style="add">to worship him</char>. They each had a harp, and they had golden bowls full of incense that <char style="add">represents</char> the prayers of God’s people. <verse eid="REV 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 5:9"/>The living <char style="add">creatures</char> and the elders sang a new song. They sang:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:9">You are worthy to receive the scroll and to open its seals,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:9">because you were killed, and because you redeemed/bought people for God from every tribe, language [MTY], people-group, and nation with the blood that flowed from your body when you died.<verse eid="REV 5:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 5:10"/>You have caused them to become a people over whom our God rules,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:10">and to become priests who serve him, and they will rule on [MTY] the earth.<verse eid="REV 5:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 5:11"/>As I <char style="add">continued to</char> look, I heard the voices of many angels around the throne and around the living <char style="add">creatures</char> and the elders. There were millions of them, a <char style="add">crowd so large that no one could count them</char>. <verse eid="REV 5:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 5:12"/>They were singing in a loud voice:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:12">“The one who is like a lamb was killed {whom his enemies killed}</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:12">but he became alive again.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:12">He is worthy that all created beings acknowledge that he is infinitely powerful, infinitely rich, infinitely wise, and infinitely strong!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:12">He is worthy of being honored and praised by all created beings!”<verse eid="REV 5:12"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 5:13"/>I also heard every creature that is in heaven and on the earth and under the earth and on the ocean, every creature in all those places, saying (OR, singing):</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:13">“We must forever praise and honor the one who sits on the throne</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:13">and the one who is like a lamb,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 5:13">May they reign with complete power forever!”<verse eid="REV 5:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 5:14"/>The four living <char style="add">creatures</char> said, “◄Amen!/May it be so!►” Then the elders prostrated themselves and worshipped <char style="add">God and Jesus</char>.<verse eid="REV 5:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="REV 6"/>
  <para style="s1">When the Lamb opened each of the first four seals of the scroll, each of the four living creatures called forth a mounted horseman who brought judgment to people on the earth.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 6:1-8">Revelation 6:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 6:1"/>I saw that <char style="add">Jesus, the one who is like a</char> lamb, opened the first of the seven seals <char style="add">of the scroll</char>. Then I heard one of the four living <char style="add">creatures</char> say in a voice <char style="add">as loud</char> as [SIM] thunder, “Come!” <verse eid="REV 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 6:2"/>Then I saw a white horse <char style="add">come out</char>. The one who sat on it had a bow <char style="add">and arrows</char>. <char style="add">God</char> gave him a crown <char style="add">to show that he was the king</char>. Then the one who conquers <char style="add">people</char> went out to continue to conquer <char style="add">people</char>. <verse eid="REV 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 6:3"/>When the <char style="add">one who was like a</char> lamb opened the second seal, I heard the second living <char style="add">creature</char> say, “Come!” <verse eid="REV 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 6:4"/>Then a red horse came out. The one sitting on it was allowed {<char style="add">God</char> allowed the one sitting on it} to cause <char style="add">people</char> to no longer <char style="add">live</char> peacefully, but instead to be killing each other. <char style="add">For this purpose</char> he was given {<char style="add">God’s agent</char> gave to him} a large sword. <verse eid="REV 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 6:5"/>When <char style="add">the one who is like a</char> lamb opened the third seal, I heard the third living <char style="add">creature</char> say, “Come!” This time, I saw a black horse <char style="add">come out</char>. The one who sat on it had a pair of scales in his hand. <verse eid="REV 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 6:6"/>I heard a voice <char style="add">that sounded</char> like <char style="add">it was coming from</char> among the four living <char style="add">creatures</char>. It was saying ◄<char style="add">to the horseman/to the man who was sitting on the black horse</char>►, “A quart of wheat <char style="add">will cost so much that</char> a man must work a whole day to earn enough money to buy it, and three quarts of barley will sell for the same price. But do not cut off <char style="add">the supply of</char> olive oil or the wine [MTY]!” <verse eid="REV 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 6:7"/>When the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb opened the fourth seal, I heard the fourth living <char style="add">creature</char> say, “Come!” <verse eid="REV 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 6:8"/>This time I saw a pale horse <char style="add">come out</char>. The one who sat on it is named ‘<char style="add">The one who causes</char> death [PRS]’, and <char style="add">the one that is named ‘The place where dead people go’</char> accompanied him. <char style="add">God</char> gave them authority over one quarter of the people on earth to incite them to kill each other with weapons [SYN], and also authority to kill them ◄by <char style="add">causing them to</char> starve, by <char style="add">their causing them to become</char> sick from epidemics, and by <char style="add">their causing them to be attacked by</char> wild animals.<verse eid="REV 6:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When the Lamb opened the fifth seal, the souls of dead believers appealed to God to judge those who killed them, but God told them to rest a bit longer.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 6:9-11">Revelation 6:9-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 6:9"/>When the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb opened the fifth seal, I saw under (OR, at the base of) the altar <char style="add">in heaven</char> the souls of <char style="add">God’s servants</char> who had been killed {whom <char style="add">people had</char> killed} because of <char style="add">their believing</char> God’s message, and because they told others <char style="add">the message about Jesus</char>. <verse eid="REV 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 6:10"/>They spoke loudly <char style="add">to God</char> saying, “Sovereign/Almighty Lord, you are holy and faithful. How long <char style="add">will it be</char> before you judge <char style="add">and punish</char> the people on earth who murdered <char style="add">us(exc)</char>?” <verse eid="REV 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 6:11"/><char style="add">God</char> gave to each of them a long white robe, and <char style="add">he</char> told them to rest a little longer until <char style="add">people</char> killed all the believers who served <char style="add">the Lord</char> with them. They were believers whom <char style="add">God wanted to die in just the same way</char> that these others had been killed.<verse eid="REV 6:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When the Lamb opened the sixth seal of the scroll, the upheaval in the sky and on the earth caused all the rebellious people on earth to hide because they knew God’s time to judge people had come.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 6:12-17">Revelation 6:12-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 6:12"/>I saw that when <char style="add">the one who is like a</char> lamb opened the sixth seal, the earth shook violently. The sun became as black as cloth made ◄of <char style="add">black</char> wool/of pitch►. The whole moon became <char style="add">red</char> [SIM] like blood. <verse eid="REV 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 6:13"/>The stars fell to the earth <char style="add">in great numbers</char>, just [SIM] like immature figs fall when a fig tree is shaken by a strong wind {when a strong wind shakes a fig tree}. <verse eid="REV 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 6:14"/>The sky split open and <char style="add">rolled up on either side</char> just [SIM] like an <char style="add">old</char> scroll rolls up <char style="add">when it is split in two</char>. Every mountain and island moved out of its place. <verse eid="REV 6:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 6:15"/><char style="add">As a result, all the rebellious people</char> of the earth, <char style="add">including</char> kings, high-ranking people, generals, the rich people, the powerful people, along with everyone <char style="add">else</char>, both slave and free, hid themselves in caves and between the mountain rocks. <verse eid="REV 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 6:16"/>They shouted to the mountains and to the rocks, “Fall on us <char style="add">(exc)</char> and hide us <char style="add">(exc)</char> in order that the one who sits upon the throne will not be able to see us <char style="add">(exc)</char> [MTY], and <char style="add">in order that</char> the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb will not be able to punish [MTY] us <char style="add">(exc)</char>. <verse eid="REV 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 6:17"/>This is the terrible day on which they will punish [MTY] us <char style="add">(exc)</char>, and <char style="add">when that happens</char>, no one will be able to survive! [RHQ]”<verse eid="REV 6:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="REV 7"/>
  <para style="s1">An angel came up from the east and commanded the four angels stationed in four directions to continue restraining the destructive winds until angels had sealed God’s servants.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 7:1-8">Revelation 7:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 7:1"/>After this I saw four angels. One was standing at the north, one at the east, one at the south, and one at the west. They were restraining the winds that blew from all directions [MTY] to keep them from blowing <char style="add">destructively</char> on the earth or on the ocean or even on any tree. <verse eid="REV 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 7:2"/>I saw another angel come up from the east. He was carrying God’s seal. <char style="add">With this</char> seal God, who is all-powerful, marks <char style="add">his own people to protect them</char>. The angel called out with a loud voice to the four angels to whom <char style="add">he</char> had given <char style="add">power</char> to harm the earth and the ocean. He said <verse eid="REV 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 7:3"/><char style="add">to them</char>, “Do not harm the earth or the ocean or the trees until we <char style="add">(exc)</char> have marked the servants of our <char style="add">(inc)</char> God on their foreheads.” <verse eid="REV 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 7:4"/><char style="add">Then the angel and his fellow angels marked all God’s servants</char>. I heard the number of people who were marked {whom <char style="add">the angels</char> marked} <char style="add">because of their being God’s servants. The number was</char> 144,000. They were from all the tribes of Israel. <char style="add">They symbolized the complete number of people whom God would protect</char>. <verse eid="REV 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 7:5"/><char style="add">The angels</char> marked 12,000 people from the tribe of Judah, 12,000 from the tribe of Reuben, 12,000 from the tribe of Gad, <verse eid="REV 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 7:6"/>12,000 from the tribe of Asher, 12,000 from the tribe of Naphtali, 12,000 from the tribe of Manasseh, <verse eid="REV 7:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 7:7"/>12,000 from the tribe of Simeon, 12,000 from the tribe of Levi, 12.000 from the tribe of Issachar, <verse eid="REV 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 7:8"/>12,000 from the tribe of Zebulun, 12,000 from the tribe of Joseph, and 12,000 from the tribe of Benjamin.<verse eid="REV 7:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The triumphant crowd stood before the throne in heaven and acknowledged that God and the Lamb had rescued them. Then the angels, the elders, the living creatures, and a huge crowd of people worshipped God and praised him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 7:9-12">Revelation 7:9-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 7:9"/>After these things I saw a huge crowd. There were so <char style="add">many people</char> that no one would be able to count them. <char style="add">They were</char> from every nation, every tribe, every people-group, and every language [MTY]. They were standing before the throne and before <char style="add">Jesus, the one who is like a</char> lamb. They were wearing white robes and held palm branches <char style="add">to wave them in order to celebrate</char>. <verse eid="REV 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 7:10"/>They shouted loudly, “<char style="add">O</char> our <char style="add">(exc)</char> God, you who sit on the throne, and <char style="add">Jesus, you who are like a</char> lamb, <char style="add">you two</char> have delivered <char style="add">us(exc) from Satan’s power</char>!” <verse eid="REV 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 7:11"/>All the angels were standing around the throne and around the elders and the four living <char style="add">creatures</char>. They all bowed down before the throne with their faces <char style="add">to the ground</char> and worshipped God. <verse eid="REV 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 7:12"/>They said, “May it be so! <char style="add">We(exc)</char> praise, thank, and honor <char style="add">you</char>, our <char style="add">(exc)</char> God, forever! <char style="add">We(exc) acknowledge</char> that you are completely wise, the powerful one, who is forever able to accomplish everything he wants to. ◄May everyone acknowlege that it is so!/Amen!►”<verse eid="REV 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">One of the elders explained to John about the saints who are dressed in white robes.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 7:13-17">Revelation 7:13-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 7:13"/>Then one of the elders asked me, “These <char style="add">people</char> who are wearing white robes, <char style="add">do you know</char> who they are, and where they come from?” <verse eid="REV 7:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 7:14"/>I answered him, “Sir, <char style="add">I do not know. Surely</char> <char style="bd">you</char> know <char style="add">who they are</char>!” He said to me, “These are the people ◄whom <char style="add">others</char> have caused to suffer greatly/who <char style="add">have been persecuted</char>►. <char style="add">Because they believed that Jesus, the one who is like a sacrificial</char> lamb, <char style="add">atoned for our sin when</char> his blood <char style="add">flowed from his body when he died, it is as though</char> [MET] they have washed their robes and have made them <char style="add">clean and</char> white. <verse eid="REV 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 7:15"/>Because of this, they are in front of God’s throne, and they serve him day and night in his <char style="add">heavenly temple. God</char>, the one who sits on the throne, will shelter/protect them [MTY]. <verse eid="REV 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 7:16"/><char style="add">As a result</char>, they will never again be hungry. They will never again be thirsty. The sun will never again ◄beat on/burn► them, nor will any heat <char style="add">scorch them</char>. <verse eid="REV 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 7:17"/>This is because the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb who is at the throne will <char style="add">take care of them, just like</char> a shepherd <char style="add">takes care of his sheep</char> [MET]. He will guide them <char style="add">to the source of eternal life, just like a shepherd leads his sheep</char> to springs of water, <char style="add">which enable the sheep</char> to live [MET]. God will <char style="add">cause them to no longer be sad. It will be as if he were</char> wiping away all tears from their eyes [MTY].”<verse eid="REV 7:17"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="REV 8"/>
  <para style="s1">When the Lamb opened the seventh seal, it thundered, lightning flashed, and the earth shook.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 8:1-5">Revelation 8:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 8:1"/>When <char style="add">Jesus</char>, the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb, opened the seventh seal, there was no sound at all in heaven for ◄a very short time/about half an hour►. <verse eid="REV 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 8:2"/>I saw the seven angels who stand in front of God. A trumpet was given {◄<char style="add">God/An angel</char>► gave a trumpet} to each one of them. <verse eid="REV 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 8:3"/>Another angel, who had a golden container for burning incense, came and stood at the altar. <char style="add">He was given</char> {<char style="add">An angel</char> gave to him} a large quantity of incense, in order that he might offer it, with the prayers of all God’s people, upon the golden altar that is in front of <char style="add">God’s</char> throne. <char style="add">Then he burned this incense on the altar</char>. <verse eid="REV 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 8:4"/>From the <char style="add">pot in</char> the angel’s hand, the smoke of the incense, along with the prayers of God’s people, went up to God. <verse eid="REV 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 8:5"/><char style="add">In response</char>, the angel took the golden incense burner and filled it with <char style="add">coals of</char> fire from the altar. He threw <char style="add">the contents of</char> the [MTY] incense burner onto the earth. Thunder sounded and rumbled, lightning was flashing, and the earth shook.<verse eid="REV 8:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The successive trumpet blasts by each of the first four angels resulted in great catastrophes on the earth and in the sky.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 8:6-12">Revelation 8:6-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 8:6"/>The seven angels, <char style="add">each</char> of which had <char style="add">one of</char> the seven trumpets, prepared to blow them. <verse eid="REV 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 8:7"/>When the first angel blew his trumpet, hail and fire mixed with blood poured down onto the earth. <char style="add">As a result</char>, a third of <char style="add">everything on the surface of</char> the land was burned up {<char style="add">the fire</char> burned up a third of <char style="add">everything on the surface of</char> the land}. A third of the trees were also burned up {It also burned up a third of the trees}, and <char style="add">a third of</char> all the green grass was burned up. <verse eid="REV 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 8:8"/>When the second angel blew his trumpet, something that was like a huge burning mountain fell into the ocean. <char style="add">As a result</char>, a third of the ocean became <char style="add">red like</char> [MTY] blood, <verse eid="REV 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 8:9"/>a third of the living creatures in the ocean died, and a third of the ships <char style="add">in the ocean</char> were destroyed. <verse eid="REV 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 8:10"/>When the third angel blew his trumpet, a huge star, which was burning like a torch, fell from the sky into a third of the rivers and into <char style="add">a third of</char> the springs. <verse eid="REV 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 8:11"/>The name of the star is Bitterness. <char style="add">As a result</char>, the water in a third <char style="add">of the rivers and springs</char> became bitter, and many people died from <char style="add">drinking</char> the water because it had become bitter. <verse eid="REV 8:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 8:12"/>When the fourth angel blew his trumpet, <char style="add">God</char> struck the sun, the moon, and the stars, so that they lost a third of their light. The <char style="add">sun</char> also did not shine during a third of the day, and <char style="add">the moon and stars did not shine during a third</char> of the night.<verse eid="REV 8:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">An eagle announced that rebellious people on earth would suffer greatly.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 8:13">Revelation 8:13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 8:13"/>As I watched, I heard an eagle that was flying high in the sky, shouting in a loud voice, “Terrible things will happen to <char style="add">rebellious</char> people who live on the earth! Terrible things will happen when the three remaining angels blow their trumpets! And they are about to blow them!”<verse eid="REV 8:13"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="REV 9"/>
  <para style="s1">When the fifth angel blew his trumpet, locusts with stings like scorpions appeared on the earth and attacked rebellious people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 9:1-12">Revelation 9:1-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 9:1"/>The fifth angel blew his trumpet. Then I saw <char style="add">an evil angel. He was like</char> a star that had fallen from the sky to the earth. He was given {<char style="add">Someone</char> gave him} the key to the shaft <char style="add">that descended</char> ◄<char style="add">to</char> the underworld/<char style="add">to</char> the deep dark pit►. <verse eid="REV 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 9:2"/>When he opened that shaft, smoke arose from it like smoke from a huge burning furnace. The smoke prevented <char style="add">anyone from seeing</char> the sky and the light of the sun. <verse eid="REV 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 9:3"/>Locusts came out of the smoke onto the earth. <char style="add">They were given</char> {<char style="add">God</char> gave them} power <char style="add">to sting people</char>, like scorpions <char style="add">sting people</char>. <verse eid="REV 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 9:4"/><char style="add">God</char> told the locusts that they should not harm grass, nor any plants, nor any tree. <char style="add">God said that they should harm only</char> those people who did not have a mark on the forehead <char style="add">to show that they belonged to God</char>. <verse eid="REV 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 9:5"/><char style="add">God</char> did not allow the locusts to kill those people. Instead, <char style="add">he</char> allowed them to continue torturing people for five months. When they tortured people, the pain those people felt was like the pain a scorpion causes when it stings someone. <verse eid="REV 9:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 9:6"/>During the time <char style="add">when the locusts torture rebellious people, the pain will be so bad that</char> people will want to find a way to die, but they will not be able to [PRS]. <verse eid="REV 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 9:7"/>The locusts looked like horses that are ready for battle. They had on their heads what looked like golden crowns. Their faces were like the faces of people. <verse eid="REV 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 9:8"/>They had <char style="add">long</char> hair like the <char style="add">long</char> hair of women. Their teeth were <char style="add">strong</char>, like lions’ teeth. <verse eid="REV 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 9:9"/>They wore metal breastplates. <char style="add">When they were flying</char>, their wings made a noise like the roar when many horses <char style="add">pull chariots as they are</char> rushing into battle. <verse eid="REV 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 9:10"/>They had tails like scorpions have. With their tails they stung <char style="add">people</char> for five months. <verse eid="REV 9:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 9:11"/>The king who ruled over them was the angel of the underworld. His name in the Hebrew language is Abaddon. In the Greek language it is Apollyon. <char style="add">Both of</char> those names <char style="add">mean ‘Destroyer’</char>.<verse eid="REV 9:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 9:12"/>That was the end of the first terrible event. <char style="add">Be aware that</char> two tragic events are still to come.<verse eid="REV 9:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When the sixth angel blew his trumpet, a third of the rebellious people on earth died. But the rest of the rebellious people did not repent of their false worship or of their evil practices.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 9:13-21">Revelation 9:13-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 9:13"/>The sixth angel blew his trumpet. Then I heard a voice from the four corners of the golden altar that is in God’s presence. <verse eid="REV 9:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 9:14"/>It was saying to the sixth angel, the one who had the trumpet, “Release the four angels whom <char style="add">I</char> have bound at the great river Euphrates!” <verse eid="REV 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 9:15"/>The four angels were released, those who had been {<char style="add">He</char> released the four angels, whom <char style="add">God</char> had} kept ready for that <char style="add">exact</char> hour of that day, of that month, of that year. They were released {<char style="add">He</char> released them} in order that they might enable <char style="add">their soldiers to</char> kill a third of the <char style="add">rebellious</char> people. <verse eid="REV 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 9:16"/>The number of the soldiers riding on horses who did that was 200 million. I heard <char style="add">someone say</char> how many there were. <verse eid="REV 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 9:17"/>In the vision I saw what the horses and the <char style="add">beings</char> that rode them looked like. They <char style="add">wore</char> breastplates that were <char style="add">red</char> like fire, <char style="add">dusky blue</char> like smoke, and <char style="add">yellow</char> like sulfur. The heads of the horses were like the heads of lions. From their mouths came fire, smoke, and <char style="add">fumes of burning</char> sulfur. <verse eid="REV 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 9:18"/>Those three things—the fire, the smoke, and the <char style="add">burning</char> sulfur from <char style="add">the horses’</char> mouths—killed a third of the <char style="add">rebellious</char> people. <verse eid="REV 9:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 9:19"/>The horses had power with their mouths and with their tails. Their tails have heads like snakes by which they harm people. <verse eid="REV 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 9:20"/>The rest of the <char style="add">rebellious</char> people, those who were not killed by these plagues of <char style="add">fire and smoke and burning sulfur</char>, did not turn from their sinful behavior. <char style="add">They did not stop worshipping</char> the idols that they had made with their own hands. They did not stop worshipping demons and idols <char style="add">that were made</char> of gold, of silver, of bronze, of stone, and of wood, <char style="add">even though they are idols</char> that can neither see nor hear nor walk. <verse eid="REV 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 9:21"/>They did not stop murdering people, or practicing sorcery, or acting in sexually immoral ways, or stealing <char style="add">things</char>.<verse eid="REV 9:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="REV 10"/>
  <para style="s1">John saw a mighty angel coming down out of heaven and holding a small open scroll. When the angel shouted, it thundered several times, but a voice from heaven prohibited John from recording what the thunder said. The angel affirmed that the living Creator of the universe would no longer delay in completing what he planned for his creation.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 10:1-7">Revelation 10:1-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 10:1"/>
    <char style="add">In the vision</char> I saw another mighty angel that was coming down out of heaven. A cloud <char style="add">surrounded him</char>. There was a rainbow over his head. His face <char style="add">shone</char> [SIM] like the sun. His legs looked like pillars of fire. <verse eid="REV 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 10:2"/>He had in his hand a small scroll that was open. He set his right foot on the ocean and his left foot on the land. <verse eid="REV 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 10:3"/>He shouted something with a loud voice, a voice like the roar of a lion. When he shouted this, it thundered seven <char style="add">times</char>, speaking <char style="add">words that I could understand</char>. <verse eid="REV 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 10:4"/>When it thundered <char style="add">like that</char>, I was about to write <char style="add">the words that I</char> heard, but a voice from heaven said to me, “Keep secret what the thunder said! Do not write it down!” <verse eid="REV 10:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 10:5"/>Then the angel whom I had seen standing on the ocean and the land raised his right hand toward heaven, <verse eid="REV 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 10:6"/>and he asked the one who lives forever, the one who created heaven and everything that is in it, <char style="add">who created</char> the earth and everything that is in it, and <char style="add">who created</char> the ocean and everything that is in it, to affirm that what he said was true. <char style="add">He said that he</char> would surely no longer delay <char style="add">what he had planned to do</char>. <verse eid="REV 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 10:7"/>He said that when the time <char style="add">came</char> for the seventh angel to blow his trumpet, <char style="add">he</char> would complete what God had secretly planned, just like he announced <char style="add">long ago</char> to his servants, the prophets.<verse eid="REV 10:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The heavenly voice told John to take the open scroll from the angel and eat it. When he had eaten it, he was commanded by God to prophesy again about all people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 10:8-11">Revelation 10:8-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 10:8"/>The one whose voice I had heard from heaven spoke to me again. He said, “Go and take the open scroll from the hand of the angel who is standing on the ocean and on the land.” <verse eid="REV 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 10:9"/>So I went to the angel and asked him to give me the little scroll. He said to me, “Take it and eat it. In your mouth it will <char style="add">taste</char> sweet like honey, but it will make your stomach bitter.” <verse eid="REV 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 10:10"/>I took the little scroll from the angel’s hand and ate it. In my mouth it <char style="add">tasted</char> sweet like honey, but when I had eaten it, <char style="add">it</char> made my stomach turn sour. <verse eid="REV 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 10:11"/>The one whose <char style="add">voice spoke from heaven said to me</char>, “You must ◄prophesy again/proclaim again what I will reveal to you► about many people-<char style="add">groups</char>, many nations, <char style="add">speakers of</char> many languages [MTY], and many kings.”<verse eid="REV 10:11"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="REV 11"/>
  <para style="s1">Christ told John to count his worshipers from the nations, and he appointed two witnesses to prophesy to the nations for a limited time. When they finished witnessing, the beast from the underworld killed them, causing the nations to enjoy temporary victory. God resurrected his witnesses, took them to heaven, and punished the nations. Survivors feared and acknowledged God as awesome.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 11:1-14">Revelation 11:1-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 11:1"/>
    <char style="add">An angel gave</char> to me a reed similar to a measuring stick. He said <char style="add">to me</char>, “<char style="add">Christ says this: ‘Go</char> to the temple <char style="add">where people worship</char> God, measure it and the altar <char style="add">in it</char>, and count the people who worship there. <verse eid="REV 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 11:2"/>But do not measure the courtyard outside <char style="add">of the temple</char> [DOU], because <char style="add">it</char> has been given {<char style="add">God</char> has given it} to <char style="add">the</char> non-Jewish <char style="add">people. As a result</char>, they will trample <char style="add">Jerusalem city</char> for 42 months. <verse eid="REV 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 11:3"/>I will appoint my two ◄witnesses/men who will tell others about me►. They will proclaim what I reveal to them for 1,260 days. They will wear <char style="add">rough</char> clothes made from goat’s hair <char style="add">to show that they are sad about people’s sin</char>.’ ” <verse eid="REV 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 11:4"/>Those <char style="add">witnesses are the ones</char> that are represented by the two olive trees and the two lampstands that are in the presence of the Lord <char style="add">who rules</char> the earth [SYM]. <verse eid="REV 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 11:5"/>If enemies try to harm those <char style="add">witnesses</char>, fire will come from the mouths of the witnesses and destroy them. If people want to harm them, <char style="add">the two witnesses</char> will certainly kill them similarly. <verse eid="REV 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 11:6"/>Those <char style="add">witnesses</char> will have authority to keep rain from falling during the time that they are proclaiming what God reveals to them. They also will have authority to cause water <char style="add">everywhere</char> to become <char style="add">red like</char> [MET] blood, and <char style="add">authority</char> to cause all kinds of plagues to occur. They will do this as often as they want to. <verse eid="REV 11:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 11:7"/>When they have finished proclaiming <char style="add">to people the message from God</char>, the beast that comes up ◄from the underworld/from the deep dark pit► will attack them, overcome them, and kill them. <verse eid="REV 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 11:8"/>The dead bodies of the <char style="add">two</char> witnesses will lie in the street of the great city where their Lord was crucified, the city that is symbolically named Sodom or Egypt <char style="add">because its people are very evil, like the people who lived in Sodom and Egypt</char>. <verse eid="REV 11:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 11:9"/>Individuals of many people-<char style="add">groups</char>, tribes, language <char style="add">groups</char> [MTY], and nations will look at their dead bodies for three and a half days. But these individuals will not allow <char style="add">anyone</char> to bury their bodies. <verse eid="REV 11:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 11:10"/>When the <char style="add">rebellious</char> people who live on the earth <char style="add">see that the witnesses are dead</char>, they will rejoice and celebrate. They will send gifts to each other, because these two prophets had <char style="add">caused plagues to occur which</char> tormented the <char style="add">rebellious</char> people on the earth. <verse eid="REV 11:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 11:11"/>But after three and a half days, God will cause those two witnesses to breathe again and live. They will stand up, and those who see them will be terrified. <verse eid="REV 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 11:12"/>The <char style="add">two witnesses</char> will hear a loud voice which came from heaven saying to them: “Come up here!” Then they will go up to heaven in a cloud. Their enemies will see them <char style="add">as they ascend</char>. <verse eid="REV 11:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 11:13"/>At that same time there will be a terrible earthquake, which will cause a tenth of <char style="add">the buildings in</char> [MTY] the city will collapse, and 7,000 people will die. The rest of the people will be afraid and <char style="add">acknowledge</char> that the God <char style="add">who rules in</char> heaven is awesome.<verse eid="REV 11:13"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 11:14"/>That will be the second terrible event. <char style="add">Be aware that</char> the third tragic event will happen soon.<verse eid="REV 11:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When the seventh angel sounded his trumpet, voices from heaven declared that the Lord God and his Messiah now govern everyone, and the elders declared that the time had come for God’s final judgment. With the heavenly sanctuary open, lightning flashed, thunder reverberated, the earth shook, and large hail fell.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 11:15-19">Revelation 11:15-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 11:15"/>Then the seventh angel blew <char style="add">his trumpet</char>. Angels in heaven shouted loudly, “Our Lord <char style="add">God</char> and the Messiah <char style="add">whom he has appointed</char> can now govern <char style="add">everyone in</char> [MTY] the world, and they will continue to rule people forever!” <verse eid="REV 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 11:16"/>The 24 elders who sit on their thrones in God’s presence ◄prostrated themselves/bowed down low► and worshipped him. <verse eid="REV 11:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 11:17"/>They said:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:17">Lord God, you are the Almighty One!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:17">You are the one who exists now!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:17">You are the one who has always existed!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:17">We thank you that you have defeated by your power everyone who has rebelled against you,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:17">and you now rule over everyone in the world.<verse eid="REV 11:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 11:18"/>The unbelieving people of [MTY] the nations were raging at you.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:18">As a result you have become very angry with them.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:18">You have decided that this is the appropriate time for you to judge all the dead people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:18">You have also decided that it is the time for you to reward all your servants,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:18">both the prophets and the rest of your people who reverence you [MTY],</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:18">whether they were considered socially significant/important or socially insignificant/unimportant.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:18">It is time for you to reward all of them!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 11:18">You have also decided it is the time for you to destroy the people who are destroying others on the earth.<verse eid="REV 11:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 11:19"/>Then God’s temple in heaven was opened {was open} and <char style="add">I</char> saw in the temple the sacred box/chest that contains God’s commandments. Lightning was flashing, it was thundering and rumbling, the earth shook, and large hailstones <char style="add">fell from the sky</char>.<verse eid="REV 11:19"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="REV 12"/>
  <para style="s1">When a royal woman gave birth to a royal son, she fled to safety and care in a place in the wilderness that was prepared by God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 12:1-6">Revelation 12:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 12:1"/>Then something very unusual appeared in the sky. It was a woman, whose <char style="add">appearance and</char> clothing were [MET] as bright as the sun. The moon was under her feet. On her head was a crown <char style="add">that was made</char> of twelve stars. <verse eid="REV 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 12:2"/>She was pregnant. Then, as she was about to give birth, she cried out because she was suffering pain. <verse eid="REV 12:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 12:3"/>Something else very unusual appeared in the sky. It was a huge red dragon. It had seven heads and ten horns. On each of its heads was a royal crown. <verse eid="REV 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 12:4"/>The dragon’s tail dragged a third of the stars from the sky and threw them to the earth. The dragon set himself in front of the woman who was about to give birth, in order that he might eat her child as soon as it was born. <verse eid="REV 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 12:5"/>The woman gave birth to a son, who <char style="add">is destined</char> to rule all the nations with <char style="add">complete authority as if he was using</char> [MET] an iron rod [MET]. <char style="add">God</char> snatched away her child and took him to <char style="add">rule from</char> his throne. <verse eid="REV 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 12:6"/>The woman fled to a desert. She has a place there that God has prepared for her, in order that <char style="add">the angels</char> may take care of her for 1,260 days.<verse eid="REV 12:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">There was a battle in heaven in which Michael and his angels fought the dragon. The dragon and his angels were thrown out of heaven to earth. A loud voice from heaven declared the victory and the sovereignty of God, and lamented the tragic struggle coming to people on earth.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 12:7-12">Revelation 12:7-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 12:7"/>
    <char style="add">In the vision I saw that</char> there was a battle in heaven. Michael and the angels that he <char style="add">commanded</char> fought against the dragon. The dragon and his angels fought back <char style="add">against Michael and his angels</char>. <verse eid="REV 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 12:8"/>But the dragon did not win the battle, so <char style="add">God</char> did not allow the dragon and his angels to stay in heaven any longer. <verse eid="REV 12:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 12:9"/>The huge dragon was thrown {<char style="add">Michael and his angels</char> threw the huge dragon} out <char style="add">of heaven</char>. The dragon is the ancient serpent, <char style="add">the one</char> who is called the Devil and Satan. He is the one who deceives <char style="add">people all over</char> the earth. He was thrown down to the earth, along with all his angels. <verse eid="REV 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 12:10"/>Then I heard <char style="add">someone</char> in heaven shout loudly, saying,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:10">Now our God has saved his people by his power, and he rules everyone!</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:10">Now the Messiah, the one who is the supreme ruler whom God appointed,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:10">has authority to rule all people, because our God has thrown out of heaven the one who accuses our fellow believers!</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:10">The dragon is the one who accuses them day and night before our God,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:10">saying that they have sinned and that God ought to punish them.<verse eid="REV 12:10"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 12:11"/>Our fellow believers overcame the dragon because they never stopped trusting</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:11">(OR, never stopped telling people about) Jesus,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:11">and because they trusted in what Jesus, the one who is like a lamb, accomplished when his blood flowed when he died.</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:11">Even though those believers wanted to live,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:11">they were willing to let people kill them for speaking the truth about him.<verse eid="REV 12:11"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 12:12"/>So, all you angels living [MTY] in heaven, rejoice!</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 12:12">But terrible things will happen to you ungodly people who [MTY] live on the earth and on the ocean, because the devil has come down to you!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 12:12">He is very angry because he knows that he has only a short time during which he can harm people.<verse eid="REV 12:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When the dragon pursued the woman who had given birth to a son, he was thwarted, so he prepared to fight against her other offspring.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 12:13-18">Revelation 12:13-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 12:13"/>When the dragon realized that he had been thrown {that <char style="add">the angels</char> had thrown him} down to the earth, he pursued the woman who had given birth to a son. <verse eid="REV 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 12:14"/>But the woman was given two wings like the wings of a very large eagle, in order that she might fly to a desolate place. That is a place <char style="add">that God</char> has prepared for her. There she was taken care of {<char style="add">God’s angels</char> took care of her} for three and a half years. The serpent, <char style="add">that is, the dragon</char>, was not able to reach her there. <verse eid="REV 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 12:15"/>The serpent spewed water like a river from his mouth in the direction of the woman, in order that the water might sweep her away. <verse eid="REV 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 12:16"/>But the ground helped the woman <char style="add">by</char> opening up and swallowing the river that the dragon spewed out from his mouth! <verse eid="REV 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 12:17"/>Then the dragon was very angry with the woman, so he went away to fight against <char style="add">the people who are like</char> the rest of her descendants. They are the people who obey God’s commandments and who tell other people about Jesus (OR, hold fast to what Jesus taught them). <verse eid="REV 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 12:18"/>The dragon stood on the ocean shore.<verse eid="REV 12:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="REV 13"/>
  <para style="s1">A beast rose from the ocean. It received power and authority from the dragon. Everyone worshipped it; that is, all people whose names were not recorded in the book of life worshipped the beast for 42 months.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 13:1-10">Revelation 13:1-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 13:1"/>I saw a beast that was coming up out of the ocean. It had ten horns and seven heads. On each <char style="add">of</char> its horns there was a royal crown. On <char style="add">each</char> of its heads there was a name that insulted <char style="add">God</char>. <verse eid="REV 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 13:2"/>The beast that I saw was like a leopard. But its feet were like the feet of a bear, and its mouth was like the mouth of a lion. The dragon gave the beast <char style="add">power</char>. From his own throne he also gave it authority <char style="add">to rule people</char> [DOU]. <verse eid="REV 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 13:3"/>One of the heads of the beast had been wounded {<char style="add">The Lord</char> had wounded one of the heads of the beast}, causing the beast to almost die. But its wound was healed. <char style="add">As a result, nearly</char> all <char style="add">the people of</char> the earth [HYP, MTY] marveled at the beast and became his disciples. <verse eid="REV 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 13:4"/>They worshipped the dragon, because he had given to the beast authority <char style="add">to rule people</char>. They also worshipped the beast, saying, “No one is <char style="add">as powerful</char> as the beast!/ [RHQ] ◄No one would dare to fight against it!/Who would dare to fight against it?►” [RHQ] <verse eid="REV 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 13:5"/>The beast was allowed {<char style="add">God</char> allowed the beast} to speak [MTY] in a boastful way and to insult <char style="add">God</char>. <char style="add">It was also</char> allowed {<char style="add">God</char> also allowed it} to rule <char style="add">over people</char> for 42 months. <verse eid="REV 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 13:6"/>It [MTY] insulted God, insulted the place where he lives, and insulted everyone who lives with him in heaven. <verse eid="REV 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 13:7"/><char style="add">It was</char> allowed {<char style="add">God</char> allowed it} to fight against God’s people and to conquer them. <char style="add">It was</char> allowed {<char style="add">God</char> allowed it} to have authority <char style="add">to rule</char> over every tribe, over every people-<char style="add">group</char>, over <char style="add">speakers of</char> every language [MTY], and over every nation. <verse eid="REV 13:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 13:8"/>Most of [HYP] the <char style="add">people</char> living on earth worshipped it. They were people whose names were not written in a book by the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb, the one who had been killed. Since the beginning of the world <char style="add">he wrote in it the names of the people who</char> will have <char style="add">eternal</char> life. <verse eid="REV 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 13:9"/>Everyone who wants to understand [MTY] must listen carefully to <char style="add">this message from God</char>: <verse eid="REV 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 13:10"/>If <char style="add">God has determined</char> that some people will be captured by their <char style="add">enemies</char>, they will be captured. If <char style="add">God has determined that</char> some people will be killed with a sword, they will be killed with a sword. So God’s people <char style="add">must be</char> steadfast, and remain faithful <char style="add">to him</char>.<verse eid="REV 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Another beast appeared, having the same authority to rule people that the first beast had, and it caused people on earth to worship the first beast. People made an image of the first beast, and the beast had everyone killed who refused to worship the image. It caused all people to be marked with the name of the first beast. The number of the beast’s name is 666.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 13:11-18">Revelation 13:11-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 13:11"/>I saw another beast, which was coming up from the earth. It had two small horns <char style="add">on its head</char> like a sheep has. But it spoke <char style="add">things to deceive people</char>, like the dragon does. <verse eid="REV 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 13:12"/>While the first beast watched, it used all the <char style="add">same</char> authority <char style="add">to rule people that the first beast had</char>. It forced the people who live on the earth [MTY, DOU] to worship the first beast, that is, the one who was healed of the wound that had caused it to almost die. <verse eid="REV 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 13:13"/>The second beast performed awesome miracles, even causing fire from the sky to fall to earth while people watched. <verse eid="REV 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 13:14"/>He performed miracles ◄on behalf of/with the authority of► the <char style="add">first</char> beast. By doing that he deceived the <char style="add">unbelieving</char> people on the earth so that they <char style="add">believed that they should worship the first beast. But this happened only because God</char> allowed <char style="add">it to happen</char>. The second beast told the people living on earth to make an image of the <char style="add">first</char> beast, the one that <char style="add">people</char> had almost killed with a sword and that then came back to life again. <verse eid="REV 13:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 13:15"/>The image of the <char style="add">first</char> beast was allowed to breathe, in order that it might speak and in order that <char style="add">it might command that</char> whoever refused to worship its image should be killed {that <char style="add">people</char> should kill whoever refused to worship its image}. <verse eid="REV 13:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 13:16"/><char style="add">The second beast</char> required also that <char style="add">the first beast’s name</char> be marked {<char style="add">its agents</char> mark <char style="add">the first beast’s name</char>} on the right hand or on the forehead of everyone, those of little <char style="add">social importance</char> and of great <char style="add">social importance</char>, the rich and the poor, free <char style="add">people</char> and slaves. <char style="add">Everyone</char>! <verse eid="REV 13:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 13:17"/>They did this in order that people could not buy <char style="add">anything</char> or sell <char style="add">anything</char> if they did not have the mark, which represents the name of the beast or the number of its name, <char style="add">on their foreheads</char>. <verse eid="REV 13:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 13:18"/>You must <char style="add">think</char> wisely to understand <char style="add">the meaning of the mark</char>. Anyone who thinks wisely should calculate from the number of the beast what the man’s name is. That number is 666.<verse eid="REV 13:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="REV 14"/>
  <para style="s1">John saw the Lamb standing on Zion Mountain with 144,000 redeemed people, who were marked with God’s seal. They were singing a new song that only the redeemed could sing.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 14:1-5">Revelation 14:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 14:1"/>But then I saw the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb standing on Zion Hill <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>. With him were 144,000 <char style="add">people</char>. His name and his Father’s name had been written {<char style="add">He</char> had written his name and his Father’s name} on their foreheads. <verse eid="REV 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 14:2"/>I heard a sound from heaven, which was as <char style="add">loud</char> [SIM] as the sound of a huge waterfall (OR, a great/wide <char style="add">river of rushing</char> water) and which was <char style="add">also as loud as</char> [SIM] mighty thunder. The sound that I heard was like <char style="add">the sound that</char> people make when they are playing their harps. <verse eid="REV 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 14:3"/>The 144,000 people were singing a new song <char style="add">while they stood</char> in front of the throne, in front of the four living <char style="add">creatures</char>, and in front of the elders. Only the 144,000 <char style="add">people</char>, the ones who have been {whom <char style="add">the one who is like a lamb</char> has} redeemed/bought from among the people on the earth, could learn that song. No one else could learn the song <char style="add">that they sang</char>. <verse eid="REV 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 14:4"/>Those 144,000 are the people who are <char style="add">spiritually</char> pure, <char style="add">like</char> virgins <char style="add">are morally pure</char>. They have not ◄defiled themselves/made themselves impure► [MET] <char style="add">by worshipping any false god</char>. They are the ones who accompany Jesus, the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb, wherever he goes. They <char style="add">represent all those whom he has</char> redeemed/bought for God from among the people <char style="add">of earth, in order that he might offer</char> them to God and to <char style="add">himself</char>. <verse eid="REV 14:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 14:5"/><char style="add">Those people</char> never lie when they speak [MTY], and they never act immorally.<verse eid="REV 14:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">An angel announced that after God judged and then destroyed the wicked cities symbolized as Babylon. Another angel declared individual judgment on worshipers of the beast, who symbolizes the head of this world power. The saints are called to remain steadfast.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 14:6-13">Revelation 14:6-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 14:6"/>I saw another angel that was flying between the sky and heaven. He was bringing <char style="add">God’s</char> eternal good message <char style="add">to earth</char>, in order that he might proclaim it to people who live on the earth. He will proclaim it to every nation, <char style="add">to every</char> tribe, <char style="add">to speakers of every</char> language [MTY], and <char style="add">to every</char> people-<char style="add">group</char>. <verse eid="REV 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 14:7"/>He said in a loud voice, “Revere God and honor him, because it is now time for him to judge <char style="add">people</char>! Worship <char style="add">God, because he is</char> the one who created the heaven, the earth, the ocean, and the springs of water.” <verse eid="REV 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 14:8"/>A second angel came after him saying, “The very evil <char style="add">cities</char> (OR, <char style="add">city</char>) <char style="add">represented by</char> Babylon are completely destroyed! <char style="add">God</char> has punished <char style="add">their people because</char> they <char style="add">have persuaded people of</char> all the nations <char style="add">to forsake God, just like a prostitute</char> [MET] persuades <char style="add">men</char> to drink <char style="add">strong</char> wine and <char style="add">as a result</char> commit sexual immorality.” <verse eid="REV 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 14:9"/>A third angel came next, saying in a loud voice, “If people worship the beast and its image and <char style="add">allow</char> its mark to be put {its <char style="add">agent to</char> put its mark} on their foreheads or on their hands, <verse eid="REV 14:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 14:10"/>God will be angry with them and punish them very severely [MET]. They will be tormented {<char style="add">God</char> will torment them} in burning sulfur in the presence of his holy angels and in the presence of the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb. <verse eid="REV 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 14:11"/>The smoke <char style="add">from the fire</char> that torments them will rise forever. <char style="add">They will</char> be tormented {<char style="add">God will</char> torment them} continually, day and night. <char style="add">That is what will happen to</char> the people who worship the beast and its image and who allow its name to be marked on them {allow <char style="add">its agent</char> to mark them with its name}.” <verse eid="REV 14:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 14:12"/>So God’s people, those who obey what God commands and who trust in Jesus, must faithfully continue <char style="add">obeying and trusting him</char>. <verse eid="REV 14:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 14:13"/>I heard a voice from heaven saying, “Write <char style="add">this: God will</char> now <char style="add">abundantly</char> bless the people who have a close relationship with the Lord <char style="add">Jesus</char> for the rest of <char style="add">their lives</char>.” <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit says, “Yes, <char style="add">after they die</char>, they will no longer have to work hard. Instead, they will rest, and <char style="add">the record of the good deeds</char> [MTY] that they have done will go with them (OR, <char style="add">God</char> will <char style="add">reward them</char> for the good deeds that they have done).”<verse eid="REV 14:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Someone like the One who came from heaven sat on a cloud, holding a sharp sickle. An angel from the sanctuary commanded him to harvest the earth. Another angel was commanded to reap fruit that grows on vines. He threw the fruit that he harvested into the place where God angrily crushes people like a winepress crushes grapes. When the winepress was trodden, the flow was like a flood of blood on the earth.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 14:14-20">Revelation 14:14-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 14:14"/>Then I was surprised to see a white cloud, and on the cloud <char style="add">someone</char> was sitting who looked like the one who came from heaven. He <char style="add">was wearing</char> a golden crown on his head. In his hand <char style="add">he held</char> a sharp sickle. <verse eid="REV 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 14:15"/>Another angel came out of the temple <char style="add">in heaven</char>. In a loud voice, <char style="add">speaking figuratively about gathering people for God to judge them</char>, he said to the one who was sitting on the cloud, “The time has come to reap <char style="add">the grain on the earth</char>, so with your sickle <char style="add">reap</char> the <char style="add">grain</char>, because the grain on the earth is ripe.” <verse eid="REV 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 14:16"/>The one who was sitting on the cloud forcefully gathered together <char style="add">all the people</char> on earth, <char style="add">as</char> [MET] <char style="add">a farmer</char> reaps grain with his sickle. <verse eid="REV 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 14:17"/>Another angel came out of the sanctuary in heaven. He also held a sharp sickle. <verse eid="REV 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 14:18"/>From the altar came another angel. He is the one who takes care of the fire <char style="add">of the altar. Also speaking figuratively about gathering the wicked people for God to judge and punish them</char>, he said in a loud voice to the angel who held the sharp sickle, “With your sharp sickle cut off the clusters of grapes in the vineyards on the earth! Then gather the clusters of grapes together, because its grapes are ripe!” <verse eid="REV 14:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 14:19"/>So, <char style="add">just like a man would</char> cut off with his sickle the clusters of grapes in his vineyard [MET], an angel forcefully <char style="add">gathered the wicked people</char> on the earth. Then he threw them into the huge place where God will angrily punish them. <verse eid="REV 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 14:20"/><char style="add">The wicked people</char> were trampled on {<char style="add">God’s agent</char> trod on <char style="add">the wicked people</char>} <char style="add">in</char> the winepress outside the city. The blood that came out from the winepress flowed <char style="add">in a stream so deep that it reached</char> to the bridles of the horses, <char style="add">and extended</char> ◄180 miles/300 kilometers►.<verse eid="REV 14:20"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="REV 15"/>
  <para style="s1">John saw in the sky a marvelous sign of the seven angels who were responsible for inflicting people with the seven last plagues.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 15:1">Revelation 15:1</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 15:1"/>Something else very unusual <char style="add">appeared</char> in the sky. I saw seven angels, whose duty it was to <char style="add">punish</char> (OR, inflict hardship upon) <char style="add">rebellious people</char> with seven different plagues (OR, in seven different ways). God is so angry <char style="add">with rebellious people that</char> this is the last <char style="add">time that he will punish them with the purpose of giving them an opportunity to turn away from their sinful behavior</char>.<verse eid="REV 15:1"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John saw those who had been victorious over the beast respond to God’s judgment of rebellious people on earth by singing praise to God for his mighty deliverance and righteous judgment.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 15:2-4">Revelation 15:2-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 15:2"/>I saw what looked like an ocean <char style="add">that was made of</char> glass and mixed with fire. And I saw the people who overcame the beast <char style="add">by not worshipping it</char> or its image, or <char style="add">allowing its agent to mark them with</char> the number that corresponds to the beast’s name [PRS]. They were standing by the ocean <char style="add">that looked like it was made</char> of glass. They had harps <char style="add">for praising</char> God. <verse eid="REV 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 15:3"/>They were singing a song <char style="add">like</char> God’s servant Moses <char style="add">sang long ago</char>. They sang <char style="add">like this to praise Jesus, the one who is like</char> a lamb:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 15:3">Lord God Almighty,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 15:3">whatever you do is powerful and marvelous!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 15:3">You always act righteously and truthfully.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 15:3">You are king forever!<verse eid="REV 15:3"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 15:4"/>O Lord, you alone are holy!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 15:4">People of [MTY] all nations will come and worship you,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 15:4">because you show everyone that you have judged everyone righteously.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 15:4">So, everyone will fear you and honor you! [RHQ].<verse eid="REV 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John saw angels being given the seven bowls of judgment in the heavenly sanctuary, which became filled with the smoke of God’s unapproachable glory.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 15:5-8">Revelation 15:5-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 15:5"/>After this, <char style="add">in the vision</char> I saw in heaven the temple <char style="add">that ◄corresponds to/was represented by</char>► the tent <char style="add">that the Israelites pitched in the desert. That was the tent that contained</char> the <char style="add">Ten Commandments. The temple door</char> was opened {was open}. <verse eid="REV 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 15:6"/>The seven angels <char style="add">who had the bowls containing</char> the seven plagues came out of the temple. The angels were dressed in clean, white linen <char style="add">garments</char>, and they wore gold bands around their chests. <verse eid="REV 15:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 15:7"/>One of the four living <char style="add">creatures</char> gave <char style="add">each of</char> the seven angels a golden bowl, filled with <char style="add">wine/liquid. That wine/liquid symbolized</char> that God, who lives forever, would severely punish <char style="add">rebellious people</char>. <verse eid="REV 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 15:8"/>The temple was filled with smoke <char style="add">that symbolized</char> the presence of the glorious and all-powerful God. No one was able to enter the temple until the seven angels finished <char style="add">pouring out</char> the seven plagues.<verse eid="REV 15:8"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="REV 16"/>
  <para style="s1">Four angels emptied their judgment bowls.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 16:1-9">Revelation 16:1-9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 16:1"/>
    <char style="add">In the vision</char> I heard <char style="add">someone</char> in the temple speak in a loud voice to the angels <char style="add">who had the seven bowls</char>. He said, “Go <char style="add">from here</char> and pour out on the earth <char style="add">the wine/liquid in</char> [MTY] the seven bowls. <char style="add">This will show that</char> God is angry with <char style="add">rebellious people and will punish them</char>.” <verse eid="REV 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 16:2"/>So the first angel went and poured out on the earth <char style="add">the wine/liquid that was in</char> [MTY] his bowl. <char style="add">As a result</char>, horrible and painful sores broke out on God’s enemies who had allowed the beast’s <char style="add">agents</char> to mark them and who worshipped the image of the beast. <verse eid="REV 16:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 16:3"/>The second angel poured out on the ocean <char style="add">the wine/liquid that was in</char> [MTY] his bowl. <char style="add">As a result</char>, the <char style="add">water in the ocean stank like the blood</char> of a person who has died. <char style="add">And</char> [MTY] every living creature that was in the ocean died. <verse eid="REV 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 16:4"/>The third angel poured out on the rivers and water springs <char style="add">the wine/liquid</char> [MTY] <char style="add">that was in</char> his bowl. <char style="add">As a result, the water in the rivers and springs</char> turned into blood. <verse eid="REV 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 16:5"/>I heard the angel <char style="add">who has authority over</char> the waters say <char style="add">to God</char>, “<char style="add">O God</char>, you exist and have always existed. You are the holy one. You judge people justly. <verse eid="REV 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 16:6"/><char style="add">The rebellious people</char> murdered your holy people and prophets. So you are just in punishing them by giving them blood to drink. This is what they deserve!” <verse eid="REV 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 16:7"/>Then I heard <char style="add">an angel</char> respond <char style="add">from</char> the altar [PRS], “Yes, Lord God, you who are almighty, you punish <char style="add">people</char> rightly and justly!” <verse eid="REV 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 16:8"/>Then the fourth angel poured out on the sun <char style="add">the wine/liquid that was in</char> [MTY] his bowl. <char style="add">He</char> enabled the sun to scorch <char style="add">people</char> with fiery <char style="add">heat</char>. <verse eid="REV 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 16:9"/>Because people were severely burned by the intense heat {the intense heat severely burned people}, they said evil things about God [MTY], <char style="add">because</char> he had the power <char style="add">to strike people with</char> plagues like those. But they refused to stop their evil behavior and refused to honor him.<verse eid="REV 16:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Two more angels emptied their judgment bowls on the earth. Demons gathered armies to fight against God. But Jesus warned his people to watch faithfully for his imminent coming. The battle was ready to begin at Armageddon.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 16:10-16">Revelation 16:10-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 16:10"/>When the fifth angel poured out on the throne of the beast <char style="add">the wine/liquid that was in</char> [MTY] his bowl, it became dark in the kingdom that the beast <char style="add">ruled. As a result, the beast and the people whom it ruled</char> were biting their tongues because <char style="add">they were suffering intense</char> pain. <verse eid="REV 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 16:11"/>They insulted God <char style="add">who rules in</char> heaven, because their sores were so painful. But they refused to stop doing the <char style="add">evil</char> things that they were doing. <verse eid="REV 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 16:12"/>The sixth angel poured out on the huge river Euphrates <char style="add">the wine/liquid that was in</char> [MTY] his bowl. <char style="add">As a result, the</char> water <char style="add">in the river</char> was dried up so that the rulers from the eastern [MTY] <char style="add">countries could cross it with their armies</char> [SYN]. <verse eid="REV 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 16:13"/>I saw evil spirits that looked like frogs. One came out of the mouth of the dragon, one from the mouth of the beast, and one from the mouth of the false prophet. <verse eid="REV 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 16:14"/>Those spirits were demons who were <char style="add">able to</char> perform miracles. They went out to the rulers of the whole world, in order to gather their <char style="add">armies</char> [SYN] together to the battle that <char style="add">they will fight</char> on the wonderful day when Almighty God <char style="add">punishes his enemies</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="REV 16:14"/><verse number="15-16" style="v" sid="REV 16:15-16"/>The evil spirits will gather the rulers at a place that is called in the Hebrew <char style="add">language</char> Armageddon.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="REV 16:15-16">
    <char style="add">I heard the Lord Jesus say</char>, “<char style="add">You must</char> listen carefully to <char style="add">me</char>: I am coming unexpectedly [SIM], like a thief. <char style="add">So</char>, I will be happy with those who stay alert and <char style="add">keep on living righteously so that they will not be ashamed</char>, just like [MET] a person keeps his clothes <char style="add">on</char> so that he will not be ashamed <char style="add">like a person who is</char> naked.”<verse eid="REV 16:15-16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">After the seventh angel emptied his bowl, God punished the very evil city symbolized by Babylon, and destroyed other cities, and terrible disasters followed.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 16:17-21">Revelation 16:17-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 16:17"/>The seventh angel poured out into the air <char style="add">the wine/liquid that was in</char> [MTY] his bowl. <char style="add">As a result, someone</char> said with a loud voice from the throne in the temple, “<char style="add">The time for God to finish punishing rebellious people</char> is <char style="add">about to be</char> start.” <verse eid="REV 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 16:18"/><char style="add">When the angel emptied his bowl</char>, lightning flashed, there were rumblings and thunder, and the earth shook. It shook more violently than it has ever shaken since people first <char style="add">lived</char> on earth. <verse eid="REV 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 16:19"/>And <char style="add">as a result</char>, the very evil city <char style="add">that is symbolized by Babylon</char> split into three parts. <char style="add">God also</char> destroyed cities in <char style="add">other</char> nations. God did not forget that <char style="add">the people of</char> [MTY] the very evil <char style="add">city symbolized by</char> Babylon <char style="add">had sinned very much</char>. So he <char style="add">caused the people with whom</char> he was furiously angry [MET] <char style="add">to drink</char> a cup of very <char style="add">poisonous wine/liquid that represented his punishment</char>. <verse eid="REV 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 16:20"/>Also <char style="add">as a result of the earthquake</char>, every island disappeared, and the mountains became flat land. <verse eid="REV 16:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 16:21"/>Also <char style="add">as a result of the angel’s emptying his bowl</char>, huge hailstones, each weighing about 100 pounds, fell from the sky onto the people. Then people insulted God because <char style="add">he had caused</char> the destructive hail to fall on them in that terrible plague.<verse eid="REV 16:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 16"/>
  <chapter number="17" style="c" sid="REV 17"/>
  <para style="s1">One of the seven angels offered to show John how God will punish the very evil city represented by a prostitute, with whom the rulers of people on earth have been seduced to act immorally and idolatrously.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 17:1-2">Revelation 17:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 17:1"/>One of the seven angels, who had <char style="add">one of</char> the seven bowls, came to me. He said to me, “Come <char style="add">with me</char>, and I will show you how <char style="add">God</char> will punish the very evil <char style="add">city that is represented by</char> [SYM] a prostitute, a city in which there are many canals <char style="add">of</char> water. <verse eid="REV 17:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 17:2"/><char style="add">It is as though</char> the rulers of earth have acted immorally <char style="add">and idolatrously</char> with the people of that city [MET], and they <char style="add">have persuaded people</char> who live on the earth to act immorally <char style="add">and idolatrously</char> with them [MET], <char style="add">just like a prostitute persuades men to drink</char> the <char style="add">strong</char> wine <char style="add">she gives them, resulting in their</char> becoming drunk <char style="add">and</char> then committing sexual immorality. with her.”<verse eid="REV 17:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When the angel took John to a wilderness, he saw an immoral woman who was drunk with the blood of God’s people. The sight caused John to react with great bewilderment.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 17:3-6">Revelation 17:3-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 17:3"/>Then, as <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">controlled me</char>, the angel carried me away to a desolate area. There I saw a woman who was sitting on a red beast. The beast had names <char style="add">written</char> all over itself. They were names that ◄insulted/spoke evil against► <char style="add">God</char>. The beast had seven heads and ten horns. <verse eid="REV 17:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 17:4"/>The woman <char style="add">that I saw</char> was wearing purple and red <char style="add">clothes</char>; and gold, precious stones, and pearls were fastened to her <char style="add">clothes and her body</char>. She held in her hand a golden cup. The cup was full of <char style="add">a liquid that represents</char> [SYM] the detestable/disgusting, idolatrous things and filthy immoral things that she <char style="add">does</char>. <verse eid="REV 17:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 17:5"/>This name, that has a hidden/secret <char style="add">meaning</char>, was written on her forehead<char style="add">:</char> “<char style="add">This woman is</char> Babylon, the very evil <char style="add">city! She acts like</char> the mother of the prostitutes on the earth. She teaches them to <char style="add">act</char> immorally and to worship idols.” <verse eid="REV 17:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 17:6"/>I saw that the woman had become drunk as a result of drinking the blood of God’s people, those who had told others about Jesus. When I saw her, I was very bewildered/perplexed.<verse eid="REV 17:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The angel revealed the meaning of what John had seen, identifying as ruling entities both the beast which amazed people and his seven heads and ten horns, and the angel declared that they would be overcome by the Lamb and defeated. The angel identified the prostitute as representing the very evil city that dominates people, and he declared that it would be destroyed.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 17:7-18">Revelation 17:7-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 17:7"/>The angel said to me, “Do not be bewildered [RHQ]! I will explain to you the hidden/secret meaning of the woman and of the beast on which she rides, the beast that has the seven heads and the ten horns. <verse eid="REV 17:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 17:8"/>The beast that you saw <char style="add">lived</char> previously. Eventually God will destroy him, but now he is dead. He is <char style="add">about to</char> come up ◄from the underworld/from the deep dark pit►. <char style="add">When</char> the beast who had previously lived, and who then had died, reappears, the people who live on the earth will be amazed. <char style="add">They are people whose</char> names were not in the book in which are written the names of people <char style="add">who will</char> have eternal life. <char style="add">The angels have been writing those names in a list</char> ◄from the beginning of the world/from the time when the world began►. <verse eid="REV 17:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 17:9"/>Those who <char style="add">think</char> wisely <char style="add">can understand</char> this: The seven heads <char style="add">of the beast</char> on which the woman sits <char style="add">symbolize</char> the seven hills <char style="add">of the city that the woman represents</char>. They also <char style="add">symbolize</char> seven rulers. <verse eid="REV 17:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 17:10"/>Five <char style="add">of those rulers</char> have died. One is <char style="add">still alive</char>. The seventh <char style="add">ruler</char> has not yet come. When he comes, he must remain on earth for <char style="add">only</char> a short <char style="add">time</char>. <verse eid="REV 17:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 17:11"/>The beast that <char style="add">lived</char> before and then was not <char style="add">alive</char> will be the eighth <char style="add">ruler</char>. He will be <char style="add">evil like</char> the seven <char style="add">rulers were, but God</char> will surely destroy him. <verse eid="REV 17:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 17:12"/>The ten horns that you saw <char style="add">represent</char> ten rulers who have not yet begun to rule. They, together with the beast, will be authorized to rule <char style="add">people for only a short time, as if it were</char> [MET] for one hour. <verse eid="REV 17:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 17:13"/>Those <char style="add">rulers</char> will all agree to do the same thing. <char style="add">As a result</char> they will give to the beast their power <char style="add">to rule people</char> as well as their authority <char style="add">to rule people</char> [DOU]. <verse eid="REV 17:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 17:14"/>The rulers and the beast will fight against <char style="add">Jesus</char>, the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb. He will defeat them, because he is Lord <char style="add">who rules over all other</char> lords and the King <char style="add">who rules over all other</char> kings. Those <char style="add">people</char> who are with Jesus<char style="add">and helping him</char> are the ones whom <char style="add">God</char> has chosen, and who keep <char style="add">serving him</char> faithfully.” <verse eid="REV 17:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 17:15"/>Then the angel said to me, “The waters that you saw in the city where the prostitute sits represent people-<char style="add">groups</char>, multitudes <char style="add">of people</char>, nations, and <char style="add">speakers of many languages</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="REV 17:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 17:16"/>The ten horns that you saw <char style="add">represent rulers</char> [SYM]. They and the beast will hate <char style="add">the people in the city</char> [MTY] that the prostitute <char style="add">represents</char>. As a result, they will <char style="add">take away everything that is in the city, as if</char> they were [MET] leaving it naked. They will <char style="add">destroy it as if</char> [MET] devouring flesh/meat, and they will burn it with fire. <verse eid="REV 17:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 17:17"/>They will do that because God has caused them to decide to do what he wants them to do. As a result, they will let the beast have their power to rule until what God has said is fulfilled {until <char style="add">they</char> fulfill what God has said} [MTY]. <verse eid="REV 17:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 17:18"/>The prostitute that you saw <char style="add">represents</char> the very evil city <char style="add">whose leaders</char> [MTY] rule over the kings of the earth.”<verse eid="REV 17:18"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 17"/>
  <chapter number="18" style="c" sid="REV 18"/>
  <para style="s1">A powerful angel descended from heaven and announced that the cities represented by Babylon were about to be completely destroyed because of their immorality and idolatry.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 18:1-3">Revelation 18:1-3</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 18:1"/>After this, <char style="add">in the vision</char> I saw another angel, who had great authority, coming down from heaven. The earth became bright <char style="add">because</char> he was shining so intensely/brightly. <verse eid="REV 18:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 18:2"/>He shouted with a very loud voice, “<char style="add">God is about to</char> completely destroy [DOU] all the very <char style="add">evil</char> cities (OR, the very evil <char style="add">city</char>) <char style="add">that</char> Babylon <char style="add">represents</char>. As a result, all <char style="add">kinds of</char> evil spirits [DOU] will live there, and all <char style="add">kinds of</char> foul and detestable [DOU] birds will live there. <verse eid="REV 18:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 18:3"/><char style="add">God will destroy those cities</char> because <char style="add">their rulers have persuaded</char> the people of [MTY] all nations to act very immorally <char style="add">and idolatrously with the people of</char> [MET] <char style="add">those cities, just like</char> a prostitute persuades men to drink <char style="add">strong</char> wine and then commit fornication with her. The rulers of the earth have also acted immorally <char style="add">and idolatrously</char> with the people of [MTY] those cities. The merchants of the earth have become rich <char style="add">because the people of those cities</char> strongly desired <char style="add">and bought from the merchants</char> many ◄luxuries/expensive things►.”<verse eid="REV 18:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John heard Jesus tell God’s people to flee from those cities.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 18:4-5">Revelation 18:4-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 18:4"/>I heard <char style="add">Jesus</char> speak from heaven. He said, “My people, flee from <char style="add">those cities</char>, in order that you do not sin as the people <char style="add">of those cities do. If you sin as they do</char>, I will punish you as I will punish them. <verse eid="REV 18:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 18:5"/><char style="add">It is as though</char> their sins have been piled {have piled} up to heaven, and God remembers them [DOU], <char style="add">so now he will punish them</char> [MTY].”<verse eid="REV 18:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus sentenced the cities represented by Babylon to destruction.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 18:6-8">Revelation 18:6-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 18:6"/>
    <char style="add">To the angels whom God assigned to punish those cities, Jesus said</char>, “Pay back/Punish the people of those cities to the same extent that they harmed <char style="add">other people</char>. Cause them to suffer twice as much <char style="add">as they caused other people to suffer</char> [DOU, MET]. <verse eid="REV 18:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 18:7"/>To the same extent that they have boasted about themselves and done the things that they wanted to do, to that extent torment them and cause them to grieve. <char style="add">Do that because</char> in their minds they think, ‘We rule as queens! We are not widows, and we will never mourn <char style="add">as widows do</char>’! <verse eid="REV 18:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 18:8"/>So in one day terrible calamities/troubles will come upon them. <char style="add">The people in those cities</char> will die, others will mourn for them, people will be hungry <char style="add">because there will be no food</char>, and <char style="add">their cities</char> will be burned up. The Lord God is able to punish those cities <char style="add">like that</char>, because he is very powerful.”<verse eid="REV 18:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Earth’s kings, merchants, and maritime traders mourned the loss of those cities.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 18:9-19">Revelation 18:9-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 18:9"/>“The kings of the earth who have acted immorally <char style="add">with people of those cities</char> and have lived with the people of those cities, doing just what they wanted to do, will weep and mourn [DOU] for them when they see the smoke of the fire that is burning those cities. <verse eid="REV 18:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 18:10"/>They will stand far away <char style="add">from those cities</char>, because they will be afraid <char style="add">that they will suffer just like the people of those cities</char> are suffering. They will say, ‘Terrible things will happen to the awesome and mighty cities <char style="add">represented by</char> Babylon! <char style="add">God</char> will punish them suddenly and swiftly [MTY]!’ <verse eid="REV 18:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 18:11"/>The merchants of the earth will weep and will mourn [DOU] <char style="add">for those cities</char>, because no one will ever again buy the things that they have <char style="add">to sell to the people in those cities</char>. <verse eid="REV 18:11"/><verse number="12-13" style="v" sid="REV 18:12-13"/><char style="add">They sell ornaments made</char> of gold, silver, precious stones, and pearls. They sell <char style="add">expensive cloth made of</char> fine linen and silk, <char style="add">expensive cloth that is dyed</char> purple and crimson. They sell all kinds of <char style="add">rare</char> wood, all kinds of items <char style="add">made of</char> ivory, costly wood, bronze, iron, and marble. They sell cinnamon, spice, perfume, frankincense, wine, olive oil, fine flour, and grain. They sell cattle, sheep, horses, and chariots. They even sell human beings [SYN, DOU] to become slaves. <verse eid="REV 18:12-13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 18:14"/><char style="add">The merchants will say</char>, ‘The good things you people longed to have are gone! All your luxurious and splendid [DOU] <char style="add">possessions have vanished!</char>! They will be gone forever/You will never have them again [LIT]!’ <verse eid="REV 18:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 18:15"/>The merchants <char style="add">who sold</char> these things and who had become rich by <char style="add">supplying them</char> for those <char style="add">cities</char> will stand far away, because they will be afraid <char style="add">that they will suffer just like</char> the people <char style="add">of those cities</char> are suffering. They will weep and mourn [DOU], <verse eid="REV 18:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 18:16"/>and they will say, ‘Terrible things [DOU] have happened to the awesome/great [MET] cities! <char style="add">They were like queens</char> who dressed themselves in <char style="add">clothes made of</char> [MTY] fine linen <char style="add">cloth</char> and expensive cloth dyed purple and crimson, and who were adorned with gold, precious stones, and pearls. <verse eid="REV 18:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 18:17"/>But suddenly and swiftly [MTY] <char style="add">God</char> has destroyed these expensive things.’ Every ship captain, all people who travel by ship, all ◄sailors/those who work on ships►, and all others who earn their living <char style="add">by traveling on</char> the ocean will stand far away <char style="add">from those cities</char>. <verse eid="REV 18:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 18:18"/>When they see the smoke of the fire that is burning those cities, they will shout, ‘No <char style="add">other</char> cities have ever been so awesome!’ [RHQ] <verse eid="REV 18:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 18:19"/>They will throw dust on their heads <char style="add">to show that they are sad</char>, and they will shout, weep, and mourn [DOU]. They will say, ‘Terrible things have happened to the awesome/great cities, the cities that made all people who own ships <char style="add">that sail</char> on the ocean become rich by <char style="add">carrying</char> their costly ◄things for them to sell/merchandise►! <char style="add">God</char> has suddenly and swiftly destroyed [MTY] those cities!’”<verse eid="REV 18:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">All of God’s people are called to rejoice because God has pronounced judgment on the cities represented by Babylon.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 18:20-24">Revelation 18:20-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 18:20"/>Then someone spoke from heaven saying, “All you who live in heaven, rejoice over what has happened to <char style="add">the cities represented by</char> Babylon! You who are God’s people, including you apostles, you ◄prophets/who speak messages that come directly from God►, rejoice, because God has justly punished the people of those cities because they acted in an evil way toward you!”<verse eid="REV 18:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 18:21"/>Then a mighty angel picked up a boulder the size of a large stone for grinding grain, and threw it into the ocean. Then he said, “O you people in [APO] the awesome/great cities <char style="add">represented by</char> Babylon, your cities will be destroyed so that they will disappear just like that stone disappeared in the ocean! Your cities will be gone forever [LIT]! <verse eid="REV 18:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 18:22"/>In your cities there will never again be <char style="add">anyone</char> playing harps, singing, playing flutes, and blowing trumpets. There will no longer be any ◄skilled workers/craftsmen► making things. There will never again be people grinding <char style="add">grain at</char> [MTY] the mills. <verse eid="REV 18:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="REV 18:23"/>No lamplight will ever again shine. There will never again be the <char style="add">happy</char> voices of a bridegroom and his bride. <char style="add">God will destroy your cities</char> because your merchants were the most <char style="add">deceitful</char> men in the world. You persuaded them to deceive <char style="add">people of</char> [MTY] all nations. <verse eid="REV 18:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="REV 18:24"/>You are also <char style="add">responsible for killing</char> [MTY] <char style="add">the</char> prophets and <char style="add">others</char> of God’s people. Indeed, you are the ones who are guilty for the deaths of all those who have been {whom <char style="add">others</char> have} killed on the earth!”<verse eid="REV 18:24"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 18"/>
  <chapter number="19" style="c" sid="REV 19"/>
  <para style="s1">After the destruction of Babylon, John heard a huge crowd praising God for saving his people and announcing the marriage of the one who is like a lamb.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 19:1-8">Revelation 19:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 19:1"/>After these things I heard <char style="add">what sounded</char> like a huge crowd in heaven. They were shouting things like,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 19:1">“◄Hallelujah!/Praise our God!►” “He has saved us!”</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 19:1">“He is glorious and mighty!”<verse eid="REV 19:1"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 19:2"/>“Praise him because he judges truly and justly!”</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 19:2">“He has punished the very evil cities that are like a prostitute,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 19:2">because their people persuaded the other people of earth [MTY] to act immorally and idolatrously like they do.”</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="REV 19:2">“Praise him because he has punished them for murdering his servants [MTY]!”<verse eid="REV 19:2"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 19:3"/>
    <char style="add">The crowd</char> shouted a second time saying:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 19:3">◄Hallelujah!/Praise God!► The smoke of the fire that is burning the cities will rise forever!<verse eid="REV 19:3"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 19:4"/>The 24 elders and the four living <char style="add">creatures</char> ◄prostrated themselves/knelt down► and worshipped God, who sits on the throne. Then they said, “<char style="add">It</char> is true! ◄Hallelujah!/Praise God!►” <verse eid="REV 19:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 19:5"/>Someone spoke from the throne and said, “All you who are our God’s servants, praise him! All you who reverence him, <char style="add">whether you are socially</char> significant or insignificant, praise him! <char style="add">Everyone</char>!” <verse eid="REV 19:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 19:6"/>I heard something like the noise of a huge crowd <char style="add">of people</char>, like the sound of a huge waterfall (OR, a great/wide river of rushing water), and like the sound of loud thunder. They were shouting:</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 19:6">◄Hallelujah!/Praise God!► Because the Lord God, the Almighty One, reigns!<verse eid="REV 19:6"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 19:7"/>We should rejoice, we should be extremely glad, and we should honor him,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 19:7">because it is now time for Jesus, the one who is like a lamb, to be united</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 19:7">permanently with his people, which will be like a man [MET] marrying his bride, and</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="REV 19:7">because those who belong to him have prepared themselves to be united with him.<verse eid="REV 19:7"/></para>
  <para style="pi1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 19:8"/>God has permitted them to be completely pure, like a bride who [MET] dresses in fine linen that is bright and clean.</para>
  <para style="p" vid="REV 19:8">Fine <char style="add">bright and clean</char> linen represents the righteous acts of God’s people.<verse eid="REV 19:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God will abundantly bless the people who have been invited to celebrate the marriage of the Lamb. Only God should be worshipped. All his servants are on an equal basis.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 19:9-10">Revelation 19:9-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 19:9"/>Then the angel said to me, “Write <char style="add">this: God will abundantly</char> bless the people who are {whom <char style="add">he</char> has} invited to the feast <char style="add">that celebrates Jesus, the one who is like a</char> lamb, <char style="add">permanently uniting with his people, like someone</char> [MET] <char style="add">marrying a wife</char>.” He also said <char style="add">to me</char>: “These words that God <char style="add">declares</char> are true!” <verse eid="REV 19:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 19:10"/>I <char style="add">immediately</char> ◄prostrated myself/knelt down► at his feet in order to worship him. But he said to me, “Do not <char style="add">worship me</char>! I am <char style="add">just</char> your <char style="add">(sg)</char> fellow servant and the fellow servant of your <char style="add">(sg)</char> fellow believers who tell people about Jesus. God is the one whom you should worship, because it is the Spirit of God who gives people the power to tell others about Jesus (OR, <char style="add">those who tell others about</char> Jesus are <char style="add">truly</char> declaring <char style="add">the words that the Spirit of God has given them</char>)!”<verse eid="REV 19:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John saw heaven open and saw the one whom he described as King of kings and Lord of lords mounted on a white horse.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 19:11-16">Revelation 19:11-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 19:11"/>
    <char style="add">In the vision</char> I saw heaven opened {open}, and I was surprised to see a white horse. <char style="add">Jesus</char>, the one who was riding on the horse, is called ‘Trustworthy and Genuine/True’. He judges <char style="add">all people according to</char> what is right, and fights righteously <char style="add">against his enemies</char>. <verse eid="REV 19:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 19:12"/>His eyes <char style="add">shone like</char> [MET] a flame of fire. There were many royal crowns on his head. A name had been written <char style="add">on him</char>. Only he knows <char style="add">the meaning of that name</char>. <verse eid="REV 19:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 19:13"/>The robe he was wearing was drenched with blood. His name is <char style="add">also</char> “◄The one who expresses what God is like/The Word of God►.” <verse eid="REV 19:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 19:14"/>The armies of heaven were following him. <char style="add">They were also</char> riding on white horses. They were wearing clothes <char style="add">made of</char> clean white linen. <verse eid="REV 19:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 19:15"/><char style="add">The words</char> that Jesus speaks <char style="add">are like</char> [MTY] a sharp sword with which he will strike <char style="add">the rebellious people of</char> the nations. He himself will rule them <char style="add">powerfully, as though he had</char> [MET] an iron rod. He will crush <char style="add">his enemies just like</char> [MET] <char style="add">a person crushes grapes in a</char> winepress. <char style="add">He will do this for</char> God Almighty, who is extremely angry <char style="add">with them because of their sins</char>. <verse eid="REV 19:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 19:16"/>On his cloak close to his thigh a name had been written {<char style="add">he</char> had written a name}, which is “King who <char style="add">rules over all other</char> kings and Lord who <char style="add">rules over all other</char> lords.”<verse eid="REV 19:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">An angel invited all flesh-eating birds to feast on the flesh of people who would be killed by the Rider on the white horse. When the beast and the false prophet gathered kings with their armies to fight against the Rider and his army, the beast and the false prophet were thrown into the lake of fire. The Rider killed rebellious people with his sword, and the birds gorged themselves on their flesh.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 19:17-21">Revelation 19:17-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 19:17"/>I saw an angel who was standing in <char style="add">the light of</char> [MTY] the sun. He called loudly to all the <char style="add">flesh-eating</char> birds flying high in the sky, “Come and gather for the wonderful feast that God <char style="add">is providing for you</char>! <verse eid="REV 19:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 19:18"/><char style="add">Come</char> and eat the flesh of all <char style="add">God’s enemies who are dead—</char> the flesh of kings, army commanders, <char style="add">people who fought</char> powerfully, horses and the <char style="add">soldiers</char> who rode them, <char style="add">and the flesh of all other kinds of people</char>, whether <char style="add">they were</char> free or slaves, <char style="add">socially</char> insignificant or significant. <char style="add">All kinds</char>!” <verse eid="REV 19:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 19:19"/>Then I saw the beast and the kings of earth with their armies gathered together to fight against the Rider on the horse, and against his army. <verse eid="REV 19:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 19:20"/>The beast and the false prophet were captured {<char style="add">He</char> captured the beast and the false prophet}. The false prophet is the one who had performed miracles in the beast’s presence. By doing that he had deceived the people who had accepted the beast’s mark <char style="add">on their foreheads</char> and who worshipped its image. The beast and the false prophet were thrown {<char style="add">He</char> threw the beast and the one who falsely said that he spoke messages that came directly from God} alive into the lake of fire that burns with sulfur. <verse eid="REV 19:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 19:21"/>The rider on the horse killed the rest <char style="add">of their armies</char> just by <char style="add">speaking words</char>, <char style="add">which were like</char> [MTY] a sword that extended from his mouth. All those birds gorged themselves on the flesh of <char style="add">the people whom he had killed</char>.<verse eid="REV 19:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 19"/>
  <chapter number="20" style="c" sid="REV 20"/>
  <para style="s1">John saw an angel coming down from heaven. He seized, bound, and imprisoned the dragon for 1,000 years.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 20:1-3">Revelation 20:1-3</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 20:1"/>I saw an angel coming down from heaven. He had the key to the deep dark pit, and he was carrying a large chain in his hand. <verse eid="REV 20:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 20:2"/>He seized the dragon. That dragon is the ancient serpent, the devil, that is, Satan. The angel bound him with the chain. That chain could not be loosed {<char style="add">No one could loose</char> that chain} for 1,000 years. <verse eid="REV 20:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 20:3"/>The angel threw him into the deep dark pit. He shut <char style="add">the door of the pit</char>, locked it, and sealed it <char style="add">to prevent anyone from opening it</char>. He did that in order that Satan might no longer deceive <char style="add">the people of the</char> nations [MTY], until those 1,000 years are ended. After that <char style="add">time</char>, Satan must be released {<char style="add">God/God’s angel</char> must release Satan} for a short time <char style="add">in order that he can do what God has planned</char>.<verse eid="REV 20:3"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John saw the thrones of the martyrs who lived again and had authority to judge people. Those martyrs are the first people whom God will cause to live again. They will reign with Christ during the 1,000 years.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 20:4-6">Revelation 20:4-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 20:4"/>I saw thrones on which people were sitting. <char style="add">They were given</char> {<char style="add">God</char> gave those people} <char style="add">authority</char> to judge <char style="add">other people</char>. I also saw the souls <char style="add">of people</char> whose heads had been {whose heads <char style="add">others</char> had} cut off because of <char style="add">their telling people about</char> Jesus and declaring God’s message. They were people who refused to worship the beast or its image, and who did not allow <char style="add">the beast’s agents</char> to put the beast’s mark on them, either on their foreheads or on their hands. They became alive again, and they ruled with Christ <char style="add">during those</char> 1,000 years. <verse eid="REV 20:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 20:5"/>They were the ones who lived again the first time <char style="add">that God caused dead people</char> to live again. The rest of <char style="add">the believers who</char> had died did not live again until after those 1,000 years. <verse eid="REV 20:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 20:6"/>◄<char style="add">God</char> will be pleased with/<char style="add">How</char> happy will be► those who live again that first time. God will <char style="add">consider</char> them holy. They will not die [PRS] a second time. Instead, they will be priests <char style="add">who serve</char> God and Christ, and they will rule with <char style="add">Christ</char> during those 1,000 years.<verse eid="REV 20:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">When Satan is released, he will deceive the nations in order to assemble them to fight against God and his people. God will send fire to burn up the rebellious nations. He will cause Satan to be thrown into the lake of fire for everlasting punishment.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 20:7-15">Revelation 20:7-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 20:7"/>When the 1,000 years are ended, Satan will be released {<char style="add">God’s angel</char> will release Satan} from <char style="add">the deep pit</char> in which he was imprisoned. <verse eid="REV 20:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 20:8"/>He will go out to deceive <char style="add">rebellious</char> people in nations [IDM] all over the earth. <char style="add">These are the nations that the prophet Ezekiel called</char> Gog and Magog. Satan will gather them to fight against <char style="add">God’s people</char>. There will be <char style="add">so many of them fighting against God’s people that no one will be able to count them</char> [SIM], just like <char style="add">no one can count the grains of</char> sand on the ocean shore. <verse eid="REV 20:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 20:9"/>They will march over the whole earth and surround the camp of God’s people <char style="add">in Jerusalem</char>, the city that <char style="add">God</char> loves. Then <char style="add">God will send</char> fire down from heaven, and it will burn them up. <verse eid="REV 20:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 20:10"/>The devil, who had deceived those people, will be thrown {<char style="add">God’s angel</char> will throw the devil, who had deceived those people} into the lake of burning sulfur. <char style="add">This is the same lake</char> into which both the beast and the false prophet had been <char style="add">thrown</char> {<char style="add">he</char> had <char style="add">thrown</char> both the beast and the false prophet}. <char style="add">As a result</char>, they will continually suffer severely forever.<verse eid="REV 20:10"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 20:11"/>Then I saw a huge white throne on which <char style="add">God</char> was sitting. He <char style="add">was so awesome that</char> the earth and the sky disappeared from his presence completely; they were completely destroyed {<char style="add">God</char> completely destroyed them}. <verse eid="REV 20:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 20:12"/>I saw that the people who had died <char style="add">but now lived again</char> were standing in front of the throne. <char style="add">They included people of</char> every social status! The books <char style="add">in which God records what people do</char> were opened {<char style="add">God/God’s angel</char> opened the books <char style="add">in which God records what people do</char>}. Another book was opened {<char style="add">He</char> opened another book}, which is <char style="add">called the Book</char> of Life, <char style="add">in which God has written the names of people who have eternal life</char>. <char style="add">God</char> judged the people who had died <char style="add">and now lived again</char> according to what they had done, just like <char style="add">he</char> had recorded it in the books. <verse eid="REV 20:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 20:13"/><char style="add">The people whose bodies were buried in the</char> sea <char style="add">became alive again in order to stand before God’s throne</char>. Everyone who had been buried on the land (OR, Every person who was waiting in the place where dead people stay) <char style="add">became alive again, in order to stand before the throne</char>. <char style="add">God</char> judged each one of them according to what each one had done. <verse eid="REV 20:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 20:14"/>All the unbelievers [PRS, MTY] —those who had been in the place where they waited after they died— <char style="add">were thrown into the burning lake</char>. The burning lake is <char style="add">the place in which people</char> die the second time. <verse eid="REV 20:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 20:15"/>The people whose <char style="add">names</char> [MTY] are not in the book, the one <char style="add">where God</char> has written <char style="add">the names of people who</char> have <char style="add">eternal</char> life, <char style="add">were also thrown</char> {◄<char style="add">God/God’s angel</char>► threw them also} <char style="add">into the lake</char> of fire.<verse eid="REV 20:15"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 20"/>
  <chapter number="21" style="c" sid="REV 21"/>
  <para style="s1">John saw a new heaven, a new earth, and a New Jerusalem, the city where God will dwell permanently with his people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 21:1-4">Revelation 21:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 21:1"/>Then <char style="add">in the vision</char> I saw a new heaven and a new earth. The first heaven and the first earth had disappeared, and the oceans no longer existed. <verse eid="REV 21:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 21:2"/>I saw <char style="add">God’s</char> holy city, which is the new <char style="add">city of</char> Jerusalem. It was coming down out of heaven from God. <char style="add">The city</char> had been prepared <char style="add">and decorated</char> {<char style="add">God</char> had prepared <char style="add">and decorated the city</char>} as [SIM] a bride is decorated {decorates herself} <char style="add">beautifully in order to marry</char> her husband. <verse eid="REV 21:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 21:3"/>I heard a loud voice that spoke from the throne <char style="add">of God</char>. It said, “Listen to this! Now God will live with people. He will live <char style="add">right in the midst of</char> them [DOU]! They will be his people. God himself will be with them, and he will be their God. <verse eid="REV 21:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 21:4"/><char style="add">As a result</char>, he will <char style="add">cause them to no longer be sad. It will be as though he will</char> [MTY] wipe every tear from their eyes. <char style="add">None of them</char> will ever again die or mourn or cry [DOU] or suffer pain, because the former things <char style="add">that make us sad</char> will have disappeared.”<verse eid="REV 21:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God declares that he has made everything new and has accomplished everything he intended to do. He declares himself to be the beginning and the end, and so he will give abundant eternal life to all who seek him, but will punish all the wicked in the lake of fire.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 21:5-8">Revelation 21:5-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 21:5"/>Then <char style="add">God</char>, who sits on the throne, said, “Listen to this! I am <char style="add">now</char> making everything new!” He said <char style="add">to me</char>: “Write these things <char style="add">that I have told you</char>, because you can trust <char style="add">that I will certainly cause them to happen</char>.” <verse eid="REV 21:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 21:6"/>He said to me, “I have finished <char style="add">doing all the things I needed to do</char>. I am the one who began all things [MET] and the one who will cause all things to end [MET]. To everyone who is <char style="add">spiritually</char> thirsty [MET], I will ◄freely give/give as a free gift► water from the spring <char style="add">that causes people</char> to live <char style="add">forever</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 21:7"/>I will give this to every person who is victorious over <char style="add">the evil powers</char> (OR, <char style="add">over Satan</char>). I will be their God, and they will be my children. <verse eid="REV 21:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 21:8"/>But those who are cowardly, those who do not believe <char style="add">in me</char>, those <char style="add">who do</char> detestable things, those who are murderers, those who sin sexually, those who commit sorcery, those who worship idols, and every liar, will <char style="add">all suffer</char> in the lake that burns with fire and sulfur. <char style="add">Anyone who suffers in that lake</char> will be dying the second time.”<verse eid="REV 21:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">One of the seven angels who had the seven bowls offered to show John the Bride of the Lamb.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 21:9">Revelation 21:9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 21:9"/>One of the seven angels who had one of the seven bowls that had been full of <char style="add">the wine/liquid causing</char> [MTY] the seven last plagues came and said to me, “Come <char style="add">with me</char> and I will show you <char style="add">the people who have permanently united with Christ, the one who is like a</char> lamb! They will be <char style="add">like</char> [MET] a bride <char style="add">for him</char>.”<verse eid="REV 21:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">An angel showed John the city of God, the New Jerusalem, that was coming down out of heaven from God, shining with his glory, having a huge wall with twelve gates and twelve huge foundation stones.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 21:10-14">Revelation 21:10-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 21:10"/>Then, while <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">controlled me</char>, the angel took/carried me to the top of a very high mountain. He showed me <char style="add">God’s</char> holy city, <char style="add">the New</char> Jerusalem. It was coming down out of heaven from God. <verse eid="REV 21:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 21:11"/>It was shining with his glory. The city was shining like a very precious jasper stone <char style="add">shines, and</char> it was clear like crystal. <verse eid="REV 21:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 21:12"/><char style="add">Around the city</char> was a very high wall. The wall had twelve gates. An angel was at each gate. The names of the twelve tribes of Israel were written {<char style="add">God</char> had written the names of the twelve tribes of Israel} over the gates. <char style="add">Each gate had the name of one tribe</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 21:13"/>Three gates were on the east <char style="add">side</char>, three gates were on the north <char style="add">side</char>, three gates were on the south <char style="add">side</char>, and three gates were on the west <char style="add">side</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 21:14"/>The wall of the city had twelve foundation <char style="add">stones</char>. On each foundation <char style="add">stone was</char> the name of one of the twelve apostles of <char style="add">Jesus, the one who is like a</char> lamb.<verse eid="REV 21:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The angel guide measured the city and its wall.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 21:15-17">Revelation 21:15-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 21:15"/>The angel who was speaking to me carried a golden measuring rod, in order to measure the city, its gates, and its wall. <verse eid="REV 21:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 21:16"/>The city was square <char style="add">in shape</char>; it was as long as it was wide. After the angel measured the city with his rod, <char style="add">he reported that it was</char> ◄1,500 miles/2,400 kilometers► long, and that its height was the same as <char style="add">its length and width</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 21:17"/>He measured its wall <char style="add">and reported that it was</char> ◄<char style="add">216 ft./70 meters</char>► <char style="add">thick</char> (OR, <char style="add">high</char>). The angel used the measure that people <char style="add">normally use</char>.<verse eid="REV 21:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John described the composition of the city, its wall, its foundations, its gates, and its street, emphasizing the great value of each part.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 21:18-27">Revelation 21:18-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 21:18"/>The <char style="add">city</char> wall was made of <char style="add">something like the green stone that we call</char> jasper. The city <char style="add">itself</char> was <char style="add">made of something like</char> pure gold <char style="add">that looked</char> like clear glass. <verse eid="REV 21:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 21:19"/>The foundations of the wall of the city were beautifully made with <char style="add">wonderful stones that are like</char> precious stones <char style="add">on earth</char>. The first foundation <char style="add">stone was a crystalline stone like</char> jasper, the second <char style="add">foundation stone was a blue stone like</char> sapphire, the third <char style="add">foundation stone was a green stone like</char> agate, the fourth <char style="add">foundation stone was a green stone like</char> emerald, <verse eid="REV 21:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 21:20"/>the fifth <char style="add">foundation stone was a brown and white layered stone like</char> sardonyx, the sixth <char style="add">foundation stone was a red stone like</char> carnelian, the seventh <char style="add">foundation stone was a yellow stone like</char> chrysolite, the eighth <char style="add">foundation stone was a green stone like</char> beryl, the ninth <char style="add">foundation stone was a yellow stone like</char> topaz, the tenth <char style="add">foundation stone was a green stone like</char> chrysoprase, the eleventh <char style="add">foundation stone was a blue stone like</char> hyacinth, and the twelfth <char style="add">foundation stone was a purple stone like</char> amethyst. <verse eid="REV 21:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 21:21"/>The twelve gates <char style="add">of the city</char> were <char style="add">something like huge</char> pearls. Each gate was like <char style="add">it was</char> a single pearl. The <char style="add">ground of</char> the main plaza of the city (OR, The streets of the city) <char style="add">appeared to be</char> pure gold <char style="add">that looked</char> like clear glass.<verse eid="REV 21:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="REV 21:22"/>There was no temple in the city. The Lord God Almighty <char style="add">himself</char>, and the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb, are <char style="add">there, so there was no need for</char> [MET] a temple. <verse eid="REV 21:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="REV 21:23"/>The city will not need the sun or the moon to light the city, because the glory of God will illuminate the city, and <char style="add">Jesus, the one who is like a</char> lamb, will also be its light. <verse eid="REV 21:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="REV 21:24"/>The people of [MTY] the nations will live with the light of the city <char style="add">shining upon them</char>. And the kings of the earth will bring their wealth into the city <char style="add">to honor God and the one who is like a lamb</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="REV 21:25"/>The gates of the city will not be shut {No one will shut the gates of the city} <char style="add">at the end of each day as they usually are shut</char>, because there will be no night there. <verse eid="REV 21:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="REV 21:26"/>The <char style="add">people of the</char> world will also bring their wealth into the city to honor <char style="add">God and the one who is like a lamb</char>. <verse eid="REV 21:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="REV 21:27"/>No one who is morally impure, no one who does things <char style="add">that God considers</char> detestable, and no one who tells lies, will ever enter that city. Only those people whose names are written in the book of the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb {whose <char style="add">names</char> the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb has written in his book}, <char style="add">the names</char> of people who have <char style="add">eternal</char> life, will be there.<verse eid="REV 21:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 21"/>
  <chapter number="22" style="c" sid="REV 22"/>
  <para style="s1">God will cause there to be abundant life in the city, his servants will worship him face-to-face, no one will be there whom God would curse, and his servants will reign forever and ever.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:1-5">Revelation 22:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="REV 22:1"/>The angel showed me the river of water <char style="add">that causes people who drink from it</char> to live <char style="add">forever</char>. The water was sparkling and clear like crystal. The river was flowing out from the throne where God and the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb <char style="add">were sitting</char>. <verse eid="REV 22:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="REV 22:2"/>It flowed down through the middle of the <char style="add">main</char> street of the city. On each side of the river were trees <char style="add">bearing fruit that causes people who eat it</char> to live forever. <char style="add">The trees</char> bear twelve <char style="add">crops</char> (OR, twelve <char style="add">kinds</char>) of fruit; <char style="add">they</char> produce one crop each month. The <char style="add">people of the</char> nations [MTY] <char style="add">use</char> the leaves of these trees <char style="add">as medicine</char> in order that they may feel stronger <verse eid="REV 22:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="REV 22:3"/>There will never be <char style="add">anyone or anything there that God</char> will be <char style="add">under God’s</char> curse. The throne of God and the <char style="add">one who is like a</char> lamb will be in the city. And God’s servants will worship him there. <verse eid="REV 22:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="REV 22:4"/>They will see him face-to-face, and his name will be <char style="add">written</char> {<char style="add">he</char> will <char style="add">write</char> his name} on their foreheads. <verse eid="REV 22:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="REV 22:5"/>There will never again be night. <char style="add">God’s servants</char> will not need the light of a lamp or the light of the sun, because the Lord God will shine his light upon them. And they will rule forever.<verse eid="REV 22:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God revealed to his servants his message in which he showed them what must happen soon.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:6-7">Revelation 22:6-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="REV 22:6"/>The angel said to me: “These words that <char style="add">God has revealed to you</char> are true, and he will certainly do what he has promised to do. The Lord God who ◄<char style="add">inspires</char> the prophets/tells the prophets what to say► sent his angel to show the people who serve him the events that must happen soon.” <verse eid="REV 22:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="REV 22:7"/><char style="add">Jesus says to all his people</char>, “Listen <char style="add">to</char> this! I am coming soon; <char style="add">God will abundantly</char> bless everyone who obeys what <char style="add">has been commanded</char> in this book.”<verse eid="REV 22:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John attested that he himself has heard and seen all these things. He was told to tell others what has been revealed to him because its fulfillment was near, and everyone should be ready.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:8-11">Revelation 22:8-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="REV 22:8"/>I, John, am the one who heard and saw <char style="add">in a vision</char> these things <char style="add">that I have written down</char>. When I had heard and seen <char style="add">them</char>, I immediately knelt down at the feet of the angel who was showing them to me, in order to worship him. <verse eid="REV 22:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="REV 22:9"/>But he said to me, “Do not <char style="add">worship me</char> I am <char style="add">just</char> your fellow servant! I am also the fellow servant of your fellow believers who are ◄the prophets/the ones who tell messages that come directly from God►, and I am a fellow servant of those who obey what has been commanded in this book. <char style="add">Instead</char>, worship God!” <verse eid="REV 22:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="REV 22:10"/>He also said to me, “Do not keep secret the message about what <char style="add">God</char> has foretold in this book, because it is almost time [MTY] for him to <char style="add">what he has promised to do in this message</char>. <verse eid="REV 22:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="REV 22:11"/><char style="add">Since that time is near, if</char> those who act in an evil manner <char style="add">want to</char> continue to act that way [IRO], <char style="add">that is up to them. God will soon</char> ◄<char style="add">pay them back/punish them</char>► <char style="add">for that. If</char> those who are vile <char style="add">want to</char> continue to be vile [IRO], <char style="add">that is up to them. God will soon</char> ◄<char style="add">pay them back/punish them</char>► <char style="add">for that</char>. Those who are <char style="add">acting</char> righteously should continue to act righteously. And those who are holy should continue to be holy.”<verse eid="REV 22:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus announced that he had sent his angel to bear witness to the congregations about all that John had seen. Jesus authoritatively identified himself as the Descendant of King David and as the Messianic Morning Star.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:12-16">Revelation 22:12-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="REV 22:12"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus says this to everyone</char>: “Listen! I am coming soon! And I will pay back everyone according to what each one has done, by <char style="add">punishing or</char> rewarding them. <verse eid="REV 22:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="REV 22:13"/>I <char style="add">am</char> the one who began all things [MET] and the one who will cause all things to end [MET]. I existed before <char style="add">all things existed</char> and I will exist at the end <char style="add">of all things</char> [DOU]. <verse eid="REV 22:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="REV 22:14"/><char style="add">God</char> is very pleased with the people who wash their robes, <char style="add">making themselves spiritually clean</char> [MET], because they will be able to <char style="add">eat the fruit of</char> [MTY] the tree <char style="add">that enables people</char> to live <char style="add">forever</char>, and because they will <char style="add">be able</char> to enter the gates into the <char style="add">holy</char> city. <verse eid="REV 22:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="REV 22:15"/><char style="add">People who are unholy</char> will not be allowed to enter the city. They include people who practice sorcery, people who sin sexually, murderers, idol worshipers, and everyone who enjoys telling lies and are continual liars. <char style="add">They can never enter that city</char>.”<verse eid="REV 22:15"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="REV 22:16"/>“I, Jesus, sent my angel in order that he might tell you who are in the congregations <char style="add">that all</char> these things <char style="add">that have been said are true</char>. I am the descendant of <char style="add">King</char> David <char style="add">whom the prophets promised would come</char> [MET]. I am the <char style="add">one who is like</char> the bright morning star [MET], the one <char style="add">that Moses promised would come</char>.”<verse eid="REV 22:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Spirit and the Bride invite all who desire to drink the living water to come and drink, and they invite all who hear that invitation to extend it to others.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:17">Revelation 22:17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="REV 22:17"/>
    <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit and <char style="add">his people, who are like</char> [MET] the bride <char style="add">of Christ</char>, say <char style="add">to each one who desires to believe</char>, “Come!” Whoever hears <char style="add">this</char> should also say <char style="add">to each one who desires to believe</char>, “Come!” <char style="add">Spiritually thirsty people should come</char> [MET]! Everyone who desires the water <char style="add">that enables people to</char> live <char style="add">forever</char> should take it as a free gift!<verse eid="REV 22:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus warned about what would happen to anyone who adds to the message of this book or who takes away any part of its revelation.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:18-19">Revelation 22:18-19</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="REV 22:18"/>“I, <char style="add">Jesus, solemnly</char> warn everyone who hears what <char style="add">I</char> have foretold in this book: If anyone adds anything to this message, God will cause him to experience the plagues that are {that <char style="add">I</char> have} described in this book. <verse eid="REV 22:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="REV 22:19"/>If anyone omits any of the message about what <char style="add">I</char> have foretold in this book, God will take away that person’s right <char style="add">to eat fruit from</char> [MTY] the tree <char style="add">that enables people</char> to live <char style="add">forever</char>. He <char style="add">will also take away</char> that person’s right <char style="add">to enter</char> God’s city. <char style="add">Both these things</char> are described {<char style="add">I</char> have described <char style="add">both these things</char>} in this book.”<verse eid="REV 22:19"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Jesus declares that he is certainly coming soon.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:20">Revelation 22:20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="REV 22:20"/>
    <char style="add">Jesus</char>, who says that <char style="add">all</char> the things written here are true, says, “Certainly I am coming soon!” <char style="add">I, John, reply</char>, “◄May it be so!/Amen!► Lord Jesus, come!”<verse eid="REV 22:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">John closes with a prayer that Jesus will continue to bless all God’s people.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="REV 22:21">Revelation 22:21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="REV 22:21"/>
    <char style="add">I pray that our</char> Lord Jesus <char style="add">will continue to</char> act kindly to all <char style="add">of you who are God’s people</char>. ◄Amen!/May it be so!►<verse eid="REV 22:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="REV 22"/>
</usx>
