<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.0">
  <book code="ROM" style="id">- Translation 4 Translators 1</book>
  <para style="ide">65001 - Unicode (UTF-8)</para>
  <para style="h">ROMANS</para>
  <para style="toc1">Romans</para>
  <para style="toc2">Romans</para>
  <para style="toc3">Rom</para>
  <para style="mt2">This book is a letter that the Apostle Paul wrote to the Christians at Rome. We call this book</para>
  <para style="mt1">Romans</para>
  <chapter number="1" style="c" sid="ROM 1"/>
  <para style="s1">Romans 1:1-7</para>
  <para style="s1">I, Paul, an apostle whom God appointed to proclaim the good message about Jesus Christ, am writing this letter to all you believers who are in Rome. I pray that God will continue to act kindly toward you and grant you peace.</para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 1:1"/>
    <char style="add">I</char>, Paul, who serve Christ Jesus, <char style="add">am writing this letter</char>. God chose me to be an apostle, and I was appointed by him {he appointed me} in order that <char style="add">I should proclaim</char> ◄the good message/the gospel► that <char style="add">comes from him</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 1:2"/>Long before <char style="add">Jesus came to earth, God</char> promised <char style="add">that he would reveal</char> this good message by means of what his prophets <char style="add">wrote</char> in the sacred Scriptures. <verse eid="ROM 1:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 1:3"/>This good message is <char style="add">about the one whom we know as</char> his Son. As to his Son’s physical/human nature, he was born a descendant of <char style="add">King</char> David. <verse eid="ROM 1:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 1:4"/>As to his divine nature, it was shown {<char style="add">God</char> showed} powerfully that he is ◄God’s own Son/the man who is also God►. <char style="add">God</char> showed this by his Holy Spirit causing him to become alive again after he died. He is Jesus Christ our Lord. <verse eid="ROM 1:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 1:5"/>He is the one who appointed me, who did not deserve it, <char style="add">to be</char> an apostle. He did that in order that <char style="add">many</char> among the non-Jews would honor <char style="add">him</char> and would obey him as a result of their believing <char style="add">my message about him</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 1:6"/>You <char style="add">believers</char> who are living in Rome <char style="add">city</char> are included among those whom God has chosen to belong to Jesus Christ. <verse eid="ROM 1:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 1:7"/><char style="add">I am writing this letter</char> to all of <char style="add">you in Rome</char> whom God loves and whom he has chosen <char style="add">to become his</char> people. <char style="add">I pray that</char> God our Father and Jesus Christ our Lord will <char style="add">continue to</char> act kindly toward you and <char style="add">will continue to</char> cause you to have <char style="add">inner</char> peace.<verse eid="ROM 1:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I thank God that people everywhere are talking about how you believers in Rome are trusting Jesus Christ. I pray that God will permit me to visit you soon. I want you to know that I have longed to visit you, but things have always prevented me from doing that. I am eager to proclaim the gospel to you who are living at Rome also.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 1:8-15">Romans 1:8-15</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 1:8"/>As I begin <char style="add">this letter</char>, I thank my God for all you <char style="add">believers in Rome</char>. It is because of <char style="add">what</char> Jesus Christ <char style="add">has done for us that</char> I <char style="add">am able to do that</char>. I thank him because your trusting <char style="add">in Jesus Christ</char> is something that people all over <char style="add">the Roman Empire</char> [HYP] are talking about. <verse eid="ROM 1:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 1:9"/>God, whom I devotedly serve as I <char style="add">proclaim to people</char> the gospel concerning his Son, knows that I tell the truth when I say that I always mention you whenever [DOU] I pray <char style="add">to God</char> [HYP]. <verse eid="ROM 1:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 1:10"/>I especially ask God that if he desires <char style="add">me to visit you</char>, somehow at last I shall be able to do so. <verse eid="ROM 1:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 1:11"/><char style="add">I pray this</char> because I long to visit you to help you spiritually, in order that you will become stronger <char style="add">spiritually</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 1:12"/>I long to visit you in order that you and I might encourage each other <char style="add">by means of our sharing with each other</char> how each of us trusts <char style="add">in Jesus</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 1:13"/>My fellow believers, many times I planned to visit you. I certainly want you to know [LIT] that. <char style="add">But I have not been able to come to you because</char> I have been hindered {<char style="add">things</char> have always prevented me} until the present time. I have wanted to come in order that I might help you to mature spiritually [IDM], as <char style="add">I have helped people to mature spiritually</char> in many other non-Jewish groups [HYP]. <verse eid="ROM 1:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 1:14"/>I feel obliged <char style="add">to proclaim the gospel to all non-Jewish people</char>, specifically to <char style="add">people who know</char> the Greek <char style="add">language and culture</char> and to those who do not know it, to people who are educated and to those who are uneducated. <verse eid="ROM 1:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 1:15"/>So what I have eagerly desired is that I might proclaim this good message to you who are living in Rome also.<verse eid="ROM 1:15"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I very confidently proclaim the good message about what Christ has done, both to Jews and non-Jews, because by that message God reveals his way of declaring all people righteous.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 1:16-17">Romans 1:16-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 1:16"/>
    <char style="add">That leads me to say that</char> I very confidently proclaim [LIT] the good message <char style="add">about what Christ has done</char>, because this good message is the powerful <char style="add">means</char> that God <char style="add">uses</char> to save <char style="add">from the guilt of their sins</char> all people who trust <char style="add">in what Christ has done for them</char>. Specifically, God first has saved the Jews <char style="add">who believe the good message</char>, and then he has saved non-Jews. <verse eid="ROM 1:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 1:17"/>By means of this good message God reveals how he erases the record of people’s sins (OR, declares people no longer guilty for having sinned); and his doing this is entirely because [IDM] they trust <char style="add">in Christ. This is confirmed</char> by what <char style="add">a prophet long ago</char> wrote <char style="add">that God said</char>, “Those ◄whose record of sin <char style="add">I</char> have erased/whom <char style="add">I</char> have declared no longer guilty for sin► because they trust <char style="add">in me</char> will live <char style="add">forever</char>.”<verse eid="ROM 1:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God is making it clear to all non-Jewish people who are godless and wicked that he is angry with them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 1:18">Romans 1:18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 1:18"/>From <char style="add">where God rules in</char> heaven he is making it clear to all <char style="add">non-Jewish</char> people who show no respect for God and who do wicked things, that he is angry with them <char style="add">and that they deserve to be punished</char> {<char style="add">that he would punish them</char>} [MTY]. By means of <char style="add">their behaving</char> wickedly, they keep other people <char style="add">from believing what they know</char> to be true <char style="add">about God</char>.<verse eid="ROM 1:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Everyone can clearly know what God is like; so no one has a basis for saying, “We never knew about God.”</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 1:19-23">Romans 1:19-23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 1:19"/>
    <char style="add">Everyone</char> can clearly know what God <char style="add">is like</char>, because God himself has revealed to everyone <char style="add">what he is like</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 1:20"/><char style="add">People</char> cannot see what God is like. But ever since he created the world, by means of what he created he has clearly revealed what he is like. He has made clear to everyone that he has always been able to do very powerful things. <char style="add">Therefore, we should recognize that</char> God is powerful, <char style="add">completely different from all that he created</char>. So no one has a basis for saying, <char style="add">“We never knew about God</char>.” <verse eid="ROM 1:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 1:21"/>Although <char style="add">the non-Jews</char> knew what God <char style="add">is like</char>, they did not honor him as God, nor did they thank <char style="add">him for what he had done</char>. But instead, they began to think foolish <char style="add">things about him</char>, and they became unable to understand [MET] <char style="add">what he wanted them to know</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 1:22"/>Although they claimed that they were wise, they became foolish, <verse eid="ROM 1:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 1:23"/>and they refused to <char style="add">admit that</char> God is glorious and will never die. Instead, they made and worshipped idols <char style="add">that resembled people who</char> will some day die, and <char style="add">then they made other idols that resembled</char> birds and four-footed animals, and <char style="add">finally</char> they made idols that resembled reptiles.<verse eid="ROM 1:23"/></para>
  <para style="s1">So God let the non-Jewish people feel compelled to do disgraceful things, which resulted in their dishonoring their bodies sexually. He did this because they worshipped idols and things that were created instead of worshipping God. As a result of both men and women having unnatural sexual relations, they have been punished as they deserve.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 1:24-27">Romans 1:24-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 1:24"/>So God allowed <char style="add">the non-Jews</char> do immoral sexual things that they [SYN] strongly desired, things <char style="add">that their desires were compelling them to do</char>. As a result, they <char style="add">began to</char> dishonor each other’s bodies <char style="add">by their sexual actions</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 1:25"/>Also, they <char style="add">chose to worship</char> false <char style="add">gods</char> instead ◄of admitting/of choosing to believe► what is true <char style="add">about</char> God. They worshipped and served things <char style="add">that God</char> created instead of <char style="add">worshipping and serving God himself</char>, the one who created <char style="add">everything. They did this even though</char> he <char style="add">deserves that those he created</char> would forever praise him. Amen!/May it be so!<verse eid="ROM 1:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 1:26"/>So, God allowed <char style="add">the non-Jews to do</char> shameful <char style="add">sexual</char> things that they <char style="add">strongly</char> desired. As a result, many women did not have natural sexual relations <char style="add">with their husbands</char> [EUP]. Instead, they were doing sexual actions with other women [EUP]. <verse eid="ROM 1:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 1:27"/>Similarly, <char style="add">many</char> men stopped having/did not have natural sexual relations with women [EUP]. Instead, they strongly desired to have sexual relations with other men. They committed <char style="add">homosexual</char> acts with other men, acts that were shameful. As a result, <char style="add">God has</char> punished them <char style="add">by sicknesses</char> in their bodies, which is what they deserve <char style="add">because</char> they <char style="add">thought</char> wrongly <char style="add">that God would not punish them for doing that</char>.<verse eid="ROM 1:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The result of God’s letting people become obsessed by their own depraved thoughts was that they themselves began to do all manner of evil things that God says are improper. They even approve of others doing such things.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 1:28-32">Romans 1:28-32</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 1:28"/>Furthermore, because they decided that it was not <char style="add">worthwhile</char> to know God, he allowed their own worthless thoughts <char style="add">to completely control them</char>. As a result, they began doing <char style="add">evil</char> things that <char style="add">God says that people</char> should not do. <verse eid="ROM 1:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 1:29"/>They strongly desire to do all <char style="add">kinds of</char> unrighteous <char style="add">things</char>. They strongly desire to do all <char style="add">kinds of</char> evil things <char style="add">to others</char>. They strongly desire to possess things that <char style="add">belong to others</char>. They strongly desire to harm <char style="add">others</char> in various ways. <char style="add">Many non-Jews</char> are constantly envying <char style="add">other people. Many</char> constantly desire to murder <char style="add">people. Many</char> constantly desire to cause strife <char style="add">between people. Many</char> constantly desire to deceive <char style="add">others. Many</char> constantly desire to speak hatefully <char style="add">about others</char> (OR, <char style="add">to speak harmful things about others, things that are not true</char>). <char style="add">Many</char> gossip <char style="add">about others</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 1:30"/><char style="add">Many</char> slander <char style="add">others. Many</char> act especially hatefully toward God. <char style="add">Many</char> speak or act in an insulting way <char style="add">toward others. Many</char> treat others contemptuously. <char style="add">Many</char> boast <char style="add">about themselves to others. Many</char> invent new ways to do evil things. <char style="add">Many non-Jewish children</char> disobey their parents. <verse eid="ROM 1:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 1:31"/><char style="add">Many non-Jews</char> act in other morally foolish ways. <char style="add">Many</char> do not do what they promised <char style="add">others that they would do. Many</char> do not <char style="add">even</char> love <char style="add">their own family members. And many</char> do not act mercifully <char style="add">toward other people</char>. <verse eid="ROM 1:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 1:32"/>Although they know that God has declared that those who do such things deserve to be killed, they not only habitually do these <char style="add">kinds of evil</char> things, but they also approve of others who habitually do them.<verse eid="ROM 1:32"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 1"/>
  <chapter number="2" style="c" sid="ROM 2"/>
  <para style="s1">Any one of you Jews who condemns non-Jews for doing evil will be condemned by God, because you also do the same evil things.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 2:1-5">Romans 2:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 2:1"/>
    <char style="add">God will severely punish non-Jewish people who habitually do evil things, because he has clearly revealed that he is angry with them</char>. So, <char style="add">when God judges people</char>, he will not excuse any one of you Jews <char style="add">to whom I am writing</char>. You <char style="add">(sg)</char> say that <char style="add">God should</char> punish <char style="add">non-Jews for doing evil things</char>. But when any one of you says that, it is you yourself whom you are saying that God should punish, because you <char style="add">(sg)</char> do <char style="add">some of</char> the same <char style="add">evil</char> things <char style="add">that the non-Jews do</char>. <verse eid="ROM 2:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 2:2"/>We know very well that God will judge and punish fairly <char style="add">non-Jewish</char> people who do such <char style="add">evil</char> things. <verse eid="ROM 2:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 2:3"/>So, you who <char style="add">say God should punish</char> others for doing evil things yet you do evil things yourself, ◄you should certainly not think that you yourself will be able to escape from being punished by God!/do you think that you yourself will be able to escape from being punished by God?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 2:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 2:4"/>And you should not say, “God is acting very tolerantly and patiently toward me, <char style="add">so I do not need to stop sinning</char> [DOU].” ◄You should realize that God is acting in a kind manner <char style="add">toward you</char> in order to encourage you <char style="add">(sg)</char> to turn away from your sinful behavior!/Do you not realize that God is acting in a kind manner <char style="add">toward you</char> in order to encourage you <char style="add">(sg)</char> to turn away from your sinful behavior?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 2:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 2:5"/>But instead, by your stubbornly refusing to turn away from your sinful behavior [DOU], you are causing [MET] God to punish you even more severely. <char style="add">He will do that</char> at the time when he shows that he is angry and judges people fairly.<verse eid="ROM 2:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because God is not influenced by a person’s status, he will pay back each person according to what that person has done.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 2:6-11">Romans 2:6-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 2:6"/>God will pay back everyone according to <char style="add">what they deserve for</char> what they have done. <verse eid="ROM 2:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 2:7"/><char style="add">Specifically</char>, some people, by continuing to doing good things, strive to be highly honored <char style="add">by God</char> [DOU] and to receive a life that will not end. <char style="add">God will reward them by enabling them</char> to live forever. <verse eid="ROM 2:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 2:8"/>But some people act in a selfish way and refuse to believe that <char style="add">what God says is</char> true, and they do the things that <char style="add">God says</char> are wrong. <char style="add">God will</char> punish them very severely [DOU, MTY]. <verse eid="ROM 2:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 2:9"/>He will cause everyone who habitually does evil deeds to suffer greatly, <char style="add">with the result that they will become severely</char> distressed [DOU]. This certainly will happen to the Jews <char style="add">who refuse to accept God’s message, because God gave them the privilege to be his special people</char>, but it will also happen to the non-Jews. <verse eid="ROM 2:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 2:10"/>But <char style="add">God will</char> greatly reward spiritually [MET, DOU] every person who habitually does good deeds. He will <char style="add">certainly</char> do this for the Jews <char style="add">because God chose them as his special people</char>, but he will also do it for the non-Jews. <verse eid="ROM 2:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 2:11"/>God <char style="add">will do this fairly</char>, because people’s status does not influence him.<verse eid="ROM 2:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">All non-Jews and all non-Jews will be eternally separated from God for their sin, since it is only those who have continually obeyed his laws whom God will justify.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 2:12-16">Romans 2:12-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 2:12"/>Although <char style="add">non-Jews do not have</char> the laws that <char style="add">God gave to Moses</char>, all <char style="add">non-Jews</char> who sin will be eternally separated from God. He will <char style="add">not consider whether or not they knew</char> the laws that he <char style="add">gave to Moses</char>. And all the <char style="add">Jews</char> who have sinned in spite of knowing the laws that <char style="add">God gave to Moses will also be punished</char> {<char style="add">God will also punish them</char>}. <char style="add">They will be punished for disobeying</char> God’s laws. <verse eid="ROM 2:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 2:13"/><char style="add">It is right for them to be punished</char> {<char style="add">God to punish them</char>} <char style="add">because</char> it is not those who <char style="add">merely</char> know God’s laws whom he considers to be righteous. On the contrary, it is only those who continually have obeyed <char style="add">all</char> ◄of <char style="add">God’s</char> laws/of the laws that <char style="add">God gave to Moses</char>► ◄whom God will consider righteous/whose record of sins God will erase►. <verse eid="ROM 2:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 2:14"/>Whenever the non-Jews, who do not have the laws <char style="add">God gave to Moses</char>, naturally obey those laws, <char style="add">they prove that</char> they have a law within their own minds, even though they do not have the laws <char style="add">God gave to Moses</char>. <verse eid="ROM 2:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 2:15"/>They show that they know in their own minds what God <char style="add">commands in his</char> laws [MET], as each person in his very own conscience either accuses or excuses/defends himself <char style="add">concerning his own behavior</char>. <verse eid="ROM 2:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 2:16"/>God <char style="add">will punish people</char> at the time when he will judge them according to what they have thought and done. He will judge them <char style="add">even</char> for the things that they have done secretly. He will judge people by <char style="add">authorizing</char> Christ Jesus <char style="add">to judge them</char>. This is <char style="add">what I tell people when</char> I preach the gospel to them.<verse eid="ROM 2:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It is disgusting that any one of you who has all the advantages of being a Jew would disobey God’s law and, by doing so, insult God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 2:17-24">Romans 2:17-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 2:17"/>
    <char style="add">Now I have something to say to any one of</char> you <char style="add">Jews to whom I am writing</char>: You <char style="add">(sg)</char> boast about yourself saying, “I am a Jew.” You <char style="add">(sg)</char> trust <char style="add">that God will save you because you possess</char> the laws <char style="add">that he gave to Moses</char>. You boast that <char style="add">you belong to</char> God. <verse eid="ROM 2:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 2:18"/>You know what God desires. Because you have been taught {<char style="add">people</char> have taught you} <char style="add">God’s</char> laws, you are able to know which things are right and to choose to do them. <verse eid="ROM 2:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 2:19"/>You are certain that you <char style="add">are able to</char> show <char style="add">God’s truth to non-Jews</char>, as guides <char style="add">show the road</char> to those who are blind [MET]. You are certain that by what you say you can show God’s way to the <char style="add">non-Jews who do not understand it</char>, as a light shows the way to <char style="add">those who walk in</char> the darkness [MET, DOU]. <verse eid="ROM 2:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 2:20"/><char style="add">You are certain that you</char> can instruct/correct <char style="add">non-Jews, whom you consider</char> foolish <char style="add">because of their not understanding God’s message</char>. Because you have in <char style="add">God’s</char> laws a <char style="add">written</char> expression of true knowledge [HEN], you are certain that you can teach <char style="add">people who, being like</char> children, do not know <char style="add">God’s truth</char> [MET]. <verse eid="ROM 2:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 2:21"/><char style="add">Since you claim that you have all these advantages because you are a Jew</char>, ◄it is disgusting that you who teach other people <char style="add">that they should obey the laws God gave Moses</char> do not <char style="add">obey the laws that you</char> yourself teach!/why is it that you who teach other people <char style="add">that they should obey the laws God gave Moses</char> do not <char style="add">obey the laws that you</char> yourself teach?► [RHQ] You who preach that people should not steal things, it is disgusting that you yourself steal things! [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 2:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 2:22"/>You who command people not to have sexual relations with someone to whom they are not married, it is disgusting that you commit adultery yourself! [RHQ] You who detest idols, it is disgusting that you rob temples <char style="add">where people worship idols</char>! [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 2:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 2:23"/>You who boast saying, “<char style="add">I have God’s</char> laws,” it is disgusting that you disobey those same laws! [RHQ] As a result you are insulting God! <verse eid="ROM 2:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 2:24"/><char style="add">You must not be like our ancestors, about whom</char> were written <char style="add">these words in the Scriptures:</char> “The non-Jews speak evil about God because of <char style="add">the evil actions of</char> many of you <char style="add">Jews</char>.” The non-Jews say God must be a hypocrite if he condones the behavior of people like you.<verse eid="ROM 2:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God will consider non-Jews acceptable to him if they obey his laws, and such non-Jews will declare God is right in condemning those who disobey his laws, because it is only those who are changed inwardly who are true Jews and acceptable to God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 2:25-29">Romans 2:25-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 2:25"/>Any one of you who <char style="add">is</char> circumcised <char style="add">to show that he belongs to God</char> can benefit from that if he obeys the laws <char style="add">God gave to Moses</char>. But if you <char style="add">(sg), a circumcised person</char>, disobey <char style="add">God’s</char> laws, <char style="add">God will consider that</char> you who are circumcised are no better <char style="add">in God’s sight</char> than <char style="add">someone who is</char> not circumcised. <verse eid="ROM 2:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 2:26"/>This means that God will certainly consider that even <char style="add">non-Jews who are</char> not circumcised can become his people if they obey the things that he commanded in his laws. [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 2:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 2:27"/><char style="add">If any one of</char> you disobeys God’s laws, even though <char style="add">you(sg) have</char> the Scriptures and even though someone has circumcised you {you are circumcised} <char style="add">God will punish you</char>. And those people who are not circumcised, but who obey God’s laws, <char style="add">will declare that God is right</char> when he says that he will punish you. <verse eid="ROM 2:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 2:28"/>It is not those who perform rituals <char style="add">to show they are God’s people</char> who are <char style="add">true</char> Jews, and it is not being circumcised in their bodies <char style="add">that causes God to accept them</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="ROM 2:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 2:29"/>On the contrary, we whom <char style="add">God has changed</char> inwardly are <char style="add">true</char> Jews [MTY]. And <char style="add">God has accepted us because we have allowed God’s</char> Spirit to change our hearts, not because we perform rituals. Even if <char style="add">other</char> people will not praise us <char style="add">for that change</char>, God will praise us.<verse eid="ROM 2:29"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 2"/>
  <chapter number="3" style="c" sid="ROM 3"/>
  <para style="s1">My reply to the objection that there is no advantage in being a Jew or being circumcised is that there is much advantage, especially since God entrusted his promises to us. My reply to the objection that God has not kept his promise is that he certainly has, for his promises are always true. My reply to the objection that it is not right for God to punish us Jews is that it certainly is right for him to punish us, because if God did not judge us Jews he could not judge anyone.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 3:1-8">Romans 3:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 3:1"/>
    <char style="add">Someone may object to this, saying</char>, “<char style="add">If being circumcised does not cause God to accept us Jews</char>, ◄there is no advantage in being a Jew <char style="add">over being a non-Jew</char>./is there any advantage in being a Jew <char style="add">over being a non-Jew</char>?► [RHQ] Being circumcised does not benefit <char style="add">us Jews at all</char>!” <verse eid="ROM 3:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 3:2"/><char style="add">I would reply that being Jews</char> benefits <char style="add">us</char> in many ways [HYP]. First of all, it benefits us because it was to <char style="add">our ancestors</char> that God’s words, <char style="add">words that contain his promises</char>, were given {that <char style="add">God</char> gave his words, <char style="add">words that contain his promises</char>}. <verse eid="ROM 3:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 3:3"/>Many <char style="add">Jews did not obey God as they promised that they would. So someone might ask</char>, “Does their not being faithful mean that God will not <char style="add">bless us Jews</char> as he promised <char style="add">that he would</char>?” <verse eid="ROM 3:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 3:4"/><char style="add">I would reply</char>, “No, it certainly does not mean that! God always does <char style="add">what he has promised</char>, even though <char style="add">people do not</char>. All those who accuse God <char style="add">of not keeping his promises to us Jews</char> are very mistaken.” <char style="add">What King David wrote about God’s justly saying that he would punish him for his sins is also true of those who accuse God of not keeping his promises. What he said to God was</char>, “So everyone must acknowledge that what you <char style="add">(sg)</char> have said <char style="add">about them</char> (OR, <char style="add">their sin</char>) is true, and you will always win the case when you are accused {when <char style="add">people</char> accuse you}.”<verse eid="ROM 3:4"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 3:5"/>So if we <char style="add">Jews’</char> being wicked [PRS] shows that it is right that God <char style="add">does not bless us</char>, what shall we say/conclude? Shall we conclude that it is not right for God to be angry <char style="add">and punish us Jews</char> [MTY]? I <char style="add">should not be saying these things</char>, <char style="add">but</char> I am speaking as ordinary humans <char style="add">speak</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 3:6"/>We should certainly not <char style="add">conclude that God should not judge us</char>, because if God <char style="add">did not judge us Jews</char>, ◄it would not possibly be right for him to judge <char style="add">anyone in</char> the world [MTY]!/how could he judge <char style="add">anyone in</char> the world?► [MTY, RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 3:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 3:7"/>But <char style="add">someone might object and say to me</char>, “The fact that God truly <char style="add">keeps his promises</char> becomes very clear/evident because of my not doing <char style="add">what God has commanded</char>. But the result is that people praise God! So ◄God should no longer say that I should be punished {that <char style="add">he</char> should punish me} on account of my having sinned!/why should God still say that I should be punished {that <char style="add">he</char> should punish me} on account of my having sinned?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 3:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 3:8"/><char style="add">If what you, Paul, say is true</char>, then ◄we might as well/it is all right for us to► do evil things in order that good things <char style="add">like that</char> will result! For example, <char style="add">then people will praise God</char>!” Some people speak evil about me by their <char style="add">falsely</char> saying that I say <char style="add">such things. God</char> will fairly/justly punish <char style="add">people who say such things about me</char>!<verse eid="ROM 3:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">My reply to a query about whether God will treat Jews more favorably than non-Jews is no, because the Scriptures make clear that all people are condemned by God for their sin.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 3:9-18">Romans 3:9-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 3:9"/>
    <char style="add">If someone would ask</char>, “<char style="add">Shall we conclude that God</char> will treat us <char style="add">Jews</char> more favorably <char style="add">and will treat</char> the non-Jews less <char style="add">favorably</char> [RHQ]?” <char style="add">I would reply that we can</char> certainly not <char style="add">conclude that</char>! I have already shown you that all people, the Jews and also the non-Jews, have sinned and <char style="add">so they deserve to be punished</char> {<char style="add">that God will punish them</char>} [PRS]. <verse eid="ROM 3:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 3:10"/><char style="add">The following words</char> that are written {prophets have written} <char style="add">in the Scriptures support this</char>,</para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 3:10">No person is righteous. There is not even one righteous person! <verse eid="ROM 3:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 3:11"/>There is no one who understands <char style="add">how to live properly</char> (OR, <char style="add">about God</char>). There is no one who seeks/desires <char style="add">to know</char> God!<verse eid="ROM 3:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 3:12"/>Absolutely everyone has turned away [MET] <char style="add">from God</char>. God considers them depraved (OR, Everyone has become useless <char style="add">to God</char>). There is no one who acts righteously; no, there is not even one!<verse eid="ROM 3:12"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 3:13"/>What people say [MTY] <char style="add">is foul/bad, like the smell that comes from</char> a grave that has been {that <char style="add">people</char> have} opened [MET]. <char style="add">By what people say</char> [MTY], they deceive people.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 3:13">
    <char style="add">By what they say</char> [MTY] <char style="add">they injure people, just like</char> the poison of snakes <char style="add">injures people</char> [MET].<verse eid="ROM 3:13"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 3:14"/>They are continually ◄cursing/asking God to do harmful things to► others and saying ◄cruel/harsh/hateful► things [MTY].<verse eid="ROM 3:14"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 3:15"/>They ◄go quickly/are eager► to murder people [MTY].<verse eid="ROM 3:15"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 3:16"/>Wherever they go, they ruin everything and make <char style="add">people</char> miserable [MTY].<verse eid="ROM 3:16"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 3:17"/>They have not/never known how <char style="add">to live</char> peacefully <char style="add">with other people</char>.<verse eid="ROM 3:17"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 3:18"/>They absolutely refuse to fear/reverence God [SYN]!<verse eid="ROM 3:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">In summary, no one is able to object to God’s condemnation; everyone has been declared guilty by God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 3:19-20">Romans 3:19-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 3:19"/>Furthermore, we know that it is to <char style="add">Jewish</char> people, <char style="add">who are</char> required to obey <char style="add">God’s</char> laws, that Moses wrote those laws [PRS]. <char style="add">We can infer from this that</char> there are no <char style="add">Jews or non-Jews</char> [SYN] who are able to say anything <char style="add">in reply to God’s saying that he will punish them for having sinned</char>. God has declared everyone in the world [MTY] guilty! <verse eid="ROM 3:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 3:20"/>It is not because people have done the things that God’s laws <char style="add">require</char> that <char style="add">God</char> will ◄erase the record of their sins/declare them no longer guilty for sin►, <char style="add">because no one has done those things completely</char>. In fact, the result of <char style="add">our knowing God’s</char> laws is that we know clearly that we have sinned (OR, are sinful).<verse eid="ROM 3:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Now God erases the record of sins of everyone, Jew and non-Jew, who trusts in what Jesus Christ has done for them. God presented Christ as the one who would atone for sins by dying on the cross.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 3:21-26">Romans 3:21-26</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 3:21"/>But God’s ◄erasing the record of our sins/declaring us no longer guilty► does not depend on <char style="add">our obeying</char> the laws <char style="add">that he gave Moses</char>. It has now been {<char style="add">God</char> has now} revealed <char style="add">to us</char> how he erases the record of our sins <char style="add">by a different way</char>. It was written about <char style="add">by Moses</char> {<char style="add">Moses</char> wrote about it} in the laws [PRS] <char style="add">God gave</char> him, and it was also written about by the prophets {the prophets also wrote about it}. <verse eid="ROM 3:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 3:22"/>God erases the record of our sins because we trust in <char style="add">what</char> Jesus Christ <char style="add">has done for us</char>. God does this for every person who trusts <char style="add">in Christ</char>, because <char style="add">he considers</char> that there is no difference <char style="add">between Jews and non-Jews</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 3:23"/>All people have done evil, and all people have failed to accomplish the glorious <char style="add">goals</char> that God <char style="add">set for them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 3:24"/>Our record of sins has been erased {God erased the record of our sins} by God acting kindly <char style="add">to forgive our sins</char>, without our doing anything to earn it. Christ Jesus accomplished this <char style="add">by dying for us</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 3:25"/>God showed that Christ was the one who would atone for (OR, forgive) our sins <char style="add">with the</char> blood <char style="add">that flowed from his body when he died. God redeems/forgives</char> us because of our trusting <char style="add">in Christ’s having died for us. God wanted</char> to show that he acts justly. <char style="add">He wanted to do that</char> because, before <char style="add">Jesus came, God</char> did not punish <char style="add">everyone who sinned. So it seemed as though he was not being just</char>. But he was overlooking people’s sins during <char style="add">that time</char>, <verse eid="ROM 3:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 3:26"/>because he is patient. <char style="add">God arranged for Jesus to die for us</char>. By doing that, God now shows that he is just, and he shows that he is justly able to erase the record of sins for everyone who trusts/believes in Jesus.<verse eid="ROM 3:26"/></para>
  <para style="s1">So we are prevented from boasting that God saves us because of our obeying the Mosaic laws. And God will also accept non-Jews on the same basis. And by agreeing that people are declared righteous by their trusting in Christ, we actually confirm, not nullify, the Mosaic laws.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 3:27-31">Romans 3:27-31</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 3:27"/>It is not at all [RHQ] because of <char style="add">our obeying the</char> laws <char style="add">of Moses that God erases the record of our sins</char>. So, ◄there is no way that we can boast <char style="add">that God does that because of our obeying those laws</char>./how can we boast <char style="add">about God erasing the record of our sins because of our obeying those laws</char>?► [RHQ] Instead, <char style="add">it is because of our</char> believing/trusting <char style="add">in Christ that God erases the record of our sins</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 3:28"/><char style="add">We cannot boast about that</char>, because we conclude that the record of our sins is erased {God erases the record of our sins} because of our trusting <char style="add">in Christ</char>. God does not erase the record of our sins because of our obeying the laws <char style="add">that he gave to Moses, because it is impossible for us to completely obey them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 3:29"/>◄You who are Jews certainly should not <char style="add">think that you</char> are the only ones whom God <char style="add">will accept</char>!/Do you Jews <char style="add">think it is you</char> alone whom God <char style="add">will accept</char>?► [RHQ] You certainly should <char style="add">realize that he will accept</char> non-Jews, too. [RHQ] Of course, <char style="add">he will accept</char> non-Jews also, <verse eid="ROM 3:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 3:30"/>because, <char style="add">as you firmly believe</char>, there is only one God, who will erase the record of Jews’ [MTY] sins if they trust <char style="add">in what Christ has done</char>, and who will similarly erase the record of non-Jews’ [MTY] sins if they trust <char style="add">in Christ</char>. <verse eid="ROM 3:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 3:31"/>So, <char style="add">if someone should ask concerning the laws that God gave Moses</char>, “By saying <char style="add">that God erases the record of our sins because of our</char> trusting <char style="add">in Christ</char>, does that mean that those laws now are useless?”, <char style="add">I would reply</char>, “Certainly not. Instead, we truly fulfill the laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char>.”<verse eid="ROM 3:31"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 3"/>
  <chapter number="4" style="c" sid="ROM 4"/>
  <para style="s1">We can draw conclusions from Abraham’s life about how God erases the record of our sins. Abraham could not boast about his accomplishing that because the Scriptures record that it was because he believed what God promised that God erased the record of his sins. God’s doing that was a gift, not a reward.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 4:1-8">Romans 4:1-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 4:1"/>Abraham is the <char style="add">revered</char> ancestor of us <char style="add">Jews</char>. So think about what we can conclude <char style="add">from what happened to Abraham about how God can erase the record of our sins</char>. [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 4:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 4:2"/>If it was because of Abraham’s doing <char style="add">good</char> things that the record of his sins was erased {that <char style="add">God</char> erased the record of his sins}, Abraham could then have been able to boast <char style="add">about that to people</char>, but he would not have <char style="add">had any basis to</char> boast to God <char style="add">about it</char>. <verse eid="ROM 4:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 4:3"/><char style="add">Remember that</char> in the Scriptures it is written {someone wrote} [PRS] that Abraham believed what God <char style="add">promised</char> [RHQ], and as a result the record of his sins was erased {<char style="add">God</char> erased the record of his sins}. <verse eid="ROM 4:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 4:4"/>If we receive wages for work that we do, those wages are not considered to be a gift. Instead, they <char style="add">are considered</char> to be what we have earned. <char style="add">Similarly, if God erases the record of our sins because we did things to earn God’s favor</char>, we would not consider that <char style="add">God’s erasing the record of our sin</char> was <char style="add">a gift. Instead, we would consider it as what we had earned</char>. <verse eid="ROM 4:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 4:5"/>But suppose that we do not do things <char style="add">to gain God’s acceptance</char>. Suppose that we instead trust <char style="add">in God</char>, who erases the record of sins of wicked people. Then the erasing of the record of our sins because of our trusting <char style="add">in Christ</char> is considered to be a gift to us, <char style="add">not something that we earned</char>. <verse eid="ROM 4:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 4:6"/>Similarly, it is as David wrote <char style="add">in the Psalms</char> about people being happy whose record of sins God has erased even though they have not done things <char style="add">to earn it. David wrote</char>:<verse eid="ROM 4:6"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 4:7"/>
    <char style="add">God</char> is pleased with people whose sins have been {whose sins <char style="add">he</char> has} forgiven, and whose sins he <char style="add">has decided</char> to forget [DOU].<verse eid="ROM 4:7"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 4:8"/>
    <char style="add">God</char> causes to be happy the people whose sins he no longer keeps a record of.<verse eid="ROM 4:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">This happiness of knowing that God has erased the record of our sins is also for the non-Jews. Remember that it was before Abraham was circumcised, when he was still in effect a non-Jew, that God did that. He later received circumcision simply as a sign of God having erased the record of his sins because of his faith. The result was that he became a spiritual father of all who believe in God as he did, whether they are circumcised or not.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 4:9-12">Romans 4:9-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 4:9"/>As for our being happy <char style="add">because God has erased the record of our sins</char>, ◄it is not something that <char style="add">only</char> we Jews <char style="add">can experience</char>./is it [MTY] something that <char style="add">only</char> we Jews <char style="add">can experience</char>?► [RHQ] <char style="add">No, it is</char> also something that non-Jews <char style="add">can experience</char> [MTY]. <char style="add">What is written in the Scriptures</char>, that it was because Abraham trusted <char style="add">in God</char> that the record of his sins was erased {<char style="add">God</char> erased the record of his sins}, <char style="add">also shows that this is true</char>. <verse eid="ROM 4:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 4:10"/>◄<char style="add">Think about</char> when <char style="add">God erased the record of Abraham’s sins</char>./When did <char style="add">God erase the record of Abraham’s sins</char>?► [RHQ] ◄Consider whether <char style="add">it happened</char> after someone circumcised <char style="add">Abraham to mark him as one who belonged to God</char>, or before someone circumcised him./<char style="add">Did it happen</char> after <char style="add">Abraham was</char> circumcised <char style="add">to be marked as one who belonged to God</char>, or before he was circumcised?► [RHQ] It happened before he was circumcised, not after he was circumcised. <verse eid="ROM 4:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 4:11"/><char style="add">Many years later, God commanded that</char> Abraham <char style="add">be</char> circumcised. Abraham’s accepting that ritual simply showed <char style="add">that he knew that God had accepted him</char>. <char style="add">He knew that God</char> had <char style="add">erased the record of his sins</char> because he trusted <char style="add">in God</char> while he was still, <char style="add">in effect, a non-Jew because</char> he had not been circumcised. <char style="add">So we can understand that</char> Abraham became ◄a spiritual ancestor/like an ancestor► to <char style="add">all</char> of us whose record of sins has been erased {whose sins <char style="add">God</char> has erased the record of} because we believe <char style="add">in God’s promise, even though some of us</char> are not circumcised. <verse eid="ROM 4:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 4:12"/>Likewise, Abraham is the <char style="add">spiritual</char> ancestor of all us Jews who are not merely circumcised but who, more importantly, <char style="add">believe in God’s promise</char> as our ancestor Abraham did, even before he was circumcised.<verse eid="ROM 4:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">It was because Abraham trusted in God that God erased the record of his sins and promised him many blessings. So what God promised is guaranteed to all, both Jews and non-Jews, who trust in God as Abraham did.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 4:13-17a">Romans 4:13-17a</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 4:13"/>God promised Abraham and his descendants that they would receive <char style="add">the blessings that he promised to give to the people in</char> the world. But when he promised that, it was not because Abraham <char style="add">obeyed</char> the laws <char style="add">that God later gave to Moses</char>. Instead, it was because Abraham believed <char style="add">that God would do what he promised that he would do</char>. As a result, God erased the record of his sins. <verse eid="ROM 4:13"/><verse number="14-15" style="v" sid="ROM 4:14-15"/>If <char style="add">we think that</char> it is those who <char style="add">obey God’s</char> laws who will receive <char style="add">what he has promised</char>, it is useless <char style="add">for us to trust in him. And what he</char> promised is worthless. <char style="add">Remember that</char> it is <char style="add">stated</char> in God’s law [PRS] <char style="add">that</char> he will punish <char style="add">people who do not perfectly obey them</char>, and remember that wherever [MTY] laws exist, <char style="add">people</char> disobey them [LIT]. <verse eid="ROM 4:14-15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 4:16"/>So it is because <char style="add">we</char> trust <char style="add">in God that we will receive the things that he has promised</char>. <char style="add">It is not because we perfectly obey God’s laws. He wants</char> ◄to <char style="add">erase the record of our sins/to declare us no longer guilty</char>► without our earning it. As a result, what God now promises, he guarantees to give to all people who are <char style="add">Abraham’s spiritual</char> descendants. <char style="add">He promises to do that not only for us Jewish believers</char>, who <char style="add">have</char> God’s laws <char style="add">and trust in him as Abraham did</char>, but also for those <char style="add">non-Jews who do not have God’s laws but</char> who trust <char style="add">in him</char> as Abraham did. Abraham is the <char style="add">spiritual</char> ancestor of all of us <char style="add">believers</char>. <verse eid="ROM 4:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 4:17"/>What is written {What <char style="add">Moses</char> wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures about what God promised Abraham shows that this is true</char>. <char style="add">God said to him</char>, “It is in order that you <char style="add">(sg)</char> may be the ancestor of many ethnic groups that I have chosen you.”</para>
  <para style="s1" vid="ROM 4:17">It was because Abraham confidently believed God’s promise to give him many descendants, when there was no physical basis for his hoping that this would happen, that God erased the record of his sins.</para>
  <para style="sr" vid="ROM 4:17">
    <ref loc="ROM 4:17b-22">Romans 4:17b-22</ref></para>
  <para style="p" vid="ROM 4:17">God <char style="add">guaranteed that he would give Abraham many descendants</char>. Abraham confidently believed that God <char style="add">would do that</char>, <verse eid="ROM 4:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 4:18"/>even though there was no physical reason for him to hope <char style="add">that he would have descendants, because he and his wife were too old to bear children</char>. But God is the one who causes dead people to live again, and who talks about things that do not yet exist as already existing. <char style="add">God said to Abraham</char>, “You will have so many descendants that they will be <char style="add">as impossible to count as the stars</char>.” And Abraham believed that, and he believed that he would become the ancestor of many ethnic groups. <verse eid="ROM 4:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 4:19"/>He did not doubt <char style="add">that God would do what he promised</char>, even though he knew that his body was already <char style="add">as incapable of begetting children as if he were</char> dead [MET] because he was about 100 years old. And <char style="add">even though he realized that</char> Sarah had never been able to become pregnant [IDM], <verse eid="ROM 4:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 4:20"/>he did not doubt at all that God <char style="add">would do what he had</char> promised. Instead, he trusted <char style="add">in God</char> more/very strongly, and he thanked God <char style="add">for what God was going to do</char>. <verse eid="ROM 4:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 4:21"/>He was also convinced {very sure} that the thing that God promised, God was able to do. <verse eid="ROM 4:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 4:22"/>And that is the reason that the record of his sins was erased {<char style="add">God</char> erased the record of his sins}.<verse eid="ROM 4:22"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The words about God erasing the record of Abraham’s sins were written also to assure us who believe in God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 4:23-25">Romans 4:23-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 4:23"/>The words <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>, “The record of his sins was erased {<char style="add">God</char> erased the record of his sins},” are not only about Abraham. <verse eid="ROM 4:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 4:24"/>They were also written {<char style="add">They</char> also wrote that} for us whose record of sins would be erased {<char style="add">God</char> would erase}. They were written {<char style="add">They</char> wrote it} for us who believe <char style="add">God</char>, the one who caused our Lord Jesus to become alive again after he died. <verse eid="ROM 4:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 4:25"/>Jesus allowed <char style="add">men</char> to execute [MTY] him so that <char style="add">God could forgive</char> our evil deeds. And <char style="add">God</char> caused Jesus to live again because <char style="add">God wanted to show that because of the death of Jesus he was able to</char> erase the record of our sins.<verse eid="ROM 4:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 4"/>
  <chapter number="5" style="c" sid="ROM 5"/>
  <para style="s1">Because God has erased the record of our sins, we have peace with him, we experience his acting kindly toward us, we rejoice because we expect to receive God’s glory, and we even rejoice in suffering because we know the results that it brings.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 5:1-5">Romans 5:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 5:1"/>Because we trusted <char style="add">in Christ</char>, the record of our sins has been erased {<char style="add">God</char> has erased the record of our sins}. So we <char style="add">now</char> have a peaceful relationship with God because of our trust in what our Lord Jesus Christ <char style="add">has done for us</char>. <verse eid="ROM 5:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 5:2"/>Because of <char style="add">what</char> Christ <char style="add">has done</char>, God has also enabled us to begin experiencing his continually acting toward us in ways that we do not deserve. Also, we rejoice because we are confidently expecting that God <char style="add">will gladly show</char> us how great he is. <verse eid="ROM 5:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 5:3"/>We rejoice even when we suffer <char style="add">as a result of our trusting in Christ</char>, because we know that when we are suffering, the result is that we learn to endure things <char style="add">patiently</char>. <verse eid="ROM 5:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 5:4"/>And <char style="add">we know</char> that when we endure things <char style="add">patiently</char>, the result is that <char style="add">God</char> approves <char style="add">of us</char>. And when we <char style="add">know that God</char> approves <char style="add">of us</char>, the result is that we confidently expect <char style="add">that he will do great things for us</char>. <verse eid="ROM 5:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 5:5"/>And we are very confident [PRS] that we will receive the things that we wait expectantly <char style="add">for</char>, because God loves us very much. His Holy Spirit, who has been {whom <char style="add">he</char> has} given to us, <char style="add">causes</char> us to understand how much God loves us.<verse eid="ROM 5:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because Christ died for us ungodly people, he will certainly save us from God’s eternal punishment, and so we boast of what he has done for us.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 5:6-11">Romans 5:6-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 5:6"/>When we were unable <char style="add">to save ourselves</char>, it was Christ who, at the time <char style="add">that God chose</char>, died on behalf of <char style="add">us</char> ungodly <char style="add">people</char>. <verse eid="ROM 5:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 5:7"/>Rarely would anyone die on behalf of another person, <char style="add">even if</char> that person were righteous, although someone might be courageous enough to die on behalf of a truly good person person. <verse eid="ROM 5:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 5:8"/>Nevertheless, as for God, the way he showed us that he loves us is that Christ died on our behalf while we were still rebelling against God. <verse eid="ROM 5:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 5:9"/>The record of our sins has been erased {<char style="add">God</char> has erased the record of our sins} because of <char style="add">what Christ accomplished when</char> his blood [MTY] <char style="add">flowed when he died</char>. So it is even more certain that we will be saved by Christ {that Christ will save us} from God’s punishing us <char style="add">eternally</char> [MTY]. <verse eid="ROM 5:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 5:10"/>Even when we were acting hostilely towards God, he enabled us to have a peaceful relationship with him as a result of his Son dying <char style="add">for us</char>. So it is even more certain that we will be saved {Christ will be able to save us} <char style="add">from God’s punishing us</char> [MTY] because Christ is alive <char style="add">again</char> and because <char style="add">God</char> has enabled us to have a peaceful relationship <char style="add">with himself</char>. <verse eid="ROM 5:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 5:11"/>And that’s not all! Now we also rejoice about <char style="add">the things that</char> God <char style="add">has done for us</char> because of our Lord Jesus Christ <char style="add">dying for us</char> and enabling us to have a peaceful relationship with God.<verse eid="ROM 5:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Although the sin of one man, Adam, led to all people dying and God declaring that they deserved to be punished, Christ’s righteous act of obedience when he died led to many people experiencing God’s kindness and being declared righteous and living eternally, and it will also result in their ruling with Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 5:12-21">Romans 5:12-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 5:12"/>
    <char style="add">What you can learn from what I have written so far is as follows</char>: All people are sinful [PRS], and that is the result of <char style="add">Adam, the first</char> man whom <char style="add">God created, sinning long ago</char>. Adam died [PRS] because he sinned. So, all people <char style="add">who have lived since then</char> die, because <char style="add">it is as though</char> all people sinned <char style="add">when Adam sinned</char>. <verse eid="ROM 5:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 5:13"/><char style="add">People in</char> [MTY] the world sinned before <char style="add">God gave his</char> laws <char style="add">to Moses</char>. But people are not considered <char style="add">by God</char> {<char style="add">God</char> does not consider people} to be guilty for their sins if there is no law <char style="add">stating that what they did was sinful</char>. <verse eid="ROM 5:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 5:14"/>But <char style="add">we know</char> that from <char style="add">the time when</char> Adam <char style="add">lived</char> until <char style="add">the time when</char> Moses <char style="add">lived</char>, all people sinned, and they died <char style="add">as a consequence</char> [PRS, MET]. Even people who sinned differently from the way Adam <char style="add">sinned, died</char>. <char style="add">Adam’s sin</char> affected <char style="add">all people</char>, just like what <char style="add">Christ did</char>, the one who came later, can affect all people. <verse eid="ROM 5:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 5:15"/>But <char style="add">the results of God’s erasing the record of our sins as</char> a gift to us are not like <char style="add">the results of Adam’s</char> sinning. The result of one man, <char style="add">Adam</char>, sinning was that many/all people have died. But <char style="add">it is certain</char>, <char style="add">however</char>, that many people have abundantly experienced God’s acting kindly toward them in a way they did not deserve. <char style="add">It is also certain</char> that they have experienced God’s erasing the record of their sins as the result of one man, Jesus Christ, acting kindly toward them/towards them in a way they did not deserve. <verse eid="ROM 5:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 5:16"/>And <char style="add">there is another way in which God’s</char> freely <char style="add">erasing the record of our sins</char> is not like <char style="add">the results of Adam’s</char> sinning. One person, <char style="add">Adam, sinned</char>. As a result, God declared that all people deserve to be punished. Many people sinned. But what God did was that he erased the record of their sins without their earning it. <verse eid="ROM 5:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 5:17"/>All people die [MET, PRS] because of what one man, <char style="add">Adam</char>, did. But now many of us experience that God has abundantly acted towards us in ways we did not deserve, and we experience that he has erased the record of our sins without our earning it. It is also very certain that we will rule <char style="add">with Christ</char> (OR, share <char style="add">the glory</char> of Christ’s being king), <char style="add">in heaven. This will happen</char> because of <char style="add">what</char> one man, Jesus Christ, <char style="add">did for us</char>.<verse eid="ROM 5:17"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 5:18"/>So, <char style="add">because one man, Adam</char>, disobeyed <char style="add">God’s law</char>, that resulted in all people deserving to be punished {that God punish them}. Similarly, because one man, <char style="add">Jesus</char>, acted righteously <char style="add">by obeying God when he died</char>, the result was that God is <char style="add">able to erase the record of</char> all people’s sins and <char style="add">enable them to</char> live eternally. <verse eid="ROM 5:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 5:19"/>It was because one person, <char style="add">Adam</char>, disobeyed <char style="add">God</char> that many/all people became sinners. Similarly, it is because one person, <char style="add">Jesus</char>, obeyed <char style="add">God when he died</char> that the record of many people’s sins will be erased {that <char style="add">he</char> will erase the record of many people’s sins}. <verse eid="ROM 5:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 5:20"/><char style="add">God gave</char> [PRS] his laws <char style="add">to Moses</char> [PRS] in order that <char style="add">people might realize</char> how greatly they had sinned; but as people sinned more, God continued to act even more kindly toward them, in a way that they did not deserve. <verse eid="ROM 5:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 5:21"/>He did that in order that just like people everywhere inevitably sin, <char style="add">which results in their</char> dying [MET, PRS], people everywhere might inevitably experience God’s acting kindly towards them in a way they do not deserve [MET, PRS] by <char style="add">erasing the record of their sins</char>. <char style="add">The result is that people can</char> live eternally because of what Jesus Christ our Lord <char style="add">did for them</char>.<verse eid="ROM 5:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 5"/>
  <chapter number="6" style="c" sid="ROM 6"/>
  <para style="s1">If someone were to say that perhaps we should continue to sin in order that God may continue to act more kindly toward us, I would reply that we who ought to consider ourselves unresponsive to sinful desires should certainly not continue sinning. We must keep remembering that it is as though our former sinful nature has ceased to function, and it is as though we have become unresponsive to sinful desires, living in a new way. So do not let the desire to commit sin control you. Instead, present yourselves to God to do righteous things.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 6:1-14">Romans 6:1-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 6:1"/>Someone might [RHQ] say <char style="add">in reply to what I have written</char> that <char style="add">since God acted kindly toward us</char> in a way we did not deserve <char style="add">because we sinned</char>, perhaps we should continue to sin in order that he may continue to act even more kindly toward us <char style="add">and keep on forgiving us</char>! [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 6:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 6:2"/><char style="add">I would reply</char>, No, certainly not! We <char style="add">ought to consider that</char> our sinful desires [MET] <char style="add">cannot make us do what they want us to do</char>, <char style="add">just like we cannot make</char> a corpse do what we want it to do. So it is not right that we continue to sin! [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 6:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 6:3"/>When we were baptized {<char style="add">asked someone to</char> baptize us} in order to show that we have a relationship with (OR, are united to) Jesus Christ, our <char style="add">being baptized was to declare that it was as though</char> we died with Christ. ◄<char style="add">I want</char> you to remember that!/Do you not know that?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 6:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 6:4"/>So, when we were baptized {someone baptized us}, <char style="add">it was as though</char> we were buried with Christ. <char style="add">We were baptized</char> in order to indicate that <char style="add">we would not let our sinful desires make us do what they want us to do, just like people cannot make</char> a corpse <char style="add">do what they want it to</char> do [MET]. We <char style="add">were baptized</char> to <char style="add">signify that we would</char> continually conduct our lives in a new way, just like Christ was caused to live again in a new way by the great <char style="add">power</char> of <char style="add">God his</char> Father. <verse eid="ROM 6:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 6:5"/>Because of our close relationship with Christ, we have <char style="add">separated ourselves from the former way in which we conducted our lives</char>, just like he <char style="add">was separated from his physical life when he</char> died [MET]. But God will also certainly <char style="add">enable us to live in a new way, just like he</char> enabled Christ to live again. <verse eid="ROM 6:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 6:6"/>We must keep remembering that when Christ died on the cross [MET], <char style="add">it was as though</char> our sinful nature <char style="add">died with him. It has</char> lost its power to make us do what it wants us to do [MET]. That happened in order that we would not do the sinful <char style="add">things that our bodies</char> [MET], which desire to sin, want us to do, and in order that we would no longer have to sin [MET], as slaves <char style="add">have to do what their masters want</char>. <verse eid="ROM 6:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 6:7"/><char style="add">We are, as it were, freed</char> {<char style="add">free</char>} <char style="add">from</char> sinful <char style="add">desires</char> [MET] <char style="add">controlling us, just like</char> those who have died are free <char style="add">from anything controlling them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 6:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 6:8"/>Since <char style="add">it is as though</char> we died with Christ, we believe that we will continue to live with him. <verse eid="ROM 6:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 6:9"/>We know that since <char style="add">God</char> enabled Christ to live again after he died, Christ will never die again. Nothing will ever be able to make him die again [PRS]. <verse eid="ROM 6:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 6:10"/>When he died, he died once for <char style="add">people</char> who had sinned, and he will never die again; but in regard to his living <char style="add">again now</char>, he lives in order to <char style="add">serve/honor</char> God. <verse eid="ROM 6:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 6:11"/>Similarly, you must consider that <char style="add">it is as though</char> you have become <char style="add">unable to do what your</char> sinful <char style="add">desires</char> [MET] want, as a corpse <char style="add">is not able to do what anyone wants it to do</char>. You must also consider that because of your relationship to Christ Jesus you are living <char style="add">in a new way</char> in order to <char style="add">serve/honor</char> God. <verse eid="ROM 6:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 6:12"/>So, do not let the <char style="add">desire to</char> sin [PRS] control your bodies [MET] with the result that you do the sinful things that you desire to do. <char style="add">Remember that</char> your bodies will surely die, <char style="add">but your spirits will never die</char>. <verse eid="ROM 6:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 6:13"/>Do not let any of your body parts do wicked things, as <char style="add">you did</char> [MET] <char style="add">when you were spiritually</char> dead. Instead, present yourselves to God as people who are alive <char style="add">spiritually</char>. Present all your body parts to God, <char style="add">to allow him</char> to use them to <char style="add">do</char> righteous things. <verse eid="ROM 6:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 6:14"/>Do not let a <char style="add">desire to</char> sin control you [PRS]. The laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char> did not enable you <char style="add">to stop sinning</char>. But <char style="add">now</char> God controls you and kindly helps you <char style="add">not to sin</char>.<verse eid="ROM 6:14"/></para>
  <para style="s1">If someone should conclude that people can sin now because they are not obligated to obey the Mosaic laws, I would say, “Certainly not!” Instead, let your minds compel your bodies to act righteously.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 6:15-23">Romans 6:15-23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 6:15"/>
    <char style="add">I suppose that certain people might think about what I have just said and they might</char> say [RHQ], “<char style="add">You say that</char> the laws <char style="add">God gave Moses</char> did not <char style="add">enable us to stop sinning, but that God is now</char> treating us kindly in ways we do not deserve. ◄<char style="add">That seems to mean that God permits</char> us to continue sinning./<char style="add">Does that mean that God permits</char> us to continue sinning?► [RHQ]” My reply to that is no, we should certainly not continue <char style="add">sinning</char> <verse eid="ROM 6:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 6:16"/><char style="add">Slaves</char> have to obey <char style="add">what their masters command</char> [MET] <char style="add">them to do</char>. ◄I want you to remember this./Do you not know this?► [RHQ] Similarly, if you present yourselves to someone <char style="add">in order to</char> obey him, you will be the slaves [MET] of the person you obey. Similarly, <char style="add">if you have yielded yourselves to do the</char> sinful things <char style="add">you desire</char>, you are slaves of your sinful desires [PRS], and you will be eternally separated from God. <char style="add">If you have yielded yourselves</char> to obey <char style="add">God</char>, you are slaves of God and you need to <char style="add">live</char> righteously. <verse eid="ROM 6:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 6:17"/>You were once slaves <char style="add">to</char> your sinful <char style="add">desires</char>. But you began to sincerely obey the new teaching [MET] that you were taught {that <char style="add">people</char> taught you}. I thank God for that. <verse eid="ROM 6:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 6:18"/><char style="add">I</char> also <char style="add">thank God that</char> you have been freed {<char style="add">that</char> he has freed you} from <char style="add">being controlled by a desire to</char> sin, and that you have become <char style="add">as though you were</char> slaves [MET] to <char style="add">living</char> righteously [MET]. <verse eid="ROM 6:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 6:19"/>I am illustrating what I say <char style="add">by talking about slavery</char> because your human nature prevents you from understanding <char style="add">spiritual truth</char> easily. <char style="add">In the past</char> you willingly did the immoral and unlawful things that <char style="add">your minds compelled</char> your bodies to do [MET], <char style="add">just like</char> slaves <char style="add">do what their masters compel them to do</char>. As a result, you did even more unlawful things. Now, <char style="add">you need to</char> willingly allow <char style="add">your minds to compel</char> your bodies to <char style="add">act</char> righteously [MET], in order that you will behave in a holy/pure way. <verse eid="ROM 6:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 6:20"/>When you were <char style="add">like</char> slaves <char style="add">because your sinful desires compelled you to do</char> sinful things [MET], you were not <char style="add">concerned about behaving</char> righteously [MET]. <verse eid="ROM 6:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 6:21"/>Nevertheless, <char style="add">doing</char> those things resulted in your being separated from God, so you did not benefit at all from <char style="add">doing</char> the <char style="add">sinful</char> things that you are now ashamed of. [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 6:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 6:22"/>But you have been freed {<char style="add">God</char> has freed you} from <char style="add">letting the desire to</char> sin control you. You have become <char style="add">as though you are</char> [MET] the slaves of God. So now the result is that God has caused you to completely belong to him and, as a result, you will live eternally. <verse eid="ROM 6:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 6:23"/><char style="add">What people receive for</char> sinning <char style="add">is that they are</char> eternally separated from God. That is <char style="add">like</char> wages that <char style="add">people receive</char> [MET]. But what God gives us is a gift. What he gives us is that we live eternally because of <char style="add">our relationship with</char> (OR, because <char style="add">we are united to</char>) Christ Jesus our Lord.<verse eid="ROM 6:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 6"/>
  <chapter number="7" style="c" sid="ROM 7"/>
  <para style="s1">You know that after people die they are freed from being required to obey any law. Similarly, God has freed us from being required to obey all the Jewish rituals and laws.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 7:1-6">Romans 7:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 7:1"/>My fellow believers, you know about laws. So you certainly know (OR, I want you to remember) that people have to obey laws [PRS] <char style="add">only</char> while <char style="add">they are</char> alive. [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 7:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 7:2"/>For example, a woman is required by the law {the law requires a woman} <char style="add">to obey and be faithful to her husband</char> as long as he is alive. But if her husband dies, she is freed <char style="add">from having to</char> {<char style="add">no longer has to</char>} <char style="add">obey</char> the law about <char style="add">remaining married to</char> her husband. <verse eid="ROM 7:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 7:3"/>Therefore, a woman will be called {people will call a woman} an adulteress if she lives with another man while her husband is alive. But if her husband dies, she no longer <char style="add">has to obey</char> that law. Then she will not be an adulteress if she marries another man. <verse eid="ROM 7:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 7:4"/>Likewise, my fellow believers, <char style="add">just like people are free from having to obey any law after they die</char> [MET], you <char style="add">and I</char> have been freed {<char style="add">God</char> has freed you <char style="add">and me</char>} from having <char style="add">to obey</char> all the Jewish rituals and laws [MET]. <char style="add">That is because it is as though</char> we died with Christ <char style="add">when he was crucified</char>. Now you <char style="add">and I</char> belong to someone else [MET], <char style="add">like a woman who marries again after her husband dies belongs to another man</char>. Specifically, you <char style="add">and I</char> belong to <char style="add">Christ</char>, who has come back to life {whom <char style="add">God</char> has caused to live again after he died}, in order that we may live righteously [IDM] to <char style="add">honor</char> God. <verse eid="ROM 7:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 7:5"/>When our self-directed nature <char style="add">controlled</char> us, desires <char style="add">that led us to</char> sin were acting in our bodies. <char style="add">Those desires were increased because of our knowing God’s</char> laws [PRS]. As a result <char style="add">we did evil things</char> [IDM] <char style="add">that</char> caused us to be separated from God. <verse eid="ROM 7:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 7:6"/>But now we are freed {free} from <char style="add">having to obey all the Jewish</char> rituals— <char style="add">it is as though</char> we have died. The result is that now we are not controlled by those rituals {those rituals do not control us now}. So we serve God, not by <char style="add">having to obey</char> those rituals, which is the old way, but in the new way, as <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">helps us to serve him</char>.<verse eid="ROM 7:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">My reply to the objection that the laws of Moses are evil because they cause us to sin is that the laws are holy and good; what the laws do are simply to reveal that what we are doing is sinful.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 7:7-12">Romans 7:7-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 7:7"/>
    <char style="add">Someone might object</char>, saying, “◄The laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char> must be evil <char style="add">if our sinful desires</char> are increased because of our knowing those laws. [MTY]/Are not the laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses</char> evil <char style="add">if they stir up our sinful desires</char>?►” [MTY, RHQ] <char style="add">I would reply</char> that they certainly are not <char style="add">evil, even though our sinful desires are increased</char>. What I would reply is that I, <char style="add">for example</char>, realized that <char style="add">what I was doing</char> was sinful only because <char style="add">of what is written</char> {<char style="add">Moses wrote</char>} <char style="add">in</char> those laws. For example, I realized that coveting <char style="add">is sinful</char> only because he wrote in those laws [PRS], “You must not covet.” <verse eid="ROM 7:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 7:8"/>And because of what that commandment <char style="add">stated</char>, my sinful <char style="add">desire to have things that belong to others</char> [PRS] caused me to covet in many ways. <char style="add">Our desire to</char> sin is not stimulated [MET] when there is no law <char style="add">that prohibits our doing sinful things</char>. <verse eid="ROM 7:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 7:9"/>Formerly, when I did not <char style="add">know</char> what God’s laws <char style="add">required</char>, I used to live <char style="add">without worrying about what I was doing</char>. But when I <char style="add">became aware that God</char> commanded, <char style="add">“You must not covet</char>,” I suddenly realized [PRS] that I was sinning, <verse eid="ROM 7:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 7:10"/>and <char style="add">I realized that</char> I was separated from God. The laws that <char style="add">I thought would enable me to</char> live <char style="add">eternally as a result of my obeying them</char> caused me <char style="add">to realize that</char> I was separated from God! <verse eid="ROM 7:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 7:11"/><char style="add">My desire to</char> sin found a way [PRS] to deceive me <char style="add">by making me think wrongly that</char> I could keep <char style="add">on sinning and at the same time obey</char> those laws <char style="add">enough so that I would live eternally</char>, and <char style="add">thus it</char> caused me to be separated from God [PRS]. <verse eid="ROM 7:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 7:12"/>So <char style="add">we conclude that</char> the laws <char style="add">that God gave to Moses</char> are holy. What God commanded <char style="add">about not coveting, along with all the other things that he commanded</char>, is also holy, and it is just and good.<verse eid="ROM 7:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">My reply to the objection that God’s law, being good, causes people to become spiritually dead is no, it is our desire to commit sin that causes us to sin and become spiritually dead.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 7:13">Romans 7:13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 7:13"/>So, <char style="add">if someone were to object</char> saying, “<char style="add">The laws that God gave Moses</char>, which are good, ◄resulted in my being separated from God!/did they result in my being separated from God?► [RHQ]” <char style="add">I would reply</char>, “Certainly they did not <char style="add">do that</char>!” But instead, those <char style="add">laws</char>, which are good, stimulated <char style="add">my desire to</char> sin. I knew that the result was that I was separated from God. And also, because I <char style="add">learned what God had</char> commanded, <char style="add">I knew that</char> what I was doing was <char style="add">truly</char> sinful.<verse eid="ROM 7:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The laws came from God’s Spirit, but you and I are influenced by our sinful natures. We often do not do the things that we desire, and we do the things that we detest because of a desire to sin that permeates us and prevents us from doing good, unless Christ frees us from being controlled by these desires.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 7:14-25">Romans 7:14-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 7:14"/>We know that the laws <char style="add">that God gave Moses came from God’s</char> Spirit. But as for me, I am <char style="add">influenced by my</char> self-directed nature. <char style="add">It is as though</char> I have been forced to become a slave of <char style="add">my desire to</char> sin [MET]. <verse eid="ROM 7:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 7:15"/>The things that I do, I <char style="add">often</char> [HYP] do not understand. That is, <char style="add">sometimes</char> [HYP] it is <char style="add">the good things</char> that I want <char style="add">to do</char> that I do not do. <char style="add">And sometimes</char> [HYP] it is the <char style="add">evil</char> things that I detest that I do. <verse eid="ROM 7:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 7:16"/>Since I <char style="add">do</char> the <char style="add">evil</char> things that I do not want <char style="add">to</char> do, I agree that the laws <char style="add">of God</char> are good. <verse eid="ROM 7:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 7:17"/>So, it is not that I do <char style="add">evil things because I wish to do them</char>. Instead, <char style="add">what happens is that</char> I do sinful things because the desire to sin <char style="add">causes me to do them</char>. The <char style="add">desire to</char> sin ◄is within/permeates► me [PRS]. <verse eid="ROM 7:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 7:18"/>I know that my self-directed nature will not <char style="add">let me</char> [PRS] <char style="add">do</char> anything that is good. I know this because I want <char style="add">to do what is good</char>, but I do not do what is good. <verse eid="ROM 7:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 7:19"/>I do not do the good things that I want to do. Instead, it is evil things that I do not want to do that I do. <verse eid="ROM 7:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 7:20"/>Because I do <char style="add">evil things</char> that I do not want to do, it is not that I do <char style="add">evil things because I want to</char>. Instead, <char style="add">I do them because</char> my self-directed nature, which permeates me [PRS], <char style="add">causes me to do them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 7:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 7:21"/>I find, then, that what always happens is that when I want to do what is good, there is an evil <char style="add">desire</char> present within me that [PRS] <char style="add">prevents me from doing good</char>. <verse eid="ROM 7:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 7:22"/>With my new inner nature I like the laws of God very much. <verse eid="ROM 7:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 7:23"/>Nevertheless, I sense that there is a different force that is in ◄my body/me► [PRS, SYN]. It is opposed to what with my mind <char style="add">I desire to do</char> [MET], and it puts me inescapably under the control of [MET] the sinful <char style="add">desires</char> that I have [SYN]. <verse eid="ROM 7:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 7:24"/><char style="add">When I consider this</char>, I <char style="add">feel that I</char> am a very wretched person. I want someone to set me free from the control of what my body <char style="add">desires</char>, in order that I might not be separated from God. [RHQ] <char style="add">I also think that what I have experienced is the same as what all believers experience</char>. <verse eid="ROM 7:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 7:25"/>I thank God that it is by Jesus Christ our Lord <char style="add">that we can be free from the control of what our bodies desire</char>. So, <char style="add">with our minds, you and</char> I on the one hand want to obey God’s laws. <char style="add">But also</char>, <char style="add">you and</char> I <char style="add">often let</char> our sinful <char style="add">desires control us</char> because of our self-directed nature.<verse eid="ROM 7:25"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 7"/>
  <chapter number="8" style="c" sid="ROM 8"/>
  <para style="s1">God will not in any way condemn those who are united to Christ Jesus, because God’s Spirit has freed us from the inevitability of sinning and from spiritual death.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 8:1-11">Romans 8:1-11</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 8:1"/>Because <char style="add">God has erased the record of our sins because we trust in what Christ has done for us</char>, now <char style="add">God will</char> not condemn and punish those/us who have a relationship with (OR, are united to) Christ Jesus. <verse eid="ROM 8:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 8:2"/><char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit causes us to live <char style="add">in a new way</char> [PRS] as a result of what Christ Jesus <char style="add">did for us</char>. And he has set up a way by which he frees <char style="add">each of</char> us from continually being forced to sin (OR, to obey our self-directed natures) and from being separated from God. <verse eid="ROM 8:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 8:3"/>What <char style="add">we</char> could not do <char style="add">by trying to obey</char> the laws <char style="add">of God</char> [PRS], because our self-directed nature was too weak <char style="add">to obey them</char>, God did. He sent his own Son <char style="add">into the world in order that his Son might atone</char> for our sin. His Son came having a body (OR, human nature) that was like <char style="add">the body</char> (OR, the <char style="add">human nature</char>) of us people who sin. <char style="add">By sending his Son in this way</char>, he condemned and punished <char style="add">his Son, who never sinned, instead of punishing us, who</char> sinned [MTY]. He did that <char style="add">by making his Son’s</char> body <char style="add">a sacrifice</char> (OR, <char style="add">by causing his Son’s</char> body <char style="add">to suffer/die</char>) for <char style="add">all our</char> sin. <verse eid="ROM 8:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 8:4"/>So we can <char style="add">now</char> fulfill all that God required in his laws. We do this, not by our acting the way our sinful human nature <char style="add">desires</char>, but instead by living as <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">desires us to live</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 8:5"/>People who live according to what their self-directed nature <char style="add">desires</char> think about and are concerned about what their self-directed nature <char style="add">desires</char>. But people who <char style="add">live</char> according to what <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">desires think about and are concerned about</char> what <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">desires</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 8:6"/>Those people who [PRS] think about and are concerned about what their self-directed nature <char style="add">desires</char> will not live eternally (OR, will be separated from God). But those people who think about and are concerned about what <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit <char style="add">desires</char> will live <char style="add">eternally</char> and have <char style="add">inner</char> peace. <verse eid="ROM 8:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 8:7"/>Let me explain this. <char style="add">To the extent that</char> people [PRS] think about and are concerned about what their self-directed nature <char style="add">desires</char>, they are acting contrary to God. They do not obey the laws of God. In fact, they are not even able <char style="add">to obey his laws</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 8:8"/>The people who let their self-directed nature <char style="add">control them</char> cannot do what pleases God. <verse eid="ROM 8:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 8:9"/>But we do not have to let our self-directed nature <char style="add">control us</char>. Instead, we can <char style="add">let</char> God’s Spirit <char style="add">control us</char>, because he lives within us. If people do not have <char style="add">living in them</char> the Spirit <char style="add">who comes from</char> Christ, they do not belong to Christ. <verse eid="ROM 8:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 8:10"/>But since Christ <char style="add">is living in you/us by his Spirit, although</char> your/our bodies <char style="add">are certain to</char> die because you/we sin, your/our spirits are alive because God has erased the record of your/our sins. <verse eid="ROM 8:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 8:11"/><char style="add">God</char> caused Jesus to live again after he died. And because his Spirit lives in you/us, <char style="add">God</char> will also make your/our bodies, which <char style="add">now</char> are sure to die, live <char style="add">again after you/we die</char>. God, who caused Christ to live again after he died, will make you/us live again by <char style="add">causing</char> his Spirit, who lives within you/us, <char style="add">to do it</char>.<verse eid="ROM 8:11"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We are compelled to live as the Spirit directs, not as our self-directed nature directs, because if we do the latter we will be eternally separated from God, but if we cease doing the latter we will live eternally.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 8:12-13">Romans 8:12-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 8:12"/>Therefore, my fellow believers, we must <char style="add">live as the Spirit directs us</char>. What we do not have to do is to live as our self-directed nature <char style="add">guides us</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 8:13"/>If you live the way your self-directed nature <char style="add">directs</char>, you will surely not live <char style="add">eternally</char> (OR, will surely be eternally separated from God). But if by <char style="add">the power of God’s</char> Spirit you quit doing the <char style="add">sinful</char> things that your bodies <char style="add">desire</char> [MET], you will live eternally.<verse eid="ROM 8:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because we who allow the Spirit of God to guide us are God’s children, we will also inherit eternal blessings from God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 8:14-17">Romans 8:14-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 8:14"/>We who are guided by the Spirit of God {allow the Spirit of God to guide us} are God’s children. <verse eid="ROM 8:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 8:15"/><char style="add">You have showed that this is true</char>, because you received <char style="add">from God</char> a Spirit that is not one that makes you fear <char style="add">God</char> again. You are not like slaves who <char style="add">fear their masters</char> [MET]. On the contrary, we have received a Spirit by whose <char style="add">work in our hearts God</char> has adopted us. The Spirit now enables us to cry out <char style="add">to God</char>, “<char style="add">You(sg) are my</char> Father [DOU]!” <verse eid="ROM 8:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 8:16"/>The Spirit himself confirms what our spirits <char style="add">say</char>, that we are God’s children. <verse eid="ROM 8:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 8:17"/>Because we are <char style="add">God’s</char> children, we also will some day receive/inherit <char style="add">eternal blessings/privileges</char>. We will receive/inherit them from God, and we will <char style="add">also</char> receive/inherit <char style="add">them</char> just like Christ has <char style="add">inherited them</char>. But we must suffer <char style="add">for doing good</char> as Christ did, in order to receive splendor as he did.<verse eid="ROM 8:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Since everything that God has created is eagerly awaiting the time when he will reveal who are his true children, I consider that what we suffer now is not worth paying attention to.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 8:18-25">Romans 8:18-25</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 8:18"/>I consider that what we suffer during the present time is not worth <char style="add">paying attention to, because</char> the future splendor/glory that will be revealed {that <char style="add">God</char> will reveal} to us <char style="add">is so great</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 8:19"/>The <char style="add">things that God has</char> created are very eagerly waiting for <char style="add">the time</char> [PRS, DOU] when God will reveal who his <char style="add">true</char> children are. <verse eid="ROM 8:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 8:20"/><char style="add">God</char> caused the things that he created to be unable to achieve <char style="add">what he had purposed. That was</char> not because they wanted to <char style="add">be unable to do that</char>. On the contrary, <char style="add">God</char> made them that way because he wanted them to keep confidently expecting <verse eid="ROM 8:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 8:21"/>that the things that <char style="add">he</char> created will be freed {that <char style="add">he</char> will free the things that <char style="add">he</char> created} from their sure decay [MET]. <char style="add">He</char> will free them in order that <char style="add">he can give them</char> the same glory that belongs to his children. <verse eid="ROM 8:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 8:22"/>We know that until now <char style="add">it is as though</char> all <char style="add">things</char> that God created have been groaning together, <char style="add">and they long for that glory, just like a mother having the pains before bearing a child</char> groans <char style="add">and longs for her baby’s birth</char> [MET]. <verse eid="ROM 8:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 8:23"/>Not only <char style="add">do those things groan</char>, but we ourselves also groan inwardly. We who have <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit, who is like a partial gift [MET] we have received as we wait for <char style="add">the future glory, groan inwardly</char>. We groan while we wait eagerly for the time when we will receive our <char style="add">full</char> rights as God’s adopted children. That <char style="add">will include</char> his freeing our bodies <char style="add">from the things that hinder us on earth. He will do this by giving us new bodies</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 8:24"/>Ever since we were saved {since <char style="add">God</char> saved us}, we have continued to confidently expect <char style="add">that future glory</char>. If we had what we waited for, we would not <char style="add">need to</char> wait for it any longer, because those who have something, certainly do not continue to wait for it! [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 8:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 8:25"/>But because we keep waiting expectantly to receive what we do not yet have, we wait for it eagerly and patiently/perseveringly.<verse eid="ROM 8:25"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God’s Spirit helps us when our spirits feel weak; he prays for us and God understands what his Spirit intends.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 8:26-27">Romans 8:26-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 8:26"/>Similarly, in addition to our continuing to wait for what God will give us, God’s Spirit helps us when our spirits feel weak. We do not know what is proper/necessary for us to pray. But God’s Spirit knows, and he prays for us when we groan (OR, he groans) in a way that cannot be expressed in words (OR, prays with us, groaning in a way that cannot be expressed in words). <verse eid="ROM 8:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 8:27"/>God, who examines our inner feelings, understands what his Spirit desires. What God understands is that his Spirit prays for us who belong to God exactly as God wants him to pray.<verse eid="ROM 8:27"/></para>
  <para style="s1">God works out all things in a way that produces good spiritual benefits for us who love him. He does this because, having known that we would be saved and thus we would have the character of his Son, he chose us and declared us righteous, and he will surely give us future splendor.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 8:28-30">Romans 8:28-30</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 8:28"/>And we know that to those/us who love God, he works out all things that happen <char style="add">to them/us</char> in a way that produces good <char style="add">spiritual</char> benefits <char style="add">for us</char>. He does these things for those/us whom he has chosen, because that was (OR, was according to) what he planned to do. <verse eid="ROM 8:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 8:29"/>God knew previously <char style="add">that we would believe</char> in him (OR, <char style="add">would be saved</char>). We are those who God also decided previously would develop a character like his Son’s character. The result of that is that <char style="add">Christ is like</char> a firstborn/highest-ranking <char style="add">son</char>, and <char style="add">those/we who are God’s children</char> [MET] are <char style="add">like</char> [MET] many <char style="add">younger</char> brothers <char style="add">of Jesus</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 8:30"/>And us who God decided previously <char style="add">that we would become like his Son</char>, he also summoned. And for us whom he summoned, he also erased the record of our sins. And for us whose record of sins he has erased, he also will surely give future splendor.<verse eid="ROM 8:30"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We must conclude from these things that no one can defeat us, and absolutely no one and nothing can separate us from Christ’s loving us and God’s loving us.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 8:31-39">Romans 8:31-39</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 8:31"/>So ◄I will tell you what we must conclude from <char style="add">all</char> these things <char style="add">that God does for us</char>./what shall we conclude from <char style="add">all</char> these things <char style="add">that God does for us</char>?► [RHQ] Because God <char style="add">is acting</char> on our behalf, ◄no one can win against us!/can anyone defeat us? (OR, it does not matter if anyone opposes us)!► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 8:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 8:32"/>God did not spare even his very own Son. Instead, he turned him over <char style="add">to others to cruelly kill him</char> in order that all we <char style="add">who believe in him</char> may benefit <char style="add">from his dying for us. Therefore, because God did that</char>, ◄he will also certainly give us freely everything <char style="add">that we need to live for him</char>, in addition to <char style="add">giving us</char> Christ./will he not also certainly give us freely everything <char style="add">that we need to live for him</char>, in addition to <char style="add">giving us</char> Christ?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 8:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 8:33"/>It is God himself who erases the record of our sins. So ◄no one who accuses us <char style="add">before God will win against us</char> (OR, <char style="add">it does not matter</char> if anyone tries to accuse us) whom God has chosen./is it possible that anyone who accuses us <char style="add">before God</char> will win against us (OR, does it matter if anyone tries to accuse us) whom God has chosen?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 8:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ROM 8:34"/>It is Christ Jesus himself who pleads <char style="add">with God</char> for us, so ◄no one can condemn us (OR, say that we are still guilty for our sin)./can anyone condemn us (OR, say that we are still guilty for our sin)?► [RHQ] Christ died <char style="add">for us</char>, but he was also brought back to life {<char style="add">God</char> also raised him from the dead}, and he is now at the place of honor <char style="add">ruling</char> with God [MTY]. <verse eid="ROM 8:34"/><verse number="35" style="v" sid="ROM 8:35"/>Absolutely no one and nothing can cause Christ to stop loving us! [RHQ] That could not [RHQ] happen <char style="add">because someone</char> caused us to have trouble [DOU], or <char style="add">because someone did things to</char> harm us, or <char style="add">because we did</char> not have anything to eat, or <char style="add">because we did</char> not have enough clothes, or <char style="add">because we lived in a</char> dangerous situation, or <char style="add">because someone killed us with</char> a sword [MTY] (OR, murdered us). <verse eid="ROM 8:35"/><verse number="36" style="v" sid="ROM 8:36"/><char style="add">Such things may happen to us, just like</char> it is written {<char style="add">as David</char> wrote} <char style="add">that David said to God</char>, “Because we are your <char style="add">(sg)</char> people, <char style="add">other people repeatedly attempt to</char> kill us. They consider that we are <char style="add">only people to be killed</char>, <char style="add">like a butcher considers</char> that sheep are <char style="add">only</char> animals to be slaughtered [MET].” <verse eid="ROM 8:36"/><verse number="37" style="v" sid="ROM 8:37"/>But even though all these bad things <char style="add">may happen to us</char>, we win a great victory/triumph <char style="add">over these things because Christ</char>, who loves us, <char style="add">helps us</char>. <verse eid="ROM 8:37"/><verse number="38" style="v" sid="ROM 8:38"/>I am absolutely certain that neither being dead (OR, being killed), nor <char style="add">what happens to us while</char> we live, nor angels, nor demons, nor present events, nor future events, nor powerful <char style="add">beings/forces</char>, <verse eid="ROM 8:38"/><verse number="39" style="v" sid="ROM 8:39"/>nor <char style="add">powerful beings</char> above <char style="add">the horizon</char> or below <char style="add">the horizon</char> [MTY], nor anything else that <char style="add">God has</char> created can cause God to stop loving us. <char style="add">God showed us that he loves us by sending</char> Jesus Christ our Lord <char style="add">to die for us</char>.<verse eid="ROM 8:39"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 8"/>
  <chapter number="9" style="c" sid="ROM 9"/>
  <para style="s1">I tell you very sincerely that I grieve greatly about most of my fellow Israelites having rejected Christ. I would be willing to be separated from Christ if that would help them believe in him.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 9:1-5">Romans 9:1-5</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 9:1"/>
    <char style="add">Now I would like to discuss the fact that most of my fellow Israelites have rejected Christ</char>. Because of my relationship with Christ, I say completely truthfully <char style="add">what I will now tell you</char>. I am not lying [DOU]! My conscience confirms what I <char style="add">say</char> because the Holy Spirit <char style="add">controls it</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 9:2"/><char style="add">I tell you that</char> I grieve very greatly and deeply [DOU] <char style="add">about my fellow Israelites</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 9:3"/>I personally would be willing to let <char style="add">God</char> curse me <char style="add">and, as a result, be separated</char> from Christ, <char style="add">if that would</char> help my fellow Israelites, my natural kinsmen, <char style="add">to believe in Christ</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 9:4"/>We <char style="add">Jews</char> are <char style="add">Israelites, God’s chosen</char> descendants of <char style="add">Jacob</char>. <char style="add">God has always considered</char> us as his children [MET]. It was to our ancestors <char style="add">that he used to appear</char> gloriously <char style="add">while they were in the desert</char>. It was with them that <char style="add">God made</char> covenants <char style="add">several times</char>. It was to them <char style="add">that God</char> gave the laws <char style="add">at Sinai Mountain</char>. They were the ones <char style="add">to whom God showed how they should</char> worship him. They were the ones <char style="add">to whom God</char> promised many things, <char style="add">especially that the Messiah would come from their race</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 9:5"/>It was our ancestors, <char style="add">Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, whom God chose to found our nation</char>. And, <char style="add">most importantly</char>, it was from us Israelites that the Messiah received his human nature. <char style="add">Nevertheless, most of my fellow Israelites have rejected Christ</char>, who is the one who controls all things! He is God, the one who is worthy that we praise him forever! This is true! (OR, Amen!)<verse eid="ROM 9:5"/></para>
  <para style="s1">This does not prove that God has failed to do for Abraham what he promised, because, as Scripture illustrates, it is not all who are naturally descended from Jacob or Abraham whom God considers to be his children, but it is those who were born as a result of what God promised whom he considers his children.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 9:6-13">Romans 9:6-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 9:6"/>
    <char style="add">God promised to Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, that their descendants would all inherit his blessings</char>. But <char style="add">although most of my fellow Israelites have rejected Christ</char>, that does not <char style="add">prove</char> that God has failed <char style="add">to do</char> the things that he promised, because it is not all who are descended from Jacob and who <char style="add">call themselves the people of</char> Israel whom <char style="add">God considers</char> to be truly his people. <verse eid="ROM 9:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 9:7"/>And it is also not all of Abraham’s natural descendants that <char style="add">God considers</char> to be his people. Instead, <char style="add">God considers only some of them to be Abraham’s children</char>. <char style="add">This agrees with what God told Abraham</char>: “It is Isaac, <char style="add">not any of your(sg) other sons</char>, whom <char style="add">I</char> will consider <char style="add">to be the true father of</char> your descendants.” <verse eid="ROM 9:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 9:8"/>That means that it is not all the natural-born descendants <char style="add">of Abraham</char> whom God <char style="add">considers as</char> his children. Instead, it is those who <char style="add">believed what God</char> promised whom <char style="add">he</char> considers to be his children. <verse eid="ROM 9:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 9:9"/><char style="add">You know that what God</char> promised <char style="add">to Abraham</char> was this: “About this time <char style="add">next year</char> Sarah <char style="add">your wife</char> will bear a son <char style="add">as a result of my enabling</char> [MTY] <char style="add">her to do so</char>.” <char style="add">So Abraham knew that it was not through Ishmael, the son that he already had, that God would fulfill what he had promised him</char> (OR, <char style="add">that his true descendants would come</char>). <verse eid="ROM 9:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 9:10"/>And not only then did God show <char style="add">that he did not determine who would be his true children according to who their ancestors were. He showed it again</char> when Rebecca conceived <char style="add">twins</char> by our ancestor Isaac. <verse eid="ROM 9:10"/><verse number="11-12" style="v" sid="ROM 9:11-12"/>Before <char style="add">the twins, Jacob and Esau</char>, were born, when neither one had yet done anything good or bad, <char style="add">God</char> said to Rebecca <char style="add">about the twins she was to bear</char>, “The older one shall later serve the younger one, <char style="add">contrary to normal custom</char>.” <char style="add">God said this</char> in order that <char style="add">we</char> might <char style="add">clearly</char> understand that what he purposed <char style="add">for people</char> was according to what he himself determined. That is, people’s <char style="add">eternal destiny</char> does not depend on what they do. Instead, their destiny depends on <char style="add">God</char>, the one who chooses them. <verse eid="ROM 9:11-12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 9:13"/>And <char style="add">this teaching is</char> ◄<char style="add">supported/shown to be true</char>► <char style="add">by</char> what is written <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char> {what <char style="add">a prophet</char> recorded} <char style="add">that God said</char>: “I favored Jacob, <char style="add">the younger son</char>. I did not favor [HYP] Esau, <char style="add">the older son</char>.”<verse eid="ROM 9:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">As the Scriptures indicate, God’s choosing people depends not on their wishes or efforts. He helps whomever he wants to help, and he makes stubborn whomever he wants to make stubborn. We cannot conclude that God is unjust in choosing the ones he wants to choose.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 9:14-18">Romans 9:14-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 9:14"/>
    <char style="add">Someone</char> might say, “◄Is God unjust <char style="add">by choosing the ones he wants to choose?/I think</char> that God is unjust <char style="add">by choosing the ones he wants to choose!</char>►” [RHQ] <char style="add">I would reply</char>, “<char style="add">He is</char> certainly not <char style="add">unjust</char>!” <verse eid="ROM 9:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 9:15"/>God told Moses, “I will pity and help anyone whom I choose [DOU]!” <verse eid="ROM 9:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 9:16"/>So <char style="add">God chooses people</char>, not because they want <char style="add">God to choose them</char> or because they try hard <char style="add">to do things so that he</char> will <char style="add">accept them</char>. Instead he chooses people because he himself has mercy <char style="add">on undeserving ones</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 9:17"/><char style="add">Moses</char> recorded [PRS] <char style="add">that God had told</char> Pharaoh, “This is why I gave you <char style="add">(sg)</char> authority [MTY]: It was in order that I might show <char style="add">by how I oppose</char> you <char style="add">how exceedingly</char> powerful I am, and in order that people everywhere [HYP] would hear about me [MTY].” <verse eid="ROM 9:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 9:18"/>So <char style="add">we conclude that God</char> kindly helps the ones he wants to act kindly towards. But he makes stubborn the ones <char style="add">such as Pharaoh</char> that he wants <char style="add">to make stubborn</char>.<verse eid="ROM 9:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">My reply to anyone’s objection to this doctrine is that God has a right to carry out his purposes; he tolerated the people who caused him to be angry, in order that he might disclose how gloriously he acts toward those on whom he intends to have mercy.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 9:19-29">Romans 9:19-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 9:19"/>
    <char style="add">One of</char> you may <char style="add">object to this by</char> saying to me, “<char style="add">Because God determines ahead of time everything that people do, that also implies that he wants us to do everything that we do</char>. ◄No one has resisted what God has willed!/Who has resisted what God has willed?► [RHQ] Therefore, ◄it would not be right that God would still condemn <char style="add">a person for having sinned</char>!/why does God still condemn <char style="add">a person for having sinned</char>?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="ROM 9:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 9:20"/><char style="add">I would reply that since</char> you <char style="add">(sg)</char> are <char style="add">just a</char> human being, ◄you do not <char style="add">have any right at all to</char> criticize God!/<char style="add">who are you to</char> say that what God does is wrong?► [RHQ] <char style="add">As a potter is the one who creates a clay pot, God is the one who created you</char>. ◄A clay pot [MET] certainly would not <char style="add">have a right to criticize</char> the potter by asking [PRS], “Why did you <char style="add">(sg)</char> make me this way?”/Would a clay pot <char style="add">have a right to criticize</char> the potter by asking [PRS], “Why did you <char style="add">(sg)</char> make me this way?”► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 9:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 9:21"/>Instead, ◄the potter certainly has the right to <char style="add">take</char> some clay and from one lump <char style="add">of clay</char> make one pot that people will honor and <char style="add">make another</char> one for ordinary purposes [MET]./does not a potter have the right to <char style="add">take</char> some clay and from one lump <char style="add">of clay</char> make one pot that people will honor and <char style="add">make another</char> pot for ordinary purposes?► [MET, RHQ] <char style="add">Similarly, God has the right to carry out what he purposes for people</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 9:22"/>Although God desires to show that he is angry <char style="add">about sin</char>, and <char style="add">although he desires to</char> make clear that he can powerfully <char style="add">punish people who have sinned</char>, he tolerated very patiently the people [MET] who caused him to be angry and who deserved to be destroyed (OR, who were made to be destroyed). <verse eid="ROM 9:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 9:23"/><char style="add">God has been patient</char> in order that he might make clear how very wonderfully <char style="add">he acts toward those</char> [MET] whom he intended to act mercifully towards and whom he prepared ahead of time in order that they might <char style="add">live</char> gloriously <char style="add">in heaven</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 9:24"/>That means us whom he chose—not only <char style="add">us</char> Jews but also non-Jews. <verse eid="ROM 9:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 9:25"/><char style="add">These words that</char> Hosea wrote [MTY] that <char style="add">God</char> said also ◄show that God has the right/<char style="add">support God’s right</char>► <char style="add">to choose from among both Jews and non-Jews</char> [MTY]:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:25">I will declare that many people who were not my people are now my people. I will declare that many people whom I did not love [HYP] before, I love now.<verse eid="ROM 9:25"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 9:26"/>And <char style="add">another prophet wrote</char>:</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ROM 9:26">What will happen is that in the places where <char style="add">God</char> told them before, “You are not my people,” in those same places <char style="add">people</char> will declare truthfully that they are children of God, who is completely powerful.<verse eid="ROM 9:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 9:27"/>Isaiah also exclaimed concerning the Israelites:</para>
  <para style="q2" vid="ROM 9:27">Even though the Israelites are <char style="add">so many that no one can count them, like</char> sand <char style="add">particles on the beach beside</char> the ocean, <char style="add">only</char> a small part of them will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save <char style="add">only</char> a small part of them}, <verse eid="ROM 9:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 9:28"/>because the Lord will punish completely and speedily the <char style="add">people who live on </char> this earth, as he said that he would do.<verse eid="ROM 9:28"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 9:29"/>
    <char style="add">Also, we can understand from what the prophet</char> Isaiah said <char style="add">that God would not save</char> anyone if he did not show mercy:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:29">If the Lord, who controls everything in heaven, had not mercifully allowed some of our descendants to survive, we would have become like the people of <char style="add">the cities of</char> Sodom and Gomorrah, who were [SIM, DOU] completely destroyed.<verse eid="ROM 9:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The non-Jews found the way by which God could declare them righteous. The Jews did not succeed in fulfilling what the Mosaic laws require. Instead, they tried to find a way to be declared righteous by doing things in order that God would accept them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 9:30-33">Romans 9:30-33</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 9:30"/>We must conclude this: [RHQ] Although non-Jews did not search out <char style="add">a way by which</char> God would erase the record of their sins, they actually found that way because they trusted <char style="add">in what Christ did for them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 9:31"/>But although <char style="add">the people of</char> Israel sought a basis <char style="add">by which God would</char> erase the record of their sins, they did not succeed in <char style="add">fulfilling the true purpose of the</char> laws <char style="add">that God gave to Moses</char>. <verse eid="ROM 9:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 9:32"/>The reason [RHQ] <char style="add">that they did not succeed</char> is that they did not trust that <char style="add">God would provide a way to save them</char>. Instead, they were trying to do certain things <char style="add">in order that God would accept them. Because they did not expect the Messiah to die, the Israelites</char> felt disgusted about <char style="add">Jesus’ death, which is like</char> the stone [MET] on which people stumble. <verse eid="ROM 9:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 9:33"/>This is what <char style="add">a prophet</char> predicted when he wrote these words that <char style="add">God said about the Messiah</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 9:33">Listen! I am placing in Israel [MTY] <char style="add">one who is like</char> a stone [MET] on which people will stumble. What he does will offend people [DOU]. Nevertheless, those who believe in him will not be disappointed.<verse eid="ROM 9:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 9"/>
  <chapter number="10" style="c" sid="ROM 10"/>
  <para style="s1">My deep desire and earnest prayer is that God will save the Jews, who do not understand how to seek him correctly.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 10:1-4">Romans 10:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 10:1"/>My fellow believers, what I deeply desire and what I pray to God earnestly for is that he will save <char style="add">my own people</char>, <char style="add">the Jews</char>. <verse eid="ROM 10:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 10:2"/>I declare truthfully about them that although they ◄zealously seek/very much want to know► God, they do not understand <char style="add">how to seek/know him correctly</char>. <verse eid="ROM 10:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 10:3"/>They did not ◄submit themselves to/accept► the way that God erases the record of people’s sins. They did not <char style="add">want to</char> recognize <char style="add">that way</char> because they wanted him to do it their own way. <verse eid="ROM 10:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 10:4"/>They wanted God to erase the record of their sins <char style="add">as a result of their obeying his laws. But</char> because of what Christ has done, it is no longer necessary for <char style="add">people to obey</char> the laws <char style="add">God gave Moses in order for the record of their sins to be erased</char>. Now God will erase the record of sins of everyone who trusts <char style="add">in what Christ has done</char>.<verse eid="ROM 10:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The message of Scripture is that those who confess publicly that Jesus is their Lord and who believe inwardly that God brought Jesus back to life will be saved, because God accepts people only because of their faith, Jews and non-Jews alike.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 10:5-13">Romans 10:5-13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 10:5"/>In regard to <char style="add">the old</char> way, Moses wrote <char style="add">concerning people who obey God’s</char> laws, “It is the people who have done <char style="add">perfectly</char> the things <char style="add">that the laws require</char> who will gain <char style="add">eternal</char> life by <char style="add">doing</char> them.” <verse eid="ROM 10:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 10:6"/>But those whose record of sins God has erased as a result of their believing <char style="add">in Christ</char> can say <char style="add">to anyone</char> [PRS] <char style="add">as Moses said</char>, “You should not <char style="add">critically</char> think inwardly, ‘◄Someone will have to go up and enter heaven!/Who will go up and enter heaven?►’ [RHQ]” That is to say, someone will have to <char style="add">go up and</char> bring Christ down <char style="add">to bring the message of salvation to us</char>! <verse eid="ROM 10:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 10:7"/>“Or <char style="add">you should not think inwardly</char>, ‘◄Someone will have to go down and enter the place where <char style="add">the spirits</char> of dead persons are!/Who will go down and enter the place where <char style="add">the spirits</char> of dead persons are?►’ [RHQ]” That is to say, someone will have to <char style="add">go down and</char> bring Christ up <char style="add">from there to bring the message of salvation to us. You should not say that because Christ has already come down to save us, and has already become alive after he died</char>! <verse eid="ROM 10:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 10:8"/>But instead, <char style="add">those who believe in Christ</char> [PRS] can say what [RHQ] <char style="add">Moses also said</char>, “You <char style="add">(sg)</char> can find out about <char style="add">God’s</char> message very easily. You can speak [MTY] about it; you can think [MTY] about it.” This is the message that we proclaim, that people must believe <char style="add">in Christ</char>. <verse eid="ROM 10:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 10:9"/><char style="add">This message is that</char> if anyone of you confesses/says publicly that Jesus is Lord, and if you <char style="add">(sg)</char> believe that God ◄caused him to become alive again after he died/raised him from the dead►, you will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save you}. <verse eid="ROM 10:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 10:10"/>If people believe <char style="add">that Christ died and that God caused him to become alive again</char> [CHI], the result is that <char style="add">God will erase the record of their sins</char>. And <char style="add">for</char> those who state/declare publicly <char style="add">that Jesus is their Lord</char>, the result is that <char style="add">God</char> will save them. <verse eid="ROM 10:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 10:11"/><char style="add">It is written</char> {<char style="add">Isaiah wrote</char>} in the Scriptures [PRS] <char style="add">about the Messiah</char>, “Whoever believes in him will not be disappointed.” <verse eid="ROM 10:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 10:12"/><char style="add">God</char> treats Jews and non-Jews similarly. Because he is the same Lord for all people <char style="add">who believe in him</char>, he abundantly <char style="add">blesses</char> all who ask him <char style="add">to save them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 10:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 10:13"/>This is <char style="add">just like what the prophet Joel wrote</char>: “All those who ask the Lord <char style="add">God</char> to save them will be saved {The Lord <char style="add">God</char> will save all those who ask him to save them}.”<verse eid="ROM 10:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">There may be those who object by saying, “If God does not send someone to preach to the Jews, they cannot ask Christ to save them.” My reply to them is that God has already sent people to preach about Christ to them, but most of the Jews have not accepted the gospel. However, some Jews do believe in Christ, and many other people are indeed hearing the message.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 10:14-17">Romans 10:14-17</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 10:14"/>
    <char style="add">In regard to the people of Israel rejecting the gospel, some people might object by saying</char>, (OR, <char style="add">This raises another problem about the Jews</char>:) “◄They certainly cannot ask <char style="add">Christ to save them</char> if they have not <char style="add">first</char> believed <char style="add">in him</char>!/How can they ask <char style="add">Christ to help/save them</char> if they have not <char style="add">first</char> believed <char style="add">in him</char>?► [RHQ] And ◄they certainly cannot believe <char style="add">in him</char> if they have not heard about him!/how can they believe <char style="add">in him</char> if they have not heard about him?► [RHQ] And ◄they certainly cannot hear <char style="add">about him</char> if someone does not preach to them <char style="add">about him</char>!/how can they hear <char style="add">about him</char> if someone does not preach to them <char style="add">about him</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 10:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 10:15"/>And those who preach to them <char style="add">about Christ</char>, ◄certainly cannot preach if they are not sent <char style="add">by God</char> {if <char style="add">God</char> does not send them} <char style="add">to preach!</char>/how can they preach if they are not sent <char style="add">by God</char> {if <char style="add">God</char> does not send them} <char style="add">to preach</char>?► [RHQ] <char style="add">His sending messengers to them would be</char> just like it is written {like someone wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>, ‘The arrival [MTY] of those who preach the good message is wonderful!’ ” <verse eid="ROM 10:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 10:16"/><char style="add">I would reply in this way to people who say such things: God has indeed sent people to preach the message about Christ</char>. But not all <char style="add">the people of Israel</char> have paid attention to the good message! <char style="add">It is like what</char> Isaiah said <char style="add">when he felt very discouraged</char>, “Lord, it seems as if hardly anyone believed what they heard us <char style="add">(exc)</char> preach! [RHQ]” <verse eid="ROM 10:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 10:17"/>So then, <char style="add">I tell you that people</char> are believing <char style="add">in Christ</char> as a result of hearing <char style="add">the message about him</char>, and people are hearing <char style="add">the message</char> as a result of <char style="add">people</char> preaching <char style="add">about</char> Christ!<verse eid="ROM 10:17"/></para>
  <para style="s1">In reply to a question of whether the Jews have heard or understood about Christ, I would say that, as is supported by the Scriptures, they have heard it and should have understood it, because even non-Jews, who were not searching for God, understood it.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 10:18-21">Romans 10:18-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 10:18"/>But <char style="add">if someone were to</char> ask, “Have not <char style="add">the people of Israel</char> heard <char style="add">the message about God?</char>” <char style="add">I would reply that they</char> certainly <char style="add">have heard it</char>! It is like <char style="add">what is written in the Psalms</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 10:18">
    <char style="add">People living</char> all over the world [PRS, MTY] <char style="add">have seen the stars</char>, and what they indicate <char style="add">about God’s character has reached people living in</char> the most remote places in the world [DOU]!<verse eid="ROM 10:18"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 10:19"/>But <char style="add">someone might ask</char>, “<char style="add">Is it true that the people of</char> [MTY] Israel understood <char style="add">the message about Christ</char>?” <char style="add">I would reply that certainly they understood it, but they rejected it! Remember that</char> Moses was the first <char style="add">one who warned the people of Israel about disobeying God. He told them that God said</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 10:19">
    <char style="add">You consider that</char> non-Jewish groups are not nations at all [CHI]. But some of them <char style="add">will believe in me, and I will bless them</char>. Then you will envy them. I will cause you to be angry with those people whom <char style="add">you Jews think</char> do not understand <char style="add">my ways</char> [IRO].<verse eid="ROM 10:19"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 10:20"/>Remember also <char style="add">what God</char> said <char style="add">very</char> boldly to Isaiah:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 10:20">Non-Jews who did not ◄try to know/seek► me will surely find me [DOU]!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 10:20">I will surely reveal what I am like to those who did not ask for me!<verse eid="ROM 10:20"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 10:21"/>But concerning <char style="add">the people of</char> Israel, <char style="add">Isaiah</char> tells <char style="add">us that God said</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 10:21">For a long time I have held out my arms to people who disobeyed and rebelled against me, <char style="add">in order</char> to invite them to return to me.<verse eid="ROM 10:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 10"/>
  <chapter number="11" style="c" sid="ROM 11"/>
  <para style="s1">God has certainly not rejected all Jews. I am evidence of that. Just like in the past, there is also at the present time a small group of us Jews who have become believers.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 11:1-6">Romans 11:1-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 11:1"/>Because of that, <char style="add">if anyone should ask</char>, “Has God rejected his people <char style="add">the Jews?” I would declare that</char> he certainly has not <char style="add">rejected all of us! You can realize that by remembering that</char> I also belong to the <char style="add">people of</char> Israel. I am a descendant of Abraham, and I belong to the tribe of Benjamin, <char style="add">but God has not rejected me</char>! <verse eid="ROM 11:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 11:2"/>No, God has not rejected his people, whom he chose long ago <char style="add">to be people whom he would bless in a special way</char>. Remember [RHQ] what is written [PRS] in the Scriptures about Elijah when he <char style="add">mistakenly</char> complained to God about <char style="add">the people of</char> Israel, saying, <verse eid="ROM 11:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 11:3"/>“Lord, they have killed <char style="add">the rest of</char> your <char style="add">(sg)</char> prophets, they have destroyed your altars. I am the only one <char style="add">who believes in you</char> who remains <char style="add">alive</char>, and now they are trying to kill me!” <verse eid="ROM 11:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 11:4"/>God answered him like this: “<char style="add">You(sg) are not the only one who believes in me</char>! I have protected for myself <char style="add">not just you, but</char> 7,000 <char style="add">other</char> men who have not worshipped <char style="add">the false god</char> Baal. ◄Remember that!/Do you not remember that?► [RHQ]” <verse eid="ROM 11:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 11:5"/>So, similarly, there is also at this time a small group <char style="add">of us Jews</char> who have become <char style="add">believers. God</char> has chosen us <char style="add">to become believers</char> (OR, <char style="add">his people</char>) only because he acts kindly toward us, in ways that we do not deserve. <verse eid="ROM 11:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 11:6"/>Since it is because he acts kindly <char style="add">toward those whom he chooses, it is</char> not because they have done good things <char style="add">that he has chosen them</char>. If <char style="add">God chose people because they did good deeds</char>, then it would not be because he was acting toward them in a way that they did not deserve.<verse eid="ROM 11:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">The Scriptures confirm that the people of Israel as a whole did not find the way of being declared righteous, although those whom God had chosen did find it.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 11:7-10">Romans 11:7-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 11:7"/>
    <char style="add">Since God chose only some people of Israel</char>, <char style="add">this is what I conclude: [RHQ] Most of the people of</char> Israel did not find <char style="add">the way for him to erase the record of their sins</char>, even though some of them were earnestly looking for it. The <char style="add">people of Israel whom God had</char> chosen found it, but the rest <char style="add">of them</char> were {<char style="add">God</char>} made spiritually insensitive/unresponsive. <verse eid="ROM 11:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 11:8"/><char style="add">Our</char> fellow Jews are just like the <char style="add">ones</char> about whom Isaiah wrote,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:8">God ◄caused their senses to be dull/made them unable to think clearly►. Up to this very day, <char style="add">they have</char> eyes but they cannot see <char style="add">spiritually</char> [MET]. <char style="add">They have</char> ears, but they cannot understand <char style="add">spiritually</char> what they hear.<verse eid="ROM 11:8"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 11:9"/>And <char style="add">they remind me of what King</char> David said, <char style="add">when he asked God to cause his enemies’ senses to be dull</char> [MET],</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:9">
    <char style="add">Make them stupid</char> [MTY], <char style="add">like animals that are</char> caught in snares!</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:9">May they <char style="add">feel secure because of the things that they enjoy but which will catch them like a</char> trap [DOU, MET], with the result that you will destroy them.<verse eid="ROM 11:9"/></para>
  <para style="q1">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 11:10"/>May their ability to perceive <char style="add">danger</char> be dulled {Dull their ability to perceive <char style="add">spiritually</char>} [MET], with the result that they will not <char style="add">become alarmed</char> [MET] <char style="add">when there is danger</char>.</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:10">May you cause them to carry heavy loads on their backs continually <char style="add">as slaves do</char> [MTY].<verse eid="ROM 11:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">My reply to a question as to whether the result of the Jews’ unbelief is a permanent falling away from God is, “No! God is saving many non-Jews to make many Jews envious and seek to be saved.”</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 11:11-12">Romans 11:11-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 11:11"/>
    <char style="add">Perhaps someone will ask</char>, “<char style="add">When the Jews</char> sinned <char style="add">by not believing in Christ, did</char> it result in their separating themselves from God <char style="add">permanently?</char>” Then I <char style="add">would reply</char>, <char style="add">No</char>, they have certainly not <char style="add">separated themselves from God permanently</char>! What is happening is that because they sinned, <char style="add">God</char> is saving non-Jews in order to cause <char style="add">the Jews</char> to envy <char style="add">the way he blesses non-Jews and so ask Christ to save them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 11:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 11:12"/><char style="add">When the Jews</char> sinned (OR, rejected Christ), <char style="add">the result was that God</char> abundantly <char style="add">blessed other people in</char> [MTY] the world by <char style="add">offering them the opportunity to believe</char>. And <char style="add">when the Jews</char> failed <char style="add">spiritually, the result was that God</char> abundantly <char style="add">blessed</char> the non-Jews. Since that is true, think how wonderful it will be when the complete number <char style="add">of the Jews whom God has chosen will believe in Christ</char> [RHQ]!<verse eid="ROM 11:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I highly esteem the work that God has called me to do as an apostle among you non-Jews. I hope that I will make my fellow Jews jealous, and as a result, some of them will be saved.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 11:13-16">Romans 11:13-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 11:13"/>Now it is to you non-Jews that I am saying <char style="add">what follows</char>. I am the one who is the apostle to non-Jews, and I highly esteem this work <char style="add">that God appointed</char> me to do. <verse eid="ROM 11:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 11:14"/>But I also hope that <char style="add">by my labors</char> I will make my fellow Jews ◄jealous/want what you non-Jews have►, <char style="add">with the result that</char> some of them will <char style="add">believe and</char> be saved. <verse eid="ROM 11:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 11:15"/><char style="add">God</char> has rejected <char style="add">most of my fellow Jews because they refused to believe, with the result that</char> he reconciled <char style="add">many other people in</char> the world [MTY] <char style="add">to himself</char>. But he will accept <char style="add">my fellow Jews again when they trust in Christ</char>! And ◄this is what the result will be./do you know what the result will be?► [RHQ] It will be <char style="add">as though God is making them</char> alive again after they have been dead! <verse eid="ROM 11:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 11:16"/><char style="add">Just like</char> the whole lump <char style="add">of dough</char> will belong to God if <char style="add">people offer</char> to God [MET] the <char style="add">bread baked from</char> the first part <char style="add">of it</char> [MET], <char style="add">so the Jews will belong to God because their ancestors belonged to God</char>. And just like the branches <char style="add">of a tree</char> will be good if the roots are good [MET], <char style="add">so the descendants of our great Jewish ancestors who belonged to God will also some day belong to God</char>.<verse eid="ROM 11:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">You non-Jews who trust in Jesus must not despise the Jews whom God has rejected. You must not become proud, but instead beware. God will not spare you if you fall away from him, and he will certainly act kindly toward the Jews if they trust in Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 11:17-24">Romans 11:17-24</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 11:17"/>
    <char style="add">God has rejected</char> many of <char style="add">the Jews</char> [MET], <char style="add">like</char> branches <char style="add">of a tree</char> are broken off {<char style="add">like people</char> break off <char style="add">dead</char> branches <char style="add">of a tree</char>}. And each of you <char style="add">non-Jews whom God has accepted is like</char> [MET] <char style="add">a branch of</char> a wild/uncultivated olive tree <char style="add">that</char> was {<char style="add">that someone</char>} grafted among the branches (OR, onto one of the branches) <char style="add">that were left on a cultivated olive tree</char>. <char style="add">God has caused</char> you <char style="add">to benefit from how he blessed our(exc) first Jewish ancestors, as branches</char> benefit from the nutritious sap from the roots of a <char style="add">cultivated</char> olive tree [MET]. <verse eid="ROM 11:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 11:18"/>However, you <char style="add">non-Jews</char> must not despise <char style="add">the Jews whom God rejected</char> [MET], <char style="add">who are like</char> the branches that <char style="add">were broken off from the tree</char> If any of you <char style="add">wants to</char> boast <char style="add">about having received blessings from God</char>, <char style="add">remember this: Branches</char> do not nourish the roots. Instead the roots nourish <char style="add">the branches</char> [MET]. <char style="add">Similarly, you are blessed by God because of what</char> you <char style="add">have received from the Jews! It is not what the Jews have received from</char> you <char style="add">that blesses them</char> [MET]! <verse eid="ROM 11:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 11:19"/>If one of you then says, “<char style="add">God rejected the Jews</char> [MET] <char style="add">like</char> branches [MET] that are broken {that people broke} off <char style="add">a tree and rejected</char>, in order that <char style="add">he might accept us non-Jews, as</char> branches [MET] of a tree are grafted in {<char style="add">as people</char> graft in branches of a tree},” <verse eid="ROM 11:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 11:20"/><char style="add">I would reply that</char> this is true. However, it is because the Jews did not believe <char style="add">in Christ</char> that they were rejected [MET] {that <char style="add">God</char> rejected [MET] them}. As for you, it is <char style="add">only</char> because you believe <char style="add">in Christ</char> that <char style="add">God has accepted</char> you! <char style="add">So</char> do not <char style="add">any of you</char> become proud, but instead beware <char style="add">of what could happen to you</char> <verse eid="ROM 11:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 11:21"/>Since God did not spare <char style="add">the unbelieving Jews</char> [MET] <char style="add">who were like a tree’s</char> natural branches, he will not spare any of you <char style="add">if you do</char> not <char style="add">keep trusting in him</char>!<verse eid="ROM 11:21"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 11:22"/>Note then, that God acts kindly, but he also acts severely. He has acted severely toward <char style="add">the Jews</char> who have stopped trusting in him. On the other hand, he acts kindly toward each of you <char style="add">non-Jews only</char> if you continue <char style="add">to appreciate his acting</char> kindly <char style="add">toward you</char>. However, you will be rejected {<char style="add">he</char> will reject you} if you do not <char style="add">keep trusting in him</char>. <verse eid="ROM 11:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 11:23"/>And if the Jews believe <char style="add">in Christ</char> [LIT], God also will <char style="add">reunite them to himself as</char> branches are grafted {<char style="add">as people</char> graft branches} into <char style="add">a tree again</char>, because God is able to do that. <verse eid="ROM 11:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 11:24"/>Each of you <char style="add">non-Jews who were previously separated from God has benefited from the ways in which God blessed the Jews</char> [MET]. <char style="add">That is like taking branches</char> that have been cut {that someone has cut} from a wild olive tree that just grew <char style="add">without being planted</char> {<char style="add">someone planting it</char>} and, contrary to what people usually do, grafting them into a cultivated olive tree. So God will much more readily <char style="add">receive back the Jews because they belonged to him before</char> [MET]! <char style="add">That will be like</char> the original branches <char style="add">that had been cut off</char> being grafted {like grafting the original branches <char style="add">that someone cut off</char>,} back into the olive tree to which they <char style="add">originally belonged</char>!<verse eid="ROM 11:24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I want you to know that all the people of Israel will some day be saved, as the Scriptures say will happen. God still loves them because of their ancestors. It is his purpose to act mercifully towards them as well as toward all non-Jews.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 11:25-33">Romans 11:25-33</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 11:25"/>My <char style="add">non-Jewish</char> fellow believers, I certainly want you to understand [LIT] this truth that God has now revealed <char style="add">about my fellow Jews who are refusing to believe</char>. You should not proudly think <char style="add">that</char> God <char style="add">now favors you</char> more <char style="add">than the Jews</char> (OR, <char style="add">that you understand God’s further plans for the Jews</char>). Many <char style="add">people of</char> Israel will continue to be stubborn until all the non-Jews <char style="add">whom God has chosen have believed in Jesus</char>. <verse eid="ROM 11:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 11:26"/>And then all [HYP] <char style="add">the people of</char> Israel will be saved {<char style="add">God</char> will save all [HYP] <char style="add">the people of</char> Israel}. Then these words that are written {that <char style="add">a prophet</char> wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures will</char> ◄<char style="add">become true/be fulfilled</char>►:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:26">The one who sets <char style="add">his people</char> free will originate from <char style="add">the place where</char> God dwells (OR, from the Jews) [MTY]. Then he will remove the guilt of the Israelite people (OR, descendants of Jacob) [MTY].<verse eid="ROM 11:26"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 11:27"/>And <char style="add">as God says</char>,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="ROM 11:27">The contract that I will make with them is that I will forgive their sins.<verse eid="ROM 11:27"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 11:28"/>With regard to <char style="add">the Jews rejecting</char> the good message <char style="add">about Christ, God treats</char> them as enemies, which has benefited you <char style="add">non-Jews</char>. But in regard to <char style="add">their being the people whom God</char> chose, <char style="add">God still</char> loves them because of <char style="add">what he promised</char> their ancestors. <verse eid="ROM 11:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 11:29"/><char style="add">He still loves them</char>, because he never changed his mind about the privileges/blessings he <char style="add">gave to them</char> and about his choosing <char style="add">them to be his people</char>. <verse eid="ROM 11:29"/><verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 11:30"/>You <char style="add">non-Jews</char> once disobeyed God, but now he has acted mercifully towards you because the <char style="add">Jews</char> disobeyed him. <verse eid="ROM 11:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 11:31"/>Now the Jews have disobeyed God. The result is that by the very same way in which he acted mercifully towards you, he will act mercifully towards them <char style="add">again</char>. <verse eid="ROM 11:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 11:32"/>God has declared and proved that all people, <char style="add">both Jews and non-Jews</char> [MET], disobey ◄<char style="add">him/his laws</char>►. He has declared that because he wants to act mercifully towards us all.<verse eid="ROM 11:32"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I marvel at how great God’s wisdom and knowledge are, and his decisions and actions toward us!</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 11:33-36">Romans 11:33-36</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 11:33"/>
    <char style="add">I marvel how</char> vast and great are the wise things that God <char style="add">has done</char> and what he has <char style="add">always</char> known [DOU]! We are completely unable to understand the things that he has decided and the ways <char style="add">in which he acts toward us</char> [DOU]! <verse eid="ROM 11:33"/><verse number="34" style="v" sid="ROM 11:34"/><char style="add">I remember the Scriptures that say</char>,</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 11:34">◄No one has known what the Lord thinks./Who has known what the Lord thinks?► [RHQ] ◄Absolutely no one has given him advice <char style="add">about what he should do!</char>/Who has advised him <char style="add">about what he should do</char>?► [RHQ]<verse eid="ROM 11:34"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="35" style="v" sid="ROM 11:35"/>And,</para>
  <para style="pi1" vid="ROM 11:35">◄No one has given anything to God that <char style="add">he did not previously receive from God!</char>/Has anyone given anything to God that <char style="add">he did not previously receive from God</char>?► [RHQ] So God ◄is not obligated to/does not have to► pay back anything to anyone!<verse eid="ROM 11:35"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="36" style="v" sid="ROM 11:36"/>God <char style="add">is the one who created</char> all things. He is also the one who <char style="add">sustains all things</char>. The reason that he created them was that <char style="add">everything he created might praise</char> him. May <char style="add">all people</char> honor him forever! ◄May it be so!/Amen!►<verse eid="ROM 11:36"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 11"/>
  <chapter number="12" style="c" sid="ROM 12"/>
  <para style="s1">I appeal to you that you present yourselves to God by making yourselves like living sacrifices, which is the appropriate way to serve him. Do not let anything non-Christian determine how you act, but instead let God change your way of thinking.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 12:1-2">Romans 12:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 12:1"/>My fellow believers, since God has acted mercifully <char style="add">toward you</char> in so many ways, I appeal to <char style="add">all of</char> you that you present yourselves [SYN] <char style="add">to him by making yourselves like</char> holy sacrifices [MET]. <char style="add">Make yourselves sacrifices</char> that he is pleased with, sacrifices that are living/alive, <char style="add">not ones that are dead/killed. Since God has done so much for you/us</char>, this is the <char style="add">only</char> appropriate way to serve him. <verse eid="ROM 12:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 12:2"/>Do not let anything non-Christian determine how you should act. Instead, let God change your <char style="add">way of life</char> by making your way of thinking new, in order that you may know what he wants you to do. That is, you will know what is good, and you will know what pleases <char style="add">God</char>, and you will know how to be all that he wants you to be.<verse eid="ROM 12:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not think about yourselves more highly than you should. Instead, think about yourselves sensibly, in a way that corresponds to the abilities that God has given to you because you trust in Christ. May we do diligently and cheerfully what God has given us the ability to do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 12:3-8">Romans 12:3-8</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 12:3"/>Because God has kindly appointed me <char style="add">to be his apostle</char>, which I did not deserve, I say this to every one of you: Do not think about yourselves more highly than what is right for you to think! Instead, think <char style="add">about yourselves</char> in a sensible way that <char style="add">corresponds to the abilities</char> that God has given you <char style="add">because</char> you trust <char style="add">in Christ</char>. <verse eid="ROM 12:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 12:4"/>Although a person has one body, it consists of many parts. All of the parts are needed for <char style="add">the body</char>, but they do not all function the same way. <verse eid="ROM 12:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 12:5"/>Similarly we, <char style="add">although we are</char> many, are <char style="add">united into</char> one group because of our relationship with Christ, and we belong to one another. <char style="add">So no one should act as though he</char> is needed by God more <char style="add">than others are!</char> <verse eid="ROM 12:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 12:6"/><char style="add">Instead</char>, since each one of us can do various things that differ according to the abilities that <char style="add">God has</char> given to us, <char style="add">we should do them diligently and cheerfully</char>! Those whom <char style="add">God has enabled</char> to speak messages from him <char style="add">should speak</char> what corresponds to what they believe <char style="add">God told them</char>. <verse eid="ROM 12:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 12:7"/><char style="add">Those whom God has enabled</char> to serve <char style="add">others</char> should do that. <char style="add">Those whom God has enabled</char> to teach <char style="add">his truth</char> should do that. <verse eid="ROM 12:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 12:8"/>Those <char style="add">whom God has enabled to</char> encourage/exhort <char style="add">his people</char> should do that. Those who share <char style="add">their goods/money with others</char> should do it sincerely/generously. Those who lead <char style="add">the congregation</char> should do it wholeheartedly. Those who help the needy should do it cheerfully.<verse eid="ROM 12:8"/></para>
  <para style="s1">In the various ways in which you act toward people, love them sincerely.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 12:9-18">Romans 12:9-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 12:9"/>Love others sincerely! Hate what is evil! Continue to eagerly do what <char style="add">God considers to be</char> good! <verse eid="ROM 12:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 12:10"/>Love one another as members of the same family do; and, you should be ◄the first ones/eager► to honor each other! <verse eid="ROM 12:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 12:11"/>Do not be lazy. <char style="add">Instead</char>, be eager <char style="add">to serve the Lord</char> God! <verse eid="ROM 12:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 12:12"/>Rejoice because you are confidently awaiting <char style="add">what God will do for you</char>! When you suffer, be patient! Keep praying and never give up! <verse eid="ROM 12:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 12:13"/>If any of God’s people lacks anything, share with them <char style="add">what you have</char>! Readily take care of <char style="add">travelers who need a place to stay</char>! <verse eid="ROM 12:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 12:14"/><char style="add">Ask God to</char> be kind to those who ◄persecute you/cause you to suffer► <char style="add">because you believe in Jesus! Ask him to</char> be kind to them; do not <char style="add">ask him to</char> cause bad things to happen to them. <verse eid="ROM 12:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 12:15"/>If someone is joyful, you should rejoice also! If someone is sad, you should also be sad! <verse eid="ROM 12:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 12:16"/>Desire for others what you desire for yourselves (OR, Live harmoniously with each other)! Do not do things because you want to be <char style="add">famous</char>! Instead, be content to do <char style="add">tasks that others consider that only</char> unimportant people do (OR, <char style="add">to associate with unimportant</char> people). Do not consider yourselves wise. <verse eid="ROM 12:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 12:17"/>Do not do something evil to anyone <char style="add">who has done</char> something evil to you. Act in a way that all people will recognize as good! <verse eid="ROM 12:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 12:18"/>Live peacefully with other people whenever it is possible, to the extent that you <char style="add">can influence the situation</char>.<verse eid="ROM 12:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Instead of avenging yourselves, allow God to avenge you; and instead of being overcome by something evil done to you, overcome evil deeds by doing good to those who do evil to you, because this is what the Scriptures command.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 12:19-21">Romans 12:19-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 12:19"/>
    <char style="add">My fellow believers</char> whom I love, do not do something evil in return when people do something evil to you! Instead, allow <char style="add">God</char> to punish them [MTY], because it is {someone has} written <char style="add">in the Scriptures that</char> the Lord <char style="add">said</char>, “‘It is my responsibility to take revenge; I am the one who will punish <char style="add">people who do something something evil to you</char> [DOU],’ says the Lord.” <verse eid="ROM 12:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 12:20"/>Instead of <char style="add">doing something evil to those who have done something evil to you</char>, <char style="add">do as the Scriptures teach</char>: “If your <char style="add">(sg)</char> enemies are hungry, feed them! If they are thirsty, give them something to drink! By doing that, you <char style="add">(sg)</char> will cause them to feel ashamed <char style="add">and perhaps they will change their attitude toward you</char> [IDM].” <verse eid="ROM 12:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 12:21"/>Do not let evil <char style="add">things that others have done to you</char> overcome you <char style="add">(sg) by making you do evil things to them!</char> [PRS] Instead, overcome the evil <char style="add">things that they have done</char> by <char style="add">doing</char> good <char style="add">deeds to them</char>!<verse eid="ROM 12:21"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 12"/>
  <chapter number="13" style="c" sid="ROM 13"/>
  <para style="s1">Be subject to civil authorities, because those who oppose them oppose what God has established and will bring punishment on themselves. Do what is good and then they will commend you. Give to all the authorities what you are obligated to give to them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 13:1-7">Romans 13:1-7</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 13:1"/>Every <char style="add">believer</char> must be subject to the authorities. <char style="add">Remember that</char> God is the only one <char style="add">who gives officials their</char> authority. Furthermore, those officials that exist are ones who have been appointed by God {God has appointed}. <verse eid="ROM 13:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 13:2"/>So whoever resists the officials is resisting what God has established. Furthermore, those who resist officials will bring on themselves <char style="add">from the officials</char> the punishment <char style="add">that God considers fitting</char>. <verse eid="ROM 13:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 13:3"/>What rulers <char style="add">do</char> is not <char style="add">to cause people who</char> do good deeds to be afraid. Instead, <char style="add">what they do is to cause people who do</char> evil to be afraid. So, if any of you [RHQ] wants to be unafraid of officials, do what is good! <char style="add">If you(sg) do good</char>, they will commend you <char style="add">instead of punishing you!</char> <verse eid="ROM 13:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 13:4"/>It is in order to serve God <char style="add">by doing their work that every official exists</char>, in order that they may benefit each of you. If any of you does what is evil, you <char style="add">(sg) will rightfully have reason to</char> be afraid, because the authority that they have to punish people [MTY] is very real [LIT]! The officials exist to serve God. That is, they act as God’s agents as they punish those who do evil. <verse eid="ROM 13:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 13:5"/>So, it is necessary for you <char style="add">(pl)</char> to be subject <char style="add">to officials</char>, not only because they will punish you [MTY] <char style="add">if you disobey them</char>, but also because you know <char style="add">that you should be subject to them</char> <verse eid="ROM 13:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 13:6"/>It is for this reason that you also pay taxes, because the officials are ones who serve God as they continually do their work. <verse eid="ROM 13:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 13:7"/>Give to all <char style="add">the officials</char> what you are supposed to give to them! Pay taxes to <char style="add">those who require that you pay taxes</char>. Pay duties <char style="add">on goods to those who require that you pay those</char> duties. Respect <char style="add">those who ought to</char> be respected. Honor <char style="add">those who ought to</char> be honored.<verse eid="ROM 13:7"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Do not leave any debt unpaid. Your only continual obligation is to love one another, because doing so fulfills all that God’s law requires.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 13:8-10">Romans 13:8-10</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 13:8"/>Pay all of your debts <char style="add">when you are supposed to pay them</char>. The only thing <char style="add">that is like</char> a debt that <char style="add">you</char> should never stop paying is to love one another. Whoever loves others has fulfilled all that <char style="add">God requires in</char> his laws. <verse eid="ROM 13:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 13:9"/><char style="add">There are many things that God</char> commanded <char style="add">in his laws, such as</char> do not commit adultery, do not murder <char style="add">anyone</char>, do not steal, and do not desire anything that belongs to someone else. But the command by which they are all summed up {that includes them all} is this: Each of you must love the people with whom you come in contact, just like you <char style="add">(sg)</char> love yourself. <verse eid="ROM 13:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 13:10"/>If you love people with whom you come in contact [PRS], you will not do any evil to them [LIT]. So, whoever loves <char style="add">others</char> fulfills all that <char style="add">God’s</char> laws <char style="add">require</char>.<verse eid="ROM 13:10"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because it is time for us to be fully alert and active, we must quit doing wicked deeds. We must do those things that will help us resist that which is evil, we must live properly, and we must be like Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 13:11-14">Romans 13:11-14</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 13:11"/>
    <char style="add">Do</char> what I have just told you, especially since you know <char style="add">the significance of</char> the time <char style="add">in which we are living. You know that it is</char> time for you to be <char style="add">fully alert and active</char> [MET], <char style="add">like people who have</char> awakened from sleeping [MET], because <char style="add">the time when Christ will finally</char> deliver us <char style="add">from this world’s pain/sin and sorrow</char> is near. That time ◄is closer than/was not so close► when we first believed <char style="add">in Christ</char>. <verse eid="ROM 13:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 13:12"/><char style="add">Our time to live in this world</char> [MTY] <char style="add">is almost ended</char> [MET], <char style="add">like</char> a night that is nearly ended. The time <char style="add">when Christ will return</char> [MTY] is near. So we must quit doing wicked deeds [MET] <char style="add">such as people do</char> in the darkness, and <char style="add">we must be doing the things that will help us resist Satan/evil</char> [MET], <char style="add">as soldiers who</char> put on their armor in the daytime <char style="add">get ready to resist their enemies</char>. <verse eid="ROM 13:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 13:13"/>We must behave properly, as though the time <char style="add">when Christ will return</char> [MTY] <char style="add">were already here</char>. We must not participate in drunken carousing [HEN]. We must not commit any kind of sexual immorality [MTY, DOU]. We must not quarrel. We must not be jealous <char style="add">of other people</char>. <verse eid="ROM 13:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 13:14"/>On the contrary, you/we should <char style="add">be like</char> the Lord Jesus Christ <char style="add">so that others will see that we belong to him</char>, just as <char style="add">people</char> put on <char style="add">special clothes so that others will see what group they belong to</char> [MET]. You/We should stop thinking about <char style="add">doing the things that your/our</char> self-directed nature desires.<verse eid="ROM 13:14"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 13"/>
  <chapter number="14" style="c" sid="ROM 14"/>
  <para style="s1">Accept those who are not sure whether they are permitted to do certain things. Anyone who thinks that it is all right to eat all kinds of food must not despise those who do not think that, and those who do not think that it is all right to eat certain foods must not condemn those who do, because God has accepted them.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 14:1-4">Romans 14:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 14:1"/>Accept those who are not sure <char style="add">whether God will permit them to do certain things some people think are wrong</char>. But <char style="add">when you accept them</char>, do not argue with them about what they think/their opinions. <verse eid="ROM 14:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 14:2"/>Some people believe that they may eat all <char style="add">kinds of food</char>. Others believe <char style="add">that God does not want them to eat certain things, so they</char> believe that they may not eat meat. <verse eid="ROM 14:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 14:3"/>Anyone who <char style="add">thinks that it is all right to</char> eat <char style="add">all kinds of food</char> must not despise those who <char style="add">think it is</char> not <char style="add">all right to</char> eat <char style="add">all kinds of food</char>. Anyone who <char style="add">thinks it is</char> not <char style="add">all right to</char> eat <char style="add">all kinds of food</char> must not ◄condemn/say that <char style="add">God</char> will punish► those who <char style="add">think that it is all right to</char> eat <char style="add">all kinds of food</char>, because God himself has accepted those people. <verse eid="ROM 14:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 14:4"/><char style="add">God is the master of us all, so</char> ◄<char style="add">he is the one who will decide whether those people have done wrong!/who are you to decide whether they have done wrong</char>?► [RHQ] <char style="add">Therefore</char>, you have no right [RHQ] to condemn those who eat everything, because they are <char style="add">also God’s servants! And just like</char> it is the servants’ own master who accepts or condemns [MTY] his servants, <char style="add">it is God who accepts or condemns us</char>. And <char style="add">believers</char> will be accepted <char style="add">by</char> the Lord {<char style="add">the Lord</char> will accept <char style="add">believers</char>} <char style="add">regardless of whether they eat meat or not</char>, because he is able to keep them <char style="add">trusting in him</char>.<verse eid="ROM 14:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Each person should be fully convinced about observing special days, thinking and deciding for himself and not for others. We should try to please God by everything we do.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 14:5-9">Romans 14:5-9</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 14:5"/>Some people regard certain days as <char style="add">holy</char> and think that the other <char style="add">days</char> are not <char style="add">holy</char>. Other people regard all days as <char style="add">equally suitable for worshipping God</char>. Each person should be fully convinced <char style="add">about such matters</char>, thinking and deciding for himself <char style="add">and not for others</char>. <verse eid="ROM 14:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 14:6"/>As for those who believe that they should worship on <char style="add">a certain</char> day <char style="add">of the week</char>, it is to <char style="add">honor</char> the Lord <char style="add">that they worship on that day</char>. And as for those who <char style="add">think that it is all right to</char> eat <char style="add">all kinds of food</char>, it is to <char style="add">honor</char> the Lord <char style="add">that they eat those foods</char>, as is clear from their thanking God <char style="add">for the food that they eat</char>. As for those who abstain from <char style="add">eating certain kinds of</char> food, it is to <char style="add">honor</char> the Lord that they do not eat <char style="add">those foods</char>, and they also thank God <char style="add">for the food that they do eat. So doing either of those things is not wrong in itself</char>. <verse eid="ROM 14:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 14:7"/>None of us should live <char style="add">merely</char> to <char style="add">please</char> ourselves, and none of us <char style="add">should choose when or how we will</char> die, <char style="add">merely</char> to <char style="add">please</char> ourselves. <verse eid="ROM 14:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 14:8"/>While we live, it is the Lord whom we belong to <char style="add">and should be trying to please, and not just ourselves</char>. And when we die, it is the Lord whom we should <char style="add">be trying to please</char>. So, while we live and also when we die, we should be trying to please the Lord to whom we belong, <char style="add">not just ourselves</char>, <verse eid="ROM 14:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 14:9"/>because the very purpose for which Christ died and became alive again is that he might be Lord whom all people should try to please, both of those who have already died and of those who are still living.<verse eid="ROM 14:9"/></para>
  <para style="s1">You should neither condemn nor despise your fellow believers who believe differently about religious regulations than you do, because it is God who will say whether he approves of what we have done.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 14:10-12">Romans 14:10-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 14:10"/>◄It is disgraceful that you <char style="add">who practice certain religious regulations</char> say that God will punish your fellow believers <char style="add">who do not practice those regulations</char>!/Why do you <char style="add">who practice certain religious regulations</char> say God will punish your fellow believers <char style="add">who do not practice such regulations</char>?► [RHQ] <char style="add">I say this because the time will come when</char> all of us will stand before God in order that he will say whether or not he approves [MTY] <char style="add">of what we have done</char>. So you <char style="add">who do not practice such regulations</char>, ◄should not despise your fellow believers <char style="add">who practice them</char>!/why do you despise your fellow believers <char style="add">who practice them</char>?► [RHQ] <verse eid="ROM 14:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 14:11"/><char style="add">We know this</char> because it is written {<char style="add">a prophet/Isaiah</char> wrote} <char style="add">what God has said</char>:</para>
  <para style="q1" vid="ROM 14:11">Everyone will bow down before me! That is as <char style="add">certain as the fact that</char> I live [IDM]! Everyone [SYN] will acknowledge <char style="add">that because I am</char> God, I have the <char style="add">right to judge and punish people.</char><verse eid="ROM 14:11"/></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 14:12"/>So <char style="add">it is clear that</char> it is God who will decide <char style="add">whether or not he approves of</char> what each of us has done.<verse eid="ROM 14:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Instead of condemning each other, decide not to do anything that might lead your fellow believer to sin by following your example and which would then cause others to speak evil of you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 14:13-18">Romans 14:13-18</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 14:13"/>Since <char style="add">it is God who will judge everyone</char>, we must stop saying that <char style="add">God should</char> punish some of our fellow believers! Instead, you/we should decide that you/we will not do anything that would <char style="add">be an example that might cause</char> fellow believers to stop trusting in God [DOU]. <verse eid="ROM 14:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 14:14"/>I am absolutely certain [DOU] because of <char style="add">my close relationship with</char> (OR, <char style="add">my belonging to</char>) the Lord Jesus that there is nothing that by itself is wrong <char style="add">to eat</char>. But if people think it is wrong to eat something, then to them it is wrong to eat it. <char style="add">So you should not encourage them to eat it</char>. <verse eid="ROM 14:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 14:15"/>If you <char style="add">eat</char> food [MET] that anyone for whom Christ died <char style="add">thinks that it is wrong to eat, that person might be encouraged</char> {<char style="add">you might be encouraging that person</char>} <char style="add">to do something that he believes is wrong. As a result, you might cause that</char> fellow believer <char style="add">to stop trusting in God</char>. In that way he would be ruined <char style="add">spiritually</char> just because you have stopped behaving as one who loves <char style="add">others should behave</char>! <verse eid="ROM 14:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 14:16"/>Similarly, do not <char style="add">do something that you think is</char> good if, <char style="add">as a result, your fellow believer would sin and then</char> others would speak evil <char style="add">of you who say that you are Christians</char>. <verse eid="ROM 14:16"/><verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 14:17"/>Letting God rule our lives [MET] does not mean <char style="add">that we must obey regulations about</char> eating or drinking <char style="add">something</char>! Instead, <char style="add">it means we must</char> live righteously, <char style="add">act</char> peacefully <char style="add">towards others</char>, and be joyful by <char style="add">the power of</char> the Holy Spirit. <verse eid="ROM 14:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 14:18"/>Those who serve Christ <char style="add">by acting</char> in such ways please God, and others will also respect them.<verse eid="ROM 14:18"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Try to do what will help fellow believers to be at peace with each other and to grow spiritually. Do not destroy what God has done in others’ lives as a result of your eating certain things.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 14:19-23">Romans 14:19-23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 14:19"/>So we should always eagerly try to <char style="add">live in a way that will cause</char> peace <char style="add">among fellow Christians</char>, and we should try to do what will help each other to mature <char style="add">spiritually</char>. <verse eid="ROM 14:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 14:20"/>Do not destroy what God has done <char style="add">in the life of any believer</char> just because of <char style="add">your eating certain kinds of</char> food [MET] <char style="add">which that person considers wrong to eat! God</char> permits us to eat every <char style="add">kind of food</char>. But if, by your eating <char style="add">certain kinds of food</char>, you encourage another person to sin <char style="add">by doing what he believes is wrong</char>, you are doing wrong. <verse eid="ROM 14:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 14:21"/>It is good neither to eat meat nor to drink wine, nor <char style="add">to do anything else at any time if it</char> will cause one of your fellow believers to stop trusting in God. <verse eid="ROM 14:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 14:22"/>Let God tell you <char style="add">what things are right for you to do, but do not try to force others to accept what you believe. God is</char> pleased with those who do what they know is right and as a result do not feel guilty <char style="add">concerning what they have done</char>, <char style="add">because they have done only</char> those things that they believe are right. <verse eid="ROM 14:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 14:23"/>But some believers are not certain <char style="add">that God will approve of their eating a certain kind of food</char>. So if they eat it, <char style="add">they think that God will punish</char> them. And they <char style="add">truly</char> will be punished {<char style="add">God truly</char> will punish them}, because <char style="add">they have done things that they</char> believe <char style="add">are not right</char>. Those who do anything without being certain <char style="add">that God considers it to be right</char> are sinning.<verse eid="ROM 14:23"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 14"/>
  <chapter number="15" style="c" sid="ROM 15"/>
  <para style="s1">We should not be irritated by the practices of those who are uncertain whether God will condemn them for doing certain things that the Mosaic laws forbid. Instead, we should do things that please our fellow Christians, because Christ has set us an example.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:1-4">Romans 15:1-4</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 15:1"/>Most of us are sure <char style="add">that God will not punish us for doing certain things that the laws and rituals God gave Moses said the Jews should not do. But we</char> should be patient with those who are uncertain <char style="add">about such things</char>, and we should not let them irritate us. We should not <char style="add">simply</char> please ourselves. <verse eid="ROM 15:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 15:2"/>Each of us should <char style="add">do the things that</char> please the fellow <char style="add">believers with whom we come in contact, and things that will</char> benefit them. <char style="add">We should do those things</char> in order to help them mature <char style="add">spiritually</char>. <verse eid="ROM 15:2"/><verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 15:3"/><char style="add">We should please our fellow believers</char>, since Christ <char style="add">has set us an example</char>. He did not <char style="add">do things to</char> please himself. On the contrary, <char style="add">he tried to please God even when others insulted him. That was</char> as it is written {as ◄<char style="add">someone/the Psalmist</char>► wrote} <char style="add">in Scripture that the Messiah said to God</char>: “When people insulted you <char style="add">(sg)</char>, <char style="add">it was as though</char> they were also insulting me.” <verse eid="ROM 15:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 15:4"/>And <char style="add">you need to remember that</char> what was written previously {what <char style="add">God’s servants</char> previously wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>, was written {<char style="add">they</char> wrote} to teach us in order that we would be patient and be encouraged by <char style="add">reading/believing </char> what they wrote. If we do that, we can confidently expect <char style="add">God to do for us all he has promised</char>.<verse eid="ROM 15:4"/></para>
  <para style="s1">May God enable you all to live harmoniously with each other.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:5-6">Romans 15:5-6</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 15:5"/>God is the one who enables us to be patient and encourages us. ◄<char style="add">Ask/Pray to</char>► <char style="add">him that he would</char> enable you <char style="add">all</char> to live harmoniously with each other, doing as Christ Jesus <char style="add">did</char>. <verse eid="ROM 15:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 15:6"/>Then, as you are united in what you think and say [MTY], you will praise God, <char style="add">who is the heavenly</char> father [MET] of our Lord Jesus Christ.<verse eid="ROM 15:6"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Accept each other as Christ has accepted you, remembering that what Christ has done was both to help the Jews and to cause non-Jews to praise God.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:7-12">Romans 15:7-12</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 15:7"/>So <char style="add">I say to all of you believers at Rome</char>, accept each other. <char style="add">If you do that</char>, people will praise God <char style="add">as they see you behaving like Christ. Accept each other</char> just like Christ accepted you! <verse eid="ROM 15:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 15:8"/>I want <char style="add">you to remember</char> that Christ <char style="add">helped us</char> Jews [MTY] by what he did, in order to show that God ◄is faithful/does what he says he will do►. That is, <char style="add">his coming as our Messiah</char> fulfilled what God promised to <char style="add">our Jewish</char> ancestors. <verse eid="ROM 15:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 15:9"/>And <char style="add">by acting mercifully to them, he also caused</char> non-Jews to praise him. <char style="add">What he has done for non-Jews</char> fulfills what is written <char style="add">in the Scriptures that David said to God</char>: “So I will praise you <char style="add">(sg) when I am</char> among the non-Jews, and I will sing to you [MTY].” <verse eid="ROM 15:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 15:10"/><char style="add">David</char> also wrote, “You non-Jews, rejoice with us who are God’s people.” <verse eid="ROM 15:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 15:11"/><char style="add">And Moses wrote in</char> the <char style="add">Scriptures</char>, “Praise the Lord, all <char style="add">you</char> non-Jews, and may everyone praise him [DOU].” <verse eid="ROM 15:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 15:12"/>And Isaiah wrote <char style="add">in the Scriptures</char>, “There will be a descendant [MET] of <char style="add">King</char> David who will begin to rule the non-Jews. They will confidently expect him <char style="add">to fulfill what he has promised</char>.”<verse eid="ROM 15:12"/></para>
  <para style="s1">May God make you completely joyful and peaceful in order that you may confidently expect him to do what he has promised.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:13">Romans 15:13</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 15:13"/>God is the one who causes you to confidently expect <char style="add">him to do what he has promised. I pray/ask</char> that he will cause you to be completely joyful and peaceful as you trust <char style="add">in him</char>. As you do that, the Holy Spirit will enable you to more and more confidently expect <char style="add">to receive what God has promised you</char>.<verse eid="ROM 15:13"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I have written frankly to you in this letter because of what God has kindly commissioned me to do among non-Jews.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:14-16">Romans 15:14-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 15:14"/>My fellow believers, I myself am <char style="add">completely</char> sure that you yourselves <char style="add">have acted toward others</char> in a completely good way. You have done that because you have known completely <char style="add">all that God wants you to know</char> [HYP], and because you are able to teach each other. <verse eid="ROM 15:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 15:15"/>However, I have written to you quite frankly <char style="add">in this letter</char> about some things in order to remind you <char style="add">about those things</char>. <char style="add">I have written this letter</char> because I have been appointed by God {God has <char style="add">appointed</char> me}, which I did not deserve, <verse eid="ROM 15:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 15:16"/>in order that I would work for Jesus Christ among non-Jews. <char style="add">God has appointed me</char> to act like a priest as I <char style="add">proclaim</char> his good message in order that he will accept the non-Jews <char style="add">who believe in Christ. They will be</char> like an offering [MET] <char style="add">to God</char> as a result of their being dedicated <char style="add">to him</char> by the Holy Spirit {the Holy Spirit dedicating them <char style="add">to God</char>}.<verse eid="ROM 15:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I am happy about my work for God that I have now completed in this region by proclaiming the gospel in places where people have not heard about Christ.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:17-21">Romans 15:17-21</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 15:17"/>It follows that, because <char style="add">of my relationship with</char> (OR, because <char style="add">I belong to</char>) Christ Jesus, I am happy about <char style="add">my work for</char> God. <verse eid="ROM 15:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 15:18"/>I will speak boldly only [LIT] about the work that Christ has enabled me to do. <char style="add">I do that work</char> in order that non-Jews might pay attention to <char style="add">the message about Christ</char> as a result of what I have said and done, <verse eid="ROM 15:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 15:19"/>specifically, by <char style="add">my performing</char> many powerful miracles [DOU]. <char style="add">I have done those things</char> as a result of <char style="add">God’s</char> Spirit powerfully <char style="add">enabling me</char>. As a result <char style="add">of doing those things, while traveling</char> all the way around from Jerusalem to Illyricum <char style="add">province</char>, I have completed <char style="add">my work</char> of proclaiming the message about Christ <char style="add">in those places</char>. <verse eid="ROM 15:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 15:20"/>As <char style="add">I proclaim</char> that message, I am always eagerly trying to proclaim it <char style="add">in places</char> where people have not already heard about Christ. I do that in order that <char style="add">as I work for God</char> I might not <char style="add">be continuing the work for him that someone else already started</char> [MET]. <char style="add">I do not want to be like a man who</char> builds <char style="add">a house</char> on someone else’s foundation. <verse eid="ROM 15:20"/><verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 15:21"/>On the contrary, <char style="add">I teach non-Jews, so that what happens may be like</char> what was written {the prophet Isaiah wrote} <char style="add">in the Scriptures about the Messiah</char>: “Those who did not hear about him previously will know <char style="add">the truth about him</char>. Truly, those who have not heard <char style="add">about him will hear and</char> understand <char style="add">his message</char> [DOU].”<verse eid="ROM 15:21"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Because of this work, I have often been hindered from visiting you, but I hope to see you as I journey through your area and I hope that you will give me what I need for my next journey. But now I am about to go to Jerusalem to take funds to God’s people there. So later I will visit you in Rome, and I know that Christ will bless us there.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:22-29">Romans 15:22-29</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 15:22"/>Because <char style="add">I have attempted to preach the message about Christ in places where they have not heard about him</char>, I have been hindered {things have hindered me} many times <char style="add">from being able</char> to visit you. <verse eid="ROM 15:22"/><verse number="23" style="v" sid="ROM 15:23"/>But now there are no more places in these regions <char style="add">where people have not heard about Christ</char>. Furthermore, for several years I have wanted to visit you. <verse eid="ROM 15:23"/><verse number="24" style="v" sid="ROM 15:24"/><char style="add">So I hope to go/come to see you</char>. I hope to do that as soon as I am on my way to <char style="add">the provinces in</char> Spain. I hope to see you as I journey through <char style="add">your area</char>, and I hope that <char style="add">by whatever you give me</char> [EUP] you will help me on my journey to Spain. But before <char style="add">I go there</char>, I want to enjoy being with you for a little while, although <char style="add">I would like to stay with you longer</char>. <verse eid="ROM 15:24"/><verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 15:25"/>But <char style="add">I cannot visit you</char> now, because I am about to go to Jerusalem in order to take money [EUP] for God’s people <char style="add">there</char>. <verse eid="ROM 15:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 15:26"/><char style="add">The believers in</char> Macedonia and Achaia <char style="add">provinces</char> [MTY] decided to contribute some <char style="add">money</char> [EUP] for those of God’s people in Jerusalem who are poor. <verse eid="ROM 15:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 15:27"/>They themselves decided <char style="add">to do this, but</char> truly they owe something to God’s people in Jerusalem. The non-Jewish <char style="add">believers</char> benefited spiritually from Jewish <char style="add">believers as a result of hearing the message about Christ from them</char>, so the non-Jews should also help the Jewish believers <char style="add">in Jerusalem by giving them</char> material things (OR, money) [EUP]. <verse eid="ROM 15:27"/><verse number="28" style="v" sid="ROM 15:28"/>So when I have finished this <char style="add">task</char> by safely delivering all this money [MET, EUP] <char style="add">that the believers in Macedonia and Achaia have given</char>, I will leave <char style="add">Jerusalem and visit</char> you <char style="add">in Rome while I am</char> on my way to Spain. <verse eid="ROM 15:28"/><verse number="29" style="v" sid="ROM 15:29"/>And I know that when I visit you, Christ will abundantly bless <char style="add">us</char> (OR, enable <char style="add">me</char> to bless <char style="add">you</char>).<verse eid="ROM 15:29"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I urge you to pray fervently that God will protect me from the unbelieving Jews in Judea and that God’s people there will accept the money that I take to them, and also that I may be refreshed by visiting you. May God be with you all.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 15:30-33">Romans 15:30-33</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="30" style="v" sid="ROM 15:30"/>Because <char style="add">we belong to</char> our Lord Jesus Christ and because the Spirit <char style="add">of God causes us to</char> love <char style="add">each other</char>, I urge you <char style="add">all</char> that <char style="add">you help me</char> by fervently/intensely praying to God for me. <verse eid="ROM 15:30"/><verse number="31" style="v" sid="ROM 15:31"/><char style="add">Pray that</char> I will be protected {<char style="add">that God</char> will protect me} so that the <char style="add">Jews</char> in Judea who do not believe <char style="add">the message about Christ will not harm me</char>. Also pray that God’s people in Jerusalem will accept the money [EUP] that I <char style="add">take</char> to them. <verse eid="ROM 15:31"/><verse number="32" style="v" sid="ROM 15:32"/>Pray these things in order that I may go/come to you if God wants me to go/come, and that I may go/come joyfully, and that then God will refresh my <char style="add">spirit as a result of my visiting/being</char> with you. <verse eid="ROM 15:32"/><verse number="33" style="v" sid="ROM 15:33"/><char style="add">I pray that</char> God, who <char style="add">causes us to have inner</char> peace, will be with all of you <char style="add">and will help</char> you. ◄May it be so!/Amen!►<verse eid="ROM 15:33"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 15"/>
  <chapter number="16" style="c" sid="ROM 16"/>
  <para style="s1">I am introducing and commending Phoebe to you, and I ask that you receive her as a fellow believer and that you give her whatever she needs.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 16:1-2">Romans 16:1-2</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="1" style="v" sid="ROM 16:1"/>
    <char style="add">By means of this letter</char> I am introducing and recommending to you our fellow believer Phoebe, <char style="add">who will be taking this letter to you</char>. She is a deacon in the congregation in Cenchrea <char style="add">city</char>. <verse eid="ROM 16:1"/><verse number="2" style="v" sid="ROM 16:2"/><char style="add">I request that</char> you receive her because of her relationship with the Lord. <char style="add">You should do that because</char> those who are God’s people ought to receive <char style="add">their fellow believers</char>. <char style="add">I am also requesting</char> that you help her <char style="add">by giving her</char> [EUP] whatever she needs, because she has helped many people, including me.<verse eid="ROM 16:2"/></para>
  <para style="s1">I send my greetings to many individuals among the believers there. All the congregations in this area also send their greetings to you.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 16:3-16">Romans 16:3-16</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="3" style="v" sid="ROM 16:3"/>Tell Priscilla and <char style="add">her husband</char> Aquila that I ◄send greetings to/am thinking fondly of► them. They worked with me for Christ Jesus, <verse eid="ROM 16:3"/><verse number="4" style="v" sid="ROM 16:4"/>and they were even willing to die [IDM] in order <char style="add">to save</char> my life. It is not only I who thank them <char style="add">for helping me</char>, but the people in all [HYP] the non-Jewish congregations also <char style="add">thank them for saving my life</char>. <verse eid="ROM 16:4"/><verse number="5" style="v" sid="ROM 16:5"/>Also tell the congregation <char style="add">that meets</char> in their house that I ◄send my greetings to/am thinking fondly of► them. Tell my dear friend Epaenetus the same thing. He is the first man in Asia <char style="add">province</char> who <char style="add">believed</char> in Christ. <verse eid="ROM 16:5"/><verse number="6" style="v" sid="ROM 16:6"/>Tell Mary, who has worked hard <char style="add">for Christ</char> in order to <char style="add">help</char> you, that I ◄send my greetings to/am thinking fondly of► her. <verse eid="ROM 16:6"/><verse number="7" style="v" sid="ROM 16:7"/>Tell the same thing to Andronicus and <char style="add">his wife</char> Junia (OR, and <char style="add">his sister</char> Junia) who are my fellow Jews and who were also <char style="add">previously</char> in prison with me. They are well-known/respected (OR, respected by the) apostles, and they became Christians before I did. <verse eid="ROM 16:7"/><verse number="8" style="v" sid="ROM 16:8"/>I also send my greetings to Ampliatus, who is a dear friend because of his relationship with the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 16:8"/><verse number="9" style="v" sid="ROM 16:9"/>I also send my greetings to Urbanus, who works for Christ with us, and to my dear friend Stachys. <verse eid="ROM 16:9"/><verse number="10" style="v" sid="ROM 16:10"/>I also send my greetings to Apelles, whom Christ has approved <char style="add">because Apelles successfully endured trials</char>. Tell the <char style="add">believers</char> who <char style="add">live in the house</char> of Aristobulus that I send my greetings to them. <verse eid="ROM 16:10"/><verse number="11" style="v" sid="ROM 16:11"/>Also tell Herodion, who is my fellow Jew, that I send my greetings to him. Tell the same thing to those who <char style="add">live in the house</char> of Narcissus who belong to the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 16:11"/><verse number="12" style="v" sid="ROM 16:12"/>Tell the same thing to Tryphaena and <char style="add">her sister</char> Tryphosa, who work hard for the Lord. I also send my greetings to Persis. <char style="add">We all</char> love her and she has worked very hard for the Lord. <verse eid="ROM 16:12"/><verse number="13" style="v" sid="ROM 16:13"/>Tell Rufus, who is an outstanding Christian, that I send my greetings to him. <char style="add">Tell the same thing to</char> his mother, <char style="add">who has treated me as though</char> I <char style="add">were her son</char> [MET]. <verse eid="ROM 16:13"/><verse number="14" style="v" sid="ROM 16:14"/>Tell Asyncritus and Phlegon and Hermes and Patrobas and Hermas and the fellow believers who <char style="add">meet</char> with them that I am sending my greetings to them. <verse eid="ROM 16:14"/><verse number="15" style="v" sid="ROM 16:15"/>I also send my greetings to Philologus, to <char style="add">his wife</char> Julia (OR, <char style="add">his sister</char> Julia), to Nereus and his sister, and to Olympas, and to all God’s people who <char style="add">meet</char> with them. <verse eid="ROM 16:15"/><verse number="16" style="v" sid="ROM 16:16"/>Greet one another affectionately, but in a pure way, <char style="add">when you gather together</char>. The <char style="add">believers in</char> all the Christian congregations [HYP] <char style="add">in this area ◄send their</char> greetings to/say they are thinking fondly of► you.<verse eid="ROM 16:16"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Note those who are causing quarrels among you and those who cause people to turn away from God. Avoid them, because they only want to satisfy their own desires and deceive those who do not suspect their motives. If you avoid such people, God will soon crush Satan under your feet.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 16:17-20">Romans 16:17-20</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="17" style="v" sid="ROM 16:17"/>My fellow believers, I exhort you that you beware of those people who are causing divisions among you and who cause people to turn away <char style="add">from God</char> [MTY] <char style="add">because they teach things that</char> are contrary to the message <char style="add">about Christ</char> that you have learned (OR, that others taught you). Keep away from such people! <verse eid="ROM 16:17"/><verse number="18" style="v" sid="ROM 16:18"/>They do not serve our Lord Christ! On the contrary, they only want to satisfy their own desires [MTY]! Also, by all the eloquent things that they say [DOU] they deceive those people who do not realize <char style="add">that their teaching is false</char>. <verse eid="ROM 16:18"/><verse number="19" style="v" sid="ROM 16:19"/><char style="add">Believers</char> everywhere know that you have paid attention to <char style="add">the good message about Christ</char>, with the result that I rejoice about you. But I also want you to be wise, <char style="add">with the result that you do</char> what is good. I also want you to avoid doing what is evil. <verse eid="ROM 16:19"/><verse number="20" style="v" sid="ROM 16:20"/><char style="add">If you avoid people who teach what is false</char>, what will <char style="add">soon happen</char> [MET] <char style="add">will be as though</char> God, who causes us to be peaceful, will be crushing Satan under your feet! <char style="add">I pray that</char> our Lord Jesus will continue to act kindly towards you.<verse eid="ROM 16:20"/></para>
  <para style="s1">Several of those who are with me send their greetings.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 16:21-23">Romans 16:21-23</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="21" style="v" sid="ROM 16:21"/>Timothy, who works with me, and Lucius and Jason and Sosipater, who are my fellow Jews, <char style="add">want you to know that they are</char> ◄sending their greetings to/thinking fondly of► you. <verse eid="ROM 16:21"/><verse number="22" style="v" sid="ROM 16:22"/>I, Tertius, <char style="add">one who belongs to</char> the Lord, <char style="add">also want you to know</char> that I am ◄sending my greetings to/thinking fondly of► you. <char style="add">I am writing this letter as Paul tells me what to write for him</char>. <verse eid="ROM 16:22"/><verse number="23-24" style="v" sid="ROM 16:23-24"/>I, <char style="add">Paul</char>, am staying in the house of Gaius, and the whole congregation <char style="add">here meets</char> in his house. He <char style="add">also wants you to know</char> that he is ◄sending his greetings to/thinking fondly of► you. Erastus, the treasurer of <char style="add">this</char> city, also <char style="add">wants you to know that</char> he is ◄sending his greetings to/thinking fondly of► you. Our fellow believer Quartus also ◄sends his greetings to you./says he is thinking fondly of you.►<note caller="+" style="f"><char style="fr" closed="false">16:23-24 </char><char style="ft" closed="false">Some Greek manuscripts add v. 24, “May the Lord Jesus Christ continue to act kindly toward you all. Amen!/May it be so!”</char></note><verse eid="ROM 16:23-24"/></para>
  <para style="s1">We should forever praise the One who alone is God, who alone is truly wise.</para>
  <para style="sr">
    <ref loc="ROM 16:25-27">Romans 16:25-27</ref></para>
  <para style="p">
    <verse number="25" style="v" sid="ROM 16:25"/>As <char style="add">I</char> proclaim <char style="add">the good message about</char> Jesus Christ, <char style="add">I tell about God</char>, the one who is able to strengthen you <char style="add">spiritually</char>. I also proclaim the <char style="add">truth</char> that was not revealed {which <char style="add">God</char> did not reveal} in all previous ages/times <verse eid="ROM 16:25"/><verse number="26" style="v" sid="ROM 16:26"/>but which has now been {which <char style="add">he</char> has now} revealed. <char style="add">I, along with others, have proclaimed</char> what the prophets wrote <char style="add">about Christ</char>. We are doing what the eternal God commanded <char style="add">us(exc)/me to do</char>. We want <char style="add">people in</char> all ethnic groups to know <char style="add">Christ</char> so that they can believe <char style="add">in him</char> and obey <char style="add">him</char>. <verse eid="ROM 16:26"/><verse number="27" style="v" sid="ROM 16:27"/><char style="add">I desire that by</char> Jesus Christ <char style="add">enabling us, we</char> will forever praise the one who alone is God, who alone is <char style="add">truly</char> wise. ◄May it be so!/Amen!►<verse eid="ROM 16:27"/></para>
  <chapter eid="ROM 16"/>
</usx>
